So, let's get started. Welcome to cs372. Like
i mentioned last time, we got into the final
lecture series on "Consciousness and Mind."
The first lecture was given by Dr. Duvvuri
because we really want a psychiatrist to come
in to tell us the real-world situations. Something
is normal and something, e.g., mentally disorder,
is abnormal (or atypical, deviant, or unhealthy).
You know psychiatrists when they try to diagnose
whether someone has mental disorders they
definitely compare normal behaviors with the
abnormal behaviors. (As we will illustrate,
finding order or disorder by comparing the
two.) Let me project the slides first.
Okay, so today's lecture we will be focusing
on consciousness: how to model consciousness.
As I mentioned last time there are several
topics we need to cover and started with a
comparison between normal and abnormal behaviors.
Today we focus on "what is consciousness"
and next time will be "where is consciousness"
and then how it works. And finally we will
address mind and ethics, which at this point
you may consider to be a little bit abstract.
But once we lay out the foundation of "what
is consciousness" and "where it is", maybe
mind and ethics can be more evident. And we
even attempt to quantify them (ethics and
love). Let's look at why we want to study
the topic. It all started about two and a
half years ago, when Yoshua Bengio at the
Neurips conference, he gave a keynote on the
limitations of the current AI. In the talk,
basically we all understand the limitations
today, AI today requires large volume of training
data, and lacking robustness. If you're just
changing a few pixels, classification could
be erroneous. We have problems with explainability,
reasoning, and causal analysis. We all understand
we have generalization problems. Bengio mentioned
there are two avenues to address the issues.
One is that we develop some bandaids to try
to patch so-called system one today. And then
the second approach is let's start from afresh,
start from scratch, start from high level
cognition. There are two philosophical thinkings.
One is consciousness, or they call system
two. Is consciousness purely computational
just like system one? I will get into slightly
details about why we think unconsciousness,
the processing, is only computation, and consciousness
may be computation only or may be beyond computation.
Bengio's idea was computation all the way.
If you talk to other scholars, their thoughts
like Roger Penrose's, he would say no because
consciousness and unconsciousness, their mechanisms
are different. Some "matters" may not be purely
computational. It's interesting when i came
across the book published by Erwin Schrodinger
in 1944. This is a very very long time ago.
Erwin is the grandfather or the father of
quantum mechanics. In his book even almost
80 years ago he actually depicted the idea
of consciousness. I think his book is interesting
because he doesn't talk about philosophy or
theology. He really focuses on physics, using
physics to explain consciousness. So you see
some science there rather than just abstract
thinking and debating. In bengio's talk, he
mentioned a book published by Daniel Kahneman.
The title of book is "Thinking Fast and Thinking
Slow". System one at the bottom (of the slide)
is the current AI. Daniel characterizes the
current AI to be thinking fast, thinking habitually,
intuitively, and unconsciously. And we cannot
explain the mechanisms or causality. System
two, on the other hand, is thinking slow.
We think logically, sequentially. We plan
and we conduct reasoning.
Mapping thinking fast and thinking slow or
system one and system two to psychological
study, we look at the father of psychology
Sigmund Freud. His view of human mind has
two parts. At the bottom we consider to be
unconsciousness. Let us blow up the figure
on the right hand side. Unconsciousness, according
to Freud, there are fears, violent motives,
unacceptable sexual desires, irrational wishes,
and so on so forth. And consciousness includes
thoughts and perceptions. This is really in
the early days, and Freud came up with this
kind of classification. It's interesting to
me, in unconscious level Freud put down a
few very negative adjectives. For instance,
before wish Freud put irrational, and urges
immoral, right. Or needs, and you put selfish
in front of it. But our needs: we have urge,
perhaps we are really hungry or we get some
external stimuli, and we we feel hurt. You
couldn't actually put a moral value in front
of those needs. Moral judgment should be probably
in the consciousness level. So let's don't
judge morality at this point until the last
lecture. Basically a lot of functions of human
being work in the unconscious state. One evident
example is our breathing. We don't have to
pay attention to our breathing and we don't
have to be conscious about our heartbeat.
Everything is done virtually automatically.
Let's define what is consciousness. This is
a very challenging topic and you get perspectives
from different disciplines including physicists,
biologists, neuroscientists, theologians,
philosophers, computer scientists, and so
on so forth. There have been over 20,000 papers
published so far but producing little results.
Let's come back to consciousness. Let's look
at some a prominent definitions. The first
definition was given by Michio Kaku. He is
a very famous physicist and he said well,
consciousness can be defined in relation to
the space. To us, if we want to be conscious
about our presence, yes we have the the sense
of space, and we also have the sense of time.
Time is critical because if we want to derive
some thoughts, we need to probably look into
the past so we have to tap into the memory.
We want to do planning, we want to be able
to project into the future. So space and time,
we accept those are critical foundations of
consciousness. And also in relationship to
others. Let's give some examples. These are
the examples given by Kaku. Though it's debatable
whether plants have consciousness or not,
Kaku basically saying if you look at consciousness,
which can be quantified by the number of feedback
loops. Any organisms have feedback loops and
can enhance their livings, you can probably
just consider that (they have) consciousness.
For plants, plants can sense temperature and
can sense where the water is. So the roots
of the plant would grow toward or grow toward
the direction of water. There are many flowers
would grow toward the sun, or toward the high
temperature direction. If you look at our
pets, these are mammals, typically. They would
react to threats and they have interactions
with human and other animals. For human beings,
we have a lot of sensors or feedback loops.
We do learning and like for example learning
i think teacher will provide feedback. We
have emotion. Emotion reacts to other people
and other people would also provide us feedback.
We have constantly been evaluated in this
society.
Next, consciousness versus attention. These
are two different terms. Attention has already
been studied thoroughly by psychiatrists.
Also in computer science you know our "attention
model" using the term attention. But strictly
speaking these are two different ideas and
two different terms. It's possible or it's
actually kind of consciousness and attention
they are entangled with each other. But they
are distinct in the brain functionality. We
generally we can treat consciousness as a
synthesizer or a summarizer. Consciousness,
would kind of summarize the entire environment
using different sensors. For instance, sitting
in the classroom we use our visual (eyes),
ears, we use our different organs to sense
the entire environment. But analyzer is done
by the attention module. Attention module,
for example I look at the entire classroom,
then i want to talk to Bill. I pay my attention
to one individual and this is because I already
know the entire contextual information. When
I want to zoom into a specific individual
i'm doing the attention, more focused. So
you could say consciousness may operate in
a longer time scale including information
summary, planning, decision making. Attention
is to select the information to meet the current
behavior objective. So, one is longer term
and one is shorter term.
Let's look at one example used by psychiatrists.
If we look at the screen right now we see
some symbols here. For the bottom-up consciousness,
basically we are sensing the pixels our eyes,
retina, sensing these pixels and there's an
image perception in our brain. Consciously
we're trying to detect or try to recognize
this symbol. How many people consider this
is a digit,
two digits, or an alphabet? B, 13, and B,
is ambiguous, right? Let's say if you have
these three characters in a row. This is called
top-down attention. You are consciously aware
of several characters here. Then when you
zoom in to pay attention to the middle character,
you tend to say this is a B. If you have another
sequence of numbers and here you would probably
say 13. So top-down attention works differently
from bottom-up attention. In the end of this
lecture i would go back to talk about the
current machine learning model, the attention
model. The attention model, the current implementation
is pretty much bottom-up not top-down. Do
we need to have top-down attention built into
machine learning? My answer is absolutely
yes. So this is a really interesting opportunity.
When we talk about system one system two integration
this is an opportunity to enhance system two.
We can model subjectivity into AI, right?
Subjectivity, let's do a very simple discussion.
Two different people look at the same instance
of object, they may have different feelings.
But when you say objectively, when a machine
perceives an object, the machine can only
come up with one classification. Otherwise
it's a bug. Otherwise we say it's an error.
So, subjectivity has to be top down. Where
is this top? If you say objectivity, then
bottom up would be sufficient. Discussion
one. Is it possible that consciousness is
absent of attention. We are in a conscious
state but there's no attention whatsoever.
Pretty much i have already given the answer.
But it's still debatable, I mean if you look
at articles in psychiatry about what's the
difference between consciousness and attention,
they've done lots of experiments and looking
at the brain activities under different situations.
They're still not conclusive. But in principle
people agree the top-down attention mechanism
needs to be in consciousness state. But the
bottom-up is debatable because if you talk
to psychiatrists they have different ideas.
But if i read into Schrodinger's model and
which i will show in the next slide. The question
is when do we transition from unconscious
state to conscious state. When you ride your
bike today or take Margherita to the campus
today are you consciously... are you always
in conscious mode when you ride your bike?
You say i'm balancing on the bike. When we
learned how to
bike, do you see kids learn how to walk? They
are constantly in the consciousness state:
They want to balance themselves they don't
want to fall. But i don't think most of us
walking on the campus today, we we are very
conscious about balancing our body, right?
We are walking in pretty much in unconscious
state. In the biking situation, I saw my neighbors,
because i live in front of Palo Alto high
school, and quite a few students biking at
the same time watching on their phones. Definitely
they are not paying any attention, not probably
not even in the conscious state when they
are biking. The notion of biking, it's already
kind of in unconscious state because it's
already
habitual. Let's look at how they (consciousness
and unconsciousness) transition to each other,
so we may be able to understand some insights.
According to schrodinger,
if we are in unconsciousness state, to get
into consciousness state, there must be a
quantum jump, quantum jump a quantum mechanism
phenomenon. Quantum jump means there are
two different states of an atom, and it wants
to transition from one state the second one
(on the slide, points 1 and 2),
there must be the energy surge (point 3).
Once you have energy surge to a certain level,
then there's a
probability that quantum jump or state transition
will happen. Likewise here, Schrodinger saying
if a person is in unconsciousness state. Let's
say we continue sensing the environment. Our
body is sensing the temperature but in the
beginning we don't feel anything different.
But accumulatively and we started to feel
very warm and getting hotter and hotter. And
then suddenly there's a quantum jump and we
start to feel if there's some kind of heat
or cold. Now the feeling of heat or feeling
of cold really gets into the consciousness
state.
But there's another situation which would
look at some scenarios in the next slide.
Look at the left-hand side. Sensitization
typically is classified to act in unconscious
state. Like acrophobia, i don't know, i do
have
fear of heights and when i walk on like Chicago's
Wills Tower...
In this tall building, there's an observatory.
You walk out there's a piece of glass under
your feet. And i just couldn't stand up! You
asked me whether i'm consciously fear about
height or unconsciously fear about height?
I have to say I cannot control myself. So
that's considered to be a phobia and considered
to be in unconsciousness state. A lot of people
have phobia about noise about something they
don't like like my one of my daughters phobia
with spiders. The second one is habituation---
something going on for a long long time, and
something repetitive going on. One example
is sensing, and sensing if there is no sufficient
energy to incur a state transition, it just
continues to to be done in the unconscious
state.
Like right now i'm watching this entire classroom
and if i don't pay attention to anything.
Do you think i can sense the water fountain
outside? outside the windows? Actually i could!
Water fountain is out there. Unless i pay
attention to matters outside the window it's
in my sensing in the domain of my sensing
but it's in unconsciousness state.
Our organ operations---breathing, heartbeat---
there's no way we can control them. They just
function so called "normally", and we pay
attention to them only when our breathing
gets into trouble or our heartbeats get into
trouble. Metabolism right? You don't care,
you don't actually pay attention to how you
digest the food and how the nutrition get
distributed into blood vessels. This figure
here shows there are two dimensions: in the
x axis is computational complexity. On the
left-hand side computational complexity is
very low, on the right-hand side computation
requirement is very high. In the vertical
axis, we show on the top is consciousness
and at the bottom is unconsciousness. The
first question here is "1 + 7", we probably
consider this to be computational non-intensive,
and pi square, it's more complex. To us, 1
+ 7 we can do it in seconds but pi square
requires us to work on this arithmetic for
really some time. Actually pi squared does
not have an answer! Pi it's a huge number
(infinite decimal). We do arithmetic in unconsciousness
state or consciousness state?
Even computationally it can be very simple,
right? 1 + 7 is very simple, we have to do
it in the consciousness state. This is probably
an easy example. Do you have a disagreement?
Let's now look at more challenging situations.
I'm going to show uh different applications
and let's try to put them in the right place.
The first is let's play Go, not playing with
computers just people playing go. Where should
we place
this kind of chess playing, or Go game?
Should it be computationally intensive? or
it's trivial? or it's in conscious state?
or we can play the game in unconscious state?
Computationally high? okay. Conscious, right?
We cannot just sleep and play chess. The second
question is vision, our vision, is it conscious
state or unconscious?
Student: both. Instructor: Yes good point.
sensing can be in unconscious state but when
we have feeling when we try to pay attention
to certain things then we get into a consciousness
state. that's good.
And AlphaGo, what do you think? AlphaGo is
for sure computationally intensive, when the
training was being performed. But if AlphaGo
has already recorded all the possible moves,
during playing with an individual. That individual
is really in a hustling state---
consciousness and high computation complex---thinking
very very slow, and try to project all the
possible moves in the future. But how about
alpha go in a playing mode? not in a training
mode. Do you think the computational complexity
is extremely high?
And do you think it's in the consciousness
state to play with human? We know machine
may not have consciousness, right? AlphaGo
in the playing mode it's in unconsciousness
state and what it's doing is doing search.
Seeing the current layout of the board, and
because it already tried itself to see all
possible moves, so it said, oh, this is the
current board configuration. Let me search
the best move given this particular configuration.
That's just a search kind of method.
We can consider this search, compared with
the training process, it's much less computational
intensive. Let's plot these four (applications)
inon the diagram.
AlphaGo, i would say it's at the bottom (unconsciousness).
Computationally high? i kind of question that,
we can move it to the left a little bit. And
vision is in between and getting into preconscious
state. And nature language processing for
sure, we talk about when we have language
to have conversation with each other, we have
to get into consciousness state.
Of course if we just look at alphabets, we
probably in unconscious state. But eventually
when we formulate an article, a conversation
with others, we get into the consciousness
state. These are just some examples. Now we
look at Schrodinger's point of view. A look
at consciousness in relation to learning and
adaptation. He's looking from the evolution
perspective, and more specifically, he uses
physics to try to explain these two modes.
The first one is the second law of thermodynamics,
the second we already mentioned, quantum mechanics,
that is, quantum jump. Finally he mentioned
the relationship with mortality.
Mortality we will talk about in the last lecture.
Humans select to learn so when we want to
learn something we learn for two purposes.
We learn for wants or we learn for needs.
Needs are basic survival requirements like
eating, cooking, those are you can consider
to be needs. Or we want to find water, we
want to learn how to dig a well, and those
are for needs, not optional. And for needs
we talk about in the bottom (of the slide)---survival
or adaptation. Human must learn to survive.
If we have a drought condition here in Santa
Clara, we probably would go to supermarket
to buy drinking water or we go to other states
to find water. We have to be able to adapt
to survive. However, there are certain essential
skills we don't have to learn at all. In fact
we cannot learn, we cannot afford learning,
and we don't know how to learn them! We don't
have time to learn them. Just give you two
examples---breathing and heartbeat.
(An) embryo can already start having heartbeats.
Do you think embryo learns how to do heartbeats?
No. Embryo doesn't have consciousness (to
learn).
It's interesting the complex operations of
human beings were already given before we
were born. We did not have to learn them and
actually we couldn't learn them. Can you learn
how to breathe differently or changing your
heartbeat rhythms consciously? The answer
is no, not really. Philosophically you'll
say oh most challenging matters already been
given by someone or evolution. Only the not
so important things, I say, wants your desire.
I want to have something better to eat, I
want to swim, I want to bike. If you (we)
don't don't bike you can still survive. You
can walk to the classroom maybe get more healthier.
For the optional things, yes, we can learn.
But for the essential matters, we cannot learn.
We don't have time to learn, and they are
embedded in our our body. I actually, when
i translated Schrodinger's "What is Life",
my own feeling at the end was saying: well,
what we could learn in the world is really
really limited. First of all essential skills
already be given, right. Secondly when we
were born we are confined by our heredity.
Heredity includes broadly not only our chromosome
DNA, but also includes
our identity. Our DNA gave us our IQ, maybe
mortality means diseases, and EQ, personality.
We also we were born with identity: nationality,
family. Nationality and family already give
us some intrinsic directions, inertials. Nationality
already gives you a set of hates. Your family
may already give you a set of possible religions
you would you would try to convert into so
you don't really have a lot of choices. Yes,
some people are more rebellious, and they
can defy their identities. But most of people
would just be conformative.
Therefore, what we could learn mostly is for
our wants, and they are optional, they are
extra-curriculum. I was joking about the the
free will we have? Probably just for
ordering dishes, on doorDash or in a restaurant.
Other things pretty much restricted. Okay
free will...
when we go to lecture #18 (#17). Free will
is it's kind of a philosophical question.
Do we really have free will? It's just a survey
for the fun of it.
How many consider you have free will? (~50%
of the class)
How many consider you don't have free will
whatsoever? (zero vote)
Okay. Lex Fridman, an MIT professor, who has
produced many podcasts. So far i think he
has gotten about 270 episodes. In the early
days the podcast each episode is about one
hour. And started about Eps#200, there's no
limit of time. There are podcasts lasting
even four or five hours. It's really really
intriguing, some subjects, The two questions
he always asked, to most of the guest speakers
he
would ask... The first question is
"Are you a robot? Then, "Do you really think
human
has free will?" "Do you have free will or
not?" "Everything is predetermined or not?"
Surprisingly those smart people he interviewed
including Nobel laureates, Turing Award winners.
Their answers are pretty coherent.
Most of people like including myself, I consider
I'm a robot. Free will is my illusion.
Let's come back (laughing) to the lecture.
Human, how do we learn? We learn starting
from we have a need to learn, then starts
from external stimulus. Suppose here we're
just using "vision" as an example. Our retinas
start
sensing pixels (light) and then our perception,
our sensing circuits will convert input signals
into
quantifiable, we call sensual quality. In
vision, sensing we sensing a lot of pixels
into our eyes, those like electrical signals,
then the sensual quality is kind of color.
It's a it's a vital one. Then you could say
texture and shape.
Eventually we have understanding we recognize
objects, and object recognition requires our
memory at the same time. Let's just look at
the first stage of sensing. We have 1) sensing
the signals and then 2) central quality. Do
we get identical sensual quality. Here again
we may only be in unconsciousness state right?
The picture on the top.
Let's blow up the picture. it's only sensing
and producing sensual quality, and then get
into our either cerebrum or cerebellum, either
processing consciously or unconsciously. Finally
we have responses. This is process of learning.
In just the sensing mode, do we have...
is it a one-to-one relationship: do we have
one signal producing one sensual quality or
there could be a mixture of multiple signals
can produce one sensual quality? And one (input)
signal can produce multiple different sensual
qualities?
Very simple question is: when we perceive
sensual quality to be yellow, yellow color.
What should be the input to our retinas?
If we look at the light spectrum, when we
have this 600 nanometer signal and it peaks
in our eyes as yellow color. This is given
by schrodinger and now it's well known. The
same sensual quality can come from different
mixtures of signals.
If we have two other signals 535 which is
green and plus 760 which is red, the combine
of the two also gives us yellow sensation.
Here we have possibility of multiple signals
combinations, different mixtures, can give
us the same sensation or sensual quality.
Then we have to think about computers, how a
computer operates? can compute function under
this situation? Different inputs have different
outputs, i think computer could do that, right?
Function can handle many to one mapping.
But the problem is the other way. The other
way is same color (light), but different sensual
qualities in different individuals.
It's very evident for people having colorblind,
their essential quality is different even
we are perceiving the same thing. They have
red-green color blind blue-yellow and also
complete color blind. Let's look at one example
of red-green color blind. On the left-hand
(of the slide) side there's no colorblind;
on the right-hand side this person has a red-green
color blind,
and how the person perceived. Here is already
interesting this is a good picture produced
by psychiatrists, but how can psychiatrists
figure out like---how can I figure out your
color quality? When we look at this picture
on the left hand side, i myself see yellow,
green, and the red, and maybe other colors.
You may also see the same colors or you may
not.
For color blind, they only see green. But
suppose we don't have colorblind. Even the
same red for us, the sensation in our retinas
may be different. your ReD is probably different
from my REd. This is already to us it's very
challenging to compute it's also very challenging
because you have different inputs, we all
consider to be the same. And here even we
have different color qualities, still people
can recognize there are different fruits,
apples, and pineapple, and so on so forth.
Now let's review two math concepts the first
one is relation. Relation defines as a relationship
between two values. We have four different
relations on this slide: one too many, one
to one, many to one, and many too many. However,
function is a relation where each input has
only one output. Among the four relations,
only the two in the middle: one to one, and
many to one, (each) produces one output. They
are legitimate functions. Now let's go back
to visit our visual system. We have input
as senses and input generates sensual qualities.
As we already mentioned using colorblind as
an example, here we have one to many relationship.
Then from the sensual quality, let's say you
and I both look at the ocean, and we may have
different emotions incurred, because maybe
our memory or our computational information.
Therefore, we encounter this interesting problem
of from senses to sensual quality is not a
function, and from sensual quality to emotion
is not a function either.
But in our CNN or machine learning algorithms,
we typically implement everything as a function.
Therefore the interesting challenge to us
is how can we model one to many?
When we consider contextual information in
memory, and this we call subjectivity... Now
let's pop up one level. Let's revisit our
stimulus-response pathway. We already talked
about input generating sensing quality. Before
human can produce a response, our brain will
be operating on the signals and making a decision.
Our brain operates in two different modes,
consciousness and unconsciousness. When we
define consciousness in the beginning of the
lecture, we try to contrast the term consciousness
with attention. Attention can be either bottom-up
as shown on the left hand side
of this diagram or top-down. When attention
is top-down, it's pretty much goal driven
and it operates in the consciousness mode.
However, when attention is bottom-up, it's
a stimulus driven. We continue sensing our
world, and when the collected energy reaches
a certain threshold, then there's a transition
going on from unconsciousness to consciousness.
I really appreciate the explanation done by
Erwin Schrodinger, the father of quantum mechanics.
Let's take a look at how a CNN neuron works.
A neuron collects information from upstream
neurons. When the energy level reaches a threshold,
the neuron will fire, and would propagate
the signal to the downstream neurons. This
is precisely how Schrodinger explains the
state transition in an atom. An atom can be
in two different modes
---on this slide mode 1 and mode 2. An atom is
in the stable state until the energy level
reaches 3. Once the energy level reaches a
threshold,
there's a probability that a state transition
will happen. This is exactly the ingenious
of the CNN model,
which models exactly how schrodinger depicts
the state transition physically in the atoms.
How about the other way? How do we transition
from the consciousness state to unconscious
state?
When we listen to music, in the beginning
we may be paying attention to the lyric, but
eventually, or in my case, i would fall into
sleep. Driving is another experience. If I'm
very familiar with the route, I do
not really pay attention to the details. The
emotion or emotion of sadness or happiness
eventually will fade away. And these are all
good things because in the emotion scenario
we don't want to be sad forever. Evolution
builds in, in our brain we will forget about
the sadness, and at the same time, we cannot
be happy forever we have to transition into
the normal mode and to continue to live with
our lives. Schrodinger saying well the transition
is kind of fading away can be thought as second
law of thermodynamics.
The second law of thermodynamics expresses
the fundamental and the simple truth about
the universe that disorder characterized by
a quantity called entropy, always increases.
When the entropy is peaked, the
isolated system is we call in the dead state
or inert state. And like our physical body,
eventually aging is a phenomenon of the second
law of thermodynamics. Schrodinger in his
book actually made a joke about how can we
live longer by slowing down our increase of
disorder.
There he suggested a couple of remedies. If
you are interested (in living longer) we can
talk about it offline.
The second law may be formulated by the observation
that the entropy is in the isolated system
left to spontaneous evolution cannot decrease
as this system always arrives at the state
of thermodynamic equilibrium where the entropy
is the highest. There are several experiments
and which can illustrate how this second law
works.
A popular one is in a closed space you inject
some color particles, and eventually the color
particles will be distributed evenly in the
close space. Or maybe you input two different
kind of air one in green color the other one
in red color and after a period of time those
two colors will mix together.
Now we put everything together and we start
with the in this consciousness state we learn
how to walk how to bike and the first time
come to stanford we have to navigate using
a map and so on so forth. Once we get familiar
with walking, biking, and driving directions,
we get into a habitual and repetitive mode.
Then there's the transition happens
---when we continue doing these tasks we will
be operating most of these tasks in unconsciousness
mode. As we mentioned this is really good
for the human being and for animals because
our emotions, we like them to fade away so
we can get on with our lives. In the unconscious
mode, see here we do a lot of tasks including
our heartbeats, metabolism unconsciously.
But if we drive to the campus and suddenly
we see an unexpected pediatric pedestrian
we are suddenly transitioning back to the
conscious mode to try to figure out how to
handle that situation. If you bike you hit
a tree suddenly, yes we need to stop there
and transition into the conscious mode and
handle the abruptive situation. This (process)
is called adaptation, which is necessary for
survival. Okay, let's now make some observations.
In consciousness and unconsciousness and when
they need to transition, they transition via
two physics mechanisms---quantum jump and
the second law of thermal dynamics. These
are great because we have a solid foundation
to implement the transitions. We're learning
for adaptation is done in the consciousness
mode and mainly for our biological needs and
for our our wants, which could be optional.
We eventually fade emotion into unconscious
state when things are repetitive. We also
talk about in the conscious state and when
we pay attention it could be top-down attention,
because we are aware of the bigger picture
then we want to focus on some specifics. In
attention or in a conscious mode one important
element is we cannot model this as just a
function because there could be one too many
mapping, which means that one sensing quality
can map to different emotions. And this we
call subjectivity a machine does not have
subjectivity if you look at today's machine
learning to this machine learning is the results
average of subjectivity. The training data
may be labeled by different people, they have
their own subjectivities. And we aggregate
everything together and uniformly or universally
we learn a set of parameters and then perform
prediction. How can we model subjectivity?
This, we can talk about it shortly after these
observations. We, one way to do it to avoid
this function definition issue is we can take
more arguments. If we take space, time, and
value into the arguments of a function, then
there's the possibility that we could have
a one-to-one mapping. Bottom-up attention
is performed in the unconsciousness mode.
So we can only pay attention to one or two
things and at the same time there are many
things going on in the environment and our
sense organs continuously sensing the environment
or heart continue to beat until something
unusual happens, which will trigger a high
energy then a transition will be made into
the conscious mode. But when quantum jump
performs prematurely, it means the threshold
is abnormally low, like Dr Duvvuri introduced
mental disorders on Monday's lecture for phobia.
Let's say acrophobia the fear of heights got
triggered at a much lower threshold. This
must be treated. At this moment the patient
can only be treated, targeting symptoms. But
in the future, hopefully we can get down to
the source. And this is precisely what the
next lecture will cover ---where is consciousness.
Let's defer the discussion to next Monday.
In closing the first half of the lecture:
we were born with a lot of sophisticated skills---metabolism
heartbeat and so so forth. They all operate
in unconsciousness mode. Then because we need
to adapt, we need to survive, we learn knowledge
and we learn skills. Once we are familiar
with the skills they become our second nature.
We can then perform the skills habitually.
However, our learned knowledge and skills
is never written back to the DNA. That's very
ironic, so our next generation they have to
learn reading, they have to learn biking all
over again. Evolution will not be helpful
for our future generations to be able to born
with the biking and the driving skills. This,
we can also address why in the next lecture
through a thorough investigation on the evolution
theory. Now we get to how to model subjective
consciousness. We know in machine learning
one of the most important constructs is distance
function. We measure similarity. Machine learning
tasks, for example, clustering or classification,
we need to measure similarity between instances.
We also need to be able to quantify differential.
Here this example shows classification in
machine learning. I argue all the classification
problems in machine learning considers a nearest-neighbor
problem. In this example we have two known
classes: one, rectangle blue, and the other
one is a triangle red. Now we have our unknown
instance. We don't know its label sitting
in the middle of the circle, which is round
green. How should we determine the color and
the shape
of the unknown (unlabeled) instance? Suppose
we draw nearest neighbors using circle. We
have two circles here---one in solid line
one in dashes. The solid line circle is smaller.
In that small neighborhood we basically look
into the labels of those instances. Here we
have three, two triangles and one rectangle.
And we perform a majority vote. They (the
neighbors) say: the instance
in the middle we are going to use red color
and triangle to label it. When we expand the
nearest neighbor to be larger, and now we
have five instances. Majority vote for us
in this case, we get "blue rectangle". I argue
all machine learning algorithms, regardless
whether it's a CNN top (neuron) level, or
support vector machines, and so on so forth.
All have the concepts of nearest neighbor,
and you measure similarity at the end is sort
of like a voting scheme. The label of the
unknown instance is then obtained. So we have
two important measures, we need to be able
to quantify---the first one is: what is the
distance? how to measure distance between
two instances? the second measure is what
is the definition of nearest neighbor. Let's
investigate further. Let's examine how do
we find nearest neighbor instances. Given
a point here we have this round blue dot in
the middle. Suppose we kind of simplify the
problem setting. Each instance has only two
attributes and one in the x dimension the
other one in the y dimension. The value of
each dimension ranges from zero to one. If
I want to find my nearest neighbor(s), i need
to give it a range. If i say range is everything
then you have to sequentially scan all your
data items. This is definitely not very efficient.
So, in data structures we have different tree
structures. The purpose of the three structures
is for efficient lookup. For range query in
this case, we'd like to be able to scan minimum
amount of data to find all the nearest neighbors.
In this example here, suppose we say my nearest
neighbor i can define to be a half of the
value. So f value is a fraction, and let's
say it's 50 percent. Dimension here is equal
to two. So nearest neighbor is 25% of the
area of the entire feature space. When d value,
d is the dimensionality of the data, and it's
getting larger and larger. Suppose we say
fraction is equal to 0.9. And 0.9 when the
dimension goes to about 100, then the volume
basically is the fraction power of d, approximates
to zero (0.9^100~0).
This means the instance in the middle cannot
find any nearest neighbors! All the so-called
nearest neighbors are very far away because
the fraction of your search, range query,
is already 90%. How do we mitigate this problem?
How to address this problem? There has been
many methods. I'm not going to get into details.
In the first lecture we talked about dimension
reduction, we talked about all these different
methods. Then we said well maybe transfer
learning may be pre-training, maybe other
means.
We try to... the the good thing is all the
data they don't just randomly spread out in
the future space. The objects tend to have
similar attributes, and therefore, we are
looking at the problem of clusters of objects.
Similar objects are highly clustered in the
feature space. So, that saves the day for
this
classification problem. If we can find just
a few clusters, then do attention. right?
We talk about top-down attention. At the top
we say there are this uniform distribution
situations we are dead. But there are 20 or
30 classes out there, and let's look at two
or three most likely clusters and we then
we zoom in our attention to it look into each
of these clusters. We may suffer from a lower
recall because we may miss some good clusters.
But the searching speed will be higher. Once
we get into the clusters, the precision of
course is not an issue.
Now, distance function. This is a very essential
topic for AI and at the end i'd like you to
think about do we have the right distance
function today?
Do you remember when we talked about NLP,
the history of NLP, we said well we need to
quantify the distance, similarity, between
words, and we said
well we have problems of synonym and polysemy.
Synonym may be easier you can do clustering
but polysemy can be more challenging.
Although clustering can handle the problem,
but for polysemy, we need to deal with it
very carefully (is) when we have contextual
information.
So let's look at distance functions in the
past. How we choose our distance function?
In Minkowski function basically if we have
two objects x and y and each object has k
attributes, k can be ranging from one to maybe
one thousand, and then we just say objects
x and y, we go through their attributes and
compare all the attribute differences then
sum them up. There are different ways to quantify
this sum. The first way is saying oh i want
to square the sum because i don't want to
worry about negative positive. I just want
to do a square of distance then i sum them
together. The second method is, again i don't
care about positive negative, i just care
about distance, i do this absolute value.
The third one is that, well you have squared
why not have different kind of exponential
number just have q in general then you just
normalize using 1/q. We call the first one
Euclidean distance, second one Manhattan distance,
and last one Minkowski. function in general.
For the manhattan distance they call that
because it's like a street-block distance.
You look at every dimension, you don't do
a square. Euclidean you use a straight line:
straight-line distance between two points.
Which method is better for vision? According
to all the empirical studies in the past,
Manhattan function seems to work better. Although
intuitively you want to say maybe Euclidean
makes more sense right i just want to know
the straight-line distance between two points.
But the trouble of Euclidean is the square
over there. When you have a square means when
you have a minority number of attributes that
they have large differences, then they will
impact your distance function non-proportionally.
For example, suppose you have one or
two outliers, and they have a difference of
20. The rest of the attributes difference
is only, let's say, 0.2. then this 20 or 10
when they you have an exponential over there,
power of 2, then those two attributes will
dominate your similarity measurement. Therefore,
manhattan is better, you don't have the problem.
And some folks even use q equal to 1/2, right?
Say, well one is good, one is better than
two, why not just a half?
We want to normalize the distance to make
sure all the attributes enjoy equal importance.
But that's really empirical study to figure
out. The second family of function is called
cosine function. You must heard about this
really often. In high dimensional space people
tend to use this one because computationally
you just do a dot product, and you can get
a distance function (measure). And..., but.
Let's think about attention and consciousness
now. What we have depicted so far, let's just
think about the Euclidean distance function.
The distance function, do you think it works
in unconsciousness mode or consciousness mode?
Because once the distance function is already
there, if i ask you a question of: "Do you
think New York and LA, are they similar or
not?" You cannot process using your consciousness.
You have to obey the distance function. The
distance function would say, there are many
attributes when you want to compare those
two cities, and you can compare every single
attribute and you sum together. That's your
answer. There's no subjectivity, right? But,
that's not the way
humans compare similarity between objects.
These (on the slide) are the progress in psychology
or psychiatry in the last 100 years. First
of all in 1928, psychiatrists believe objects
are similar in all respects. This is Minkowski
function. You consider all attributes, the
only difference is the exponent, square or
q. After 50 years and we have a new theory
by Tversky---objects are similar in some respects
not all respects. Certain respects you can
ignore. It came out with weighted Minkowski
function. You have to put a weight in front
of each attribute. Certain weights can be
lower and certain
weights can be higher. If you don't care about,
let's say, once you have worn a mask, the
face recognition system should just dismiss
whatever in the second region (beneath nose).
I don't know why apple takes so long to come
up with the new face recognition system. Now
you can unlock your phone even with your mask
on. But to me (it) still fails. I don't know
what the (iPhone) algorithm was working on?
But you can say it definitely downplays whatever
beneath your eyes. Similarity, in 1994, Goldstone
saying similarity is a process of determining
the respects rather than using predefined
respects. And this really flips consciousness
and unconsciousness. (Function) one and two,
the paradigm is really unconsciousness.
You are given a function and you don't even
need to think. That's it. But Goldstone saying
no no no. You are in a conscious state, you
are determining the respects, not respects
already determined for you. Therefore, in
this example I put in one of our publications,
which was quite interesting. The question
is: "pick two cities similar to San Francisco."
I assume, let's don't do this experiment here
because time imitation. But my assumption:
out of you, you may pick different sets (of
cities).
Why? because in my case, when I do comparison
I don't have a function to start with. Although
there are possible attributes down there (on
the slide) : location, climate, demographics,
culture, and so on so forth. But, only when
i realize the objects i want to compare, let's
say, i start to compare San Francisco and
New York, and the respects surface on my consciousness.
I say oh San Francisco New York, they are
similar in maybe traffic. Definitely not similar
in location, (since) they are one east coast and
one west coast. And of course if the context
is different, oh they are both in the US,
then that's a different story. The cultural
mixtures, they are similar, that they have
multiple cultures.
The attributes come out when you have the
objects surfaced. Let's say Los Angeles, or
Tokyo. Let's say Los Angeles is similar to
San Francisco. Los Angeles and and San Francisco,
location wise they are close. But when you
say San Francisco and Tokyo, they say no no,
they are very far apart. But some people still
consider San Francisco is similar to Tokyo
because it's a metropolitan city and San Francisco
has a Japan town and Tokyo definitely has
a lot of Japanese goods and culture.
So, this comparison is really subjective,
and which respects you want to focus on is
a consciousness operation rather than unconsciousness.
This really makes a huge difference when we're
looking forward and when we want to quantify
similarity for the machine learning task.
"Similarity is quantified only a pair of objects
being compared are realized." This is the
key sentence. You cannot predefine the distance
function. How do we implement it?
We implemented 20 years ago with my student.
On the right-hand side you can see there are
m objects, and if you want to compare them
whether they are similar or not, based on
their values here. You probably say, well,
for every pair the the common bits got flipped
to one, every pair is only two. Only minority.
So you say no, they are not very similar.
But on the left-hand side example, you say
oh a1, a2, a3 could be similar because when
you do voting, majority voting, between two,
between each pair, they have three attributes
similar---they have majority attributes similar.
They are not identical,
but they have three attributes similar. So,
at the end our finding is the following: if
you look at this next picture and this is
way before this data augmentation (AlexNet,
2012) was performed. In year 2001, my student
Beitao, he said, well, giving me these 5000
images i'm going to do conversion on those
images, including converting jpeg to GIF,
and we crop images, we rotate images, and
then we scale certain images. When we crop
the images we make sure that the gist of image
remaining in the image. Like, say, a barbecue,
you keep the bbq relevant objects or features
still in the cropped image. Then we say we
quantify every image---we do feature extraction
with three type of features, color, texture,
and the shape. If you look at the picture
here we have 144 attributes for every image
(x-axis). Then we say okay we compare the
original image with converted images, transform
images. The first one (a) compared with GIF
images,
basically we just changed the format. The
bottom one (c) rotated images, and on the
bottom-right (d): scaled images. Then you
look at the channels here, we have 144 attributes.
If we consider 0.02 (y-axis difference)
to be the similarity threshold
we are willing to accept. Even in the GIF
conversion we can harvest maybe
a half of them, about 70 or 80 (attributes)
in converted images to say: wow, they have
sufficient number of attributes similar to
the original image. If you look at rotated
images. Rotated images is very simple because
in a rotated image certain features wouldn't
change. It happens the first 108 features
are color features. If we rotate an image,
using any color histograms, the (color) features
would not change. Here you can say the differences
between colors are very small. And the scale
images, color pretty much remain the same.
Color distribution remains the same, but texture
and shape may be different. And similarly,
cropped images you have more varieties, right?
So let's say if we want to increase the threshold
to 0.1 (y-axis) and even in the cropped images
you can find sufficient number of similar
objects because they have sufficient number
of similar attributes. The idea to formulate
a distance function here, then is that we
actually just want to have (similar) majority,
we don't care about which attributes. So,
for GIF images you see similar attributes:
some in colors, some in shape, and some maybe
in texture. For cropped images the channels
with small differences are also distributed
in different features. Although in rotated
images, similar features tend to be in the
color channel. But once you say oh let me
give you a threshold let's say if you have
108 attributes similar out of 144, i declare
those two images are similar. Otherwise, i
say those two images
are not similar. Just using this heuristic,
we can detect all these kinds of transformed
images of the original image, very very accurately.
And when we competed with other state-of-the-art
results 20 years ago, we outperformed all
other methods, by just doing this very simple
change. The only question is how do you determine
the threshold (of similarity on y-axis)? The
threshold
should be 0.2 or 0.4 or 0.1? With some top-down
hints,
this can be resolved. You just say  i already
told you the cropped images were cropped non-substantially.
They should be similar to origin image or
you say scaled images should be the same as
the original image, you tell me that then
i can do reverse engineering to find out,
okay, given this particular set of attributes,
and given 144 features, how should i set the
threshold value so that i will accept enough
number of channels to be similar and declare
those objects to be similar.
And to write down the formula, the formula
was not too challenging. Basically, we only
have these m and r two attributes, and we
have this delta m, which denotes the smallest
of m sigmas. You find the smallest m sigma's,
m differences, and m is the threshold I just
mentioned about. So m all the 144, should
m be 85 or 108? That should be done through
data mining. Once you have m then distance
can be quantified using this we call Dynamic
Partial function. Dynamic means every pair
of objects the distance function to compute
similarity would be different;
partial means you don't need to weight all
attributes in the distance function. You only
pick the smallest deltas, or the smallest
attribute differences, to be into your distance
function. Although this method works so well,
but it's computational intensive. You need
to have all objects compared in a pairwise
manner. Therefore, I leave you the last slide,
and this could be some really interesting
long-term research. You look at our attention
model today. It's not good enough if you consider
top-down attention. The attention model today
is only doing bottom-up attention, because
we started from the lower-layer neurons then
we aggregate information eventually we have
a list of, we call features,
high level features learned at the top. Then
we do attention, and finally we get our target
task formulated. Here at the top level our
distance function is pretty much weighted
Minkowski function. Should that distance function
be modified so therefore we can do kind of
pairwise realizations support subjective similarity
measures, and support dynamic to (adapt to)
the contextual information. I think the answer
should be yes. This is an opportunity i consider
quantifiable to put system 2 above system
1.
This pretty much concludes the the lecture
today: what is consciousness. Next lecture
we'll talk about where is consciousness. You
may still feel what is consciousness, after
today's lecture even with Kaku's intuitions,
with schrodinger's quantum mechanics and the
second law of thermodynamics, you still don't
feel easy about it. But when we learn more
about where is consciousness, i think we can
feel slightly more comfortable, and that will
be (covered) next Monday. Next Wednesday Dr.
Duvvuri will come back to wrap up his psychology
or psychiatry perspectives on abnormality
and normality of of the mental state.
Any questions you can send me after the lecture
and hopefully you have made good progress
on your project. I will see you next week.
Thank you!