basically today i'm going to talk about
search i'll give a little brief overview
of the past person and future it'll be a
survey on a variety of topics meant to
familiar familiarize yourself with some
of the problems that
we see when we're working on search
so basically what is search so i'm going
to start with that um you've all
produced search engines in the past
um everybody uses search multiple times
a day
previously there were search engines
like yahoo ask i don't know if everybody
anybody remembers at least back in the
day
google of course is kind of
the dominant player in the market right
now there's also bing
there's also a variety of privacy
options coming up so for example
duckduckgo focuses a lot on private
search ecosia kind of focuses on social
good so when you search they plan trees
um i work at you.com which is a company
that's focused on personalized search as
well as private search
um so yeah there's there's a variety of
um
search engines out there but you know
search is actually even broader than
search engines so their search kind of
happening at an enterprise level within
companies for a variety of reasons like
searching internal documents if you
think about mail gmail also
in some ways as a search engine over
mail
in addition to allowing you to send and
receive mail
any forum like for example reddit has
their own search functionalities
so search is actually a very broad
problem
that affects kind of multiple
disciplines
so in order to talk about search i think
that academic discipline most aligned
with search is something called
information retrieval
so if you kind of look at the wikipedia
definition of information retrieval it's
basically defined as searching for
information in a document searching for
documents and then also searching for
other things
so they also describe in this in this
little snippet text images or sounds so
information retrieval can technically be
limited it's not limited to a single
modality although the most common form
of information retrieval and the most
useful one in daily practice is text
another definition that i find a little
bit more precise is
from
professor manning's book introduction to
information retrieval so this one is
basically defined as finding material of
an unstructured nature that satisfies an
information need within large
collections so if we kind of break this
down a little bit the first point is
finding material of an unstructured
nature
so
if you are looking for structured
information databases are very good so
search is kind of different than
database lookups um because we're
actually dealing with unstructured
information which makes it a little bit
more of a challenging or a little bit of
a different problem
and then the other point is large
collections so when we talk about search
information retrieval we're usually
operating over very large corpuses of
information if you had a small corporate
information then you may not actually
need to develop robust search techniques
does anybody have any questions on kind
of what searches and what information
retrieval is before i move on
cool so
i'll now talk about relevance so when we
think about search the goal of the
search system is to provide relevant
information to users
but as you can imagine relevance is kind
of a little bit of a subjective term
and it you know how you define relevant
and what relevance means matters a lot
and probably differs from domain to
domain but when you think about general
search um you can exit you can kind of
think about you know different types of
search categories so one might be facts
if you're looking up when was barack
obama born the relevant information is
quite obvious it's just literally the
year or date that obama was born
similarly with the what is the
population of california it's likely
going to be a number but then you know
there's also deeper levels like when you
think about population of california
are we talking about
or if it's like you know a more specific
city like san francisco are you talking
about the greater metropolitan area are
you talking about within the city itself
so you have to understand a little bit
about the intent when people usually ask
things like that they're talking about
the greater metropolitan area
but sometimes they're not so a lot of
it's actually understanding intent and
this is kind of what makes relevance a
pretty tricky
issue another one is recommendation so
if you say what movie should i watch
into a search engine
the relevant information there is also a
little bit less defined as in the fax
case so for example you know if there's
a new movie coming out
i recently watched that movie everything
everywhere all at once so i mean that
might be a good recommendation based on
recency
um so
there's but at the same time there's no
exact answers you have to take into
account popularity signals etc if you
look up best countries to visit
similarly i think a lot of this goal the
search engine becomes to provide
reputable sources so you want to have
people who really know
are travel guides etc
so you want to take into account signals
for example pagerank can be useful as
well
another type of category of searches is
something like research so for example
you know if you're typing an information
retrieval papers you're not looking for
a single answer or a single movie or a
single date you're looking for kind of a
set information
similarly if you look up how to paint a
wall
you're probably not looking for one
method you're looking for kind of
different methods and you want to find a
variety of sources and maybe even
extracted snippets from those sources to
allow you to do your job
uh similarly if you're doing a task say
you're filing immigration forms
um again search is kind of useful for
connecting people and making that type
of stuff more accessible
um is there any i guess i don't know do
that people have any questions about
relevance or
i don't know does anybody want to kind
of think of another category i might
have missed here of different types of
searches that you've done maybe today or
yesterday
so if you have questions also you can
dive into
zoom to uh
type in your question in the shared room
so we don't have questions so far but i
do have some connection later
okay yeah yeah sure i'll keep moving on
then
so
now let's talk about search systems so
when we're building a search system
there's a variety of considerations that
we can account and this applies to very
specialized search systems
um it applies to bigger search systems
as well so you know general search cases
are you know companies like you.com and
google
where we're trying to kind of service a
variety of
um you know search method like basically
a variety of queries not related to any
specific topic but really general but
you can also think of in the space of
healthcare so this class kind of focuses
a lot on ai and healthcare as well
imagine like electronic medical records
there that also can be thought of as a
search system
um there's a lot of unstructured
document and clinical notes so when
you're searching um a lot of these
considerations still apply and yeah i'll
go through some of them um but so one
would be relevant so is the information
relevant to the user so when building a
search system you'd want to kind of
benchmark and measure
how relevant the information you're
providing is a second important
consideration is latency so usually we
measure latency on the order of
milliseconds
um
because at you know at today's level you
know google has kind of trained all of
us to expect search to be really fast if
you're above you know a second or you're
measured in seconds that's often very
slow for consumers but of course this
can differ based on the discipline
but in general we want to operate on the
order of magnitude of milliseconds
um
and it could be like you know 100 to
like 600 milliseconds
again it depends a little bit on the use
case the user the system etc
user interfaces are very important for
search systems um so when we think about
a user interface i think there's two
fundamental questions that we have to
answer
one is how do we present the information
to the user um do we you know do we give
them the snippet do we give them links
do we give them
links plus content plus you know some
reviews
and also how do we accept input from the
user so do we allow people to kind of
are they asking a question for example
if you think about alexa it's kind of
you know voice based input
but if you think about you know the most
typical uses of search people are typing
into a keyboard into a little box
um so that's kind of the user interface
from the input side and then also the
presentation section
experience so one thing we think a lot
about is is the information actually
actionable so if we give you information
does it allow you to take action from
there so action can mean multiple things
in one case action might be
um you know finding the next link that
you want to click on that kind of brings
you closer to the goal you were
searching for
action might also be like you know an
actual tangible thing you might be
looking for plane tickets action might
be you know buying a plane ticket there
on the spot or if you're looking for
recipes action might be you know copying
the recipe that you want and you know
actually making a you know i don't know
banana bread that's what you were
searching for
modalities are another question so what
search modalities do we support when
we're building a search system um you
know text is as i mentioned the most
common one but there's also image search
there's you know
in terms of like you know ingesting
input you know voice recognition etc
throughput is another question so this
also depends on your intended use case
but how many queries per second can you
support
um so for certain systems if you don't
have that many users it's probably not
that important but if you have many
users and you want to scale to hundreds
of millions of users throughput becomes
very important as does cost it's another
you know another really important
consideration is how expensive is the
search isn't to maintain
and you know there's multiple factors
that can drive cost
one of which is
the most important of which is probably
going to be the indexing cost because
you have to store the information and
indexing is in general expensive because
you need it to be stored in a way that
can be retrieved very fast and it kind
of dies back into latency
so there's often kind of trade-offs
between relevance latency costs and
throughput
um so that's kind of a little bit of
some of the considerations of search
systems
does anybody have any questions on some
of these
considerations uh yeah please yeah yeah
another question again
oh okay
sorry
uh yeah i can hear you
uh
relevance and latency
like
is it
can you be considered between relevance
and agencies and then you mean you have
like if you would want to show the
showcase the most relevant um
search then you could go through like
brute force even in your recommendation
system otherwise you can do like
something like that
or is it like
i i just want to tell you if you can go
to a big defender that's how you kind of
like make this train up at eu.com
yeah yeah so sorry your voice is a
little bit grainy my my apologies but i
think
your question it seemed to be what is
the trade-off between relevance and
latency um in practice right and going a
little bit deeper onto that yeah
okay yeah yeah sure so yeah that's
that's a great question so and i'll get
into this a little bit later in the talk
when we go into some of the more
technical concepts
but you can imagine that
having as you mentioned a brute force
approach
could you know provide more relevance if
you're able to
you know look at more information within
a document and do more computation
you're likely to improve relevance at
the cost of latency one simple example
might be long documents so imagine you
have
um a corpus of 100 million really long
documents you might be able to surface
more relevant information if you
um do some type of processing that looks
across all the information across all
the documents
another approach might be to only look
at the summary
field of each of these documents so
that's a very simple example of how
one approach might have lower latency
but the other one might yield more
relevant information
but yeah there's a there's a lot i think
you also mentioned some techniques like
lsh etc like hashing
um yeah i mean there but i mean the goal
is really to provide relevant
information at low latency um so we do
want to kind of optimize on both to the
degree we can
and i'll go more into some of the
technical details there does that answer
your question or do you have another did
you have something more specific in mind
no that's good thank you
cool does anybody else have any
questions on some of the search system
considerations
okay so i'll talk a little bit about the
high-level architecture of common search
systems um so in general when we think
about search systems um there's some
steps that kind of go there's it's
almost you can think of it as a pipeline
so a query is what the user inputs into
the search system expecting some type of
relevant output so the query comes in
oftentimes we do things like query
transformation what this means is we
might want to transform the query
normalize it
um you know do multiple versions of the
query
um based on kind of what we see from
other users etc so we can transform the
query
understand the intent behind it a little
bit better
we then bring it to a retrieval system
so retrieval is usually when people talk
about retrieval we're thinking about
kind of generating a large set of
candidate documents from an even larger
corpus so you can imagine if we have
billions of documents or hundreds of
millions of documents the retrieval step
might get 100 or 1 000
of the relevant documents
and then re-ranking is kind of the last
stage where once you have some of these
documents you want to re-rank them
in an order that will be best for the
user because when we think about search
really precision and recall are very two
very important concepts
i'll assume you all kind of understand
what those are but you can imagine that
precision is really important for search
um recall is also important but
um you know when you have hundreds of
millions of documents there are likely
going to be you know more documents for
a specific topic than a user can you
know ever read so that's why precision
becomes important
if you show a user you know the wrong
document at the first link they're going
to be it's going to be a pretty poor
user experience
so precision is generally very important
but of course you want to have you know
recall be good as well and again usually
people only look at the first couple
links i think one of the things to think
about search is that it's really um
people you know are often trying to find
information very fast
you don't want to burden the user at all
so you want you know real information to
come up first but yeah so that's kind of
some of the steps in the pipeline of you
know common search systems and this
again applies across domains from web
general web search to more specific
search um within you know emrs etc
or even within mail like you know
outlook for example
so here i have a question here
yeah
so query basic can be divided into two
types one is informational query
and the other one is called navigational
query
so informational means for example you
guys have been covered nineteen
treatment
and i don't know the ground truth
so therefore precision is important
right if you're missing some
much better articles because i have no
idea their existence so i wouldn't
complain
but for navigational means something
like something i typed in michael jordan
and you give me uh the researcher
michael jordan in berkeley
and most of people will be offended
because they want to look at this
basketball player right in that
situation the recall will be critical
so
do you have to handle
uh kind of classified search type
internally or
how do you deal with the trade-off
yeah yeah that's that's actually a great
question um and again i think the things
i'm talking about are you know concepts
that are in the public domain i can't go
too much into
a lot of the specific technologies we
use but at a high level um
it is important and it depends on the
domain like as you mentioned domain can
be defined as are you searching you know
for travel or for recipes or for
you know something like academic
research that's one you know level in
which
one could classify a query the other one
is the query itself as you mentioned
there's informational and navigational
queries
um and i think one thing is you know a
lot of it comes down to
the evaluation infrastructure
um so you know when you think about
recalling precision
as you mentioned the trade-offs might be
different between the two different
types of queries
and we would want to
be able to kind of have good metrics on
both types
in general it's kind of you know
it's nice to have end-to-end systems um
having lots of you know special like
logic for different queries
um can also make sense
but you know as we see like you know
and you know this is not just limited to
search but you know just generally
um you know problems driven by ai like
self-driving it's often nice to kind of
be able to wrap everything end-to-end
and learn a lot of this
um
you know
through you know deep learning
approaches etc to avoid kind of you know
having separate classification models et
cetera but sometimes you know it is
necessary in practice so it's kind of a
difference between
um domain yeah there's a little bit of
nuance to it but yeah in general it's
definitely a good point to be aware of
and also also i think so far you talked
about search engine in general right
hopefully eventually you talk about what
the delta between you.com
and the google search
and uh
you did mention about
uh query transformation
in the end of the slide right query then
you do query transformation
i would imagine
so like query query rewriting you can do
two two or three kind of things one is
that you want to consider a person's
contextual information like location if
i type in pizza you want to say well i
don't want to display pizza in europe i
know you are in california
and the the other possibility is if i
type in toyota you say well
maybe i don't have too many results
about toyota and i can give you honda
and maybe bmw so i in addition to the
the semantic kind of expansion
or be more specific based on contextual
information
what are the kind of query
transformation
i think the search engine will perform
yeah yeah that's a great point so i
think one very simple example is spell
check
um a lot of the you know also a lot of
the point of query transformation is to
make the retrieval step easier
um so query transformation in and of
itself is not useful insofar as it kind
of helps the retrieval process so you
can think of this as being a joint
problem where the query transformation
retrieval and re-ranking all have to
work in close like lockstep with each
other
but one simple example would be spell
check um if the user misspelled
something
we can kind of you know
correct that at the queer transformation
level
and that can help with the retrieval
stage
other examples might be
adding information
if you know certain things you know
maybe that can help personalize it
if you're looking for a certain fridge
um i don't know
maybe there's some
you know based on other signals we can
kind of specify the query a little bit
more
we can also do multiple queries at once
if we want to that's kind of a more
compute heavy approach but if you want
to maximize your you know retrieval uh
you might want to
um transform it in different ways
but yeah i mean there's like a probably
a breadth of approaches those are just a
couple i think spell check is probably
the most
um intuitive example
okay
there's another question i can ask is uh
people consider not in a big data era
google is really hard to be beaten
the reason is the following because
google like in
1998 when they get started because i was
their classmates and they used page rank
right that paper was never really
published
in a conference but
the paper is well cited
and patreon everybody knows right you
have an important page lots of important
pages point to your your page then the
ranking of your page can be higher
and they found out there are a lot of
lots of spamming kind of cheating
techniques
uh so my team
uh in
2000 or so we were working on spam
fighting we want to get rid of kind of
cheating websites
but
about in 2010
and page rank
was pretty much start to be utilized
because google has already collected so
much data so
when
the user feedback to the search results
they click on let's say i give you 10
results and most of the user in
california they click on the second one
people in connecticut they click on the
third one so eventually they know well
from the user feedback
i don't i can just give you the ranking
right there i don't need to have this a
generic or universal uh
ranking system which is easy spam
so if that's true they call the system
netboost
if that's true the more data about user
you have
and the
the better the quality will be
and how can you compete with google and
i i this is this is a kvi i had another
story you know i knew
the the leader of bing.com really well
and if you trace back to be.com's
history
and
beat.com when the explorer was are still
very popular
so bean.com did the following thing and
i was
caught by google so ping.com when you do
you use explorer do a google search and
be.com will record
the search repeat of google
so that means google itself is not
recording
which one you click right what all the
search results so they can do this uh
collaborative filtering but bing.com did
not have a successful search anyway they
couldn't collect signal but they were
dominated 10 years ago on explorer
navigation navigators so they collect
that data within their browsers
and that was called by google where
google can do
this a lot of games can be played very
interesting
so how do you comment on that i mean how
can u.com you don't have a browser
and you cannot cheat and you don't have
a lot of user to start with
and uh okay so
yeah
that's it that's a great question um and
yeah that is the challenge i guess you
know
um there are at some level there are
economies of scale when it comes to
search as you mentioned user signals are
important for any search system
um i think we think that we have
some creative ways of
kind of bootstrapping and developing a
system and kind of building our
functionality in a way that
you know uses
like user signals that we get but also
is able to kind of provide an initially
good experience out of the box a lot of
it is kind of focusing on
um you know
like innovative presentations of
information etc
um having a different way of
like servicing information to the user
is a lot of it
but yeah i mean you are right that um
like you know there are advantages to
having large amounts of user data that
you can train and fine-tune models on
and you know that's what you see google
has done um as well as bing and kind of
a lot of folks who build search engines
um you know user feedback is is
obviously very important um but yeah i
mean i didn't really give a clear answer
and i can go a little bit more into
like you.com questions at the end um i
could talk a little bit about that too
if there's interest but
um
yeah i unfortunately can't go too deep
into the specific technology right now
um but
i think you know it's going to come down
to developing a good experience that
users like and draws them away from
google uh focusing on things you know
like privacy like innovative apps is
what we call them so i talked about you
right before um so we see that kind of
is interesting to users and brings them
in because it's functionality that you
can't see other places if you want to
generate code
or if you want to like you know look up
code snippets we also have an app called
um
it's basically
a code generator u code it's a i guess
like it's it's a code generation app
where you can actually generate code
using like a neural model
so these are all things you can't do in
google right now so the idea is that by
making like some key bets there along
with just lowering our foundational
strength in search and allowing for more
personalization uh we can kind of
compete so that's kind of uh the one
answer is um
you know
that different presentation
personalization as well google it's kind
of a black box um you don't really get
to personalize what you see so we can
focus on that a little bit and then also
privacy um so it's not all about just
relevance some of it's also about
privacy not tracking users
and generally kind of
being respectful so yeah those are those
are some ways in which we think we can
differentiate
okay thank you maybe more questions
later
yeah so now i'll kind of talk a little
bit about classical information
retrieval um so classical information
retrieval deals with um
like you know the kind of problem
setting is you give it a corpus of text
documents and a user query we want to
provide relevant documents in a ranked
order so when we think about classical
ir one of the most important concepts is
an inverted index
so an inverted index is basically a
common efficient data structure used to
index and support keyword search over
documents
as you can imagine
it basically is like a mapping from
words to documents
um but you can think that this might be
really sparse a lot of words may
not be used in a lot of documents
um so you kind of want to have a sparse
encoding of it and there's kind of very
efficient ways of doing this and this is
kind of very old technology it's been
used for a while and it still actually
is very useful so some questions when it
comes to inverted indices are how do you
tokenize documents
thinking about things like stemming
we can do so stemming basically means
that if you have a plural word can we
kind of normalize it into its stemmed
version and that way we can do it to put
the query and the document
um so
we can kind of be a little bit more
robust to those types of things
another you know important concept is
about calculating relevant scores from
the query and document
one common approach is called tfidf
so tf idf stands for term frequency
inverse document frequency the idea here
is that you know if a term
if you're looking up a query a query is
composed of terms if a term appears
multiple times in a document that
document is likely to be relevant
but you know if documents are
you know you know if you also have to
normalize by how often that term is in
documents so if that term is a really
common term we probably want to kind of
down weight that as well so that's what
the inverse document frequency does
so you basically multiply these two
terms and you have a score called tf idf
and you know in practice what you might
want to do is something like this where
you have a query consisted in many terms
you basically sum the score of every
single term
within the query
against the documents and you're able to
compute a score
so tf idf is kind of the very
traditional approach
in practice
bm25 is like the fancier more effective
method commonly used in large-scale
search systems
um so bm25 and if you're curious you can
kind of read more online there's it's a
little bit more of a complicated formula
i definitely recommend that you look
into it more if you're interested but
the idea is that you also penalize
longer documents so
25 also means there's like 25 versions
of it so it's something that has been
iterated on for a while and you know has
found to be effective
in doing a keyword search
we talked about query expansions a
little bit and also learning to rank is
also important learning to rank is
basically can we like train you know
very simple models based on document
fields
um to you know be able to
better provide
like improve relevance so for example a
lot of fields are textual but some are
not you can imagine likes for example as
like a popularity signal so we need to
be able to kind of learn and kind of you
know use all of these different signals
whether it's textual or non-textual
so this is kind of you know the state of
classical information retrieval
kind of the next evolution is really
neural information retrieval um or
neural ir
so as you can imagine one of the
limitations of classical ir is that
keywords does not equal understanding
um you know there's been a ton of
advances in nlp over the last five years
most significantly with the rise of
these large pre-trained language models
or large language models
which are able to kind of also
understand the semantics a little bit
better
instead of just the keywords and some of
the lexical you know
uh format of the word
um so the so basically the question is
can we take advantage of recent advances
in nlp over the last couple years and
the answer is yes so you know these
pre-trained language models or language
models produce embeddings that you can
you know that correspond to both the
queries and documents and then we can
use this in techniques like semantic
search
so semantic search is kind of asking the
question of
can we efficiently use embedding models
to search over large corpus of documents
and the answer is yeah yes so this is
actually something that's very new right
now so it's kind of the cutting edge
there's a lot of research happening here
one question you might have is when
you're doing using embeddings
you can imagine it being very compute
heavy so imagine you have a query and
you have embeddings for every single
document in your corpus that could be
hundreds of millions of documents
um you know even if you're able to
pre-compute the embeddings for the
documents you don't know what the query
is ahead of time
so you may need to if you want to just
do a very simple method you would embed
the query you compare it to every single
document and then you would surface
the top 10 documents by score
you could imagine that's going to be
very slow and latency is an important
search system consideration
so the way we solve this is using
techniques like approximate nearest
neighbor search so a ns allow low
latency to achieve from dense
representations if you're curious about
learning more you can look into this
technique called hnsw hierarchical
navigational small world graphs
and there's also open source solutions
like face
so face is you know
a way of kind of creating some of these
a n
clusters so that you can do and take
advantage of some of these advances if
you're doing embedding lookups
so yeah now i'll kind of move into a
little bit of neural ir as it relates to
re-ranking so this is a little bit
different so this is assuming that we
have retrieved k documents uh we want to
generate a score for every query
document and then sort the documents by
score
so some of the retrieval approaches we
described earlier earlier like bm25 can
generate a small set of candidate
documents that we then want to re-rank
and when we talk think about re-ranking
here
this is kind of going back to one of the
students questions earlier latency
versus performance becomes a little bit
more clear
but i'll go into a specific kind of
example of a trade-off
um but the task itself is we have a
candidate set of documents we want to
re-rank them and we can now use fancier
approaches because we don't have to look
across the entire corpus we're looking
across the subset of the corpus
so two important kind of techniques are
things called bi-encoders and
cross-encoders so by encoders are allow
you to embed
the query and the document separately
and then you can basically do a cosign
similarity or dot product etc in order
to get a score the advantage of buying
coders is that you can kind of
pre-compute the embeddings for all your
documents and you could take advantage
of advances like a m approximation your
they research
but you can imagine that um it's a
little bit limited because you don't
you're not able to kind of get
interactions between the query and
documents so that's what where
cross-encoder comes in a encoder embeds
both the query and document at the same
time
and the idea is that you pass in the
query and document through a language
model like bert and you know you're
doing interaction over all the tokens so
all the query is interacting with all
the document and you're able to kind of
get some type of score that you're able
to train and that's able to kind of as
you can imagine
be a lot better signal of relevance
but this is where latency comes into
play if you're doing the buy encoder
it's going to be fast and cheap
or maybe not cheap but it'll at least be
fast if you're doing the cross-encoder
approach
latency is probably going to be more of
a consideration
because you actually have to
pass the query and document together and
you can't really predict what the query
is going to be beforehand
so this is kind of a nice image from
this paper called colbert
i actually recommend there's a class
that's stanford called cs2020 224u i
think
in which they have a section on
information retrieval which you know
it's nice if you all have um
if you're interested in this topic um
i'm not sure if there's other i don't
think there's too many information
reveal specific courses
but there are like i guess some courses
like 224n is also probably going to be
important um which is a
nlp class but basically at a very i'll
just quickly go through some of these
paradigms so one is representation
representation based similarity that's
what i described before
we embed the query and document and then
we kind of compute like a cosine
similarity or dot product another one is
you can imagine kind of constructing
some type of
matrix based on the query and document
and then doing like cnns convolutions et
cetera
the other one i mentioned the cross
encoder approach all to all interaction
we embed the query and document together
and you can see that there's this rich
set of interaction happening and you can
use the signal at the end
and then in this paper they talk about
kind of another approach in which we uh
still kind of do something called late
interaction so you're not doing
you don't basically have to use all the
layers of the transformer you can
basically you can cache um the layers
like the last layers of the documents
and then when you embed the query uh you
select embed the query and like from the
beginning and pass it through all the
layers of the transformer but you can
use the last layers of the document and
use some type of
mathematical operations in order to kind
of simulate a little bit of the alto
interaction
so
a question here yeah uh
query seems to be pretty short compared
to the length of a document right yes
yeah the query i remember google's
statistical query typically would be
like less than three words
so in that sense the embedding of query
and the embedding of document
they are in in kind of different i would
say in different space i mean
dimensionality could be different
the query embedding
cannot be a very in a very smart space
right the very smart space doesn't make
sense
so query typically
you do a semantic classification of the
query whether the query is belonging to
let's say apple you say okay this apple
is this an i.t apple or it's a
agricultural apple it's kind of course
gram classification semantic
classification then you go for
the documents documents also classified
in cement you know semantics place but
when you talk about embedding that's
really fine grant
singularity fine when comparison i i
don't i don't know how helpful that
could be
yeah that's uh so you're basically your
question is
um queries and documents are very
different how do we and that's a great
point and i'll yeah that's actually one
of the challenges in the field is
the documents can be much longer so
there is a concept called like symmetric
search and asymmetric search symmetric
search is basically when your query and
document have similar lengths so you can
imagine that a document might have
something like a title field in that
case the query and document do live in
the same space if you define the
document to just be a title
or a very small field of document
but as you imagine documents are much
bigger so then we're dealing with
asymmetric search i think the idea here
is that you can still put them in the
same space
um but you would need to train a model
that kind of takes that into account
so there's actually a lot of uh so
sentence transformers this kind of
initiative um
and i think it's kind of yeah so they
talk they have like a lot of models um
some of which have actually been trained
on the asymmetric search task
um so i think you're you're right
um that it does pose challenges but
there are approaches that are developing
where
the models are specifically there's like
different embedders for the query and
different embedders for the document and
you can
put them into the same space so you can
do a comparison
does that kind of make sense or
that's okay i mean without any details i
think at high level i i got the idea uh
richard social right he he published a
paper his team in salesforce about four
five years ago about modeling all the
nlp tasks into just a qa model
like i i i gave an example if you say
you want to do translation you say you
can say what is the translated version
of this english document in french
friends french so
uh
in tpd3 right now they also have this
kind of in context
text learning it's pretty similar to
rich's idea five years ago
so here you have a query right if you
can
formulate query or search into a qa
model so i query something
you don't just return me to
to to point to some documents but you
aggregate the documents you summarize
relevant information within the document
and that will be much more relevant my
problem right now in a lot of searches
is i really i mean you give me the
entire paper i have to really search for
the most relevant articles i mean those
most relevant paragraphs and that's kind
of very painful
so do you do are you do you think one of
the user experience u.com will endeavor
will be
some sort like find find grand query or
find grand qa kind of kind of system
yeah i mean i think um we're probably
like whatever provides the best
experience for our users and fulfills
kind of
that need we'll definitely explore
i mean a lot of it you know a lot of
what we do right now is you can see kind
of summarize content from the web so if
you look up and you kind of see some of
our apps we do summarize a lot of the
content from the web page but i think
you're right i mean i think
there are a lot of exciting advances you
know qa models etc
that you know
um you know we'll keep investigating and
will likely um
yeah like you like but but our focus is
really on like the users and what we
think will
kind of provide like a you know an
innovative user experience
um i can't go too much into details
about like um some of the technology and
stuff but i can talk to kind of other
things happening in the public domain so
for example i think one cool thing is um
i know i think there's like a model
released by openai i think it's called
like web gpt
where they look across different
documents
and try to summarize it
one of the problems with using gpt3
is that you know there's no trust there
um jbt3 has no guarantees on its output
so if you look up when was obama born
using gpt3
you know it's kind of just it's very
probabilistic you don't really have
guarantees that the answer will be
correct
um so that's also like you know thinking
about trust thinking about you know
providing facts
and those are some of like the values i
guess um so
yeah it's a little bit it's interesting
a lot of these
neural approaches like especially the
generative type approaches
um have some pretty clear downsides but
i think that you know there's cool
research going on i know at stanford and
a bunch of research institutions
um on nlp and it's like kind of you know
proceeding at a really fast pace so it's
it's exciting
i don't know if that answered you that
probably didn't answer the specifics of
the question but yeah that's a that's a
high level answer i i kind of okay but
if you get into deep digging to find
grant
uh it's really tough but let's just what
you use your one very simple query say
okay
the war in ukraine
what is the latest status right so there
are two issues one is you need to get
relevant documents and also like you
said gp3 doesn't know whether the
document is a fake one or it's a real
one right now that's the one issue fake
or real
or credible
and number two
it's uh when you talk about one event
even covet
uh the timing is very important
uh because if you talk about if you
summarize documents even that document
is very prominent but that was published
last year
so
how do you prioritize
when you do summarization like if you
talk about the worst situation in
ukraine
perhaps the news
this morning is more important than the
news yesterday
and
at google this is a big struggle because
they
do not want to have a new website
to
show in a prominent place right away
because
they called they talked about top rights
inquiry comprising uprising results when
you have a top rising result it tends to
be a spam page
right people can scam your system
to have their advertisement
highly ranked
so this trade-off saying timeliness and
and comprising so i gave you an example
in 206 206 google started this uh
beijing branch
and there was a very kind of
interesting story the next day so we
started we had a huge ceremony press
event let's say
on may 1st okay
and on may 2nd you see baidu search
engine
you search on google whatever they show
the top result a google launch a new
division in china but google itself has
no doubt not news until a week later
because they want the information
to gain their ranks in time
so all those kind of problems will
affect your summarization quality right
those are really nitty-gritty details
yeah uh when we do research in
university we were typically saying well
you give me a whole bunch of documents
they are equally important you don't
consider citations you don't consider
timeliness or maybe some papers resolved
already been invalidated by the
future papers or something on papers
so how could one deal with that kind of
question i'm not trying to pick your
brand or get into you.com
secrets i'm trying to say there are lots
of other problems just
in addition to just the relevance
yeah you're absolutely correct i think
i mean what you stated is spot on um
there's a lot of different you know
issues i think you talked about
uh recent news being an example um like
how do you know if a query is
you know merits having a new source at
the top um that's something we think a
lot about um so we have for example
these different apps that we show some
of which are kind of news related and we
do have to think about that and you're
right it is a very nitty gritty problem
um and there's like tons of very like
little nitty gritty issues
that happen in practice that often we
don't really see in research
more at least aren't as emphasized in
research
so yeah i think that's that's a good
point
um
yeah i don't have too much to add to
what you said i think what you said
kind of summarizes a little bit of the
problems there
there are i guess you know
solutions like obviously like we can
like you know there are
you know approaches one can take so i'm
sure google for example
um looks at and tries to kind of have
some type of understanding of the query
whether this is a type of query that's
kind of an information like a news type
query etc so i think a lot of it has to
do with intent and understanding
a lot of it has to do with
other methods as well
okay great thank you
yeah so i think one really important
concept when it comes to building a
search system and again this applies to
any search system so if you're building
search for mail or search across medical
information
or search for like a like an emr system
some pretty standard
metrics are you know concepts like
average precision
so and when we talk about precision
usually in the search setting
we talk about precision at k
where k is a number of the first results
that you've returned so usually things
like k at 5 and k at 10 are important
because actually in practice how many
times you actually go to the second page
of the search results probably very few
times you're usually looking at the
first page which has around 10 results
in traditional systems
so average position is important average
recall is also kind of a useful metric
mean reciprocal rank is also an
important one
um
so and again if you want to like
actually learn more about these i would
just look them up these are pretty
standard terms but me and reciprocal
rank measures the first relevant
document um so basically if the second
document is a relevant one the
reciprocal rank is going to be 1 divided
by 2 or 0.5
and then mean simply implies that you're
going to get the average across many
queries there's concepts like average
precision which is kind of a way of
computing precision across you know
various ranked documents
um and then another one is normalized
ndcg
normalized discounted cumulative gain um
this is kind of a different type of
metric in that you're using relevance
labels
so if you can take into account not just
whether or not a document is relevant
but how relevant it is so for example
you can have like four grades one two
three four and ndcg can kind of measure
how well the search performs taking into
account the rank of the document as well
as its um
its graded scale
and again this is like a very i don't
expect you all to
understand all these metrics at a deep
level just
um from this one slide but if you're
curious you can just definitely like
look online there's tons of resources
and you can look into the formulas and
stuff to get more of a deep
understanding but the idea here is that
the metrics are averaged across multiple
queries in a test set and these are some
of the standard ones that you might want
to look more into
if you're building search systems
does anybody have any questions on
evaluating search systems
yeah so i guess on the topic of
evaluation
important so there's some publicly
available benchmarks so for example
benchmarking ir or beir
it had a really interesting table so
over here you can see that
um we off it's actually quite
interesting because bm25 which we
discussed before actually performs
pretty well even now compared to a lot
of the neural approaches so you can see
here average performance versus bm25 and
a lot of these deep learning approaches
have negative performance compared to
bm25
which is quite fascinating
um especially because a lot of them are
very specific to certain domains so even
if they do better on a domain like ms
marco
they do a lot worse on domains
like outside of that yeah they don't
transfer across domains basically so we
see that bm25
um surprises it still performs pretty
well and there are approaches like here
coming up
um and especially using bm25 plus cross
encoding seems to work really well
but we don't see that many improvements
so this is quite exciting because it
means that there's a lot of
room to grow in terms of neural
approaches
but it's also interesting because the
electrical approach is still
you know when we're looking at zero shot
performances do pretty well
um so it's a little bit of i talked a
lot about the promise of neural ir i'm
also like just briefly mentioning that
there still are a lot of limitations
and speaking of limitations some future
you know research directions one is long
document search so language models have
token limits so bert has a limit of 512
tokens
this can be quite
important when you're talking about you
know trying to understand large sets of
documents and this is why inverted
indices still work pretty well
because they're they're designed to
handle really large documents because
you're just literally looking at the
keywords you don't have to embed and
understand all of it
um that kind of brings us to the
question of how do we effectively embed
long documents for semantic search
neural remake a re-ranking so there's
techniques like long former etc that
have come out
and i think professor chang may have
talked about it in a previous lecture or
a future one when he talks about nlp
another concept is how do we effectively
chunk long documents into smaller
semantic pieces
these are all kind of topics related to
long document search
um how do we combine lexical systematic
search effectively so can we kind of
take the best of both worlds
when we get to semantic search are there
better approaches for fine tuning
embeddings different architectural
improvements training procedures
when we train you know these types of
models often you deal with triplets
which is like a query a positive example
a negative example and you use some type
of cross-entropy loss
to you know fine-tune the embeddings to
kind of be better aligned with relevance
um so how do you effectively efficiently
capture potential information with the
query and document jointly
transfer learning can that be used in
multi in ir
multi-task learning as well
kind of you know what is the the future
there
um another another kind of research
direction is learning to rank
how do we incorporate non-textual
signals with technical signals well and
then lastly i'll kind of leave it with a
multimodal search so i think multimoodle
search is going to be very interesting
but can we search within various
modalities so if you look can we
actually
provide documents as well as images at
the same time or if you want to just do
image search
and also you know maybe in more
specialized search modalities and fields
like healthcare multimodal search
becomes important a lot of healthcare
deals with images
as well as kind of unstructured text
as well as structure text so multimodal
search is kind of a very interesting
area of you know innovation
but yeah so these are some of the future
research directions and i'll just leave
it at that that's um
i've been talking for a while but i hope
you'll thank you all for listening
and i'll i'll just hang on if you have a
couple of questions
yeah thank you so much
[Music]
yeah i can hear you much better now
so i can mute right yeah
um
does it work this way yeah yeah this is
perfect
okay okay yeah i was wondering because
last time i remember when you were
presenting the um
the
uh project ideas you were saying that
currently you don't
monetize the product and you are
thinking about
um
actually doing non-personalized ads and
i was thinking whether you ever looked
as a company into stuff like the brave
browser and this association to like
crypto that you're being paid for
advertisements and what you take about
like these
um kind of like i mean it's not
necessarily search but these alternative
browsers are in their
approach
yeah yeah that's a that's an interesting
question um
also professor chang do you mind if we
just stop recording for the
this session
is this part of it