this week in virology the podcast about
viruses the kind that make you sick from
microbe TV this is 12 this weekend
virology episode 591 recorded on March
13th
2020 I'm Vincent raccoon yellow and
you're listening to the podcast all
about viruses joining me today from Fort
Lee New Jersey Dixon de Pommier hello
Vincent it's Friday the 13th Friday the
13th interesting these stores are
crowded I must say before anything else
the stores are so crowded Costco has a
line that goes all the way around it
what are they looking for toilet paper
and milk in that order also joining us
from Western Massachusetts Alan dove
good to be here and I have a public
service message stop flying so damn much
toilet paper why I went to the store
today just to do my routine shopping and
the toilet paper shelf is empty
exactly I don't understand I think
they're gonna plan on celebrating when
this is all over by throwing toilet
papering everything yes yeah it's for
the ticker tape parade they're not gonna
stop making it from Madison New Jersey
Brianne Barker hi everybody it's great
to be here been gone for a little while
but it's really nice I'm spending some
time now learning how to teach online so
my Twitter experience is coming in very
handy yeah online yet and from Austin
Texas rich Condit everybody's Fahrenheit
and cloudy here in Austin Texas and you
know being a person of elevated
spiritual status I don't need toilet
paper we have a returning guest this is
5th appearance on twit he was last year
in January from the University of North
Carolina Chapel Hill Ralph barek welcome
back
pleasure to be here Vincent and I have
15 cases of toilet paper anyone here on
this call we're the slightly inflated
price of $10 a roll Wow do people not
know that they have showers if they
really got desperate right that's right
that's right water does the trick yeah
and and paper production is not
something that is gonna get disrupted
that's just anyway what about the milk
why are they buying up milk because they
like milk is this that's a that's a
blizzard thing everybody goes and buys
bread and milk before the blizzard I
don't know why and eggs and eggs right
and they wake up the next morning they
say I guess we'll have french toast
right yeah by the way I have a little
bit of breaking news three minutes ago I
did this email just came in from the
superintendent of my daughter's school
closing the schools for our whole
district until March 27th Roger that
so even here in western asked well we
don't have any confirmed cases yet
they're shutting it down yeah this is an
excellent decision yeah I agree
yes we're trying to convince the
governor of New York City to shut down
public schools it's a little more
complicated here because a lot of these
kids don't have anywhere to go during
the day right I think that it's
important because everything else is
pretty much she is gonna have that to
deal with but that's yeah yeah well
Ralph when you joined us back in
February on the 24th there were fewer
than a thousand cases globally most of
them in China Tsarskoe v2 talking about
in case anybody didn't realize sorry yes
talk about these days exactly yeah we're
well over well over hundred thousand and
I would just want to say New York City
so far has 328 cases with no deaths and
we have a good hospital system with
capacity and the governor has been
proactive in getting a testing online
it's important for the states to be
independent anyway Ralph let's chat with
you last time one of your key points was
that
looked like czars covetous community
spread which you said is different from
SARS one and has that been borne out in
our experience I think we're approaching
150,000 cases globally in the United
States we have 2,000 cases we may be a
few cases short of 2,000 cases so
there's no question there's community
spread there's no question that there's
a symptomatic spread and there's no
question that we are now in a full-blown
pandemic and that's 2,000 known cases
that's correct there are there's no
question that there are undetected
networks and transmission chains that
exist across the country that are
infecting additional people okay so
that's really by the way Ralph thanks
for being here this is terrific that's
really critical to me because I had
questions about this so asymptomatic
spread you mean that there are people
walking around who themselves are not
experiencing any symptoms but are
nevertheless infected and can't infect
other people correct that's what I
believe yes okay correct and then there
are people of course with mild symptoms
who may have they think they have the
flu or something else and they don't
bother to get check that all in they're
spreading virus as well right that's
correct so the the asymptomatic
asymptomatic spread is really is really
critical because that means that you
can't for example if you're questioning
whether or not to convene your regular
small meeting or something you can't say
we're safe as long as you stay home if
you're feeling sick that's correct okay
and looking looking globally one of the
things that stood out to me there's a
kind of a general notion in any kind of
emergency is that no news is often bad
news and there are a whole bunch of
countries in the world mostly poorer
countries that we've heard nothing from
right I think that all I've seen is one
report from Nigeria representing all of
sub-saharan Africa I haven't seen any
other subsets there are theirs that have
actually been okay the just
but there's a there's a paucity of news
and of reports from the whole region and
from Southeast Asia and from just large
swaths of the globe and and I'm
wondering yeah why should we should we
expect those sometimes soon as somebody
trying to get there and test people
about a month ago it was fairly clear
that there were only two places in
Africa that for example that could
actually do testing for the new virus
that's change now but in reality huge
tracts and nation tracts are doing
little if any testing and so this is
this is a problem also in other
countries around the world and and I
don't know what we can really do about
it in the United States we have our own
problems with tests yes speaking of
countries in third-world countries with
that testing system Ralph if you have a
case confirmed case what's your
estimation of how many other cases there
would be associated with that I've heard
all kinds of numbers ten hundred a
thousand give us the RO or the number of
people that become infected from an
infected individual arm is is estimated
somewhere between 2.5 and 3.2 that's
actually quite high that means that for
every case there is two and a half to
three additional cases contemporary flu
is much closer to two or one point eight
one point six you know so this is very
explosive spread and rapid transmission
it's even more explosive because you
have rare individuals or maybe not so
rare individuals who are super spreaders
who can infect 1520 people
just passing through room and I'd like
to throw in a shout out to any Biogen
employees who are listening at
Massachusetts now is number one in New
England for confirmed Tsarskoe b2 cases
and the vast majority of those so far
are due to a single meeting at Biogen
headquarters near Boston which resulted
in I think 77 people getting infected
when was that meeting that was just last
week or no that was sorry that was that
was a couple of weeks ago that was yeah
that was back in February and so Ralph
thanks for being here so there is now
confirmed evidence of super spreaders
there were there was confirmed evidence
of super spreaders by the Chinese back
on the 22nd of January where they
documented a single person infecting
thirteen healthcare workers so I don't
think there's ever been any doubt that
that's been well confirmed and that's
that's fairly typical of infectious
diseases though isn't it I am less super
spreaders from what I understand are
much more rare with influenza and okay
this this is probably this is clearly
common with the emerging ground of
what's not known as weather the
contemporary corona viruses have a
similar phenotype or not and it would
actually be a very interesting model to
look at is this a property of this this
family of viruses right yeah one of the
things I've seen bandied about also is
this doubling time of cases right I
don't know where that comes from do you
have some sense of that Ralph that
sounds like epidemiology to me aren't
you in the school of Epidemiology okay
that's why I'm feeling intimidated by
the question it's like we don't
necessarily to know the answers so the
the doubling time can be affected by a
large number of things one of which is
the incubation time
so in this case we have individuals who
can Inc you may be exposed but don't
begin to show symptoms until 14 days
although most people are in the range of
5 to 7 days and they begin to show
symptoms the doubling time is also
dependent on population density probably
virus titer where the virus is
replicating in the upper respiratory
tract and exactly where in the upper
respiratory tract it may be replicating
that would help fuel rapid transmission
to contacts so in comparison for example
the incubation time and the transmission
time for flu is much much shorter so I
don't have a good answer I guess the
short answer is I don't have a good
answer for your question
ok so we have 15 million flu infections
this year in the u.s. is that is that an
is that a number that we're going to get
at with SARS go V 2 you think the first
part of that depends on how well we test
and whether we begin to do serologic
testing so for example I've heard
recently that the Chinese aren't
planning on doing serology on their
population which tells me that there's
probably significantly more infections
than the 80 plus thousand that ported
and they don't want the actual number to
be report I imagine in the US and Europe
that those numbers will eventually be
reported certainly sir logical assays
are are are available now to begin to
look at those those types of questions
the big question is what is the
denominator how many right is the
denominator two or five times or 10
times higher than what we are seeing in
terms of clinical disease right and
actually seems fairly likely that that
denominator is significantly higher
which is good news because then the
mortality rates drop
accordingly for example is over 60 male
I'm I would hope that that die not
denominator is 10 or 50 times higher
than my my risk level would go down to
about 0.1% and I feel much better about
that than a 3% trouble is that if you
age just the cases and the acquisitions
and the severity z' it puts us in a
danger zone again I'd love to know how
many people have died what their average
age was and I don't know if we know that
figure or not well from an early study
in China we do yes we do yeah does it
remain the same so if you're over 80 the
mortality rate is just under 15% if
you're 70 to 79 and mortality rates 8%
if you're 60 to 69 is 3.4%
if you're over 50 I can't remember what
it is and if you're under 50 it's around
0.4 and if you're under 30 or 25 it's
less than 0.1 what was it in Washington
though because that was a place where
there were lots of elderly and in
immune-compromised I presume and their
death rate was fairly high as I recall
and I believe there's still a
significant number of people who are
intensive care so the actual reality
where that cluster is not not clear but
again that's a unique population there's
our elder leagues that are Co housed in
close proximity probably the most
vulnerable conditions to live under in
young me or an outbreak of the I guess I
call it the mo I'll call it the
Millennial virus it's everybody else is
coming up with new name I can also pick
on the Millennials that way right during
a baby boomer you know we got to get our
revenge perfect well and since give it
given the age distribution in the fact
that people in the Millennial age group
are mostly surviving it would be would
it be appropriate to say that
Millennials are killing this virus
well I have to I have to process that
for a little bit before any given the
large number of people who may be
infected can we expect some of those
people to have immunity to be may be be
protected against this virus in the
future
almost certainly and I saw some very
interesting data from Stan Perlman the
other day who has been looking at serum
neutralization titers of MERS patients
from the kingdom from the Middle East
king of Saudi Arabia area and it's quite
interesting that people peak fairly
quickly with high neutralization titers
but then they weighing over the next
year to almost background levels were
just slightly above background levels by
the second year and with with MERS there
have been several reports of people who
ser converted they were rt-pcr positive
and then their serum neutralizing titers
and even the lyza titers went to almost
zero within a few months so the and and
it has not been well studied but it
should be studied and this is the
contemporary human coronaviruses nobody
knows how they maintain themselves in
human populations they don't undergo
rapid antigenic variation like influenza
there's not a hundred and fifteen common
cold or corona virus type genotypes or
whatever they're called serotypes sorry
Vincent I just butchered the court of
artists so one hypothesis is is that
they cause a transient immune immune
response protective immune response that
wanes quickly and then they can reinfect
and cause mild upper respiratory tract
infections and that's how they maintain
themselves so it is quite possible and
there's been there's been a number now
of reported cases in China of SARS two
infections where people were documented
to be infected
and recovered they were rt-pcr negative
they went home and then they became
reinfected a month later or so so it's
an interesting question that you asked
fortunately the you fortunately that's
not the right word please delete the
word fortunately in this case the United
States has sufficient cases that we can
actually track the sarala the serologic
responses of the individuals and their
general immune both B and t-cell
responses after infection and we can get
a handle on the the long-term immunity
that may be elicited after infection and
that's a factor I assume in what so
what's going on in China now at least
from reports I've seen is that they seem
to have seen a tapering off in cases and
of course the Chinese government is
promoting this as these draconian
measures that they implemented must have
worked another interpretation might be
that everybody who was susceptible got
infected and either immune or dead and
now the virus has burned out but
presumably that's one of the reasons
they're not going to do serology testing
there but that could that is something
that hopefully other countries will be
monitoring as this develops right I
think those are certainly excellent
points another potential point is that
the Chinese are primarily reporting
cases in their quarantine zones which
involve a hundred million people and
that the Chinese in rural communities
are not being picked up by their
surveillance systems right so this there
must be memory though it is as you say
maybe the second infections are milder
but what absolutely what that case in
the case of the contemporary human
coronaviruses they would they would
thought most the data supports the idea
that they're more they're much more mild
so that would still encourage us to make
vaccines because even then you would
have a milder secondary vaccine
right the advantage of a vaccine might
may well be that you include a an
adjuvant as a boost of immunity that
circumvents whatever anti viral gene
sets are present that are attenuating
the long term protective immune response
so Brianne do you think this is a
problem with memory or is it something
else
um it could be a problem with memory I
think that I would have to look a little
bit more closely at things like the
specific cytokines and some of the
t-cell data that we can see from some of
the patients but given the short term
persistence of the virus and the lac
sorry the short term persistence of the
immunity and the lack of antigenic drift
that Ralph mentioned I could certainly
imagine this being a problem with memory
and of course you're making me want to
run into the lab and start playing
around looking at some of this right now
let's say the global expert on that
would be stayin Perlman oh he would be a
wonderful person to have on the show
good idea
all right well and another possibility
though is that the virus just confines
itself to the very upper respiratory
tract and knows and so where it's
suddenly having to deal with the
pre-existing mucosal immune response
that is present which may be you know
may which may allow for a much more
transient infection before memory gets
boosted hmm potentially now I'm gonna
okay so when we're done I'm gonna call
my sister who's working on mucosal
immunity and ask her about it good I'm
not an immunologist so I probably
insulted half of the country how does
this stop do we have to have a certain
percentage of the population
with experience this infection and
become immune so that we develop on a
population scale an appropriate herd
immunity or perhaps seasonality a little
both when does this one what are the
circumstances under which this dies down
so this is the only way to answer this
course suspect is by speculation so
there clearly one approach is that if
you do not put in any intervention
strategies in and you allow the virus to
run its course eventually you'll hit
herd immunity levels where 70% of the
population has been infected and there's
sufficient herd immunity that protects
people from reinfection that drives the
ro of the the SARS to virus below one
and it it burns itself out and goes to
the extinction that's a brutal way to
handle a new emerging infection
basically everybody has to get infected
so so a better approach is to implement
Public Health intervention strategies
where you dampen the transmission rate
of the virus and reduce the number of
infections such that the number of
potential contacts that are available
for infection are significantly reduced
and that can also help to burn out the
outbreak ultimately I think long term
protection of the human population is
going to require herd immunity to reach
about 70% in our population and that is
it's gonna that's either gonna have to
be through natural infection or
vaccinations make sure that right
vaccination would presumably be the more
humane way to accomplish that my
preferred choice yes yeah Ralph do we
have a good understanding of why the
original SARS outbreak burned itself out
sure there are three drivers for the
original SARS outbreak the first was
that we had a known animal resident
or which were civets and raccoon dogs
that were transmitting virus to people
in open markets so if you call all those
animals and close the open markets that
was the you effectively blocked that
transmission chain the second
transmission chain was that hospitals
were acting as in essence of
amplification centers where patients
would inoculate other patients and
healthcare workers who would inoculate
other patients and to stop that barrier
nursing had to be employed rapidly and
dramatically and that reduced the the
opportunity for hospital settings to be
major amplifiers of disease and then the
third was that SARS coronavirus
transmitted 24 to 36 hours after you
developed clinical disease consequently
quarantine and contact tracing allows
you to isolate those people in
sufficient time so that they couldn't
transmit and the combination of all
three blocking all three pathways or
transmit transmission chains led to the
vro or the reproductive rate of the
virus to fall below one and went extinct
Wow we we don't have any we don't know
what the animal reservoir is for SARS -
and importantly what people aren't
thinking about is that as you have a new
emerging virus that has a novel receptor
binding interface as compared to SARS
circles the globe opportunities for new
animal reservoirs hmm are now in the
United States and Canada and South
America and Africa and Europe and so we
could suddenly see through some common
animal in the United States being a
reservoir for this virus for the future
and so that's something that we need to
look at as far as I know no one is
looking at that in the United States or
elsewhere went from animals to humans in
China then circled the globe in humans
and now the main reservoir it presumably
as humans but as you point out
that's a really interesting possibility
that we can then infect animals in our
environment that then become future
reservoirs including bats including bats
including bats and so the virus could
cycle back in and then begin to undergo
recombination and mutation driven
selection to pool out new variants that
could come out again in the future
so what species in nature do we know
about that harbour coronaviruses now
said all over the place if a mammal or a
bird it's probably got a corona virus in
it right but stars like corona viruses
SARS like carnal viruses are in bats and
also panda lands yeah turns out and Peng
so true so as far as you know our other
Chinese are people in China I was told
not to say the Chinese scientists people
in China working to still find out what
the animal that transmitted the
infection was because we know it was
originally in bats because of the
sequence homology but what was the
actual immediate transfer right right as
far as I know they have they have not
identified the actual reservoir species
the closest there were there were
reports about panda lands as potentially
being the intermediate host but panda
land viruses or 88 90 percent identical
to SARS - in comparison civet and
raccoon dog strains of SARS coronavirus
were 99.8% identical the SARS
coronavirus from 2003 in other words
you're talking about a handful of
mutations between civet strains raccoon
dogs drains and human strains in 2003
panda lands have over 3,000 nucleotide
changes no way they were the reservoir
species absolutely no chance
okay so it's unknown I know they're
looking yeah but I don't believe they
have found it yet or if they found it
the paper has not been published yet but
it does raise that it does raise the
important question that other reservoir
hosts could become very important for
maintaining the virus
human populations throughout the globe I
know we talked about this last time but
I'd like to revisit as a check
seasonality is there what's your
expectation or understanding about
potential seasonality for this virus
that is as the weather changes will it
have an effect on the infection it
should reduce the ro rate it won't drive
it to extinction I don't believe so the
the typical peak season for
coronaviruses are early winter to early
spring SARS for example peak cases were
in April and even very high numbers of
cases in May through the end of May the
virus went extinct SARS coronavirus went
extinct by the end of July summertime
will reduce the rate of transmission and
so these explosive amplification
probably won't occur but the virus will
continue to spread into human
populations
it does somewhat use the rate so
sunlight warmer temperatures humidity
all reduce the the viability of virus on
surfaces and contacts bread is probably
an incredibly important means of
spreading the virus from person to
person so what's happening right now in
the Philippines there are trying to make
sense of this okay a great great
somebody's gonna get rid of it but what
happens or Iran yeah or Iran or
Australia where it's currently summer
all those are true all those are those
are very very good points there was a
case in Brazil - so right like I said if
I'd to be very clear that it would not
stop the spread of the virus it may
reduce the rate of spread
of the virus now if you have very dense
populations in close proximity that's
going to be mitigated by the sort of the
human population demographics of each
area I think also the immunity levels
make a big difference there's zero
immunity right there's zero immunity
across the globe so that's going to also
make a big difference so the idea that
the virus will go extinct in the
summertime is not going to happen I am I
am holding out hope maybe that's the
better way to say it I am holding out
hope that the rate of transmission goes
down in the summer which would make it
more vulnerable to Public Health
intervention strategies and I and I
guess we'll see a combination of things
since the virus emerged in the late
winter by summer we should see herd
immunity in most populations worldwide
starting to emerge and at the same time
we'll have the increasing temperatures
and humidity maybe a combination of
things is gonna going to help drive it
down and school gets out well know
school now that this rate right and I
think those are all important features
that would that would help sure we
should point out that flu influenza is
seasonal in temperate climates like ours
but it's also seasonal in the tropics
and we have no idea what drives that
seasonality right because in temperate
climates it's as ralph said
low humidity low temperature but in the
tropics it's hot and humid so what's
going on there Ralph what's the fraction
of roughly that droplet transmission
versus that contact for SARS Cova - do
we know unknown okay but both make a
contribution right I believe so I think
the the cruise liners have clearly
demonstrated that's the case there were
examples of workers who were putting
trays down in front of people's rooms
who weren't coming out because they were
mmm sort of like germaphobes
but they were still getting infected mmm
what about fecal oral transmission well
it's a real possibility mmm that
happened with SARS one right
did the Amory Gardens outbreak was a
community condominium that aerosolized
feces when you flush the toilets and and
that went into the ventilation system
and infected people on multiple floors
of that building in fact the plumes of
aerosolized virus feces mixtures drifted
out of the building out of the top of
the building on to other condominiums
and infected people in them as well so
it is certainly possible plumbers can
save lives that's right now we come back
to toilet paper yes now we come back to
toilet
well you wonder about things like the
restroom facilities and Airlines and you
know on airplanes mm-hmm pretty big
vacuum there does that generate an
aerosol or not
well it's interesting Lee it's not a
it's not exactly a vacuum it's the the
air pressure is being directed sort of
downward and into a holding tank
contrary to what some people believe
that it's not actually flushing to the
outside so so I would expect oh so I
don't have to look up when I walk around
anymore seven oh right so so most most
airplane Oh in fact it's a it can cause
a major disaster if any of that holding
tank content leaks out and puts ice on
the outside of the plane but I would
expect actually airplane lavatories to
do a pretty good job of aerosolizing
material and hopefully the treatment
chemicals are as effective against SARS
go v2 as they are against other better
known pathogens I think an airplane is
not where you want to be right now most
no definitely don't forget our program
and some we should we mentioned last
time that you know the air is mostly
recirculated we have an email about that
where basically they don't take in a lot
of air from the outside because it's
expensive to heat it up so you're
getting a lot of recirculation so I on
this topic we had an arc years ago about
the difference between airborne and
aerosol I aerosolized
I don't know
what words to apply here but this is
there's different degrees of this right
when you talk about droplet transmission
you're talking about virus on air at
least briefly airborne droplets but that
don't stay suspended in the air and drop
but rather drop to the ground or
whatever ultimately correct um as
opposed to the word I'm gonna use
correct me if I'm wrong is airborne
where you have particles that are so
small that they can be maintained
airborne for a long period of time and
long distances am i talking sense here
that's correct as far as I understand it
yes that's and and so where does
coronavirus and I assume that this is a
continuum right different droplet sizes
different times in the air different
distances that they can travel not a
black and white thing what's your
understanding of where the corona
viruses fall in this everyone that I
hear talk that discusses this concept
always our argues that it's large
droplets spread okay that's the major
mediator of disease I think I
fortunately people kind of use aerosol
interchangeably especially a mass media
right and it's not rice correct right
that's one of the reasons I wanted to
bring this up not only for my
understanding but for other people's
understanding as well because there's a
you know this really impacts on how you
how you think about the transmission
that's all I mean I would assume based
on that that recirculation of air in an
aircraft in an aircraft would not
necessarily be a huge source of virus
but a but I don't you know I don't
really know how aerosolized or airborne
particles behave in that circumstance
but I think of
droplet transmission as something that's
not going to stay suspended in the air
for very long or over very large
distances I think with SARS the few
examples of transmission on an airplane
the radius was about six to eight feet
from an infected individual [__] mm
okay so not a lot of roll for air
circulation that's right okay of course
this is a new virus yeah right we don't
know it's a new day it's a new day you
know we haven't seen anything like this
I don't think in a hundred years
certainly no one has also explained how
super how super spreaders infects so
many individuals troops so are there are
these rare individuals that can that can
drive airborne spread you think it's a
matter of dose in a droplet that you get
where I think
I think certainly there's there's
probably some infectious dose what
exactly that is is not clear but but I
believe in the in in Canada there was
one example of a super spreader who
simply walked through an emergency room
that was packed that was fairly packed
with individuals and infected 19 people
in the less than the 15 seconds they
were in the emergency room as they walk
through it wow that's like measles
that's like measles yeah so has there
been have there been studies done on
whether super spreaders have higher
titers than others oh I don't know I'd
have to check the literature I don't
they certainly had documented four or
five cases of super spreaders with SARS
I believe the the Saudis have also
identified ten to fifteen cases of super
spreaders that they probably have that
data whether there's sufficient numbers
to make it significant is is a is an
open question we talked a little bit
about the actual
infection so you know there's mild
infections more serious when people are
getting more serious infections we have
pneumonia I because of the viruses in
the lung so what's happening when the
virus gets down there so as he as he
mentioned 83% of the cases seemed to be
mild without any requirement for
hospitalization about 17% require that
are typically could be hospitalized that
require some sort of respiratory support
so the virus causes a pneumonia the
virus specifically it the most severe
cases that develop a disease called
acute respiratory distress syndrome are
at extremely high risk for lethal
infections and the virus replicates in
cells lining the airways especially the
smaller Airways as well as the alveoli
although I they've only been to
pathology reports and so this is based
on limited information what most likely
happens in the alveoli is it destroys
type 2 and type 1 cells that line the
the airway epithelium exposing the
alveoli to fluids that can diffuse
across the capillary beds and result in
flooding of the capillary bed and this
results in drowning in essence here your
little balloons that transmit oxygen to
your red blood your bloodstream become
water balloons and so you drowned in
your own fluids the repair system can
also go a little bit out of whack and
that's a highly highly a few minor
medical terms out of whack yeah there's
a problem I like the end and patients
can undergo a pro fibrotic response with
layer down multiple layers of fiberglass
cells on the interface and between the
alveoli and the capillary bed and this
results in multi cell thickness layers
of cells and the oxygen now can't
diffuse across it to get into the red
blood cells to oxygenate your tissue and
now it's death by suffocation both cases
you end up with hypoxia that leads to
multi organ failure and then death it's
and this is this is pretty typical viral
pneumonia right
not all viral pneumonia is lead to acute
lung injury okay is this similar to what
SARS one did is it's exactly the same
disease phenotype that SARS and MERS do
as well as h5n1 and h7n9 so all of these
viruses well it's a similar acute
respiratory distress syndrome the NIH s
but literally spent hundreds of millions
of dollars trying to figure out how to
treat this end-stage lung disease and
they've actually done quite a quite a
good job of reducing the mortality rates
from 50 percent where it used to be a
couple decades ago to about 25-30
percent now but it's still a very very
difficult disease to manage clinically
and are we seeing are we seeing people
getting secondary bacterial infections
with this know it the cause of death
seems to be exclusively viral pneumonia
leading to a Q lung injury without any
evidence of secondary bacterial
bacterial infections qualities well is
there a role for a cytokine storm say in
any of this pathogen kind of storm
certainly plays a role in that whole
process of acute lung injury yes and and
why are kids less than nine not having
any of these issues do we understand
exactly my question
that's a great question they have very
high titers of virus they have there's
no reason I mean they they should
transmit efficiently to those around us
around them which is a good reason why
we should close schools to protect their
parents not
yes exactly and don't forget their
grandparents my grandkids are with us
today that's right grandparents being a
grandparent yes I'm in favor more
grandparents in the world so your are
the spoilers that's right
so that's right that is our role yeah so
Souter a child like that was a super
spreader I don't think anyone has done
enough work to know the actual burden of
spread that's associated with young
children at this time in the in the
expanding pandemic
I believe that data will be out there
and I believe believe that the contact
tracing is occurring that will inform us
but I have not seen the papers that
doesn't mean that they haven't been
published yet but I think we're going to
find some very very important
information about that in the coming
months why did what they get back to why
children don't don't experience their
severe disease when they examine the
lungs of the children by x-ray or other
non-invasive approaches they are clearly
diseased and they are they're clearly
infected and have pathology in their
lungs but they don't show any symptoms
why is that part of it may be related to
the ACE two molecule the the receptor
for the virus which plays an important
role in homeostasis but exactly how that
could contribute is it's not clear so I
don't know the answer to the question I
know that the Aces of the cygnets phylum
of AIDS I mean do they did they develop
fevers I don't know the answer I should
know the answer that question but I
don't know the eye does anyone else on
this on the comments I I don't know the
one thing that I have seen from Sally
Parmar who is a pediatrician and
infectious disease specialist at Duke
was that she was speculating that
perhaps there were actually
physiological differences in children's
lungs
that were causing some of the difference
I was talking to another well-known
violinist who was explaining why RSV
might be more severe in the lungs of
children and it was because the Airways
are smaller so these cells of the air
whit them when the airway epithelial
cells slough off then that clogs the the
airways and prevents oxygen exchange
SARS and this SARS 2 virus grow very
well in primary human airway cells and
they cause the airway epithelium cells
to slough off but that would that would
have a tendency to drive you know based
on that hypothesis and SARS too should
be causing much more severe disease and
obstructive disease in the airways much
like RSV and that's not what's being
seen so okay I don't know it's it's a
fascinating question but it may reflect
also the biology of these viruses in
general corona viruses infect young
children and cause mild disease most of
us become immune to the kemper
contemporary corona viruses within the
first few years of life and that
immunity may well be saving us as adults
from viruses that are much like emerging
corona viruses in terms of they have an
innate capacity to cause much more
severe disease as a function of age
they're saying there may be cross
reactivity of some extent between I'm
saying that we as a scientific community
have defined contemporary human
coronaviruses as mild common cold
diseases yeah when in reality the all of
these emerge from animal reservoirs yeah
a hundred eight hundred years ago and we
have no idea how severe they were an
adult and naive adult populations most
likely they weren't they were probably
brutal diseases just like SARS MERS and
SARS - are mm-hmm
adult individuals who as they get older
and that actually if that hypothesis is
true then the prediction would be that
as SARS - goes around the globe
and infects the adult population we will
become immune and the virus will now
preserve itself in the population by
infecting young children who don't get
serious disease as they grow up they are
pre immune and so they never get serious
disease and SARS too will now be
relegated to the role of being a benign
common contemporary coronavirus that
somehow lost its pathogenic potential
when the real reason had lost its
pathogenic potential is that all the
dark adults are now immune yeah got it
if that's the case then we have a one
two three a year pandemic that we will
be facing until sufficient herd immunity
occurs to drive the virus into this into
this catalyst this type of persistence
mechanism ma minh populations until the
next one comes about that's right and an
important thing to note is that there
are two human coronaviruses that are in
the group one that are very closely
related in group one there are two human
coronaviruses in the group two a current
cat a phylogenetic grouping that are
closely related and both are both cases
they Co circulate in human populations
and don't appear to provide cross
immunity so a single SARS like virus
colonizing the human population will not
protect us from another one hmm it
sounds like good reason to do more
research on the whole family of viruses
right and and to that I would say we
probably didn't learn enough from SARS
and MERS because we didn't have enough
work going on or not surveillance in
pathogenesis and so forth would you
agree with that I would SARS SARS came
in and went so quickly that certainly
commercial interest dropped off at an
exponential rate
the virus emerged in 2002 caused 8,000
cases in 2003 and four case
in 2004 and then it was gone and so so
at the same time it of following that
same arc that was the arc of commercial
interest and it was also to some extent
the arc of of NIH interest in developing
vaccines and immunotherapy DEQ's for the
shelf that could be used in in future
outbreaks our own research has shown
that there are SARS like bat strains
that vary by at least up to 22 percent
probably up to 35 percent that are
poised to use the human receptors and
probably can grow really really
efficiently in primary human airway
cells we know that for a fact with MERS
there are two murders like viruses that
differ by 35 percent it can use human
dpp-4 receptors and grow to equal titers
in primary human airway cells and also
you it want to ask the question well
what's what are the biological features
and what's the transmissibility pattern
and how transmissible is this other
emerge like strain from china that is 35
percent different is it a sarge - in the
making or is there something in between
that that would be perfectly poised to
cause a pandemic like SARS - and the
answer is they're probably out there in
nature and it's just a question of time
between before human a human comes in
contact with the bat that has sufficient
titers to allow that individual to be
infected and then that individual go to
a location that allows for the spark to
start the fire of the next pandemic so
even if you stop the sale of meat at
these markets there will still be
contact with humans and bats so that's
correct no it's not gonna this outbreak
could have been caused by person living
in rural China who came in contact with
a bat in a bat cave either collecting
guano or doing
just by random chance with bats flying
over and they went to Wuhan and they
actually started the outbreak without
without the seeding this thing through
an open market setting in the bats by
the way who are infected with SARS like
an MERS like coronaviruses where is the
virus replicating in them and does it
cause any problems to them
most of the data argues that it's an
enteric pathogen hmm
there haven't there have been there's
been some work done on this by I believe
lint fought Weng
but in general there hasn't been much in
the way of studying coronavirus
replication and pathogenesis in in bat
species and and to some extent that's
driven by the fact that you have to have
the right type of bat right to allow for
infection so if it's an enteric virus
and bats than any contact with guano
could potentially spread it that's right
and we know it's in guano because most
of the collection is guano that's taken
back to the laboratory right where the
RNA is then extracted and then used for
deep sequencing what's the status of
vaccine development Ralph we may have
discussed this in the past but where do
we stand are there in particular are
there reasonable candidates out there
anything from SARS that have been in
human trials and I'm also interested at
the potential for complications from
antigen dependent enhancements and that
causing issues are with the vaccines so
I think I think there are at least two
major candidates that are moving forward
rapidly towards phase 1 trials and one
is an RNA based vaccine and the other is
recombinant protein based vaccines the
RNA based vaccines are known to induce a
strong th1 immune response which is good
because alum when alum was adjuvant
with SARS coronavirus vaccine it induced
a strong th2 immune response that was
associated with large amounts of immune
pathology the characteristic cells
aureus inner fills and neutrophils that
are seen in especially eosinophils
although the Ascenta fills are probably
not doing the damage it's mostly
cytokine based storms right and TNF
alpha and other things I believe that
are causing most of the tissue damage
but if anybody would like to elaborate
on that I would like to hear it so by an
RNA based vaccine we're talking about
essentially a messenger RNA encoding a
spike protein that's delivered maybe as
an Olympic nanoparticle or something
like a right okay so I don't know the
actual formulation in terms of the in
terms of the the delivery the delivery
vehicle yes right that but that one is
probably going to be first to market
simply because of the the speed of
production of that vaccine and that it's
one of the reasons that's one of the
ones early in trials is that they had
this platform and all they had to do was
plug in the sequence and and you know
make a bunch of RNA and now they can go
you know start start trials and that
hopefully is where kind of vaccine
research at least some of it is going in
the long run anyway some sort of
platforms that allow for rapid
development of vaccines rather than
having to mess around with these
complicated viruses very much so right
that's true and we are actually involved
in some of those clinical trials okay
you're using in terms of the prion
pre-ind work done in animal models and
it's fortunate to hear that they induce
the th1 response that seems to be
protective in this particular case
that's right yes so there we have an
email which will be later but it's from
a person who knows about vaccines and
they say that if if this one is licensed
in 18 months that would be a record yeah
right that's correct but that's a kind
of platform that
be associated with that although that
probably would not impact this current
outbreak right Ralph I don't know the
have not been engaged in the discussions
about what the timeline for phase 1
phase 2 and phase 3 testing are if I
were involved in it I would probably be
arguing that we need to have phase 1
trials that are probably done in
parallel with some of the animal testing
and that we try to be positioned to do
some type of phase 2 trial and
populations by October November so that
individuals will be an immune prior to
the next round of infections hmm so how
about the complication of antibody
dependent enhancement I have heard that
there have been some observations in
animal models that this phenomenon of
mmm poor immunity winding up enhancing a
real infection something like it has
been observed in animal models and that
seems to me it could complicate the
vaccine development recalling the
respiratory syncytial virus vaccine that
failed because it enhanced disease from
natural infection or the dengue vaccine
or the dengue virus uh-huh the dengue
vaccine is a good example of a de and
the RSV vaccine I think was mostly th2
driven immune pathology okay so the
classic example in a corona virus with
AD is feline infectious peritonitis
virus and the FIP vaccines induce a
antibody response that allows the the
antibody coats the virus and allows for
more efficient affection of macrophages
and monocytes cell populations and this
results in much more severe disease the
the SARS data and SARS and data is much
more controversial there are a couple of
reports of people being able to use to
demonstrate antibody and
asmin of an infection of monocytes or
reporter actually reporter cells it's
expressing FC receptors with various
antibodies in cell culture there's been
one report in primates of an ad e like
phenomena that was reported in china but
has not been replicated anywhere and so
the community i would have in general
the community's speculative is the ad e
phenomenon is more speculative and
probably controversial okay having said
that they clearly have to look for it
yeah right okay so so that's one of
those things that you might look for in
animal models you know we have good
animal models for this viral infection
right now the only real animal model is
a human ace two transgenic mouse
they were made in probably three
laboratories for laboratories around the
world back around 2004 to 2006 most were
cry were preserved they were the the ace
two molecule was either Express from CMV
promoter or tissue specific lung
promoters didn't really matter too much
the consequences of this were the same
the virus would replicate in the lung
and around day six it goes to the brain
and causes a fatal encephalitis so we
have one of those models we had sent it
a couple years back to a group of
investigators in at the Institute of
ayala G in Wuhan and they have a paper
that they've just recently submitted on
this model that I'm also an author on so
that model of that paper is under review
so remember with SARS you had to mouse
adapt the virus to infect those
transgenics is that correct that's
correct
same with SARS Co v2 with SARS to will
not replicate in mice we've tried
collaborative cross
I mean a deficient mice wild-type
regular laboratory mice mmm
if you look at the interface of the
receptor binding domain of this virus to
its receptor there are specific residues
that would be predicted to convert the
SARS to strain to a mouse adapted
strains using the worst genetics I
remember when the first paper came out
of the Wuhan lab they had a bunch of
cells where they had put in human ace 2
and the mouse cells that did not
replicate that's correct
and human and the bat and some others
did so I set up problem for a transgenic
model right yeah right so I know that
some groups are developing knock ins
mm-hmm were probably we are approaches
to use the existing human HT transgenic
mouse model in the lab as well as
working towards Mouse adapted strains
all right it's been an hour Ralph and
any quick questions from anyone before
we say goodbye all right really
appreciate it Ralph that's this was
awesome awesome so much thank you you're
all being very generous just a pleasure
to talk with you all and you have a
great weekend and stay safe and support
your local efforts at implementing
Public Health a barrier approaches to
prevent the spread of the disease yeah
good point and rally doing it will you
come back again oh sure I will do I'll
be glad to okay thanks a lot ruff okay
thank you so much
wow I'm blown away I I'm still thinking
about what he said about establishment
potentially in some other animal
reservoir spill really got me no better
no better yeah very interesting but we
have other issues right now right yes
other coronavirus issues it's it mean in
the u.s. is just getting started really
right so
we have a ways to go all right and we
have a lot of email but I wanted to
touch on just a few things very briefly
first is there is a paper submitted to
New England Journal you can find it on
med archive so we have bio archive and
med archive another place to check but
that's fine and it's all about the how
long infectivity lasts in various
situations this comes out of Rocky
Mountain labs Vincent monster's group
and also people at Princeton and UCLA so
they looked at Tsarskoe v2 and Tsarskoe
v1 and they measure infectious virus and
they look at both detection limits and
half-lives in aerosols and these are all
generated in the laboratory so it's an
artificial aerosol I don't know how fine
the particles are but you know they
mentioned it briefly in the methods yeah
I spent some time looking at the methods
and they mentioned something about
particle sizes but they also talked
about how it was made in a Goldberg drum
and I don't couldn't figure out what a
Goldberg drum Rice all right well they
make an aerosol or they put the virus on
various surfaces like copper cardboard
steel and plastic and they say what's
the half-life of infectivity what's the
detection limit and I was talking to a
reporter this morning and I gave her all
these numbers and she said that doesn't
mean anything to me what's the bottom
line
bottom line is it lasts long enough that
transmitted an aerosol or on surfaces
yes mm-hmm
that's the bomb and it lasts it lasts
longer on some surfaces than on others
it seems to last longest on plastic and
steel not quite as long on cardboard not
forget long on copper and only a few
hours as an aerosol yeah not
indefinitely no this is all it's the
drops below the detection limit after
the longest was 72 hours on plastic
right yeah and and it was interesting
they compared since they're comparing
new cyrus to classics ours here the new
czars last longer on in most of these
assays
speaking peace speaking of classic stars
that kind of reminds me of classic rock
right you know my wife told me now my
wife listens to Sirius and that there's
a coronavirus channel on Sirius XM play
they don't play they talk for all time
okay they just play interviews with
people they should play on there I know
they don't want us but well they I don't
know if they want to sign up but they
should in fact you know Columbia radio
station should be playing Twitter 24/7
right I think that that last hour with
Ralph is probably the most informative
thing we've ever done that was
incredibly that was then I think that
with Daniel Griffin last week on the
clinical ass deals with stuff that we
don't know anything about yeah I would
say that this past hour with Ralph the
episode with Daniel and the previous
episode with Ralph are where I feel like
I've learned most of what I know yes so
with Ralph so I think we should ran
father Claus even as a grandfather so
one of the things that just as an aside
interests me about this stability paper
and this is a phenomenon that's been
known for sometimes why they test it is
that things don't like pathogens don't
like Connor right that's right it
wouldn't it would make sense to make
everything in hospitals out of copper
out of copper at least high-traffic
things like bed rails and doorknobs and
that's what Michael Schmitt is doing he
does clinical trials to assess the
effect of lining these surfaces and
hospitals on copper and it certainly
brings down hospital-acquired infections
we did yesterday on twit a paper
published a couple of years ago on
coronavirus two to ninety one of these
Coronas that caused common colds and on
copper the infectivity is lost like in
seconds when you put it on it when it's
mixed with mucus I think it really in
activates it and so it's quite
antimicrobial and anti viral so so just
make your clothes out of copper right
just go out at the cop of armor and
there you go
so then
is the nice paper in The Lancet that I
saw this this week where they studied a
number of cases in China and they said
what are the biggest comorbidity risks
for getting very serious disease and the
biggest risks risks are hypertension
diabetes and coronary heart disease
which is like half the American
population exactly and so China the
patients who died typically or had the
most serious disease had those issues
and I think for me that's the driving
issue right now not that there'll be a
lot of infections because as ralph said
83% of them are mild but the most
serious ones need hospitalization and we
don't have enough ICU beds to take care
of people if we suddenly get millions
and millions of cases right right well
and that's the logic of canceling
everything because if we can yeah yeah
it may be that everybody is eventually
going to get exposed to this or at
seventy percent of the populations
eventually gonna get exposed but if that
happens next week then we're gonna have
a problem if that happens over a period
of a couple of months yeah exactly then
it's gonna be a slower trickle of people
going into the hospital and by the time
they need the bed it's emptied out from
the previous person and they'll be able
to handle the capacity so that's trying
to slow it down is a big emphasis now
yes exactly
hashtag flatten the curve yes and then
there was a Lancet article this week
maybe today out of Italy where they
predict 30,000 cases next week and that
will completely saturate their ICU bed
capacity which they'd never seen 15,000
113 right now I'm looking at the Johns
Hopkins site so just have to double it
and that's why the mortality rate is so
high if you can't handle the patients
they will die right and yeah if you can
give them good health care just like the
Ebola outbreak right when they came to
the US they survived it's a similar
situation so Italy Italy is reputed to
have a pretty good health care system
they do they're getting overwhelmed but
they don't have enough ICU beds as I
said we have 95,000 here in the US and
you know that's 10 million cases would
saturate
right am i doing if they were 1% I think
that's right yeah I think so all right
you want to do some email sure sure
all right so I'll just take Ann's who
writes a link to a link to the
comprehensive info about kovat 19 our
world and data yes this is a very nice
site with lovely statistics of all sorts
of things not just Covey's 19 I use it
for polio and HIV and AIDS and so forth
so that's really nice and and then I'll
take Volkers here are my current
questions not yet answered by your
incredible useful service to the public
pretty early in the year was mentioned
that retrospective analysis that
identified a kovat case not linked to
the fish market oh so any updates about
where the virus came from is it the fish
market so Ralph said we don't know right
we yeah it may not have been from the
fish market it may have gone into the
fish market and then spread there and
Ralph outlined the scenario that was
very realistic of somebody in rural
China catching this directly from a bat
and then going to Wuhan and bringing it
there and I mean maybe it was even a
farmer at the market who you know then
went in and spread it to people at the
market we just we don't know the the
data that was meant that this person
mentions about the retrospective
analysis about a case in early December
not connected to the fish market is
still the data that I reference yeah
we're talking about this they said how
do you interpret the evolution in China
is there already an effect of herd
immunity due to earlier spread and I
would say we don't know as as ralph said
because they're only reporting in the
quarantine zones so we don't know what's
going on elsewhere right now there are
just like ten or less cases a day in
China and reported reported hoarded and
apparently they're resuming slowly life
isn't usual if there isn't a lot of herd
immunity there will be another outbreak
I would think so
he said could you cover the effects of
potentially overwhelmed health systems
well we are not experts about that but
yes that's a problem and that's the main
concern right now which has happened
which happened in Wuhan early on which
happened in Italy and Iran and contrast
to South Korea
yeah the fatality is less than 1% and
probably a big part of South Korea's
success was that they took it very
seriously very early and implemented
implemented the the sort of self
quarantine social distancing type of
protocols immediately and they they
weren't I gather being a democracy they
weren't quite as draconian about it as
China was but they were they were
proactive and got on top of things early
and that gave them a flatter curve that
allowed them to deal with what was
happening and also they have an
excellent health care system situation
in Munich far too warm for mid March
schools will be closed from next Monday
companies are training or already
implementing emergency plans in the
shops you missed three things
disinfectants noodles toilet paper paper
- oh we are actually out of all three of
those things in our own supermarket here
in New Jersey that's exactly the same
staple
I think it's because it's a quick meal
that also is gonna keep well yeah okay
Alan can you take the next one
sure Josh writes dear Twitter's I've
been enjoying a recent coverage of the
corona virus and wanted to ask question
is it possible this corona virus has
been in circulation in the US for a time
already and we're not only now seeing
cases because we're testing for them
when we were not beforehand please
forgive this question is been asked
previously please forgive us this that
asked previously and I can guarantee
that it was here before we started
getting positive deaths i given given
the rate at which testing was being done
early on in the US and the the the risk
the testing response by I'm sorry I'm I
know we have listeners at the CDC and
there are a lot of good people there
doing there
but the CDC testing early and this was
just just not up to snuff and first the
infection was Washington in January
right the US yeah I think so yeah
there there's been some data where
people have looked at the sequence of
virus from some of the patients in
Washington and tried to determine how
long the virus was circulating how many
differences had happened and it looked
like the virus had been there about six
weeks at that point right for sure yeah
so it was it was here well before we
knew it and we have not handled this
well at all as as a country and then
Josh Peters is on a lighter note I told
my colleagues that I was going to quit
my job and follow a twig on their tour
around the world they just said what's
twig and that's part of the problem have
a failure to communicate but the 12 tour
around the world has been postponed yes
no we're not having this for sure was
that gonna ask we're still not testing
enough right now or not or not I mean
states are starting to take over so here
our governor has implemented and gotten
testing by private companies and as I
said he's the we're starting drive
through testings here that's great so
basically if you're a state you should
do it on your own because you're not
getting federal guidance sadly yeah
Brianne can you take the next one
sure Cindy writes along with being a
longtime Twix lover I'm a police officer
in a small New England town our
resources aren't as sophisticated as I
would imagine population centers are I'm
usually the only officer in my town when
I'm working and I get dispatched to
every emergency medical call for a
typical emergency say heart attack I
would get radioed about the situation at
the same time as Fire and Rescue and
we'll drive right there the on-call EMTs
would drive to the fire station get
their gear and the ambulance and drive
to the call I arrived alone to the
medical call usually 10 to 15 minutes
prior to them I carry a small oxygen
tank with that bag-valve-mask
nasal cannula
non-rebreather an AED a few tourniquets
and some narcan PPE is non latex gloves
and a glock 22 that's good I'm only a
couple of years on the job but doing
chest compressions already resulted in a
save for me along with multiple times I
kept people with oh boy
opioid overdoses breathing until medical
arrived good job I've also provided care
to young and old dying people who
probably had contagious disease I'm left
to do my best and maybe use some hand
sanitizer before I get back in my
cruiser I don't even have access to a
clothes washer at the police department
so uniforms are coming home to get
washed in an ideal world all smaller
police departments would be prepared for
this outbreak but we certainly are not
what should I plan for as far as calls I
can imagine a lot of struggling to
breathe and non-responsive or with a
pulse patients other than being
completely horrified by my situation is
there anything you can recommend I do to
protect myself to protect the next
person I go help am I wrong to be kind
of resigned to the idea that I will be
exposed and we'll just have to deal with
that and try not to be a source myself
thanks Cindy just a brief personal
perspective here my sister is a
paramedic in New Bedford Massachusetts
and my wife by the way is working in an
emergency room in Connecticut now as a
doctor but I my first suggestion would
be to talk to the EMTs and see if you
can borrow some extra gloves and maybe
maybe masks from them if they have them
although those are in real short supply
and and do the best you can I don't
think you're wrong to be resigned to the
idea that you'll get exposed yeah I
think as a frontline first responder I
I'm sorry that's it's gonna happen so
yeah your your best protection is going
to be immunity in the law
yeah so she shouldn't be wearing a
facemask you think I I think if
available maybe she should I because
she's a first responder if she's gonna
be right down there with the aerosol can
be right down there with them and you
know running into into these situations
where she's got the right PPE for a
police officer I'm glad to hear that but
yeah you know do what you can to avoid
getting coughed on I mean that sounds
kind of silly if you're gonna be
performing CPR and somebody you do what
you can
young and probably won't have a serious
infection
yeah if you're if you're you know you're
young you're you're police officer so
you've met the physical standards for
that you probably will not have an issue
with this but I applaud your concern
about exposing the next person you
respond to which is a very appropriate
and valid concern I think under the
circumstances there's probably not a lot
to be done that you're not already doing
if we have anyone listening who knows
who works in this area please let us
know yes I wouldn't taste I was would
just say Cindy thank you for all that
you're doing yes and I'm sorry that I
don't have something we don't have
something sort of fabulous to tell you
here yeah I love that we that we've got
a police officer in a small lowing in
town
listening to whiff I just think that's
great and the image I have in my mind it
won't go away as far go yes maybe she's
in your town Allen who knows yeah you're
a small New England town right we're a
small New England town that's that's my
kind of place Nixon can you take the
next one I'd be happy to Nicolas writes
dear twisters my name is Nicolas vestan
Heine
I am a GP from southern Germany and the
corona virus pandemic brought me to your
podcast at first I want to thank you it
is a pleasure to listen to
we're gonna work by bicycle every twice
a day and so I have about 40 minutes of
time to listen to all this important
information by the way we have about
five degrees Celsius and mostly cloudy
weather conditions my question is about
the testing procedure I don't really
know how this rt-pcr thing works and
today I got a text which said that it is
possible there is a lot of false
positive tests now in Italy in Germany
in this text they speculate that all
these tests do not use a specific
Tsarskoe v2 tests get but a more general
coronavirus test kit for this rt-pcr the
conjecture is that it is not possible to
produce so many specific test kits for
Tsarskoe v2 in such a short time what do
you think about this thanks and keep on
twitting I think you can make a lot of
test kits it's not a priori Nia's great
tech you could definitely do that
where we can do it we can do it why
don't we do it I didn't say we can't do
it i we don't do it there was a rather
disturbing NPR investigative report that
suggested at one explanation but I won't
get into it goes will be accused of
getting political all right I would say
that Nicolas while there might be some
questions of some things being in short
supply those things are not what would
tell you the difference between Tsarskoe
v2 and other corona viruses the parts
that are specific for Tsarskoe v2 are
pretty easy to make in large quantities
can make yes so if you go to the WHI
website they have all suggested primers
and they're certainly pan corona primers
and Tsarskoe v2 specific right so yeah
that's where you should be using now
because otherwise you're not going to
get the information you need
sorry go ahead it would be unusual to
find another Co V circulating through
those two countries and nowhere else
I think there's I think there's the
seasonal ones that Ralph's the seasonal
regular coronaviruses right but I don't
know why anybody would be producing
regular coronavirus test kits who's
capable of producing corona
our emphasis is gonna be on this and the
primers are the there's sort of the the
active ingredient in a PCR test they're
going to they're going to find the
specific sequence that you're looking
for so it is possible that somebody dug
out some old kits and use them it's
exceedingly unlikely especially in a
country like Germany or in Italy that
any significant number of those is
generating large numbers of false
positives and somehow skewing the
statistics right right seem believable
the the you know for the Caleb's out
there the rt-pcr test is in maybe the
simplest explanation I can give is it's
a way of asking whether the RNA sequence
that is diagnostic of this particular
virus is present in a sample and the way
that's the critical reagent for that is
is the RNA sequence itself that's there
for the purpose of comparison saying the
kit has the RNA sequence in there
effectively and says let's compare this
to this sample and see if it's there
it's obviously a lot more complicated
than that but it's not that's that's it
in theory and it's a very very common
procedure so if you got the kit and a
minimal amount of training you ought to
be able to run the run the test which
can take the next one Brenner writes hi
12 team long time listener
I started in academics after a PhD in a
postdoc I went into public health I hear
in the podcast that there isn't much
information on the current covet 19 or
as I prefer to call it SARS 2 Co V test
so let me give you the background oh my
goodness I could have shut up
the CBC originally came out with a
real-time reverse transcription PCR RT
RT PCR it had three targets all in the
end gene why the end gene when everybody
else uses spike your guess is as good as
mine and she gives a link they sent out
and
they sent the test out to 99 different
public health labs of the 99 only five
could make the assay work ninety-four
labs could have could have had the n3
probe could have the n3 probe react to
something in the HSC late in the
reaction causing a late positive CT for
the HSC probe - that's getting a little
dense but basically they got tests
didn't work the CDC said they were gonna
false positives CDC said that they were
gonna replace just the n3 primer probe
set but that the other two should be
good to go a week past the CDC was still
working on it were they going to change
the sequence no one knew what the
problem was however in situations like
this laboratories cannot just adjust a
protocol we are required by CLIA FDA and
every other alphabet-soup agency to do
two testing exactly as it is written he
can't homebrew this right a second week
passed and in a very surprising turn of
events the associate of public health
laboratories who work very closely with
the CDC getting a myriad of assays and
programs up and running wrote a harsh
letter to the FDA asking them to loosen
requirements for emergency authorized
testing days afterwards the CDC said you
only had to use the first 2n primer
process probe sets they remanufactured
and sent new lots out to all the labs in
about a week and basically we never
speak of the n3 primer probe again she
gives a link to this for information
testing requires both a doctor and an
epidemiologist in testing like this
there has to be an epidemiologist
sign-off a doctor cannot just order the
test even with the loosening of the
rules there is paperwork that an
epidemiologist is required to fill out
and approve before we can initiate
testing
a doctor has a great deal of sway which
reminds me of a story
about a year ago there was a small merge
Co V outbreak in the Middle East as
there is now it was still flu season I
was working for the laboratory response
network in Texas at the time the this
network the lrn is the lab that hospital
labs go to when they can't rule out a
bio threat agent so I get a call after
work does our lab do MERS Co V testing
no we didn't who did the neatest the
nearest big city or state capital lab
okay
well they're going to send over a sample
that is suspected of MERS Co v4 flu
testing and we need to be ready to
handle it our hospital level is very
concerned about taking a potential merge
Co V sample and running it over there
nice new flu PCR machine understandable
but after several meetings we go through
various safety options and decon methods
and they're ready we run the sample and
it's flu A+ I grabbed an aliquot of the
sample and take it back to our lab to do
the CDC flu panel which generates a type
a type and subtype I run the PCR a h3 I
so same thing it's flu I later ask the
original referring hospital for more
patient information turns out that this
patient also had a rapid antigen flu a
positive result about 12 hours before we
got anything while all this was going on
they shipped a sample to the Austin lab
to get tested but even with it being
cold outside they didn't pack enough
cold packs so the sample arrived melted
and was considered unsuitable for
testing so they got a new sample packed
it in dry ice and fluid by helicopter to
Austin to get it tested tested all
because the doctor said the patient was
quote too sick for just the flu so after
quite a bit of extra effort the samples
was finally tested for MERS Co V it was
found to be negative my advice
all physicians if a patient is flute
positive they have the flu as a sidenote
and you don't have to read this as I'm
not interested in fear-mongering
I didn't do my PhD on coronaviruses
coronaviruses
are much like polio in the Perez and the
presence and use of quasi species to
determine pathogenesis there are reports
or quasi species playing a role in
pathogenesis there are neurotropic
corona viruses there a mouse in origin
but they were selected from a strain
that infects the lungs when cultured
properly so it's quite possible that the
quasi species diversity of the infecting
virus and the diversity generated
throughout infection can impact
intestinal infection as well as
neurotrophins gives a couple of links to
that concept thanks for the great
podcast and if you hear Oh pick me I
know it's probably me yelling at the
podcast his name is not horshack right
nice now that's Brenna yeah there are
some nootropic Coronas but not these are
not known to be neurotropic Brenna thank
you very much for the insight on the CDC
test and what went on with that because
that was that was as been lightening
happen thank you very much I would I
would I would like to I don't want to do
it myself
but I would like to go through and shake
down the CDC you know yeah i think i
think they well i got i got people to
work there it's a great organization we
really need it they do great work but i
think they need some i think they need
some help and some i don't i will really
point out without getting political that
they they did recently have a management
change at the top yeah mmm-hmm and i'm
just gonna set that out there and people
can look into whatever they want to look
into and figure out the the director was
asked today who's
directing the diagnostic covetous issue
and he didn't know and so now they've
just appointed someone to do that and I
find it very interesting and I'm
thankful for it that the really the
public face of this is Tony foul Qi yes
it should be at least equally the CDC
director but it's Tony foul Qi and
that's appropriate that's good yes you
know under the circumstances and he's a
great person to have in that pencil
absolutely all right he's afraid to be
critical yes
all right been rights height Swift team
on your brief discussion on airplane air
recirculation I thought it would bump in
and say that while the air is brought in
from outside not enough air is brought
in it is expensive to bring in -60 sea
air heat at the cabin temp so airlines
try to keep it to a minimum in terms of
percent oxygen percent carbon dioxide
airplane air is now less fresh than when
it was when people could smoke on plane
because they brought in much more air to
get rid of visible pollution
well the cabin air was obviously more
carcinogenic than I would think less air
from outside higher co2 could mean
greater transmission potential thanks
for all your fantastic worker really
providing the public with level-headed
information at a time of mania regards
from a toilet paper deficiency it's a
global problem well ice as ralph said
the transmission seems to be really in
airplanes really close around to the
people seething around you but so it's
still not a good idea to fly because you
got all these people sitting there for
what could be hours right yes you're the
only played person in the plane and
you're flying it yes
like do the people in the cockpit get
the same air as the passengers yes well
then you should start doing Studies on
pilots because they're an older bunch of
people to begin with that's well there
they are a stringently health screened
bunch of people that's true so they are
at risk but to get a class a medical and
fly for the airlines you you do have to
pass a I'm not suggesting that they're
immunocompromised or anything I'm just
saying that they're an older group of
people okay
certainly there they could catch the
virus and transmit it right there are a
good test for this sort of aerosol
airborne thing because they're locking
and getting air
that's - no that's good point that's
what you take the next one
sure no name rights that's probably not
their real matter but anyway a high no
good to meet you hey hey guys not really
a question more of a comment there were
a lot of questions about masks and their
utility on episode 590 while I
understand people wanting answers to
these questions at this point is largely
academic as they are just not available
anywhere also as rich pointed out a lot
of people are probably not going to use
them correctly like the woman he was
sitting next to on his recent flight to
make matters worse this lack of
availability is probably going to have
an impact on health care workers and
first responders which for obvious
reasons is not good something to think
about at least from my point of view you
know this would probably be a good time
to discuss masks right yeah it's a good
time I think those are the reasons why
they're not recommended by CDC you eat
them for health care workers and they're
not enough right yeah I think that's
probably true
I'd also kind of think about the fact
that I have a hard enough time not
touching my face and I'm sure that if I
had something on my face annoying me I'd
be touching it even more often I think
that's the other issue is that people
are not wearing them correctly which I'd
like to point out
Daniel Griffin's group put out a video
this weekend for health care workers but
it's good for everyone on how to Don and
doff personal protective wear and we'll
put a link to that in the show notes
it's really very good
does he have the Glock 22 in it no no
that is not a health care worker thing
that's and there we've actually been
discussing among the 12 group on slack
in the past week a couple of papers you
can you can kind of pick your data
depending on what you want to argue but
a couple of papers from 2004 including
one in the CDC Journal emerging
infectious diseases one argues that you
know presents some data from the
original SARS epidemic in
Beijing in 2003 and shows that people
who did wear a mask had a had a lower
risk of contracting SARS
they also found other things that
correlated with that which included like
people washing their hands when they
first came home owning a pet visiting a
farmers market these were all protective
so I think there's a lot going on there
besides masks that probably has to do
with people's personal habits and who
was more conscientious about social
distancing and that kind of thing and
then there's a another paper that I
think Kathy provided in the discussion
that's also from emerging infectious
diseases also from 2004 and this was a
study on nurses in Toronto that found
there was a I'm always a little annoyed
by this phrase that the risk was reduced
by consistent use of a surgical mask but
not significantly statistics note if
something was not reduced significantly
it was not reduced so anyway we also had
some recent conversations about masks
here because we've realized that there
are so many different cultural beliefs
about masks and some people seem to get
a lot of security out of them and so
whether or not you choose to wear a mask
sort of shouldn't involve how you feel
about others who have decided to wear
them unless they've decided to wear a
hockey mask in public trail control some
conclusions about that I think that
that's true I agree there today is
Friday 13th by the way it is Friday the
13th
breanne can you take the next one sure
Jody writes
greetings twit High Council first of all
a brief but tremendous thank you for
your reading and responding to my email
a few weeks back I can't begin to
express the heart bursting joy I felt at
hearing your thoughtful advice and
consideration on how to tackle getting
started on my ID career midlife I now
have a juicy list of Doc's in Seattle to
target and will be doing so this
and feel genuinely bolstered by your
encouragement I would also like to give
a shout out to Matt Doherty of the
Doherty lab at UCSD who sat in my
backyard five and a half years ago
telling me about chikungunya over beers
when he saw the light in my eyes and the
froth billed at my mouth to know more he
said you know there's a podcast you
might have a rabies exposure maybe here
we are today as a virology enthusiast
this is an exciting time all of a sudden
everyone wants to talk about viruses
where I usually am Alec we allocated
only a few minutes of each conversation
with friends and husband to bore them
with my giddy ramblings about what I
recently learned on Twix or read about
whichever history of disease books I
happen to currently be devouring the
exception is my seven-year-old daughter
who regularly asks that we stop reading
15 minutes early each night so that we
can talk about viruses I have some more
reading to do I like her daughter yes a
professional podcaster friend actually
asked me to meet up this weekend so I
could help her prepare for a coronavirus
focused episode she was recording the
next day with her co-hosts in Italy we
spent almost four hours talking viruses
in general and Tsarskoe b2 in particular
and I shared scores of articles papers
reports harvested from your episode
links over the last month it was a hoot
she had just gotten off a plane and kept
coughing and sneezing her husband and I
did our best to maintain a metres
distance from her though our beers were
collecting respiratory droplets we
debated whether she should wash her
hands before or after using the ketchup
both and we all tapped feet in elbows
lovingly when we said goodbye at the end
of the night as you scientists like to
say so
so as the outbreak situation in Seattle
is rapidly evolving and my friends
family spouse are all coming to me not a
virologist or epidemiologist or public
health professional of any kind and
asking what should we do I thought I
would write to you with some updates
about what is happening here and as what
should we do since learning that experts
believe that the virus has likely been
circulating undetected
here in Washington State for over a
month people have gone into action
currently there is a bit of an
apocalypse come festival atmosphere in
this city for the last 4 days or so
people have been packing Costco and
local grocery stores like it's the day
before Thanksgiving or the Superbowl and
by 3 p.m. the shelves are cleared of
canned food and toilet paper local
Trader Joe's supported record sales this
past weekend and every drugstore in my
neighborhood has signs taped in the
window saying we are sold out of face
masks and hand sanitizer everyone is
very concerned and prepping like crazy
but laughing and joking at the same time
yesterday I had so many light-hearted
conversations with chipper strangers
about how many boxes of mac and cheese
would last 30 days which wine might go
fast easy I would like to know the
answer to that question yes people are
actively preparing but decidedly not
panicking good good
that said our governor and County
Executive have both declared states of
emergency large companies like f5 and
REI have closed campuses temporarily and
Facebook and t-mobile have taken
measures to limit who is coming through
their doors a number of schools have
closed King County is in the process of
buying a motel to house patients who
need to be isolated and the city is
setting up modular units to treat and
house the infected among our homeless
population which is the third largest in
the US and numbers over five thousand
people a local immigration office has
closed for 14 days due to an exposure
and scores of firefighters are in
quarantine after being exposed at the
Kirkland care center that has become the
epicenter of local outbreak those are
all really great things to hear I have
been following all along in real time as
you have speculated about possible
outcomes and looked at local and
national containment efforts with a
critical eye so my big question for you
is now that it seems clear that there is
an infectious prodrome and there are
likely perhaps hundreds of asymptomatic
people or very minor lis symptomatic
people who think they have a cold out
shedding virus and coming into contact
with scores of others every single day
what should stop should we beat
to stop this outbreak in its tracks I've
heard you criticize quarantine and
travel bans but I've also read the early
identification quarantine and citizens
changing their daily behavior haven't
been effective in stopping other
outbreaks our governor in a press
conference yesterday urged social
distancing and suggested that working
from home when sick could be seen as a
patriotic act I like this idea but is
obviously a luxury of an office worker
and not something that can be done if
you're in a service or manufacturing job
that you will lose if you don't show up
and only working from home while sick
does not solve the problem of the
asymptomatic or mildly symptomatic
shedder who might be working at a school
or riding a bus or working out in a gym
every day I think all of those are very
good points I think that there are that
a lot of what we're doing with social
distancing is great but we do need to
think about those who are not going to
be able to do so so if this continues to
spread should we close schools for a
month should everyone shelter in place
for a month which is what the city is
planning for with their hoarding of
candies and toilet paper should every
business that is able ask their
employees to work remotely how does one
survive like this that is often causing
such mild symptoms from spreading in a
big city well following the advice of
washing our hands and cell phones and
not shaking hands keep us all safe or is
this like Bush's homeland security
telling us that we all need to protect
ourselves in case of a biological or
chemical terrorist attack was duct tape
and plastic sheeting hand washing is
more effective than duct tape and
plastic sheeting hand washing staying
home all of those things I think are
going to be important can I just
interject of course so we were critical
of quarantine and travel restrictions
because early on we felt that the
infection should spread and confer hurt
immunity but then we learned of the high
serious complication rate in a certain
percentage of infections and the
possibility that that would overwhelm
the health care system and we saw that
happen in Wuhan and Italy and for that
reason I think we should reduce the
transmission
to keep the hospitals able to function
because they can save people's lives and
so I think all of these restrictions are
absolutely good today right now and and
I would just as somebody who's also been
particularly critical of quarantine and
travel restrictions in the past I want
to draw a distinction between mandatory
quarantines and trying to arrest people
in place and voluntary cancellation of
events there's a big difference there
when you when you try to do what China
did and was uniquely able to do and lock
down a region the natural human instinct
is to try to try to get the hell out of
that region and that's gonna make things
worse by making this more of a voluntary
thing and telling people look here's
what the risk is you really ought to
cancel stuff that doesn't have to be
done that involves interacting with
other people and I think people are
embracing that certainly from the emails
I'm now getting from my daughter's
school they're embracing this yeah and
and that is the kind of approach that
will work I think because it's it's
motivated from the bottom up rather than
the top down yeah I agree completely
with everything that you guys are saying
and I also think that I've become more
Pro sort of social distancing the more I
have understood about the role of
asymptomatic spread and so we cannot
have just people who are infected stay
home at this point because we realize
how important a symptomatic spread is
and and a lot of the criticism that
we've leveled against things like
quarantine travel restrictions was
during past epidemics of things like
Ebola virus which is a very very
different situation yes you're you're
not gonna have a lot of asymptomatic
people walking around happy and healthy
and spreading the virus so this is this
is a very different situation I'd like
to take this opportunity to say that
this has been on my mind for a little
while if you go back to the
our first episodes on this this is now I
think our seventh podcast on the
coronavirus thing initially as I saw
this emerging in China I was pretty
blas about it and I figured figured it
would burn out there and I remember in
particular going through a bunch of my
own calculations and figuring that it
wouldn't spread spread much and I was
dead wrong okay this is proven to be a
much bigger deal than I ever anticipated
and I'm going to school on this all
right what every every day every day as
a new day as as breanne just said I
really had it drilled into me today for
the first time from Ralph about the
asymptomatic shedding and that's a big
deal that's a big deal okay so you know
we can do it we can grow with this
epidemic
absolutely so she continues on another
note I've really enjoyed hearing the
first-hand accounts from your Chinese
listeners my husband last night told me
that he had just had a call with his
colleagues in Shanghai and they shared
the measures that they are taking
currently which include working in
shifts to limit how many people are in
contact with each other both on transit
and in the office working from home as
much as they can calling in to group
meetings in the office even when they
are there physically they are no longer
meeting in conference rooms at all and
doing temperature checks on the way to
the office each day he told me that one
of their main trade shows his business
attends and exhibits at the
International housewares trade show or
iha which usually draws about 60,000
people to Chicago each March from all
over the world was canceled the long
ranging effects of this disease on the
environment and the economy will be
interesting to watch yeah very true I've
shared a number of articles below
including the potential effects of this
situation on Chinese pollution levels
how Chinese restaurants in Seattle are
suffering and an article that explains
that the Seattle flu study a new
University of Washington group that
sends swab kits out to the public
I have three of their boxes sitting next
to my desk in fact and my daughter hates
doing the nose swabs but loves playing
virologist complete a role in
identifying the second Washington Kobe
Cove in nineteen case and lastly there's
been a lot of talk around here about how
this virus might play out differently in
places like Italy where your job is
guaranteed even if you stay home sick
and healthcare is socialized versus the
US where you can lose your job if you
don't show up and where many people do
not have access to health care or the
means to pay for it yes I think that
those are also important points to be
thinking about however it didn't stop
the outbreak in Italy it certainly did
not thanks as always for your commitment
to truth seeking and truth sharing and
for always being pedantic and
entertaining I'm glad somebody likes
being pedantic it's 52 degrees and
cloudy here in Seattle with a Chance of
coronavirus be nice to Dixon and that's
from Jody what a wonderful letter very
nice Oh Jody very nice Thank You Jody
all right there's a bunch of links here
yeah a lot of links thank you so much
for flat stuff these will be all at this
shownotes microbe dot TV slash twit
let's do two more Dixon can you take the
next one
Kevin writes hi Vincent and Friends
personal protective equipment has been a
recurrent topic on your show recently
for good reason I was very interested to
hear of the article you've been citing
my radinovich at all that showed little
difference in effectiveness between n95
s and the surgical masks in preventing
occupational exposure to flu in
healthcare settings
I thought the attached article might be
of some interest to you as well
considered in the light of the
radinovich study as it shows how much
performance can diverged between
idealized control conditions and the
real world and as you have been
emphasizing and 95s are designed to
provide protection from airborne droplet
nuclear eye wear as surgical masks are
designed to be fluid barriers only this
study demonstrates the magnitude of the
difference in protective protection
factors between the two along with
makeshift
coverings while showing that surgical
masks to provide some very limited
benefit against airborne exposure if
used properly it also explores the
reduction in particulates generated when
masks of various kinds are worn by a
6-part at the sick person in this
experiment on mechanical head which is
surprisingly low and better than nothing
you miss regards I read more
Kevin McGee yes the same one from your
IBC a few years back greetings from
Auckland New Zealand where it is a
cloudy 23 degrees C note the FFP to
masks tested in the attached study are
the Dutch equivalent of the n95 s in
case attachment doesn't work
Vander Satya tan citation sorry that's a
citation that's right yeah just a
citation okay it's funny okay Evan was
on the IBC years ago I'm on the
institutional biosafety committee that's
great that you're listening Kevin Thanks
yes let's do one more rich ok vyd writes
fascinating report you mentioned that
many different respiratory illnesses
have fallen in hong kong into in 2020
compared to 2019 right so that was
referring to the graph we did last time
that suggests that the general sort of
health awareness standards have impacted
other diseases if it has been written up
anywhere I would be interested in a link
we never got that did we now we got a
link to the raw numbers from Hong Kong
so you would have to you know for every
year previous to this one so you'd have
to regress it right I will note however
it has it may be hard to attribute the
broad decline in to any specific
interventions as it turns out I was in
Hong Kong for the month of February
tourism was already down as a result of
the political instabilities that have
been ongoing since last summer and was
absolutely cratered with reports of the
viral outbreak in Wuhan in January hotel
occupancy --zz were well below
50% and all of the US carriers cancelled
all flights between the u.s. and Hong
Kong and early February fortunately we
were booked on casaya Cathay Pacific
memories of stars SARS are still fresh
and Hong Kong reacted early and
aggressively to the Wuhan outbreak music
schools cultural centers and many
government officers offices were closed
although most businesses remain open
everyone was wearing surgical masks on
the street hand sanitizer dispensers
were ubiquitous and workers could be
seen regularly disinfecting elevator
buttons drawer fixtures and escalator
handrails hotels and high-rises had
people posted at the entrance and we're
measuring the temperature of everyone
entering the building and yes everyone
was washing their hands frequently so
I'm not surprised that the incidence of
respiratory viruses has fallen broadly
but it's hard to say which specific
innovation and intervention did how much
that's a wonderful perspective that's
great it's important to emphasize that
the infectivity of a virus r0 is not an
intrinsic feature of the virus but also
depends on the environment and social
behaviors I'm going to interject here I
believe that are not r0 is in fact an
intrinsic feature of the virus we use
these terms inappropriately but there's
R or R e which is the effective
reproduction number is r0 that has
influenced by various social behaviors
okay any rate r0 he says is a
statistical measure of how many people
on average on average a case infects
true if people practice disciplined
hygiene and social distancing the number
of new infections will on average fall
that gives you the effective
reproduction rate that call ure yes yeah
re Hong Kong and Singapore have both
seen lower rates of growth in covent 19
cases compared to other countries
outside of mainland China
non-pharmaceutical interventions NPI can
make a big difference and right now they
all have thanks David
yes on a previous show you identified me
as a professor of human genetics at the
University of Michigan I was in fact
professor of human genetics but that was
more than a decade ago and I have since
left to pursue opportunities in
biotechnology and drug development
I believe Kathy and I have met in the
context of graduate education committees
Pibbs small world go blue
David states who wrote to us last week
as well yeah I think the reproductive
number is really important and Ralph I
thought in his discussions referred to
it several times in in a really
illuminating fashion because he talked
about how our healthcare our practices
public health practices and etc and herd
immunity ultimately affect the effective
reproduction rate and the idea is to do
whatever you can to get that down to
less than one right where right where
where the you're not amplifying the
disease and once you get it down to the
effective reproduction number down to
less than one even though the are not
may still the intrinsic value may still
be 2 or whatever if you get the
effective number down to less than one
now you're gonna squash the disease
right that's a really nice explanation
to yeah
yes I have to say these are all great
questions and comments we have gotten
more twit I'm a LAN at any other time in
our existence it's great we're on page
16 out of 46 or page 15 out of 46 pages
of emails or continue come in and I have
to say don't stop because we will get to
them eventually yep right so if you want
to see some of these emails micro TV
slash twit if you want to send some in
please do twit micro TV someone said
before oh I didn't know you give out
last names we generally don't unless
you're at
doctor or scientist you know we and we
give out your last name otherwise for
most people we don't because doctors and
scientists don't have any privacy of
course we don't need usually if you're
right in is you have a preference as to
whether or not we use your name hate it
many people want to remain an ominous
that's fine but send them in we will get
to you but I want to stop here at two
hours because you got a lot to listen to
and I think yep that's about enough for
you and I can't tax my hosts anymore
well you know if listeners want more of
I R ology right now just go back and
listen to that first hour with Ralph
because that was yeah there's a lot of
information yes I would agree if you
like what we do consider supporting us
financially many new people have joined
our to support us we really appreciate
that you can go to micro TV slash
contribute and use PayPal or patreon to
give us as little as a dollar a month or
chunks of money whatever you prefer
Dixon de palma a is at parasites without
borders calm and the living river org
thank you Dixon
pleasure did you teach your course
online today I did how'd it go yeah it
was good there's always this disconnect
that you get when you're talking into a
screen that's right I like to see their
reaction to the things that I'm saying
and I like to stop sure allow them to
ask questions and it's very difficult is
to have an interactive experience long
distance yeah I taught this week and
gave an exam this week our world had
office hours yesterday which was all
questions about SARS Kofi - nothing
should I go home for spring break
yeah that's right off Brianne Barker's
over at Drew University in New Jersey on
Twitter bio prof Barker thanks Brianne
thanks it was really great to be here
and I also have been learning how to
teach online the past few days and I'm
gonna start teaching with zoom on Monday
yeah that's what I use and that's it for
the rest of the semester exams well
teaching it's all online
I think that's a good idea easy to use
sorry Dixon I said zoom is easy to use
now here twit we use Skype for this
because I think the it's easier to get
good sound done that's guy even a
caveman living in Fort Lee New Jersey
can use it apparently rich Condit is it
emeritus professor University of Florida
Gainesville currently residing in Austin
Texas thank you rich sure thing always a
good time this is great island of turbid
plaque dot-com over on Twitter he is
Alan dove Thank You Alan thank you it's
always a pleasure and by the way I've
been social distancing since before it
was cool
hey healthy well now we resume our
normal schedule a I'm not traveling home
time at yeah I'm here so we're gonna be
recording every Friday and sorry we'll
be back good to have you because some of
us I have been traveling a lot the last
few months and canceling Friday's and so
forth but I am Vincent rockin yellow you
can find me at virology dot blog I want
to thank ASM and ASV for their support
of twit and ronald jenkees for the music
this episode of twit was recorded edited
and posted by me Vincent frakkin young
you've been listening to this week in
virology thanks for joining us we'll be
back next week and other twit is viral
[Music]
you