In the last videos I talked about the derivatives
of simple functions, things like powers of
x, sin(x), and exponentials, the goal being
to have a clear picture or intuition to hold
in your mind that explains where these formulas
come from.
Most functions you use to model the world
involve mixing, combining and tweaking these
these simple functions in some way; so our
goal now is to understand how to take derivatives
of more complicated combinations; where again,
I want you to have a clear picture in mind
for each rule.
This really boils down into three basic ways
to combine functions together: Adding them,
multiplying them, and putting one inside the
other; also known as composing them.
Sure, you could say subtracting them, but
that’s really just multiplying the second
by -1, then adding.
Likewise, dividing functions is really just
the same as plugging one into the function
1/x, then multiplying.
Most functions you come across just involve
layering on these three types of combinations,
with no bound on how monstrous things can
become.
But as long as you know how derivatives play
with those three types of combinations, you
can always just take it step by step and peal
through the layers.
So, the question is, if you know the derivatives
of two functions, what is the derivative of
their sum, of their product, and of the function
compositions between them?
The sum rule is the easiest, if somewhat tounge-twisting
to say out loud: The derivative of a sum of
two functions is the sum of their derivatives.
But it’s worth warming up with this example
by really thinking through what it means to
take a derivative of a sum of two functions,
since the derivative patterns for products
and function composition won’t be so straight
forward, and will require this kind of deeper
thinking.
The function f(x) = sin(x) + x2 is a function
where, for every input, you add together the
values of sin(x) and x2 at that point.
For example, at x = 0.5, the height of the
sine graph is given by this bar, the height
of the x2 parabola is given by this bar, and
their sum is the length you get by stacking
them together.
For the derivative, you ask what happens as
you nudge the input slightly, maybe increasing
it to 0.5+dx.
The difference in the value of f between these
two values is what we call df.
Well, pictured like this, I think you’ll
agree that the total change in height is whatever
the change to the sine graph is, what we might
call d(sin(x)), plus whatever the change to
x2 is, d(x2).
We know the derivative of sine is cosine,
and what that means is that this little change
d(sin(x)) would be about cos(x)dx.
It’s proportional to the size of dx, with
a proportionality constant equal to cosine
of whatever input we started at.
Similarly, because the derivative of x2 is
2x, the change in the height of the x2 graph
is about 2x*dx.
So, df/dx, the ratio of the tiny change to
the sum function to the tiny change in x that
caused it, is indeed cos(x)+2x, the sum of
the derivatives of its parts.
But like I said, things are a bit different
for products.
Let’s think through why, in terms of tiny
nudges.
In this case, I don’t think graphs are our
best bet for visualizing things.
Pretty commonly in math, all levels of math
really, if you’re dealing with a product
of two things, it helps to try to understand
it as some form of area.
In this case, you might try to configure some
mental setup of a box whose side-lengths are
sin(x) and x2.
What would that mean?
Well, since these are functions, you might
think of these sides as adjustable; dependent
on the value of x, which you might think of
as a number that you can freely adjust.
So, just getting the feel for this, focus
on that top side, whose changes as the function
sin(x).
As you change the value of x up from 0, it
increases in up to a length of 1 as sin(x)
moves towards its peak.
After that, it starts decreasing as sin(x)
comes down from 1.
And likewise, that height changes as x2.
So f(x), defined as this product, is the area
of this box.
For the derivative, think about how a tiny
change to x by dx influences this area; that
resulting change in area is df.
That nudge to x causes the width to change
by some small d(sin(x)), and the height to
change by some d(x2).
This gives us three little snippets of new
area: A thin rectangle on the bottom, whose
area is its width, sin(x), times its thin
height, d(x2); there’s a thin rectangle
on the right, whose area is its height, x2,
times its thin width, d(sin(x)).
And there’s also bit in the corner.
But we can ignore it, since its area will
ultimately be proportional to dx2, which becomes
negligible as dx goes to 0.
This is very similar to what I showed last
video, with the x2 diagram.
Just like then, keep in mind that I’m using
somewhat beefy changes to draw things, so
we can see them, but in principle think of
dx as very very small, meaning d(x2) and d(sin(x))
are also very very small.
Applying what we know about the derivative
of sine and x2, that tiny change d(x2) is
2x*dx, and that tiny change d(sin(x)) is cos(x)dx.
Dividing out by that dx, the derivative df/dx
is sin(x) by the derivative of x2, plus x2
by the derivative of sine.
This line of reasoning works for any two functions.
A common mnemonic for the product rule is
to say in your head “left d right, right
d left”.
In this example, sin(x)*x2, “left d right”
means you take the left function, in this
case sin(x), times the derivative of the right,
x2, which gives 2x.
Then you add “right d left”: the right
function, x2, times the derivative of the
left, cos(x).
Out of context, this feels like kind of a
strange rule, but when you think of this adjustable
box you can actually see how those terms represent
slivers of area.
“Left d right” is the area of this bottom
rectangle, and “right d left” is the area
of this rectangle on the right.
By the way, I should mention that if you multiply
by a constant, say 2*sin(x), things end up
much simpler.
The derivative is just that same constant
times the derivative of the function, in this
case 2*cos(x).
I’ll leave it to you to pause and ponder
to verify that this makes sense.
Aside from addition and multiplication, the
other common way to combine functions that
comes up all the time is function composition.
For example, let’s say we take the function
x2, and shove it on inside sin(x) to get a
new function, sin(x2).
What’s the derivative of this new function?
Here I’ll choose yet another way to visualize
things, just to emphasize that in creative
math, we have lots of options.
I’ll put up three number lines.
The top one will hold the value of x, the
second one will represent the value of x2,
and that third line will hold the value of
sin(x2).
That is, the function x2 gets you from line
1 to line 2, and the function sine gets you
from line 2 to line 3.
As I shift that value of x, maybe up to the
value 3, then value on the second shifts to
whatever x2 is, in this case 9.
And that bottom value, being the sin(x2),
will go over to whatever the sin(9) is.
So for the derivative, let’s again think
of nudging that x-value by some little dx,
and I always think it’s helpful to think
of x starting as some actual number, maybe
1.5.
The resulting nudge to this second value,
the change to x2 caused by such a dx, is what
we might call d(x2).
You can expand this as 2x*dx, which for our
specific input that length would be 2*(1.5)*dx,
but it helps to keep it written as d(x2) for
now.
In fact let me go one step further and give
a new name to x2, maybe h, so this nudge d(x2)
is just dh.
Now think of that third value, which is pegged
at sin(h).
It’s change d(sin(h)); the tiny change caused
by the nudge dh.
By the way, the fact that it’s moving left
while the dh bump is to the right just means
that this change d(sin(h)) is some negative
number.
Because we know the derivative of sine, we
can expand d(sin(h)) as cos(h)*dh; that’s
what it means for the derivative of sine to
be cosine.
Unfolding things, replacing h with x2 again,
that bottom nudge is cos(x2)d(x2).
And we could unfold further, noting that d(x2)
is 2x*dx.
And it’s always good to remind yourself
of what this all actually means.
In this case where we started at x = 1.5 up
top, this means that the size of that nudge
on the third line is about cos(1.52)*2(1.5)*(the
size of dx); proportional to the size of dx,
where the derivative here gives us that proportionality
constant.
Notice what we have here, we have the derivative
of the outside function, still taking in the
unaltered inside function, and we multiply
it by the derivative of the inside function.
Again, there’s nothing special about sin(x)
and x2.
If you have two functions g(x) and h(x), the
derivative of their composition function g(h(x))
is the derivative of g, evaluated at h(x),
times the derivative of h.
This is what we call the “chain rule”.
Notice, for the derivative of g, I’m writing
it as dg/dh instead of dg/dx.
On the symbolic level, this serves as a reminder
that you still plug in the inner function
to this derivative.
But it’s also an important reflection of
what this derivative of the outer function
actually represents.
Remember, in our three-lines setup, when we
took the derivative of sine on the bottom,
we expanded the size of the nudge d(sin) as
cos(h)*dh.
This was because we didn’t immediately know
how the size of that bottom nudge depended
on x, that’s kind of the whole thing we’re
trying to figure out, but we could take the
derivative with respect to the intermediate
variable h.
That is, figure out how to express the size
of that nudge as multiple of dh.
Then it unfolded by figuring out what dh was.
So in this chain rule expression, we’re
saying look at the ratio between a tiny change
in g, the final output, and a tiny change
in h that caused it, h being the value that
we’re plugging into g.
Then multiply that by the tiny change in h
divided by the tiny change in x that caused
it.
The dh’s cancel to give the ratio between
a tiny change in the final output, and the
tiny change to the input that, through a certain
chain of events, brought it about.
That cancellation of dh is more than just
a notational trick, it’s a genuine reflection
of the tiny nudges that underpin calculus.
So those are the three basic tools in your
belt to handle derivatives of functions that
combine many smaller things: The sum rule,
the product rule and the chain rule.
I should say, there’s a big difference between
knowing what the chain rule and product rules
are, and being fluent with applying them in
even the most hairy of situations.
I said this at the start of the series, but
it’s worth repeating: Watching videos, any
videos, about these mechanics of calculus
will never substitute for practicing them
yourself, and building the muscles to do these
computations yourself.
I wish I could offer to do that for you, but
I’m afraid the ball is in your court, my
friend, to seek out practice.
What I can offer, and what I hope I have offered,
is to show you where these rules come from,
to show that they’re not just something
to be memorized and hammered away; but instead
are natural patterns that you too could have
discovered by just patiently thinking through