So what I want to talk about next is a solution,
uh, to- to these questions.
And in- in particular,
the method we'll talk about is called Query2box,
that allows us to reason over knowledge graphs using what is called, uh, Box Embeddings.
So let me first,, uh,
motivate the setting, and then give you how this method works.
So we said we wanna answer more complex predictive queries on, uh, graphs.
And let's say that we wanna be able to also include conjunctions,
so not just sets, but also intersections.
We wanna be able to take an intersection of two sets in the embedding space.
What we need to be able to do is two things.
We need to be able to now figure out how are we going to
represent a set of entities in the embedding space?
And then, how are we going to define the intersection operator in the embedding space?
How do we quickly take, uh,
two sets of entities and say,
what are the entities that are in the intersection, uh, between them?
So let's see how to do that.
The key inside that, uh,
will allow us to do this is the concept of a box eEmbedding.
What this means is that we're going to embed all the entities,
and the relations in our space as boxes,
as, uh, multidimen- dimensional, uh, rectangles.
And the intuition would be that every box is
defined by two points where it's defined by the center,
and is defined by the corner.
We'll call the center,
center, and we'll call the corner, offset.
So this basically tells me, you know,
what is the offset in, uh, one dimension?
What is the offset in the other dimension?
This basically tells me what is the size of the box.
And intuitively, we want to,
uh, let say, in our case of Fulvestrant,
we wanna embed all of its side effects in a- in a box, uh, that is,
uh- so that in basically, uh,
all the side effects caused by Fulvestrant will be- will be embedded close together,
and they will be enclosed in this,
uh, in this box.
So that's the- that's the idea.
So let me now tell you,
uh, keep kind of building on this.
So, um, the reason why we wanna embed things as
boxes is because intersection of boxes is well-defined.
Right? Basically, what I mean by that is,
uh, if you take two boxes,
and take an intersection,
intersection of two boxes is a box.
It can be an empty box,
right, a box of size 0.
But if there is any non-trivial overlap,
that overlap will be a box.
So it means we can now think about how are we going to define
trans-geometric transformations over these boxes
that corresponds to logical, uh, operators.
Right? So when we traverse the knowledge graph to find answers,
each step will basically, uh,
produce a set of reachable entities,
a set of entities that the query covers, uh, so far.
Um, and we are going to now model this set of
entities with a box that encloses all of them. All right.
So, um, this means that we can,
uh- that box provide a powerful obstruction because boxes kind of enclose,
uh, sets of, uh, entities.
And then we can define geometric intersection operator,
uh, over, uh, let's say,
two, or multiple boxes,
and when- when we intersect them,
the intersection is still a box.
So we- it's very easy again to have this compositional property,
where we can take boxes,
intersect them in arbitrary ways,
but, uh, we always are left of- are left out with a box,
which we can further kind of manipulate,
and change in shape however we like.
So that's why this is kind of cool,
um, and, uh, exciting.
So, uh, what does it mean to be a- to be able to embed with boxes?
Here is what we need to figure out or here's what we need to learn.
We need to learn uh,
opa- uh, we need to learn entity embeddings.
So every embedding, entity will have an embedding,
and it will be a box,
but it will be a- a- a trivial box.
So basically, it will be a point, right?
It will be a box of a- a size 0, or volume 0.
Then we'll have relation embeddings,
which will basically, um,
generalize the notion of params,
where we are going to take- now learn how to move around,
and, er, expand, or shrink boxes.
So the relation embeddings will be like vectors,
that are going to take boxes,
and move them around.
Then intersection operator is something that is- that is new.
Uh, the intersection operator will take, uh,
multiple boxes on the input,
and will output a single box.
And intuitively, this will be an intersection of, uh, boxes.
But we are going to learn this, uh, intersection operator.
Um, so it'll have some parameters so that our,
uh, approach will be even more,
uh, expressive, and more robust.
So how will this work?
Let me just kind of give you a cartoon.
Again, we are talking about, uh, you know,
what are drugs that cause shortness of breath,
and treat diseases associated with protein, uh, ESR2?
Uh, the way we do this,
right, in terms of query plan,
we say a-ha, we start with a anchor entity, ESR2.
We wanna move across the, um,
across the relationship called associated, uh, with.
And the way we are going to do this is that we are going to define
this relation projection operator P. Uh,
here is how it's defined.
We'll have one for every relation.
And essentially what this will do is it will take one box,
and it will kind of move it according to our given relation,
and also, um, expand its,
uh, or shrink its size.
So basically, we will have, um,
this learned, uh, ve- this learned operator for every relation.
It's going to move the center,
and it's going to change the offset.
So basically, it will change the size as well as the location,
uh, of the box.
So I can start with, uh, q,
and then I apply this, uh,
projection r to it to get a new box, uh, q prime.
So that's the projection operator.
So how would this look in our case if I started the ESR2,
and I wanna move across the associated relation?
I would take this trivial box, apply my, uh,
r- r- r associated,
and basically, this would move it, uh,
and expand it to include, uh,
all the- all the diseases associated with, uh, ESR2.
Now, um- now that I have a new box,
I can again, simply kind of follow the query plan.
Now I wanna traverse over a TreatedBy,
which again, I would take this box, apply TreatedBy, uh,
projection operator, the transformation to the box, which would, you know,
further move it, and you know,
expand or shrink it,
depends what the model we learn.
Uh, and then the idea is that whatever the answers to this path to a predictive query,
those are the entities, uh,
inside, uh, the box.
And that's essentially the idea, right?
Now, I can also try to answer the second part of the query,
which is shortness of breath CausedBy.
So I start with the shortness of breath entity,
apply this CausedBy box transformation to get another box.
And now, uh, what are the entities that are,
uh, in the intersection of the two boxes?
Uh, those will be basically the answers to my query.
In our, uh- in our case, uh,
this would be these, uh- these two entities,
uh, fulvestrant, uh, and the other drug.
Right? So that's essentially the idea.
I have one box, I have the other box I'm interested
in, what is the intersection, uh, of them?
So that's, um, the idea about how would I do the embedding grid boxes?
Now, let me talk about how does- how is this intersection operator, uh, really defined?
Uh, one approach would be to simply define it as kind of hardcore,
or just mathematically as intersection of boxes,
almost like as- as in a Venn diagram.
Uh, we wanna be a bit more, um, flexible.
And we wanna do, uh, uh,
and learn a geometric intersection operator,
we'll call it J.
Where the idea is we wanna take multiple boxes as input,
and produce the intersection,
uh, of these boxes.
We'll call it the intersection box.
Uh, and the intuition,
we are going to use this to say the center of
the new box should be close to the centers of the input boxes.
So these are the three input boxes and the centers.
Um, so we would like to take kind of intuitively the intersection between them.
So we want the new center to be kind of a function of these three centers,
and we want the intersection to be kind of close to- to them.
And then the offset,
so the size of the box,
should shrink, since, uh,
the size of the intersection is smaller than the size of,
uh, any of the input sets,
or any of the input boxes.
So formally, we'll have
this intersection operator that will take an arbitrary set of boxes,
and produce a new box.
Now the way we define this operator is we need to say what is happening to the center,
and what is happening to the offset of the intersection.
The way we are going to find the center of the intersection is,
we are going to do this through a learned oper- operation.
Our learning operation will take the following,
it will take the centers of the boxes that are on
the input and then we are going to learn this function, f,
that takes a center of the box and, um,
and transforms it and then we will apply softmax to this, uh, to dysfunctions.
What this will allow us to do is that,
basically the - the intuition is that the center of the intersection would be
somewhere in this green region defined by the centers of the input boxes.
We define the center as a weighted sum of the input box centers,
where W is this weight,
the importance of our- of our given box on the intersection of boxes.
So, W represents, in some sense,
a self attention score on the cen- how much a center of
each input box affects the center of the intersection box.
Uh, and this funny operator is called Hadamard product,
which is basically element-wise product, right?
It's just you - you uh - uh,
take product of cells uh,
that correspond, uh, to each other.
So this is how center uh,
is defined and of course,
f is a function that we are going to learn.
Similarly now, we also have to define the offset.
And the way we are going to define the offset of the intersection is to
take- is we'll take the min- smallest of all the input boxes,
so we take the minimum in terms of the offsets.
And then we are going to also learn this offset function,
f offset, that is going to aggregate and transform the offsets.
So here, the - the intuition is that if we first take
the minimum of the offsets of input boxes and then make the model more
expressive by introducing- introducing this new function f_off for extracting
the representation of the input boxes with the sigmoid function to guarantee shrinking,
uh, of the- of the offset.
Again this f_off will have some trainable parameters uh,
that will uh, that we are going to learn
through the training process uh, of the entire model.
So, uh, you know, intuitively,
the idea is that once I have two boxes on the input,
I wanna- I wanna produce the intersection of the two boxes and in our case,
the intersection of the two boxes, for example,
would be this, uh, shaded, uh, area here.
Uh, and that- and whatever entities are enclosed or are close to this box,
uh, those are the answers,
uh, to our, uh, query.
So now, what we need to do is,
so far I said, oh, um,
entities that are the answer that are included in the box,
they have to be kind of inside the box, right?
In reality, this might be uh, harder,
because, uh, data is noisy, um, uh,
there might be inconsistencies,
contradictions in the knowledge graph,
so we need to define the notion of distance between the box and a point.
And the idea will be that, uh, we are going to define this distance to have two parts.
We're going to define the distance from the center to the point,
if the point is inside the box,
and if it's outside the box,
then we'll take the distance between the center and the corner and the corner,
uh, and the point.
Um, and the point here is that we wanna be able to uh,
account for the distance differently.
We wanna measure distance, uh, uh,
from the center if, uh,
when the- when the point is inside the box in some set of units.
And then we are going to have this, uh,
weight scalar Alpha that will, uh, uh,
be less than one so that basically we- we are going to
penalize the- the- the distance from the center of the box,
uh, more if the point is, uh,
inside than if it is,
uh, outside the box.
Uh, and the intuition is that if the point is enclosing the box,
it should- the box should be, uh,
it should be very close, uh,
to the center of the box so that we get more robustness from our- from our approach.
We don't want the point to be kind of close to the border or the edge of the box,
we want it towards the center of the box.
So that's how we now define the- the distance between the entity and the box.
So now when we have the final embedding of the query,
all we do is basically apply this distance, um,
and say who are the points that are closest according to this distance,
uh, to the center,
uh, of the box.
So now we have discussed two things.
We discussed how we can embed everything, uh,
all the entities as boxes,
how we learn the- the box transformation operation,
the projection operation that is one per relation,
and then we talked about how we learn
these intersection conjunction operator that takes the- as an input,
a set of boxes,
and produces the intersection box.
Of course, our natural question next is,
could I- could I have these predictive queries,
uh, even with a union operator?
So, for example, to be able to answer queries like OR.
Um, and so next what we are going to look at is,
how would you be able to answer what we will call AND-OR queries?
Or what is technically called existential positive first-order queries.
So basically, these are queries with conjunction and disjunction operator, right?
So the question is, how would we be able to dis- are we able to
design a disjunction operator and embed
AND-OR queries in low dimensional vector space and be able to
answer predictive AND-OR queries in the,
uh, space as well.
So the question is,
can we embed AND- AND-OR queries in a low-dimensional space?
The answer is actually no.
The reason for that is that allowing union over
arbitrary sets requires high dimensional embeddings.
So let me quickly give you a sense why we need a lot of dimensions.
Imagine I'm given three queries, q1, q2,
q3, and each one of them has one answer.
Uh, you know, q1 has v1 as an entity,
v1 has answer q2,
v2, and q3,
v3 entity has the answer.
So now, imagine I- I allow an entity operation, right,
which basically means I can take, uh,
any pair of queries and do an OR between them.
So the answer set will be, uh,
the answer set for the first query union the answer set,
uh, of the second query.
So given that we have two queries,
sorry, given that we have three queries, the question is,
uh, can- would we be able to model union operation when we embed them,
let's say on a two-dimensional plane?
And yes, you could, right?
Basically, you say for every individual query,
I can simply put a box around the entity and this would mean, uh,
for a given query,
I want the entity that is the answer to it to be inside the box and that's,
uh, you know, easy to achieve.
We can space these entities apart and put a box around each one of them and say,
uh-huh, the box is the embedding of the query and
the answer to the query is embedded inside the box.
You know, all good.
How about the unions?
Um, in this case,
I can easily, uh, do the union.
This is, for example, how a box of union 1,
query 1, union query 2 would look like so, uh,
q1 or q2, this is how, uh,
q2 or q3 would look like,
and this is how uh,
q1, uh, or q3, uh, would look like.
So it seems it all works for three queries in two dimensions. However-
What if we have four points?
So imagine now I have four queries.
I have four queries each one with one entity as the answer.
Can I now use a two-dimensional space to embed them,
um, and be able to do arbitrary unions between arbitrary queries?
Uh, and it turns out I cannot design a box embedding such that, for example,
in this case, that would represent the union of q, q_2, or q_4.
Because there will always be some other kind of box or some other entity,
um, uh, in- in between them, right?
And if I move this entity away, perhaps here,
then I won't be able to- to- to model the union between v_1 and v_4.
So basically, um, there will always be, um, some issue.
And, uh, what is the conclusion, or if you,
um, if you do the, uh, mathematics carefully,
what turns out is that if you have M, uh,
queries or M entities with non-overlapping answers um,
then you need the dimensionality of order M to handle arbitrary OR queries, right?
So in our case, we said if I have three queries, I need two-dimensions,
if I have four queries I need three-dimensions,
and so on and so forth.
So because real- real world knowledge graph have a lot of entities, for example,
you know, FB15k has 15,000 entities and it's considered a small knowledge graph.
This would mean that if we want to be able to- to uh,
model arbitrary OR operation between arbitrary sets of entities,
this would mean we need an embedding dimension of 15,000.
And uh, that's far uh,
far too much for us to be able to do this.
So, um, it seems, um, hopeless, right?
Since we cannot embed AND-OR queries in low-dimensional space can we still handle them?
And actually, the answer is yes.
And the answer is yes because we can rewrite the query to, um, in uh,
into a different form so that the query is kind of logically equivalent,
but the union operation happens all at the end, right?
So the idea is if I have the original query plan, where I,
you know take two projections,
take the union, take one more projection,
and take- then take an intersection,
I can rewrite this into a different query plan that gives me the identical answer,
it's logically equivalent, but the union only happens at the end.
So why is this beneficial?
Because I already know how to answer this part to get a box.
I know how to answer this- this part up to here to get a box.
So now, uh, write these the answer to my query?
Is simply entities included in the first box and entities included in the second box.
So that's very easy to do because the union occurs,
uh, at, uh, always as- as a last step.
So what is important is any AND-OR query can be transformed into uh,
an equivalent what is called, um,
disjunctive normal form, which is a disjunction of conjunctive queries.
Um, and this means that if I have a query that's now a disjunction of conjunctions,
I can simply first answer these conjunctions,
and then take the OR or the union at the end.
So it means, um,
we can aggregate these unions uh, at the last step.
That is one caveat is that when you do this transformation into disjunctive normal form,
so from the original query to the disjunctive normal form,
the size of the query can increase exponentially.
Um, but in our case,
this is not the problem because answering queries um,
is so uh, is so fast,
it's just kind of uh,
navigating the embedding space.
So this doesn't, uh, doesn't sound like too big,
uh, of a problem.
So now that we have um,
defined the uh, the disjunctive normal form and we have rewritten the uh,
the query as a set of conjunctive queries and then apply the OR operation at the end,
then all we need to do is to change the notion of the distance between the query,
the embedding of the query um, and the entity.
And the way we can write this out mathematically is very intuitive.
We say that um, the query in the disjunctive normal forum,
conjunctive query q_1 or q_2 or q_3,
we can simply define the distance between the embedding of
this query and the entity to be- to be the minimum of
the distances between the- the box distances
between the individual conjunctive queries and that entity.
So basically we say the entity is an answer uh,
to the query if it is inside at
least one of the individual conjunctive query boxes, right?
So that it is close to at least one of the,
uh, conjunctive queries q.
So that's why we have the minimum here, right?
So as long as v is the answer to the one conjunction,
query q then the distance between that query and v will be uh, very small.
And we achieve this by using this minimum uh, based uh, distance.
So, um, this now, uh, er, uh,
allows us basically to- to answer uh,
arbitrary AND-OR predictive queries.
So the way we would go about this,
if- as we are given a query q at the beginning,
we would rewrite it into a disjunctive normal form.
So a, uh, disjunction of conjunctive queries q_1 to q_m.
We would uh, embed this q_1 to q_m using this set of box operations,
meaning uh, projections and uh, intersections.
And then we would simply calculate the box distance between each q_i uh,
from the disjunctive normal form and entity v and uh, take the minimum of these distances.
And then the final score of an entity is simply the dista- is
this minimum base distance between the entire uh, query uh, and uh,
the- and the embedding of a given entity uh,
for which we are interested in assessing how likely is that the entity an answer uh,
to our uh, to our query.
So now we have talked about how the method
works from the point of view of once the embeddings are there,
once the box operators are there, uh,
how do we apply it to answer an arbitrary predictive query?
The question is, uh what kind of training procedure do we use to learn this all?
What does this mean is,
we need basically a simil- a- a setup similar to knowledge graph
completion task so that we can learn all these parameters, right?
Um, when I say parameters,
I mean we need to learn entity embeddings,
we need to learn these relation embeddings,
these box transformations, and we need to learn the intersection operator.
And the way we are going to learn this is basically that we are going to select uh,
or sample or create a set of queries.
For every query, we are going to have a positive set of entities.
This will be our set of answers.
We are going to have a negative set of entities,
this will be non-answers.
And, uh, our goal will be to- to learn all these uh,
parameters in such a way that answers are included
in the final box and non-answers are uh, outside the box.
So let me, uh, uh, summarize this.
So we are going to first randomly sample query q from
the training knowledge graph and
identify an- an entity v that is the answer uh, to that query.
Then we are also going to identify some negative entity,
let's call it v prime,
that is not an answer to the query, right?
So for example, I could say,
uh, I start uh, with uh,
let's go back to our uh,
Barack Obama nationality American.
So, uh, I would say- I would sample a query um, uh, nationality.
This is a simple kind of knowledge graph completion query,
not even a multi- multi-hop.
Uh, I start with Obama,
along with the nationality,
I find American, so that's a positive entity.
And then perhaps I say a negative entity could be some other random uh,
entity in uh, in the graph.
Um, perhaps it could be Paris, uh,
or if I want to be smarter I say I have the true entities
of type Americans, so United States.
So I want to pick another country, perhaps Germany,
as a negative example,
as a non-answer uh, to this query.
Now that um, I,
now that I have sampled the query and the answer and non-answer,
I embed the query using the transformations and then I calculate the score function f uh,
of entity v, which is the answer entity,
and the entity v prime,
which is the non-answer uh, entity.
And then the goal is that now I can compute the gradients, uh,
with respect, uh, to this, uh,
loss function l where the goal is to maximize,
uh, the- the score of the entity v. So basically, uh,
it means maximize the negative distance,
which means minimize the distance,
while minimizing, uh, the distance of the non-answer.
So the lo- the way we write the loss is, we say, uh, s- uh, uh,
f- uh, Sigma is a sigmoid function,
uh, that has value,
you know, between 0 and 1,
so basically, I'm saying I want,
uh, to, uh, maximize, uh,
f for, uh, the answer,
and I wanna minimize,
uh, f for the non-answer.
And now I can take gradient or derivative with
respect to this loss function to then be able to update
both the entity embeddings as well as the projection and
intersection operator parameters in order to be able to learn this, uh, well.
Of course, we are not only to  going to sample one-hop queries,
we are also going to sample two-hop queries,
three-hop queries, intersection type queries, uh,
all kinds of different, uh, query structures,
and that will be, uh,
our, uh, training set.
And then given these queries,
given an answer entity,
the- and non-answer entity,
we are going to, uh, optimize this likelihood,
meaning we are going to find parameters of the model
which is embeddings of entities plus these,
uh, operators so that all these, uh,
will, uh, optimize, uh, the loss function.
So how do we, uh,
how do we instantiate, uh,
a query, uh, in the knowledge graph?
We will assume we are given a query template, and then we, uh,
in- instantiate the query, uh,
will simply be to do the backward walking.
Uh, what I mean by that is we are, uh,
basically start from the initial answer entity,
and then we are kind of going to walk backwards towards the anchored entities, right?
So, um, in our case,
for example, we could say,
let's take fulvestrant as our, uh, answer entity.
So now we are going- now that we have kind of
randomly picked this entity from the knowledge graph,
we're going to kind of move backward, uh,
along the knowledge graph to then get the- the query plan,
the query structure, right?
So we are just at fulvestrant,
then we, um, uh, move,
we say we're- we will need to take intersection of two relations,
relation 1 and relation 2,
so let's pick two relations from,
uh, fulvestrant and move backward.
And then now that we are here,
we moved across TreatedBy.
Uh, now, we can again move one step, uh,
backward along the projection operator, um,
for the second type of relation like, uh, associated.
And, uh, now this will now become my anchor entity.
And now, uh, I do the same thing for the second relation,
uh, here CausedBy and find the second, uh, anchor entity.
So now I have just sampled the query that goes from ESR2 and shortness of breath,
through associated TreatedBy, as well as from shortness of breath to CausedBy,
and the intersection of them is the fulvestrant.
So this is now my sampling, uh, of the query.
And then what I can do is, uh,
find some entity that is not answer to this query and use that as a,
uh, non, uh, answer, right?
Uh, it is important when we do this sampling to be careful, uh,
because the query q must have answers,
uh, on the KG.
Um, and we will take one of the answers as instantiated, uh,
uh, answer for our, uh,
positive example, and, um,
we're then going to basically randomly sample some negative,
uh, examples, non-answers, which are basically other entities, uh,
in the knowledge graph, but we have to be careful that we are not, uh,
by accident sampling some other entity that's also,
uh, answer, uh, to the query.
So that's, uh, essentially the idea.
Um, and the- the- the impressive thing is that we can actually make this,
uh, all work and that now we are able to answer arbitrary, uh,
predictive queries in knowledge graphs, uh,
even though they might be notoriously, uh,
incomplete or, uh, may not have,
uh, uh, all the edges.
And what I wanna do to, uh,
finish the lecture is give you a quick,
um, example of how would this look like.
So, for example, here we are going to take the Freebase 15,000, uh,
knowledge graph, which is a knowledge graph about, uh,
real-world entities, uh, people,
uh, things like that.
And imagine we wanna have a query, uh, you know,
who are all male instrumentalists who play string instruments, right?
Uh, and we are going to, uh,
use our system to learn the embedding of, uh,
all the nodes, uh, all the entities to learn the projection operator,
to learn the conjunction operator.
Um, and then we are going to take this, uh,
high-dimensional embedding and we are going to project it
down to just two dimensions so we can visualize it, right?
So, um, here's the visualization, right?
So here is at, uh,
15,000, uh, different dots,
one corresponding to the embedding of, uh, each entity,
and these are real entities with real embeddings,
and here is our, uh, query plan, right?
We, uh, we wanna answer, uh,
you know, who are male instrumentalists who play string instruments,
so we'll start with string instruments as the anchor entity, go over, um,
the instance of relation to find all st- instances of string instruments,
then we are going to go over,
uh, PlayedBy, uh, relation, uh,
to identify all the- all the people who
play these string instruments, any of them, right?
And then we are going to go from node male to say
instance of to find all the instances of male, uh,
males in our dataset,
and now we need to take the intersection to find all the males
who are also playing any of the string, uh, instruments.
So let me show you how this, uh,
actually works in this, uh, two-dimensional projection.
So, uh, the anchor node for string instrument,
if you would, uh, locate it,
is actually here, uh, the blue one.
Now I will take and apply a box transformation that will say,
uh, what are the instances of the string, uh, instrument, right?
What are all the individual string instruments?
Um, and if I do this,
um, actually notice now,
um, the- the dot- the- the dots will have different types of colors.
True-positive means, this is a string instrument inside the box.
Um, false-negative means this is a string instrument outside the box.
Uh, false-positive would be, um,
other entities that are not string instruments but are inside the box.
And true-entities are non-string instruments outside the box.
And what you see here is that basically,
we are able to perfectly enclose all the string instruments inside the box,
and there are 10- 10, uh,
instances of a string instrument in our dataset.
So we have just identified,
uh, all the string instruments in the embedding space.
Now we wanna take the box of, um,
all the string instruments and transform it to cover,
uh, the- the people,
uh, females and males, right?
Who play these instruments.
Uh, and if we do this, uh, here is the,
uh, these are the entities that are inside the box.
Again, because this is a two-dimensional projection, you know,
this is not a box,
uh, but in high-dimensions it is.
And again, we see that we are able to cover, basically, um,
98, uh, percent of all the- all the,
uh, all the- all the, uh,
instrumentalists of string instruments,
and that, we have a few false positives,
basically a few other entities, um,
that are not instrumentalists of string instruments,
but are still inside the box, right?
So there is a bit of error,
but the point is now we have 472 instrumentalists,
both musicians, female and male,
who play string instruments like a guitar, right?
So now, uh, with this,
let's move to the second part where we take the male,
uh, the node male.
Um, the male- the node, uh,
is here, uh, and now we wanna say, uh,
do the box transformation instance of to
cover all the males in this, uh, knowledge graph.
And if we do this, this is kind of the entities that are inside the male box,
it's, uh, 3,500 of them.
So we basically went from one entity to a giant box that covers,
uh, 3,500, uh, males that are,
uh, represented in this dataset.
Now that we have these two boxes,
we wanna apply the intersection,
uh, operator, uh, to this,
that you take the two boxes and take the intersection between them.
Um, and if you do this, the intersection, um,
has, uh, almost 400 different entities,
and these are the entities that are predicted to be,
uh, male players of string, uh, instruments.
What is interesting, you see that basically,
we are able to almost perfectly answer, uh,
this query even though we were doing all these operations,
uh, directly, uh, in the embedding space.
And this is just one example how we can basically answer, uh,
arbitrary predictive queries, uh,
over these, uh, types of incomplete, uh, knowledge graphs.
So, um, to summarize today's lecture;
uh, we introduced, uh,
um, the problem of a, uh,
logical reasoning in knowledge graphs using embeddings, and in particular,
we talked about how are we formulating
answering queries as a predictive machine learning task.
So we basically, rather than traversing the knowledge graph,
we have defined the task in terms of a binary prediction task that says,
"Predict what entities are the answer to a given query."
And the benefit of our approach is that it is,
uh, very scalable, meaning, uh,
answering queries is very simple because it just requires, uh,
transforming boxes and then checking what entities are inside the box.
Um, and it is also very robust because we
don't rely on individual links of the knowledge graph,
but we really rely on the embeddings and the relationships in the embedding space.
Um, and the key idea for today's lecture was we wanna
embed queries by navigating the embedding space, right?
We have this com- we've- we took advantage of
this compositional property of uh, TransE method,
and then we extended TransE to this notion of
box embeddings so that we can then define the intersection of boxes.
Um, and we learned how to transform boxes according to given relations,
we call this a projection operator,
um, and then we also showed how the,
um, how the union operations can also be carried
out- carried out by rewriting the query into the- a disjunctive normal form and,
um, apply the union operator,
uh, all the way, uh, at the end.