In the last part
of this lecture,
I'm actually going to talk about
an application of deep graph
generative models to
molecule generation, right?
So basically, if you want to
generate drug-like molecules,
you can use graph
generative models.
So let me tell you about that.
So what we are going
to do is the following.
The question is,
can we learn a model
that can generate valid and
realistic molecules that
optimize some property?
Right.
So the way you
can think of it is
that we want to have a model.
The model is going to
output a given molecule.
This molecule has to be valid--
basically, it has to obey
the rules of chemistry.
It also has to be
realistic, right?
You cannot generate some
Frankenstein type molecule.
It has to be realistic.
It has to look like a drug.
And we want it to
optimize a given property.
For example, we want it
to optimize drug likeness.
We want to optimize
its solubility.
And the paper I'm going to
talk about, or the method
is called Graph
Convolutional Policy
Network for Goal-directed
Molecular Graph Generation.
And it's linked here.
And you can read it if
you want more details.
So, here is a high level
overview of this paper,
and of this novel problem of
optimal molecule generation,
right?
The goal here is to generate
graphs that optimize a given
objective, like drug-likeness,
that obey underlying rules--
meaning that the
graphs are valid,
like chemical validity
rules, like the bonds
and things like that--
and are learned from
examples, meaning
they look realistic, right?
They imitate molecular graphs
which we use for training,
right?
And we just talked
a bit about how
do we imitate a given
distribution of graphs.
But here the difference is,
we don't want to only imitate,
we want to generate
graphs that are valid,
and we want to
generate graphs that
actually optimize a
given criteria, a given
black box, right?
And here the important point
is that the criteria is really
a black box, right?
It's this black box where
the graph generation
will get some feedback, right?
The objectives
like drug-likeness
are governed by physical
laws, which to us will
be assumed they are unknown.
What I mean by that is we don't
need them to be written down.
All we have to do is
to have a black box.
If we give it a
molecule, the black box
tells us how good
that molecule is.
But we don't have to
look into the box.
That's the important point.
So, how are we going to do this?
We are going to do this and cast
it as a reinforcement learning
problem.
And the way with
reinforcement learning,
the way that we formalize it is
that we have a machine learning
agent that observes
the environment,
takes an action to interact
with the environment,
and then receives a
positive or negative reward.
And then the agent wants
to learn from this loop.
And the key idea is
that agent can directly
learn from the
environment, which
is a black box to
the agent, right?
So we think that there
is the environment.
The agent is taking
actions, and it's
interacting with
the environment,
and the environment is
giving back some feedback,
some rewards to the agent.
And there are two
types of the rewards,
there is the
instantaneous reward
and then there is the
long term reward, right?
In our case,
instantaneous reward
will did I just add an
atom to the molecule,
and I did it according to
the rules of chemistry.
And then the long
term reward will
be after we are done with
generating the molecule, how
good was that molecule?
That's the long term reward.
OK.
So the solution to this
goal-directed molecule
generation, we call it Graph
Convolutional Policy Network
that combines graph
representation
and reinforcement learning.
And the key component
of GCPN is that we
are going to use a graph neural
network to capture the graph
structure information,
we are going
to use reinforcement
learning to guide
the generation towards
the desired objective,
and we are going to
use supervised learning
to imitate examples on a given
training data set, right?
We want our molecules
to look realistic.
How does GCPN differ
from GraphRNN?
First, what is the commonality?
The commonality is that these
are both generative models
for graphs, and they
try to kind of imitate
or they can be learned
given a data set.
What are the main
differences is that GCPN
is going to use a graph
neural network to predict
the generation of
the next action,
and while GraphRNN is using
the hidden state of an RNN
to decide on the next action.
A graph neural network
is more expressive
than a recurrent neural
network, so that's
the benefit of
the GCPN approach,
but on the negative
side, the GNN
takes longer time to
compute than an RNN.
So molecules
generally are small,
so we can afford this more
complex algorithm that
has bigger expressive
power, and it
will-- is able to learn more.
So GCPN will then also
use reinforcement learning
to direct graph generation
towards our goal,
towards our black box.
And reinforcement learning will
enable us this goal directed
graph generation.
So to give you an idea,
both of these two,
both GCPN and GraphRNN are
sequential graph generation
approaches.
But in the GraphRNN we
predict the action based
on the RNN hidden state, right?
So the node gives the hidden
state to the edge level RNN,
and then the hidden
state is passed on,
and the edges have
generated, and then
the hidden state goes back
to the node level RNN, right?
So basically all the
information, all the history
is captured in
this hidden state.
And if you have
generated 10,000 nodes,
this means this hidden state has
been transformed 10,000 times,
and then for every edge
it's also been transformed.
So it's a lot that this
hidden state needs to capture.
So in a GCPN, we won't have
this notion of a hidden state,
but we are going to use the
GNN to basically give me
the embeddings of the nodes.
So I'm going to say, here is
a partially generated graph,
and here is a new node.
What I'm going to
do is I'm going
to embed each of the nodes in
the partially generated graph,
and then I'm also going to have
some embedding for the new node
number 4.
And then, based on
these embeddings,
I'm now going to
predict which node
number 4 should link to, right?
So this means that
basically now I'm
not using the RNN to do this,
but I'm using a graph neural
network to generate the
state, and then I'm simply
doing link prediction.
So I'm kind of using--
predicting potential links
using node embeddings
rather than to directly generate
them based on the hidden state.
That's the difference.
And this would be much more
scalable, sorry, much more
expressive, much more
robust, but less scalable
because we have to now
compute these embeddings
and then evaluate
these link predictions
for every single action.
So the overview of GCPN
is that it has these
following four steps, right?
First, we are going
to insert the nodes.
Then we are going to
use the GNN to predict
which nodes are going to
connect with each other.
Then we are going
to take an action,
and we are going to
check chemical validity.
And then if the
action is correct,
we say yes, you
created a good edge,
you didn't create a good edge.
And then, after the model is
done generating the graph,
we are going to compute
the final reward.
We are going to ask
the black box, what
do you think of the
molecule we generated?
So a few questions
about the reward--
we will have two rewards.
One will be the
reward per step, which
will be basically to--
whether the model has
learned to take a valid action.
Basically, at each step
a small positive reward
will be awarded for taking a
valid action-- so basically,
by respecting the
rules of chemistry.
And the final reward will be
proportionate to the-- the goal
is for it to optimize
the desired property
of the molecule, right?
At the end, we are going
to get huge positive reward
if the molecule is
good, and a low reward,
or no reward if the
molecule is bad, right?
And the total reward is
going to be final reward
plus these stepwise rewards.
And then, in terms of training
the model, there are two parts.
First is the
supervised training,
where we are going to train
the policy by imitating
the actions given real observed
graphs using the gradient.
So basically, here
we are just kind
of going to try to
learn our model how
to generate realistic molecules
and not worry about optimizing
the structure yet.
So it's just about learning
to generate proper molecules
and obey chemistry.
And then in the second
part of the training
we are going to actually
train a policy that
optimizes the reward.
And here we are going to use
a standard policy gradient
algorithm that is kind of
classical reinforcement
learning.
But the point is, we are going
to have two steps of training,
one to learn the chemistry
and then the second one
to learn how to
optimize the reward.
And now if I want
to show you this,
we will have the
partially generated graph,
the GCPN is going to decide how
to grow it one node at a time
and how to create connections.
We are going to get
small positive reward
and the gradient
based on the fact
that we have generated
the graph correctly.
And this is going to
loop until we decide
the molecule is generated.
Now that the molecule
is generated,
we are going to ask our
black box to tell us
how good is this molecule.
And then this final
reward is going to be
also back-propagated, right?
So this generation is
going to be trained
using the supervised
learning, and then
this overall end-to-end
with the delayed reward
will be trained in this
kind of reinforcement
learning framework.
And what is the benefit
of this approach
is that we can generate
molecules that try
to optimize a given property.
So here I'm showing
you different molecules
that optimize log P, which is
a particular chemical property,
or here we are
optimizing QED, which
is the quantum energy--
again, something
that medicinal
chemists worry about.
And you can see how these
graphs that we generate
look like real molecules.
Another thing that this
allows you to do-- it
allows you to take a
partially-built molecule
and complete it.
So for example, you can start
with some starting structure,
where here, log B--
I think it's solubility.
So basically you start with some
very bad values of solubility,
and then you say, how do
I complete this structure
to improve solubility?
And here you see how it went
from minus 8 to minus 0.7,
and from minus 5 to minus
2, by basically completing
the molecule, right?
So this is the point, is
we can take, basically,
a partially built structure or
finish it, or create a brand
new structure.
So let me summarize the
lecture of graph generation.
So complex graphs can be
successfully generated
via sequential generation
using deep learning.
Each step is a decision that is
made based on the hidden state,
and this hidden state can
either be implicit or explicit.
In the RNN, this
vector representation
about keeping the
state was implicit
because it was all in this
hidden state, while in the GCPN
the state was explicit because
it was computed directly
on the intermediate graphs and
encoded by a neural network.
I also showed you possible
tasks for GraphRNN.
We talked about imitating
a given set of graphs.
For the second
part, for GCPN, we
talked about optimizing
graphs to a given goal.
I talked about the application
to molecule generation
to try to generate molecules
with optimal properties,
but you could apply this to any
kind of graph generation task,
to any kind of
property-- for example,
including generating
realistic maps,
generating realistic cities,
road networks, materials,
and things like that.