Next, we are going to talk about deep learning for
graphs and in particular, graph neural networks.
So now that we have kind of refreshed our notion of,
uh, how general, uh,
neural networks- uh, deep neural networks work,
let's now go and generalize neural networks so that they can be applicable to graphs.
That's what we are going to do next.
So, uh, the content is that we are going to talk about local network neighborhoods.
And we are then going to describe
aggregation strategies and define what is called, uh, computation graphs.
And then we are going to talk about how do we
stack multiple layers of these neural networks, uh,
to talk about how do we describe the model parameters training- how do we fit the model,
and how do we se- how do we- and give
a simple example for unsupervised and supervised training.
So this is what we are going to talk about and what we are going to learn,
uh, in this part, uh, of the lecture.
So the setup is as follows.
Um, we are going to assume we have a graph G that has a set of vertices,
a set of nodes.
It has an adjacency matrix.
Right now let's assume it's binary,
so means unweighted graph.
Let's also, for simplicity, assume it's undirected,
but, uh, everything will generalize to directed graphs as well.
And let's assume that every node, uh,
also has a para- uh,
a node feature vector X associated with it, right?
So, um, you know,
what are node features?
For example, in social network,
this could be user profile,
user image, a user age.
In biological network, it could be a gene expression profile,
uh, gene functional information.
And, for example, if there is no, um,
node feature information the- in the dataset, um,
what people like to do is either use indicator vectors,
so one-hot encodings of nodes,
or just a vector of all constants, uh, value 1.
Uh, those are two, uh, popular choices.
Sometimes people also use a degree, uh,
as fe- a node degree as a feature, uh, of the node.
And then another piece of notation,
we are going to- to denote N of v to be a set of neighbors of a given node,
uh, v. And that's basically the notation,
the setup, uh, we are going to use,
uh, for this part of the lecture.
Now, if you say,
how could I go and apply deep neural networks to graphs?
Here is a naive, uh, simple approach.
The idea you could have is to say,
why don't I represent a network with adjacency matrix?
And then why don't I append the node features to the adjacency matrix?
Now think of this as a training example and feed it through a deep neural network, right?
It seems very natural.
I take my network,
represent it as an adjacency matrix,
I append node features to it.
Now, this is, you know,
the input to the neural network,
um, and I'm able to make predictions.
Uh, the issue with this idea is several.
First is that the number of parameters of
this neural network will be multiple times the number of nodes in the network.
Because number of inputs here is the number of nodes plus the number of features.
And if you say how- what is the- how many training examples I have,
I have one training example per node.
So it means you'll have more parameters than you have training examples
and training will be very unstable and it will easily overfit.
Another issue with this is that this model
won't be applicable to graphs of different sizes.
Because if now I have a graph that has a height of seven nodes,
it's unclear how to fit a graph of seven nodes into five different inputs, right?
Because here we have a graph of five nodes.
So that's one, uh,
big- uh, big issue.
And another big issue is subtle but very
important is that this approach will be sensitive to know node ordering.
Meaning right now I number nodes as A, B,
C, uh, D, and E in the following order so my adjacency matrix was like this.
But now if I were to call for example node E- to call it A, B,
C, D, and E,
then the shape of my adjacency matrix would change, right?
The nodes, uh, would be permuted.
The rows and columns of the matrix will be permuted even
though the information is still the same.
And in that case,
the mind would get totally confused and wouldn't know what to- what to output.
So the point is that in graphs there is no fixed node ordering so
it's unclear how to sort the nodes of the graph that you could,
um, you know, put them as inputs in the matrix.
That's much easier in images because you say I'll start with the top-left pixel,
and then I- I'll kind of go line-by-line.
In- in the graph,
the same graph can represented by- in- by many different adjacency matrices,
because it all depends on the ordering or- uh,
in- in which you labeled or numbered the nodes.
So we have to be invariant to node ordering.
So the idea of what we are going to do is we're going to kind of,
take- borrow some intuition from convolutional neural networks,
from computer vision, but generalize them to graphs.
So here's a quick idea about what convolutional neural networks do.
Like if you have an image here,
you know, represented as this grid,
then you define this convolutional operator, basically,
this sliding window that you are sliding over the image, right?
You start at the top-left.
This is now a three-by-three operator.
You compute something over this,
uh, area of the image,
and then you slide the operator by, you know,
some number of steps to the right and apply the same operator again.
And- and you can keep doing this and you can imagine that now this will give
you a new image of different size, of different- uh, um, uh,
different number of rows and columns to which you can
apply another, uh, convolutional operator,
another kind of sliding window type operator that kind of goes over the rows,
uh, uh, of that- of that image.
And if you just chain this, uh,
together, uh, you can then, uh,
come up, uh, with convolutional neural networks and, uh, good predictions.
Our goal here is to generalize this notion of convolution between simple lattices,
between simple- uh, beyond simple matri- uh,
matrices, uh, and also leverage node features and attributes.
Like, for example, text or images that might be attached to the nodes of the network.
The issue is that our networks are much more complex.
So defining the node- the notion of a sliding window,
let's- let's say, uh,
you know, a three-by-three window,
it's- is- is very strange because maybe in some case, you know,
the sliding window may only cover three nodes in other-
in other case the sliding window may cover many more nodes.
And it's unclear how to define this notion of a window,
and then it's also unclear how to define the notion of sliding the window over the graph.
And this is a big, uh,
complexity and a big challenge that, uh,
graph neural networks have to do, uh,
to be able to be applied to complex network data.
So the idea that makes this,
uh, work is the following step in intuition.
So the idea is that single convolutional- single layer of a convolutional,
uh, neural network, basically what it does it,
for example, takes- uh, takes the, uh,
area of three-by-three pixels,
apply some transformation to them and creates a new pixel.
And that's the way you can think of it, right?
And now we can take this operator and slide it across the image.
What we'd like to do in the graph is something similar, but, you know,
if you wanna apply this operator in terms of a- uh,
in terms of a, uh,
let's say like a sliding window,
then we will have a center of the sliding window, which is a node,
and this center is going to kind of borrow,
uh, aggregate information from its neighbors, right?
The same way here you can imagine that this is the center of the operator and
it's kind of collecting information from- from its neighbors,
denoted by arrows, takes its own value as well and creates a new value,
a new pixel, uh, for itself.
So the idea is that- that what convolutional operators are certainly doing,
they are transforming information from the neighbors,
combining it, and creating a new kind of a message.
So this is when today's lecture also relates to the,
uh, last lecture when we talked about message passing, right?
So today here we can think about a node collecting information from its neighbors,
collecting messages from its neighbors, aggregating them,
combining them, and creating a new message.
So, uh, that is the- that is the idea.
So how graph convolutional neural networks are going to work.
Um, the idea is that node's neighborhood defines the neural network architecture.
So basically the structure of the graph around a node of
interest defines the structure of the neural network.
Um, so the idea is,
if i wanna make a prediction for this red node,
I, here, uh, in the network,
then the way we can think of this is that i is going to take information,
uh, from its neighbors and neighbors are
going to take information from neighbors of neighbors.
And we are going to learn how to propagate this information,
how to transform it along the edges of the network,
how to aggregate the heat,
and how to create a new message that then the next node up the chain can again aggregate,
transform, um, and- and compute.
So in some sense,
the way we can think of graph neural networks is a two-step process.
In the first step process we determine the node computation graph.
And in the second process,
we then propagate, um,
the- the- the information,
we propagate and transform it over this computation graph.
And this computation graph defines the architecture or the structure of the underlying,
uh, neural network, right?
So, um, in this way,
we learn how to propagate information across
the graph structure to compute node features or,
uh, node, uh, embeddings.
So that's the intuition.
Let me give you an example of what I mean by this.
Consider here a very small,
um, input graph on six nodes.
Um, and what we will want to do is,
the key idea would be that you want to generate base- node embeddings based on
the local structure of the neighborhood around that target node.
So for this input graph and this is the target node, uh,
here is the structure of the neural network that is going to
make computation to be able to make a prediction for node A.
And let me explain you why is this neural network has this structure.
The reason is that node A is going to
take information from its neighbors in the network; B, C,
and D. So here are B, C,
and D. And then of course,
this is kind of one layer of computation,
but we can unfold this for multiple layers.
So if we unfold this for one more layer,
then node D takes information from its neighbor A.
And that's why we have this edge here.
Node C, for example,
takes information from its neighbors A, B,
uh, E, and F. They are- they are here; A, B,
and F. And then D takes information from A and C because it's connected to nodes,
uh, A and C. So now,
what does this mean is that if this is the structure of the, uh,
graph neural network, now what is- what we have to define,
what we have to learn is we have to learn
the message transformation operators along the edges as well as the aggregation operator.
Say, because node B says,
"I will collect the message from A,
I will collect the message from C. These messages will be transformed,
aggregated together in a single message,
and then I'm going to pass it on."
So that now node A can again say,
"I'll take message from B,
I will transform it.
I will take a message from C,
transform it, message from D, transform it.
Now I am going to aggregate these three messages into the new message and
pass it on to whoever is kind of in the layer, uh, above me."
So that is essentially the idea.
And of course, these transformations here,
uh, uh, aggregations and transformations will be learned.
They will be parameterized and distributed parameters of our model.
What is interesting and fundamentally different from classical neural networks,
is that every node gets to define its own neural network architecture.
Or every node gets to define
its own computation graph based on the structure of the network around it.
So what this means is, for example,
that, uh, blue node,
D here, its computation graph will be like this,
will very skinny because D takes information from A,
and A takes it from B and C. So it's a- you know,
this is now a two-layer neural network,
but it's very skinny, very narrow.
While for example, node C has a much bigger,
much wider neural network,
because C collects information from- from its four neighbors and
then each of the neighbors collect it from its own set of neighbors.
So that architecture, structure of this green neural network corresponding to nodes,
target node C, is very different than the one from the node, uh,
D. So what is interesting,
um, conceptually is that now,
every node has its own, uh,
computational graph or it has its own, um, architecture.
Um, some nodes, if the neighborhood of the network around them is similar,
for example, these two nodes will have the same computation graphs.
Like this is E and F,
you see the kind of the structure of these computation graphs,
these neural network architecture trees, uh, is the same.
But in principle, every node can have its own computation graph, that's first thing.
And then the second thing that's interesting,
now we are going to train or learn over multiple architectures simultaneously, right?
So it's not that we have one neural network on which we train
now every node comes with its own neural network,
uh, architecture, neural network structure.
And of course, the structure of the neural network for
a given node depends on the structure of the network around this node,
because this is how we determine the computation graph.
And that's kind of a very important, er,
kind of deep insight into how these things are
different than kind of classical, uh, deep learning.
So now, how do- how does this work as we have multiple layers, right?
So the point is that the model can be of arbitrary depth.
We can create an arbitrary number, uh, of, uh,
layers and nodes have embeddings at each layer.
Um, and the embedding at layer 0 of a given node
is simply initialized as its input features X.
And then the layer K embedding gets information
from nodes that are kind of K hops away, right?
So the way this would work is,
layer 0 embedding for nodes is simply their feature vectors,
so here, denoted by X.
Then for example, embedding of, um,
node B at layer 1 would be sum aggregation of feature- feature vectors of, ah,
of neighbors, uh, A and C, uh,
plus its own feature vector,
and this is now embedding of this node at layer 1.
And then this will be passed on, uh,
so that now node 2 can- node A can compute its embedding at layer 2.
So what it means is that the embedding of A at layer 0
is different than its embedding at layer 1- sorry, at layer 2.
So at every layer,
a node will have a different, uh, embedding.
And also, we are only going to run this for a limited number of steps.
We are not going to run this kind of infinitely long or
until it converges as- as we did in the last lecture.
We don't have this notion of convergence.
We'd only do this for a limited number of steps.
Each step corresponds to one layer of the neural network,
corresponds to one hop,
uh, in the underlying network.
So if we want to collect information from K hops away from the starting node,
from the target node,
we are going to need a K layer neural network.
And because networks have final diameter,
it makes no sense to talk about, I know,
100 layer, uh, deep neural networks.
Again, unless your network has diameter or that you know,
the longest, shortest path is of 100 hops.
So now that we have, uh,
defined the notion of how do we create
this computation graph based on the structure of the neighborhood around a given node,
now we need to talk about these transformations that happen in the neural network.
And the key concept is neighborhood aggregation.
Um, and the key distinction between different approaches,
different graph neural network architectures is how different,
uh, how this aggregation, uh, is done.
How this information from, uh,
children nodes is aggregated and combined,
uh, with the information or message of the pattern.
One important thing to notice is because
the ordering of the nodes in a graph is arbitrary;
this means that we have to have our aggregation operator to be,
um, uh, permutation invariant.
Right? So it- it- it means that, um,
we- we can order the nodes in any order and if we aggregate them,
the aggregation will always be the same, right?
That's the- that's the idea.
It doesn't matter in what order we aggregate,
we want the- the result to be always the same because it doesn't matter whether,
you know, node B has neighbors A- A and C,
or C and A,
they are just- it's just a set of elements.
So it doesn't matter whether we're aggregating, you know,
in that sense from A- A and C or C and A.
You should always get the same result.
So neighborhood aggregation function has to be,
uh, order invariant or permutation invariant.
So now, of course,
the question here is- that we haven't yet answered is,
what is happening in these boxes?
What do we put into these boxes?
How do we define these transformations?
How are they parameterized? How do we learn?
So the basic approach is, for example,
is to simply average information from the neighbors,
uh, and apply a neural network.
So average- so a summation,
use permutation or that invariant because in any number,
you sum up the- the- the numbers,
in any way you sum up the numbers,
you will always get the same result.
So average or a summation is a,
uh, permutation invariant aggregation function.
So for example, the idea here is that every- every of
these operators here will simply take the messages from the children,
uh, and average node,
and then decide to take this average and make a new message out of it.
So the way we can, um,
do this is do the, er,
we aggregate the messages and then we apply our neural network,
which means we apply some linear transformation followed by
a non-linearity to create a next, uh, level message.
So let me, uh, give you an example.
The basic approach is that we want to average messages coming from the children,
coming from the neighbors and apply a neural network to them.
So here is how this- uh,
how this looks like in equation. So let me explain.
So first, write H is a- our embedding and, uh, subscript means,
uh, the node and superscript denotes the neu- uh,
the level of the neural network.
So at the beginning are the zeroth layer,
the embedding of the node V is simply its feature representation.
And now we are going to create higher-order embeddings of nodes.
So right so this is a level zero so at level one,
what are we going to do is- is getting an equation and let me explain.
So first we say,
let's take the embeddings of the nodes from the previous uh,
from the previous layer.
So this is the embedding of this node v from the previous layer.
And let's multiply, transform it with some matrix B.
Then, what we are saying is let's also go over the neighbor's uh,
u of our node of interest v. And let's take the previous level embedding of every node u,
let's sum up these embeddings uh,
and average them so this is the total number of neighbor's.
And then let's transform this uh, uh,
aggregated average of embeddings of ma- of uh, children,
multiply it with another matrix and uh,
send these through a non-linearity, right?
So basically we say, I have my own message- my own embedding if I'm node v,
my own embedding from the previous layer, transform it.
I aggregate embeddings from my children,
from my neighbor's from previous level,
I multiply that to be the different transformation matrix.
I add these two together and send it through a non-linearity.
And this is a one layer of my neural network.
And now of course I can run this or do this for several times, right?
So this is now how to go from level l,
to level l plus 1, um,
you know to- to- to compute the first layer embeddings,
I use the embeddings from level zero,
which is just the node features.
But now I can run this for several kinds of iterations.
Lets say several- several layers,
maybe five, six, 10.
And then whatever is the final um, eh, um,
hidden representation of the final layer uh,
that is what I call uh,
the embedding of the node, right?
So we have our total number of capital L layers and
the final embedding of the node is simply h of v at the final uh,
at the final layer- level- at the final level of uh, neighborhood uh, aggregation.
And this is what is called a deep encoder,
because it is encoding information from
the previous layer- lay- lay- layer from a given node,
plus its neighbor's transforming it using matrices B and W,
and then sending it through a non-linearity to obs- to obtain next level uh,
representation of the node.
And we can basically now do this uh,
for several iterations, for several uh, layers.
So how do we train the model if every node gets its own computational architecture,
and every node has its own transformation uh,
parameters, basically this W and B?
The way we train the model is that we want to define what are the parameters of it?
And parameters are this matrices W and B,
and they are indexed by l. So for every layer we have a different W,
and for every layer we have a different uh, B.
And the idea here is that we can now uh,
feed this embeddings into the loss function and we can
run stochastic gradient descent to train the rate parameters,
meaning uh, B_l and uh, W_l.
Um, and these are the two parameters,
right one is the weight matrix for uh, neighborhood aggregation,
and the other one is the weight matrix for transforming hidden um, hidden vector uh,
embedding of uh, of- of the node itself uh,
to create then the next level uh, embedding.
So this is uh,
how we- how we do this,
what is important is that this weight matrices are shared across different nodes.
So what- what this means is that this l and v are not indexed by the node,
but all nodes in the network use the same transformation matrices.
And this is an important detail.
Um, as I have written things out so far,
I have written them out in terms of nodes aggregating from neighbor's.
But as we saw uh, earlier in graphs,
many times you can also write things in the matrix form.
So let me explain you how to write things uh,
in the matrix form, right?
Many aggregations can be performed efficiently if you uh,
write them out in terms of matrix operations.
So what you can do is you can take your um,
matrix H and simply stag the embeddings of the nodes together,
like here so every node is an embedding for a- for a- uh,
given uh, node of a given layer.
So we can define this notion of a matrix H^l,
and then write the way I can simply compute them basically by saying,
what is the sum o- of the embeddings- aggregation of embeddings um,
of nodes u that are neighbor's of v. This is simply
taking the- taking the uh, the correct um,
entry in the- in the adjacency matrix and multiplying it with the matrix uh,
H. And this way,
I'm basically averaging or aggregating the embeddings coming from the neighbor' s. Um,
then I can also define this notion of a diagonal matrix,
where basically this matrix is zero only on the diagonal of it.
We have uh, non-zero entries that are uh,
the degrees of individual nodes,
and then if you say what is the inverse of this diagonal matrix
D. It is another diagonal matrix where on the uh,
edges where around the entries on the diagonal,
I have now one over the degree um- so that
D- D times inverse of D is an identity matrix, right?
So now if you take this and combine it with this uh,
D minus 1 then you can write the neighborhood aggregation,
basically averaging of the neighborhood embeddings simply has uh D to the minus 1.
So the inverse of D, times adjacency matrix,
times the embeddings at level H,
at level l. So basically,
what this means is that I can write things in terms of this summation and averaging,
or I can write it as a product of three matrices,
a product of this diagonal matrix that has one over the diagonal uh,
one over the degree on the diagonal.
So this corresponds to this theorem uh,
A corresponds to summing over the neighbor's and H uh,
uh, superscript l are the embeddings of the nodes from the previous layer.
So this means I can think of this in terms of this kind of matrix equation,
or I can write it basically as neighborhood uh, aggregation.
So rewriting the update functioning matrix form then write- is- is like this, right?
It's basically take the- uh,
your embedding and multiply it with B, uh,
take the embeddings of the neighbor's from previous layer um,
and multiply them with W. Um,
so red part of corresponds to neighborhood aggregation,
blue part corresponds to uh, to self-transformation um.
And in practice what this implies is that uh,
efficient sparse matrix multiplication can be used
to train these models very efficiently.
So you can basically represent everything goes matrices,
and then you have matrix gradients uh,
and everything would work uh, very nicely.
Now, in the last few minutes,
I wanna talk about how to train this thing.
So the node embeddings z are- are a function of the input graph.
And we can train this in a supervised setting in a sense that we wanna minimize the loss,
the same way as we discussed so far, right?
I wanna make a prediction based on the embedding,
and I wanna minimize the discrepancy between the prediction and the truth.
Ur, where, you know,
y could be, for example,
an old label or a- or a scalar value.
Um, or I could even apply this in an unsupervised setting,
where I would say I want, you know,
the- the similar- where node labels are unavailable,
I can use the graph structure for supervision.
So I could define the notion of similarity and say, you know,
the dot product between the embeddings of
two nodes has to correspond to their similarity in the network.
And I could use now deep encoder to come up with the embeddings of the nodes,
rather than using the shallow, uh, uh,
shallow encoder, uh, but I could use the same decoder as in node to vet,
meaning the- the random walk and,
um, similarity matching using the dot problem.
So that's you- I can apply this in both settings.
Um, to explain how I could do,
uh, unsupervised training a bit more.
So the idea would- would be that similar,
uh, nodes have similar embeddings.
So the idea would be that, you know,
let- let y- let y_u,
v denote- be kept value one if node u and v are indeed similar,
for example, they- they code- they, uh,
code according to the same random work as defined in nodes to work.
Decoder of the two embeddings,
let's say, is a simple dot-product.
It says embedding of one times the embedding of the other,
and you want the- the discrepancy between the similarity and the, uh,
similarity in the graph versus similarity in the embedding space to be,
uh, small, so we can define this through the cross entropy.
Um, and then we could again just basically run this, uh, optimization problem,
to come up with the graph neural network that makes,
uh, the predictions, um,
as we- as we discussed.
So, um, the way we are going to train this,
is that we are going to train this either, as I said,
in this kind of unsupervised way,
and of course we can also directly train this in a supervised way.
Which means that perhaps, you know,
for a given node we have some, uh,
we have- we have some label about a node,
maybe this is a drug-drug interaction network,
and you know whether this drug is toxic,
uh, or not, whether it's safe or toxic.
So we could then say, you know,
given this neural network,
predict at the end the label of the node.
Whether it's safe or toxic.
And now, we can backpropagate based on label.
So both- both are o- both are possible,
either we directly train to predict the labels,
or we can train based on the network similarity,
where network similarity can be defined using random works,
the same way as in,
uh, node to work.
So for, uh, supervised training,
uh, basically what we wanna do is,
we wanna define, uh,
the loss, uh, in terms of let's say classification,
this is the cross entropy loss for a binary classification.
Basically here is the prediction of the label for a- for a- uh,
for a given color whether it's toxic or not,
this is whether it is truly toxic or not, um,
and then the way you can think of this is y takes value one if it's toxic,
and zero if it's not.
If the true value is zero,
then this term is going to survive and it's
basically one minus the lock predicted- prob- uh,
one minus the predicted probability.
So here we want this to be the predicted probability- to be as small as
possible so that one minus it becomes close to one because log of 1 is 0,
so that this discrepancy is small.
And if the- if the,
uh, class value is one,
then this term is going to survive because
1 plus 1- 1 minus 1 is 0 and this- this goes away.
So here we want this term to be as close to one as possible.
Which again would say, if it's- uh,
if it's toxic, we want the probability to be high.
If it's not toxic,
we want the probability [NOISE] to be low- uh,
the predicted probability, uh, of it being toxic.
And this is the cross, uh, entropy loss.
So this is the encoded input coming from node embeddings.
Uh, these are the classification rates,
uh, for the final classification.
Uh and these are the, uh, node labels,
is it basically toxic, uh, or not.
Um, and I can optimize this loss function,
uh, to basically come up with, uh,
the- the parameters B and W that give me the embedding that then makes,
uh, good or accurate predictions.
So let me just give an overview and,
uh, finish, uh, and complete the lecture.
So the way we think of modern design is that given the graph,
we wanna compute the,
uh, the embedding of a target node.
First, we need to define the neighborhood aggregation function.
Um, uh, this is the first thing we have to do.
The second thing we have to do then is to define the loss function on the embedding,
like the cross entropy loss I was just discussing,
um, and then we need to train.
And the way we can train the model is that we train it on a set
of nodes in a- on a batch of nodes.
So we select a batch of nodes,
create the computation graphs,
and this is a batch of nodes on which we train.
Um, and then what is interesting is that,
after the model is trained,
we can generate embeddings for any nodes, uh, as needed,
and simply apply [NOISE] our model to them by basically just doing the forward pass.
So this means that we can apply our model,
even to nodes that we have never seen during training.
So this means that, uh,
we cannot train on one graph and transfer the model to
the other graph because this particular set of, um,
nodes could be used for training the parameters [NOISE] to be optimized here,
and then we could apply this to a new set of nodes,
to a new set of, uh, computation graphs.
So this means that our model has inductive, uh, capability,
which means that same aggregation parameters,
same W and B,
are shared across all nodes.
Uh, and the number of model parameters in
this case is sublinear with the size of the network,
because W and B only depend on the embedding dimensionality and the size,
number of features, and not on the size of the graph.
And this means that graph neural networks are able to generalize to unseen nodes.
And that's a super cool, uh,
feature of them, because for example,
this means that you can train your graph neural network on one graph,
and you can apply it to a new graph.
Because you determine matrices [NOISE] W and B here,
and then you can transfer this,
uh, to the new network.
You can, uh, for example,
train on one organism,
and transfer this to the new organism here.
This is, let's say, a biological network.
This is also very useful for the networks that
constantly evolve because you can take the snapshot of the network,
create the computation graphs here,
and determined the parameters so that when then in production,
and you know, derives,
you quickly create a computation graph for it.
Just do the forward pass,
and here you have the embedding for it.
So no- no retraining the model, um, is necessary.
And that is super cool because it means you can train- train on one graph,
transfer to another one,
train on a small graph,
transfer the model to a big,
uh, graph, or to an evolving graph.
So let me summarize,
uh, the lecture for today and finish here.
What we did is, we generated node embeddings by
aggregating no- node neighborhood information.
We saw our first basic variant of this idea that
simply averages up the messages coming from the neighbors.
Um, and the key distinction between different architectures as we are going to see next,
is that- is how this aggregation process is being done.
And, uh, what I'm going to discuss in
the next lecture will be the architecture called, um, um,
GraphSAGE that generalizes this
into basically a framework where different types of aggregations,
different kas- kinds of transformations, uh, can be used.
So, um, thank you very much, uh,
for the lecture, um,
and very happy, uh,
to take questions now.