Hi, everybody.
Welcome to Stanford's
CS224N, also known
as Ling284, Natural Language
Processing with Deep Learning.
I'm Christopher Manning,
and I'm the main instructor
for this class.
So what we hope to do
today is to dive right in.
So I'm going to spend
about 10 minutes talking
about the course,
and then we're going
to get straight into
content for reasons
I'll explain in a minute.
So we'll talk about human
language and word meaning,
I'll then introduce the ideas
of the word2vec algorithm
for learning word meaning.
And then going from there
we'll kind of concretely
work through how you can
work out objective function
gradients with respect to
the word2vec algorithm,
and say a teeny bit about
how optimization works.
And then right at
the end of the class
I then want to spend
a little bit of time
giving you a sense of how
these word vectors work,
and what you can do with them.
So really the key
learning for today
is, I want to give you a sense
of how amazing deep learning
word vectors are.
So we have this really
surprising result
that word meaning
can be represented,
not perfectly but
really rather well
by a large vector
of real numbers.
And that's sort of in a way, a
commonplace of the last decade
of deep learning, but it
flies in the face of thousands
of years of tradition.
And it's really rather
an unexpected result
to start focusing on.
OK, so quickly what do we
hope to teach in this course?
So we've got three
primary goals.
The first is to teach
you the foundation,
say a good deep understanding
of the effect of modern methods
for deep learning
applied to NLP.
So we are going to start with
and go through the basics,
and then go on to
key methods that
are used in NLP, recurrent
networks, attention
transformers, and
things like that.
We want to do something
more than just that.
We'd also like to give you
some sense of a big picture
understanding of human
languages and what
are the reasons for
why they're actually
quite difficult to
understand and produce
even though humans
seem to do it easily.
Now obviously if you
really want to learn
a lot about this topic,
you should enroll in
and go and start
doing some classes
in the linguistics department.
But nevertheless
for a lot of you,
this is the only
human language content
you'll see during your
master's degree or whatever.
And so we do hope to spend a bit
of time on that starting today.
And then finally,
we want to give you
an understanding of an ability
to build systems in PyTorch,
that's some of the
major problems in NLP.
So we'll look at learning word
meanings, dependency parsing,
machine translation,
question answering.
Let's dive in to human language.
Once upon a time, I had a
lot longer introduction that
gave lots of examples about
how human languages can
be misunderstood
and complex, I'll
show a few of those
examples in later lectures.
But since right for
today, we're going
to be focused on word meaning.
I thought I'd just give
one example, which comes
from a very nice xkcd cartoon.
And that isn't
sort of about some
of the syntactic
ambiguities of sentences,
but instead it's really
emphasizing the important point
that language is a social
system, constructed
and interpreted by people.
And that's part of how--
and it changes as people decide
to adapt its construction,
and that's part
of the reason why
human languages, great
as an adaptive system
for human beings but difficult
as a system for our computers
to understand to this day.
So in this conversation between
the two women, one says,
anyway I could care less.
And the other says, I think you
mean you couldn't care less,
saying you could
care less implies
you care at least some amount.
And the other one
says, I don't know
where these unbelievably
complicated brains drifting
through a void trying in vain
to connect with one another,
by plainly fleeing words
out into the darkness.
Every choice of phrasing,
spelling, and tone, and timing
carries countless sync signals
and contexts and subtext,
and more and every
listener interprets
those signals in their own way.
Language isn't a formal system,
language is glorious chaos.
You can never know for sure what
any words will mean to anyone,
all you can do is try to
get better at guessing
how your words affect people.
So you can have a chance
of finding the ones that
will make them feel
something like what
you want them to feel.
Everything else is pointless.
I assume you're giving me tips
on how you interpret words
because you want me
to feel less alone.
If so, then thank
you, that means a lot.
But if you're just
running my sentences
to pass some mental
checklist so you
can show off how well you know
it, then I could care less.
OK, so that's
ultimately what our goal
is, how to do a better job at
building computational systems
that try to get better at
guessing how their words will
affect other people and what
other people are meaning
by the words that
they choose to say.
So an interesting thing
about human language
is, it is a system that was
constructed by human beings.
And it's a system that was
constructed relatively recently
in some sense.
So in discussions of
artificial intelligence,
a lot of the time people
focus a lot on human brains
and the neurons passing
by, and this intelligence
that's meant to be
inside people's heads.
But I just wanted to focus for a
moment on the role of language,
there's actually--
this is kind of
controversial but it's not
necessarily the case
that humans are much more
intelligent than some of the
higher apes like chimpanzees
or bonobos.
So chimpanzees and
bonobos have been
shown to be able to use
tools, to make plans,
and in fact chimps have much
better short term memory
than human beings do.
So relative to that, if you
look through the history of life
on Earth, human beings develop
language really recently.
How recently, we
kind of actually
don't know because there's
no fossils that say,
OK here's a language speaker.
But most people estimate that
language arose for human beings
sort of somewhere in
the range of 100,000
to a million years ago.
OK, that's the way I
let go but compared
to the process of the
evolution of life on Earth,
that's kind of
blinking an eyelid.
But that powerful communication
between human beings
quickly set off our ascendancy
over other creatures.
So it's kind of interesting that
the ultimate power turned out
not to have been poisonous
fangs or being super
fast or super big, that having
the ability to communicate
with other members
of your tribe.
It was much more recently again
that humans developed writing,
which allowed knowledge to be
communicated across distances
of time and space.
And so that's only
about 5,000 years old,
the power of writing.
So in just a few thousand
years the ability
to preserve and share knowledge
took us from the Bronze Age
to the smartphones
and tablets of today.
So a key question for artificial
intelligence and human-computer
interaction is how
to get computers
to be able to understand
the information
conveyed in human languages.
Simultaneously,
artificial intelligence
requires computers with
the knowledge of people.
Fortunately now,
AI systems might
be able to benefit
from a virtuous cycle.
We need knowledge to understand
language and people well,
but it's also the case that
a lot of that knowledge
is contained in language spread
out across the books and web
pages of the world.
And that's one of
the things we're
going to look at in
this course is, how
that we can sort of build
on that virtuous cycle.
A lot of progress
has already been made
and I just want to very
quickly give a sense of that.
So in the last decade
or so and especially
in the last few years, with
newer methods of machine
translation we're now in a
space where machine translation
really works moderately well.
So again, from the
history of the world,
this is just amazing, right
for thousands of years
learning other
people's languages was
a human task which
required a lot of effort
and concentration.
But now we're in a world
where you could just
hop on your web
browser and think,
oh, I wonder what the
news is in Kenya today,
and you can head off
over to a Kenyan website
and you can see
something like this.
And you can go, huh,
and you can then
ask Google to translate
it for you from Swahili,
and the translation
isn't quite perfect
but it's reasonably good.
So the newspaper, Tuko, has been
informed that local government
minister links on
[NON-ENGLISH SPEECH] and his
transport counterparts
[INAUDIBLE] died within two
separate hours.
So within two separate hours,
this is kind of awkward,
but essentially we're
doing pretty well
at getting the information
out of this page,
and so that's quite amazing.
The single biggest
development in NLP
for the last year certainly
in the popular media
was GPT-3, which was
a huge new model that
was released by OpenAI.
What GPT-3 is about and why it's
great is actually a bit subtle,
and so I can't really go through
all the details of this here
but it's exciting
because it seems
like it's the first step on
the path to what we might call
universal models,
where you can train up
one extremely large
model on something like,
that library picture
I showed before,
and it just has
knowledge of the world
knowledge of human languages
knowledge, of how to do tasks.
And then you can apply it
to do all sorts of things.
So no longer are
we building a model
to detect spam and then a
model to detect pornography,
and then a model to detect
whatever foreign language
content, and just building
all these separate supervised
classifiers for
every different task,
we've now just built up
a model that understands.
So exactly what it does is it
just predicts following words.
So on the left it's
been told to write
about Elon Musk in the
style of Doctor Seuss,
and it started
off with some text
and then it's
generating more text.
And the way it generates more
text is literally by just
predicting one word
at a time, following
words to complete its text.
But this has a very
powerful facility
because what you
can do with GPT-3
is you can give a
couple of examples
of what you'd like it to do.
So I can give it some text
and say, I broke the window,
change it into a question,
what did I break?
I gracefully saved the day I
changed it into a question.
What did I gracefully save?
So this prompt tells GPT-3
what I'm wanting it to do.
And so then if I give it
another statement like,
I gave John flowers.
I can then say three,
predict what words come next.
And it'll follow my
prompt and produce
who did I give flowers to?
Or I can say I gave her
a rose and a guitar,
and it will follow the
idea of the pattern
and to who did I give
a rose and a guitar to?
And actually this
one model can then
do an amazing range
of things, including
many that's [AUDIO OUT]
at all, to give
just one example of that.
Another thing that
you can do is get
it to translate human
language sentences into SQL.
So this can make it
much easier to do CS145.
So having given that a couple
of examples of SQL translation
of human language text which
I'm in this time not showing
because it won't
fit on my slide,
I can then give it a
sentence like how many users
have signed up since
the start of 2020,
and it turns it into SQL.
Or I can give it
another query what
is the average number
of influences each user
subscribed to, and again it
then converts that into SQL.
So GPT-3 knows a lot about
the meaning of language
and the meaning of
other things like SQL,
and can fluently manipulate it.
OK, so that leads us trying
to this [INAUDIBLE] meaning,
and how do we represent
the meaning of a word?
Well, what is meaning?
Well, we can look up something
like the Webster's dictionary
and say, OK, the idea that is
represented by a word, the idea
that a person wants
to express by using
words signs, et cetera.
That Webster's
dictionary definition
is really focused on
the word idea somehow,
but this is pretty close
to the commonest way
that linguists
think about meaning.
So do they think of
word meaning as being
a pairing between a word
which is a signifier
or symbol, and the
thing that it signifies,
the signified thing which
is an idea or thing.
So that the meaning of the
word chair is the set of things
that are chairs.
And that's referred to as
denotational semantics.
A term that's also used
and similarly applied
for the semantics of
programming languages.
This model isn't very
deeply implementable,
like how do I go from
the idea that chair means
the set of chairs in
the world to something
I can manipulate meaning
with my computers.
So traditionally the way
that meaning has normally
been handled in natural
language processing systems
is to make use of
resources like dictionary,
and thesaurus in particular.
Popular ones, WordNet, which
organized words and terms
into both synonyms sets of words
that can mean the same thing,
and hypernyms which correspond
to ISA relationships.
And so for the ISA
relationships we
can kind of look at
the hypernyms of panda,
and panda as a kind
of procyonidae,
whatever those are, probably
with red pandas, which
is a kind of carnivore, which
is a kind of placental, which
is kind a mammal.
And you sort of head up
this hypernyms hierarchy.
So word that has been a great
resource for NLP, that's
also been highly deficient.
So it lacks a lot of nuance,
so for example in WordNet,
proficient is listed
as a synonym for good.
But maybe that's
sometimes true but it
seems like in a lot of
contexts it's not true.
And you mean something
rather different
when you say
proficient versus good,
it's limited as a human
constructed thesaurus.
So in particular there's
lots of words and lots
of uses of words that
just aren't there,
including anything that is
more current terminology.
Like wicked is there
for the wicked witch,
but not for more
modern colloquial uses.
Ninja's certainly isn't there
for the kind of description
some people make of
programmers, and it's
impossible to keep up to date.
So it requires a
lot of human labor,
but even when you have that,
it has a set of synonyms
but doesn't really have
a good sense of words
that means something similar.
So fantastic and
great means something
similar without
really being synonyms.
And so this idea of
meaning similarity
is something that would be
really useful to make progress
on, and where deep
learning models excel.
OK, so what's the problem
with a lot of traditional NLP?
Well the problem with a
lot of traditional NLP
is that words are regarded
as discrete symbols.
So we have symbols
like hotel, conference,
motel are words,
which in deep learning
speak we refer to as a
localized representation.
And that's because if you are in
a statistical machine learning
systems, want to represent
these symbols that each of them
is a separate thing so the
standard way of representing
them and this is what
you do in something
like a statistical
model if you're building
a logistic regression model
with words as features
is that you represent
them as one word vector.
So you have a dimension
for each different word.
So maybe like my example,
here are my representations
as vectors for motel and hotel.
And so that means
that we have to have
huge vectors corresponding
to the number of words
in our vocabulary.
So the kind of if you had a high
school English dictionary it
probably have about 250,000
words in it, but there
are many, many more words
in the language really.
So maybe we at least want to
have a 500,000 dimensional
vector to be able
to cope with that.
OK, but the bigger the
even bigger problem
with discrete symbols is that we
don't have this notion of word
relationships and similarity.
So for example in
web search, if a user
searches for Seattle
motel, we'd also
like to match on documents
containing Seattle hotel.
But our problem is we've
got this one word vectors
for the different words.
And so in a formal
mathematical sense,
these two vectors
are orthogonal,
that there's no natural notion
of similarity between them
whatsoever.
Well, there are some things
that we could do but try and do
about that, and people did
do about that in before 2010.
We could say, hey we could
use the WordNet synonyms
and we count things that lists
of synonyms are similar anyway.
Or hey, maybe we
could somehow build up
our representations of
words that have meaning,
overlap and people did
all of those things.
But they tended to fail
badly from incompleteness,
so instead what I
want to introduce
today is the modern deep
learning method of doing that,
where we encode similarity in
real value vector themselves.
So how do we go
about doing that?
And the way we do that is
by exploiting this idea
called distributional semantics.
So the idea of distributional
semantics is again something
that when you first see it,
maybe feels a little bit
crazy because rather
than having something
like denotational semantics,
what we're now going to do
is say that a word's
meaning is going
to be given by the words that
frequently appear close to it.
J. R Firth was a
British linguist
from the middle of last century,
and one of his pithy slogans
that everyone quotes
at this moment
is, you shall know a word
by the company it keeps.
And so this idea that you can
represent a sense for words,
meaning as a notion of what
context that appears in
has been a very successful idea.
One of the most
successful ideas that's
used throughout statistical
and deep learning NLP.
It's actually an interesting
idea more philosophically,
so that there are kind of
interesting connections.
For example in Wittgenstein's
later writings,
he became enamored of a
used theory of meaning.
And this is a sin in
some sense, a used theory
of meaning but whether it's the
ultimate theory of semantics,
it's actually still
pretty controversial.
But it proves to be an
extremely computational sense
of semantics, which
has just led to it
being used everywhere very
successfully in deep learning
systems.
So when a word
appears in a text,
it has a context which
are a set of words
that appear in the eye.
And so for a particular word,
my example here is banking.
We'll find a bunch of places
where banking occurs in text,
and will collect the
sort of nearby words
that context words
and we'll see and say
that those words
that are appearing
in that kind of
muddy brown color
around banking, that
those contexts words
will in some sense represent
the meaning of the word banking.
While I'm here let me just
mention one distinction
that will come up regularly.
When we're talking about a
word in our natural language
processing class, we sort
of have two senses of word
which are referred to
as types and tokens.
So there's a particular
instance for words.
So there's in the first example,
government debt problems
turning into banking crises.
There's banking
there, and that's
a token of the word banking.
But then I've collected a
bunch of instances of quote
unquote, the word banking.
And when I say the word banking
and a bunch of examples of it,
I'm then treating banking as a
type which refers to the uses
and meaning the word banking
has across instances.
OK, so what are we going to do
with this distributional models
of language?
Well, what we want
to do is based
on looking at the words that
occur in context as vectors
that we want to build
up dense real valued
vector for each word,
that in some sense
represents the
meaning of that word.
And the way it will represent
the meaning of that word
is that this vector will
be useful for predicting
other words that
occur in the context.
So in this example, to keep it
manageable on the slide vectors
are only eight dimensional.
But in reality we use
considerably bigger vectors,
so a very common
size is actually
300 dimensional vectors.
OK, so for each word
that's a word type,
we don't have a word vector.
These are also used
with other names,
they refer to as neural
word representations
or for a reason, they'll become
clearer on the next slide,
they're referred to
as word embeddings.
So these are now a distributed
representation, not a localized
representation because the
meaning of the word banking
is spread over all 300
dimensions of the vector.
These are called word embeddings
because effectively when
we have a whole bunch of words,
these representations place
them all in a high
dimensional vector space,
and so they're embedded
into that space.
Now unfortunately
human beings are
very bad at looking at
300 dimensional vector
spaces or even eight
dimensional vector spaces,
so the only thing that I
can really display to you
here is a two dimensional
projection of that space.
Now even that's
useful, but it's also
important to realize
that when you're
making it two dimensional
projection of a three
dimensional space,
you're losing almost all
the information in that space.
And a lot of things will
be crushed together,
that don't actually
deserve to be better.
So here's my word
embeddings, of course you
can't see any of those at all.
But if I zoom in and
then I zoom in further,
what you'll already see is
that the representations
we've learnt distributionally
to just a good job at grouping
together similar words.
So in this sort of
overall picture,
I can zoom into one
part of the space,
is actually the part that's
up here and this view of it.
And it's got words
for countries,
so not only are countries
generally grouped together,
even the sort of particular
sub groupings of countries
make a certain amount of sense.
And down here we then
have nationality words,
if we go to another
part of the space we can
see different kind of words.
So here are verbs and we
have ones like come and go,
a very similar saying
and thinking words,
say think expect, they
kind of similar and nearby.
Over on the bottom right, we
have sort of verbal exhilarates
and corpus, so have, had,
has, forms of the verb to be.
And certain content for verbs
are similar to corpus verbs,
because they describe states.
He remained angry,
he became angry,
and so they're actually
then grouped close together
to the word, the verb to be.
So there's a lot of
interesting structure
in this space that
then represents
the meaning of words.
So the algorithm I'm
going to introduce now
is one that's called
word2vec, which was introduced
by Tomas Mikolov and
colleagues in 2013
as a framework for
learning word vectors,
and it's sort of
a simple and easy
to understand place to start.
So the idea is we
have a lot of text
from somewhere, which we
commonly refer to as a corpus.
Of text corpus as just
the Latin word for body,
so it's a body of text.
And so then we choose
a fixed vocabulary
which will typically be large
but nevertheless truncated,
so we get rid of some of
the really rare words,
so we might say
vocabulary size of 400,000
and we then create for
ourselves vector for each word.
OK, so then what
we do is we want
to work out what's a good
vector for each word,
and the really
interesting thing is
that we can learn these word
vectors from just a big pile
of text by doing this
distributional similarity
task of being able to predict,
well, what words occur
in the context of other words.
So in particular,
we're going [AUDIO OUT]
through in the texts,
and so at any moment
we have a center word C, and
context words outside of it,
which we'll call O. And then
based on the current word
vectors, we're
going to calculate
the probability of a
context word occurring,
given the center word
according to our current model.
But then we know that
certain words did actually
occur in the context
of that center word,
and so what we
want to do is then
keep adjusting the word
vectors to maximize
the probability that's assigned
to words that actually occur
in the context of
the center word
as we proceed
through these texts.
So to start to make that
a bit more concrete,
this is what we're doing.
So we have a piece of text, we
choose our center word which
is here in two and
then we say, well,
if a model of predicting the
probability of context words
given the center
word and this model,
we'll come to in a
minute, but it's defined
in terms of our word vectors.
So let's see what
probability it gives
to the words that
actually occurred
in the context of this word.
It gives them some
probability, but maybe it'd
be nice if the probability
it assigned was higher.
So then how can we
change our word vectors
to raise those probabilities?
And so we'll do
some calculations
with into being the
center word, and then
we'll just go on
to the next word
and then we'll do the
same kind of calculations,
and keep on chunking.
So the big question
then is, well
what are we doing
for working out
the probability of
a word occurring
in the context of
the center word?
And so that's the
central part of what we
develop as the word2vec object.
So this is the overall
model that we want to use.
So for each position in our
corpus, our body of text,
we want to predict context words
within a window of fixed size
M, given the center word WJ.
And we want to become
good at doing that,
so we want to give high
probability to words
that occur in the context.
And so what we're
going to do is we're
going to work out
what's formerly
the data likelihood
as to how good a job
we do at predicting words in
the context of other words.
And so formally
that likelihood is
going to be defined in
terms of our word vectors.
So they're the
parameters of our model,
and it's going to be calculated
as taking the product of using
each word as the
center word, and then
the product of each
word and a window
around that of the probability
of predicting that context
word in the center word.
And so to learn
this model, we're
going to have an objective
function, sometimes also
called a cost or a loss
that we want to optimize.
And essentially
what we want to do
is we want to maximize the
likelihood of the context we
see around center words.
But following standard
practice, we slightly
fiddle that because rather
than dealing with products,
it's easier to deal
with sums and so we
work with log likelihood.
And once we take log
likelihood, all of our products
turn into sums.
We also work with the
average log likelihood,
so we've got one on, t term
here for the number of words
in the corpus, and finally
for no particular reason
we like to minimize our
objective function rather
than maximizing it.
So we stick a minus
sign in there,
and so then by minimizing this
objective function, J of theta,
that becomes maximizing
our predictive accuracy.
OK, so that's the
set up, but we still
haven't made any
progress in how do we
calculate the probability of a
word occurring in the context,
given the center word.
And so the way
we're actually going
to do that is we have vector
representations for each word,
and we're going to work
out the probability simply
in terms of the word vectors.
Now at this point there's
a little technical point,
we're actually going to give
to each word, two word vectors.
One word vector for when
it's used as the center
word, and a
different word vector
when that's used
as a context word.
This is done because
it just simplifies
the math and the optimization,
that seems a little bit ugly
that actually makes building
word vectors a lot easier,
and really we can come back
to that and discuss it later.
But that's what it is.
And so then once we
have these word vectors,
the equation that
we're going to use
for giving the probability of
a context word appearing given
the center word is
that we're going
to calculate it using the
expression, the middle bottom
of my slide.
So let's sort of pull that
apart just a little bit more.
So what we have here
with this expression is
so for a particular center word
and a particular context word
O, we're going to
look up the vector
representation of each word.
So there U of O and V
of C, and so then we're
simply going to take the dot
product of those two vectors.
So dot product is
a natural measure
for similarity
between words because
in any particular
mention of opposite,
you'll get a component that
adds to that dot product sum.
If both are negative, it'll add
a lot to the dot product sum.
If one's positive
and one's negative,
it'll subtract from
the similarity measure.
Both of them are zero,
won't change the similarity.
So it sort of seems
sort of plausible idea
to just take a dot product
and thinking, well,
if two words have a
larger dot product, that
means they're more similar.
And so then after that,
we sort of really doing
nothing more than OK, we
want to use dot products
to represent words similarity.
And now let's do the
dumbest thing that we know,
how to turn this into a
probability distribution.
Well, what do we do?
Well firstly, well
taking a dot product
of two vectors
that might come out
as positive or
negative, but well we
want to have probabilities.
We can't have negative
probabilities.
So a simple way to avoid
negative probabilities
is to exponentiate
them, because then we
know everything is positive.
And so then we are always
getting a positive number
in the numerator, but
for probabilities we
also want to have the
numbers add up to 1.
So we have a probability
distribution.
So we just normalizing
the obvious way,
where we divide through by the
sum of the numerator quantity
for each different
word in the vocabulary,
and so then necessarily
that gives us
a probability distribution.
So all the rest
of that I was just
talking through what
we're using there
is what's called the
softmax function.
So the softmax function
will take any R in vector
and turn it into
things between 0 to 1.
And so we can take numbers and
put them through the softmax,
and turn them into
the redistribution.
So the name comes from the fact
that it's sort of like a max.
So because of the fact
that we exponentiate,
that really emphasizes
the big contents
in the different dimensions
of calculating similarity.
So most of the probability goes
to the most similar things,
and it's called soft
because well, it
doesn't do that absolutely.
It'll still give
some probability
to everything that's in
the slightest bit similar--
I mean, on the other hand it's a
slightly weird name because max
normally takes a set of
things and just returns
one the biggest of them,
whereas the softmax is
taking a set of numbers
and scaling them,
that is returning the whole
probability distribution.
OK, so now we have all
the pieces of our model.
And so how do we make
our word vectors?
Well, the idea of what
we want to do is we
want to fiddle our word vectors
in such a way that we minimize
our loss, i.e. that we maximize
the probability of the words
we actually saw in the
context of the center word.
And so the theta represents all
of our model parameters in one
very long vector.
So for our model here,
the only parameters
are our word vectors.
So we have for each
word two vectors,
its context vector
and its center vector.
And each of those is a
D dimensional vector,
where D might be 300 and
we have V many words.
So we end up with this big
huge vector which is 2DV long,
which if you have a 500,000
vocab times the 300 dimensional
at the time, it's more math
than I can do in my head,
but it's got millions of
millions of parameters,
it's got millions and
millions of parameters.
And we somehow want
to fiddle them all
to maximize the prediction
of context words.
And so the way we kind of do
that then is we use calculus.
So if what we want to do is
take that math that we've
seen previously and say, well
with this objective function,
we can work out
derivatives and so
we can work out where
the gradient is.
So how we can walk
downhill to minimize loss.
So we're at some point
and we can figure out
what is downhill, and we
can then progressively
walk downhill and
improve our model.
And so what our
job is going to be
is to compute all of
those vector gradients.
OK, so at this point I
then want to kind of show
a little bit more as to how
we can actually do that.
And then a couple
more slides here
but maybe I'll just try and
jigger things again and move
to my interactive whiteboard.
What we wanted to do,
so we had our overall--
we had our overall
J theta that we
were wanting to minimize our
average neg log likelihood,
so that was the minus 1 on T of
the sum of T equals 1 to big T,
which was our text length.
And then we were going through
the words in each context,
so we were doing
J between M words
on each side except itself.
And then what we wanted to
do was in the side there,
we were then working out the log
probability of the context word
at that position given the word
that's in the center position T
.
And so then we converted
that into our word vectors
by saying that the
probability of O given C
is going to be expressed as the
noun, this softmax of the dot
product.
And so now what we
want to do is work out
the gradient, the direction of
downhill for this [INAUDIBLE]..
And so the way
we're doing that is
we're working out the partial
derivative of this expression
with respect to every
parameter in the model,
and all the parameters
in the model
are the components, the
dimensions of the word
vectors of every word.
And so we have the center word
vectors and the outside word
vectors.
So here I'm just going to
do the center word vectors
but on homework-- on a future
homework assignment two,
the outside word
vectors will show up
and they're kind of similar.
So what we're doing
is we're working out
the partial derivative
with respect
to our center word vector, which
is maybe a 300 dimensional word
vector of this
probability of O give C.
And since we're using
log probabilities
of the log of this probability
of O given C of this exp
of your U of OTVC, over--
my writing will get
worse and worse, sorry.
I've already made a
mistake, haven't I?
Sum, the sum of W equals
1 to the vocabulary
of the exp of UWTVC.
OK, well at this point
things start off pretty easy.
So what we have
here is something
that's log of A over
B, so that's easy.
We can turn this into
log A minus log B.
But before I go
further I'll just
make a comment at this point.
So at this point my
audience divides on in two,
there are some people
in the audience
for which maybe a lot of
people in the audience--
this really elementary math,
I've seen this a million times
before and he isn't even
explaining it very well.
And if you're in
that group, well
feel free to look at your
email or the newspaper
or whatever else is
best suited to you,
but I think there are also
other people in the class who
are, the last time
I saw calculus
was when I was in high school,
for which that's not the case.
And so I wanted to spend a
few minutes going through this
a bit concretely so that to
try and get over the idea
that even though most of deep
learning and even word vector
learning seems like magic,
that it's not really magic.
It's really just doing
math and one of the things
we hope is that you
do actually understand
this math that's being done.
So I'll keep along and
do a bit more of it,
so then what we have it's use
this way of writing the log.
And so then we can say
that that expression above
equals the partial
derivatives of VC
of the log of the
numerator log XUOTVC
minus the partial derivative
of the log of the denominator.
So that's then the
sum of W equals 1 to V
of the X of UWTVC.
So at that point, I
have my numerator here
and my former denominator there.
So at that point there is that's
the first part is the numerator
part, so the numerator part
is really, really easy,
so we have here that log on X
just inverses of each other.
So they'd just go away.
So that becomes the
derivative with respect
to VC of just
what's left behind,
which is U0 dot product with VC.
OK, and so the
thing to be aware of
is we're still doing this
multivariate calculus.
So what we have here is calculus
with respect to a vector,
like hopefully you saw
some of the math 51
or some other place,
not high school.
Single variable calculus.
On the other hand
to the extent, you
can't remember
some of this stuff.
Most of the time you can
justify it perfectly well
by thinking about what happens
with one dimension at a time,
and it generalizes to
multivariable calculus.
So if about all that
you remember of calculus
is that d dx of ax
equals a, really it's
the same thing that we're
going to be using here.
That here we have the outside
word dot producted with the VC.
Well at the end
of the day, that's
going to have terms of sort
of U0 component 1 times
the center word component
1 plus U0 component 2 plus.
There were component
2, and so we're sort
of using this bit over here.
And so what we're
going to be getting out
is the U0, and U01,
and the U02, so this
will be all that is left
with respect to VC1.
When we take its derivative
with respect to VC1
and this term will
be the only thing
left when we take the
derivative with respect
to the variable VC2.
So the end result of taking
the vector antiderivative
of U0 dot producted with VC
is simply going to be U0.
OK great, so that's progress.
So then at that point we go on
and we say oh damn, we still
have the denominator [AUDIO OUT]
slightly more complex, but not
so bad.
So then we want to take
the partial derivatives
with respect to VC of the
log of the denominator.
OK and so then at this
point, the one tool
that we need to
know and remember
is how to use the chain rule.
So the chain rule is
when you're wanting
to work out having derivatives
of compositions of function.
So we have F of G of whatever
X, but here it's going to be VC.
And so we want to say,
OK what we have here is
we're working out a
composition of functions.
So here's our F and here
is our X, which is G of VC.
Maybe I shouldn't call it X,
maybe it's probably better
to call it Z or something.
OK, so when we then want
to work out the chain rule,
well what do we do?
We take the derivative
of F at the point Z.
And so at that point we have
to actually remember something,
we have to remember that
the derivative of the log
is the 1 on X function.
So this is going to be
equal to the 1 on X for Z.
So that's then going to be 1
over the sum of W equals 1 to V
of exp of UTVC multiplied
by the derivative
of the inner function.
So the derivative of the
part that is remaining,
I'm getting this, the sum of--
and this one trick
here at this point
we do want to have
a change of index.
So we want to say the
sum of X equals 1 to V
of exp of U of X VC.
Since we can get into trouble
if we don't change that
variable to be using
a different one.
OK, so at that point we're
making some progress,
but we still want to work
out the derivative of this.
And so what we want to do is
apply the chain rule once more.
So now here is our F and in here
is our new Z equals G of VC.
And so, we then
sort of repeat over,
so we can move the derivative
inside a sum always.
So we then taking the
derivative of this,
and so then the derivative
of exp is itself,
so we're going to just
have exp of the UXTVC times
there's is a sum of
X equals 1 to V times
the derivative of UX TVC.
OK, and so then this is what
we've worked out before,
we can just rewrite as UX.
OK, so now we're
making progress.
So if we start putting
all of that together,
what we have is the derivative,
well the partial derivatives
with VC of this log probability.
All right, we have
the numerator,
which was just U0 minus--
we then had the sum of
the numerator, sum over X
equals 1 to V of exp
UXTVC times U of X, then
that was multiplied by our
first term that came from the 1
on X, which gives you the
sum of W equals 1 to V
of the exp of UWTVC.
And this, the fact that
we changed the variables
became important.
And so by just sort of
rewriting that a little,
we can get that equals U0
minus the sum V equals sorry--
X equals 1 to V of this X,
V of XTVC over the sum of W
equals to V of exp
UWTVC times U of X.
And so at that point it's
sort of interesting thing
has happened that we've ended
up getting straight back exactly
the softmax formula probability
that we saw when we started.
And we can just rewrite
that more conveniently
as saying this equals U0 minus
the sum over X equals 1 to V
of the probability of
X given C times UX.
And so what we have
at that moment is
this thing here
is an expectation.
And so this isn't an
average over all the context
vectors waited by
their probability
according to the model.
And so it's always the case
with these softmax style models,
that what you get out
for the derivatives
is you get the observed
minus the expected.
So our model is good
if our model on average
predicts exactly the word
vector that we actually see.
And so we're going
to try and adjust
the parameters of our
model, so [INAUDIBLE]..
Now we try and make it do
it as much as possible,
I mean of course as you'll
find you can never get close.
If I just say to you OK
the word is croissant,
which words are going to occur
in the context of croissant?
I mean, you can't answer
that, there are all
sorts of sentences that you
could say that involve the word
croissant.
So actually our particular
probability estimates
are going to be kind of
small, but nevertheless we
want to sort of fiddle our
word vectors to try and make
those estimates as high
as we possibly can.
So I've gone on about
this stuff a bit,
but haven't actually sort
of shown you any of what
actually happened.
So I just want to
quickly show you
a bit of that as
to what actually
happens with word vectors.
So here's a simple
little IPython notebook
which is also what you'll be
using for assignment one only.
So in the first cell I
import a bunch of stuff.
So we've got NumPy
for our vectors.
[AUDIO OUT] learns kind
of your machine learning,
Swiss Army Knife
GENESIM is a package
that you may well
not have seen before.
It's a package that's often
used for word vectors,
it's not really used
for deep learning.
So this is the only time
you'll see it in the class,
but if you just
want a good package
for working with word vectors
and some other application
it's a good one to know about.
OK so then in my
second cell here
I'm loading a particular
set of word vectors.
So these are glove word vectors
that we made at Stanford
in 2014, and I'm loading
a hundred dimensional word
vectors so that things are
a little bit quicker for me
while I'm doing
things here, sort
of do this model of bread
and croissant, what I've just
got here is word vectors.
So I just wanted
to sort of show you
that there are word vectors.
Well maybe I should have loaded
those word vectors in advance.
Let's see.
Oh, OK, I'm in business.
OK, so here are my word vectors
for bread and croissant,
and well you can see that
maybe these two words are
a bit similar, so
both of them are
negative in the first dimension,
positive in the second,
negative in the third,
positive in the fourth,
negative in the fifth.
So it sort of looks
like they might
have a fair bit of
dot product which
is kind of what we want
because bread and croissant are
kind of similar.
But what we can do is
actually ask the model
and these are Jensen
functions, now
know what are the
most similar words
so I can ask for
croissant, what are
the most similar words to that.
And it will tell me it's
things like brioche, baguette,
focaccia.
So that's pretty good.
Pudding is perhaps a little
bit more questionable.
We can say most
similar to the USA
and it says Canada, America,
USA with periods, United States
that's pretty good.
And most similar to banana--
take it out-- coconut, mangoes,
bananas, sort of fairly
tropical fruit grade.
Before finishing though, I want
to show you something slightly
more than just similarity, which
is one of the amazing things
that people observed
with these word vectors,
and that was to say you
can actually sort of do
arithmetic in this vector
space, that makes sense.
And so in particular, people
suggested this analogy task.
And so the idea of
the analogy task
is you should be able to
start with a word like king,
and you should be able to
subtract out a male component
from that, add back
in a woman component,
and then you should
be able to ask, well,
what word is over here?
And what should like is that
the word over there is queen.
And so this sort
of little bit of--
so we're going to do that,
with this sort of same most
similar function which
is actually more--
so as well as having
positive words,
you can ask for most similar
negative words and you might
wonder what's most negatively
similar to a banana,
and you might be
thinking, oh it's--
I don't know, some kind
of meat or something.
Actually that by itself
isn't very useful
because when you just ask
for most negatively similar
to things, you tend to
get crazy strings that
were found in the data
set that you don't know
what they mean if anything.
But if we put the
two together, we
can use the most similar
function with positives
and negatives to do analogies.
So we're going to say
we want a positive king,
we want to subtract
out negatively man,
we want to then add
in positively woman
and find out what's most similar
to this point in the space.
So my analogy function
does that, precisely that
by taking a couple
of most similar ones
and then subtracting
out the negative one.
And so we can try out
this analogy function.
So I can do the analogy, I
show in the picture with man
is the king as woman is--
sorry I'm not
saying that's right.
Yeah, man is the
king as woman is to--
well, sorry I haven't
done my cells.
OK, man is to king
as woman is to queen.
So that's great,
and that works well.
I mean-- and you can do it
the sort of other way around,
king is to man as
queen is to woman.
If this only worked for
that one freakish example,
you maybe wouldn't
be very impressed
but you know it actually turns
out like it's not perfect
but you can do all sorts
of fun analogies with this,
and they actually work.
So I could ask for something
like analogy, here's
a good one.
Australia is to beer
as France is to want?
And you can think about what
you think the answer to that one
should be, and it
comes out as champagne,
which is pretty good.
Or I could ask for something
like analogy pencil
is to sketching as
camera is to what?
And it says photographing.
You can also do the analogies
with people, at this point,
I have to point out
that this data was
and the model was built in
2014, so you can't ask anything
about Donald Trump in there.
Well you can, Trump is in
there but not as president,
but I could ask something like
analogy a bomb is to Clinton
as Reagan is to what?
And you can think
of what you think
is the right analogy there, the
analogy it returns with Nixon.
So I guess that depends on
what you think of Bill Clinton
as to whether you think that
was a good analogy or not.
You can also do sort of
linguistic analogies with it,
so you can do something
like analogy tall is
to tallest as long is to what?
And it does longest.
So it really just sort of
knows a lot about the meaning
behavior of words, and I think
when these methods were first
developed and hopefully still
for you, that people were just
gobsmacked about how
well this actually worked
at capturing enough words.
And so these word vectors
then went everywhere
as a new representation that
was so powerful for working out
word meaning.
And so that's our starting
point for this class,
and we'll say a bit more
about them next time.
And they're also the basis
of what you're looking
at for the first assignment.
Can I ask a quick question about
the distinction between the two
vectors per word?
Yes.
So my understanding is that
there can be several context
words per word in
the vocabulary,
but then there's
only two vectors
I thought the distinction
between the two
is that one it's like
the actual word and one
is the context word.
But in multiple contexts words,
how do you pick just two then?
Well, so we're doing
every one of them,
so like maybe I won't turn
back on the screen share
but we are doing in the
objective function there
was a sum over--
so you've got this big
corpus of text right,
so you're taking a sum
over every word which
is it appearing as
the center word,
and then inside that there's
a second sum which is
for each word in the context.
So you are going to count
each word as a context word,
and so then for one particular
term of that objective function
you've got a particular context
word and a particular center
word that you're then sort of
summing over different context
words for each
center word, and then
you're summing over all of the
decisions of different center
words.
And to say just a sentence
more about having two vectors,
I mean in some sense
it's an ugly detail that
was done to make things
sort of simple and fast.
So if you look at
the math carefully,
if you sort of treated the
two vectors as the same,
so if you use the same
vectors for center and context
and you say, OK, let's
work out the derivatives,
things get uglier.
And the reason that
they get uglier is it's
when I'm iterating over all
the choices of context word,
oh my God sometimes
the context word
is going to be the same
as the center word,
and so that messes with
working out my derivatives.
Whereas by taking them
as separate vectors that
never happens, so it's easy.
But the kind of
interesting thing
is saying that you have these
two different representations
sort of just ends up really
sort of doing no harm,
and my wave my hands
argument for that
is since we're kind of
moving through each position,
the corpus one by
one something--
a word that is the
center word at one moment
is going to be the context
word at the next moment,
and the word that
was the context word
is going to have
become the center word.
So you're sort of
doing the computation
both ways in each case.
And so you should be
able to convince yourself
that the two
representations for the word
end up being very similar,
and they are not identical
both for technical
reasons of the ends
of documents and things like
that, but very, very similar.
And so effectively
you tend to get
two very similar
representations for each word,
and we just average them
and collect the word vector.
And when we use
word vectors we just
have one vector for each word.
That makes sense thank you.
I have a question
purely out of curiosity.
So we don't know when we
projected the vectors,
the word vectors onto
to the 2D surface
we saw like little
clusters of squares
are similar to each
other, and then
later on, we saw that
with the analogies thing,
we kind of see that there's
these directional vectors that
sort of get like the rule of
or the C of O or something
like that.
And so I'm wondering, is there--
are there relationships
between those
relational vectors
themselves such as,
like is the rule of vector
sort of similar to the C of O
of vector which is very
different from like--
makes a good
sandwich with vector.
Is there any research on that?
That's a good question.
You've stumped me already
in the first lecture.
Yeah, I can't actually think
of a piece of research.
And so I'm not sure I
have a confident answer,
I mean it seems like
that's a really easy thing
to check with once you have one
of these sets of word vectors
that it seems like for
any relationship that
is represented well
enough by a word.
You should be able to see if
it comes out kind of similar.
I mean, I'm not sure,
we can look and see.
That's totally OK, just curious.
I'm sorry, I missed the last
little bit to your answer
to your first question.
So when you want to collapse
two vectors for the same work,
did you usually
take the average?
Different people have
done different things.
But the most common
practice is after you've--
there's still a bit more I have
to cover about running word2vec
that we didn't really
get through today.
So I still got a bit more
work to do on Thursday,
but once you've run
your word2vec algorithm
and you sort of your output
is two vectors for each word
and kind of when it's center
and when its context, and so
typically people just average
those two vectors and say OK,
that's the representation
of the word croissant,
and that's what appears in
the sort of word vectors file,
like the one I loaded.
Makes sense, thank you.
I think-- so my question
is, if a word to have
two different meanings or
multiple different meanings,
can we still represent it
as the same single vector?
Yes, that's a very
good question.
And actually there
is some content
on that in Thursday's lecture,
so I can say more about that.
But yeah, the first reaction
is you kind of should
be scared because something
I've said nothing about at all
is most words, especially
short common words
have lots of meanings.
So if you have a word like star,
that can be astronomical object
or it can be a film
star, a Hollywood star,
or it can be something
like the gold stars
that you got in
elementary school.
And just taking all those
uses of the word star
and collapsing them together
into one word vector.
And you might think that's
really crazy and bad,
but actually turns out
to work rather well.
Maybe I won't go
through all of that
right now because
there is actually stuff
on that on Thursday's lecture.
Oh, I see, thanks.
You can look ahead of the
slides for next time, oh wait.
I have a quick question, I know
this might seem kind of strange
to ask, but I guess
a lot of us were also
taking this course because of
the hype between AI and speech
recognition.
And my basic question is, do we
we look the stack of something
like Alexa or something
to provide speech
to context or actions
in this course,
or is it just primarily
understanding?
So this is an unusual
and unusual quarter,
but for this quarter there's
a very clear answer which
is this quarter there's also
a speech class being taught,
which is CS224S, a speech class
being taught by Andrew Maas,
and you know this
is a class that's
been more regularly
offered, sometimes it's
only been offered
every third year,
but it's being
offered right now.
So if what you want to do is
learn about speech recognition
and learn about sort of methods
for building dialogue systems,
you should do CS224S.
So for this class in general
the vast bulk of this class
is working with text and doing
various kinds of text analysis
and understanding.
So we do tasks like some
of the ones I've mentioned,
we do machine translation,
we do question answering,
we look at how to parse
the structure of sentences
and things like that.
In other years I sometimes
say a little bit about speech,
but since this quarter there's
a whole different class
that's focused on speech
that seem a little bit silly.
[INAUDIBLE]
--focus more and more
on speech [INAUDIBLE]..
I'm now getting a
bad echo, I'm not
sure if that's my fault or
your fault but anyway, answer,
so the speech class
does a mix of stuff.
So I mean the sort of
pure speech problems
classically have been
doing speech recognition.
So going from a speech signal to
text and doing text to speech,
going from text to a speech
signal and both of those
are problems which
are now normally done,
including by the cell phone
that sits in your pocket using
neural networks.
And so it covers both of
those, but then between that,
the class covers quite a
bit and in particular it
starts off with looking at
building dialogue systems.
So this is sort of
something like Alexa,
Google Assistant, Siri,
as to well assuming you
have a speech recognition,
a text to speech system,
then you do have
text-in and text-out.
What are the kind
of ways that people
go about building dialogue
systems like the ones
that I just mentioned.
I actually had a question.
So I think there is
some people are noticing
that the opposites were really
near to each other, which
was kind of odd but
I was also wondering,
what about positive and
negative balance or lack of it?
Is that captured well
in this type of model
or is it not captured well
with the opposite sides where
it really--
So the short answer
is both of those.
So this is a good question,
a good observation.
And the short answer
is no, both of those
are captured really,
really badly.
I mean there's a definition of--
when I say really,
really badly I
mean what I mean is, if that's
what you want to focus on,
you've got problems.
I mean it's not that the
algorithm doesn't work so
precisely, what you find
is that antonyms generally
occur in very similar topics
because whether it's saying
John is really tall or
John is really short,
or that movie was fantastic,
or that movie was terrible.
You get antonyms occurring
in the same context.
So because of that, their
vectors are very similar
and similarly sort of effect
and sentiment based words.
Well, like Mike creating
terrible example,
the context is similar.
That if you're just learning
this kind of predict words
and context models that no,
that's not captured now.
That's not the end
of the story, I
mean absolutely people
wanted to use neural networks
for sentiment and other kinds
of sort of connotation effect.
And there are very good ways
of doing that, but somehow you
have to do something more
than simply predicting words
and context because that's
not sufficient to capture
that dimension,
more on that later.
I just happen to
like adjectives too,
like very basic adjectives,
like so and like not.
Because they're sort
of like appearing
like some context here.
What was your first
example before not?
Like so.
This is so cool--
So that's actually a
good question as well.
So yeah, so there are these very
common words that are commonly
referred to as function words
by linguists, which now includes
ones like so and not,
but other ones like
and prepositions, like
to, on, you sort of
might suspect that
the word vectors
for those don't work out
very well because they
occur in all kinds of
different contexts.
And they're not very distinct
from each other in many cases,
and to a first approximation
I think that's true.
And part of why I didn't use
those as examples in my slides,
but at the end of the day, we do
build up vector representations
of those words too.
And you'll see in
a few lectures time
when we start building what
we call language models.
That actually they do a great
job in those words as well,
I mean to explain what
I'm meaning there.
I mean another feature
of the word2vec model
is that actually ignore
the position of words,
so it's said I'm
going to predict
every word around
the center word
but I'm predicting
it in the same way.
I'm not predicting
differently the word before me
versus the word after
me, or the word two
away in either
direction, they all just
predicted the same by that
one probability function.
And so if that's all
you've got, that's
sort of destroys your ability
to do a good job at capturing
these sort of common
more grammatical words
like so not an end.
But we build slightly
different models
that are more sensitive to
the structure of sentences,
and then we start doing
a good job on those two.
OK, thank you.
I had a question about the
characterization of word2vec.
Because I read [INAUDIBLE],,
and it seems the character
architecture [INAUDIBLE].
It was slightly
different from how
it's presented in
the lecture, so are
like two complimentary
ways together or--
Yeah, so I've still
got more to say,
so stay tuned Thursday for
more staff on word vectors.
So word2vec is
kind of a framework
for building word
vectors, and that there
are sort of several
variant precise algorithms
within the framework.
And one of them is whether
you're predicting the context
words or whether you're
predicting the center word.
So the model I showed was
predicting the context words,
so it was the skip grand model.
But then there's sort of a
detail of how in particular
to do the optimization
and what I presented
was the sort of easiest way
to do it, which is naive
optimization with the equation,
the softmax equation for word
vectors.
It turns out that that
naive optimization
is sort of needlessly expensive,
and people have come up
with faster ways of doing it,
in particular the commerce thing
you see is what's
called skip grand
with negative sound playing,
and the negative sampling
is then sort of a much more
efficient way to estimate.
Things and I'll mention
that on Thursday.
Right, OK, thank you.
I was asking for
more information
about how word vectors are
constructed beyond the summary
of random initialization.
And then gradient based
additive [INAUDIBLE]..
Yeah, so I sort of will do a bit
more connecting this together
in the Thursday lecture,
I guess to sort of--
I mean so much one can
fit in the first class,
but the picture is
essentially the picture
I showed the pieces of.
So to learn word
vectors you start off
by having a vector
for each word type
both for context and outside
and those vectors you initialize
randomly, so that you just
put small little numbers that
are randomly generated
in each vector component.
And that's just
your starting point,
and so from there on you're
using an iterative algorithm
where you're progressively
updating those word vectors,
so they do a better job at
predicting which words appear
in the context of other words.
And the way that
we're going to do
that is by using the gradients,
that I was sort of starting
to show how to calculate and
then once you have a gradient,
you can walk in the opposite
direction of the gradient
and you're then
walking downhill, i.e.
you're minimizing
your loss and we're
going to sort of do lots of
that until our word vectors get
as good as possible.
So it's really all math,
but in some sense word
vector learning is
sort of miraculous
since you do literally
just start off
with completely
random word vectors,
and run this algorithm
of predicting words
for a long time, and out of
nothing emergences word vectors
that represent meaning well.