Hello, everybody.
Welcome to the
CS224N, lecture 10.
This is going to be
primarily on pretraining,
but we will also discuss
subword models a little bit,
and review transformers.
OK.
So we have a lot of exciting
things to get into today,
but some reminders
about the class.
Assignment 5 is
being released today,
assignment 4 was
due a minute ago,
so if you're done with
that, congratulations.
If not, I hope that
the late days go well.
Assignment 5 is on
pretraining and transformers.
So these lectures are going to
be very useful to you for that.
And it doesn't cover anything
after these lectures.
All right.
So today let's kind of take
a little peek through what
the outline will be.
We haven't talked about subword
modeling yet, and sort of we
should have.
And so we're going to talk
a little bit about subwords.
You saw these in
assignment 4, just as
the data that we provided to you
with your machine translation
system, but we're going to
talk a little bit about why
they're so ubiquitous in NLP.
Because they are used
in pretrained models.
I mean, they're used in a
number of different models.
But when we discuss
pretraining, it's
important to know that
subwords are a part of it,
then we'll sort of
motivate-- we will
go on another journey of
motivation, of motivating model
pretraining from
word embeddings.
So we've already
seen pretraining
in some sense in the very
first lecture of this course,
because we pretrained
individual word embeddings that
don't take into account their
contexts on very large text
corpora and saw that
they were able to encode
a lot of useful
things about language.
So after we do the
motivation, we'll
go through model
pretraining three ways.
And we're going to
reference actually
the lecture on Tuesday.
So this is when we'll
review a little bit
of the transformers stuff.
We'll talk about model
pretraining and decoders,
like a transformer decoder
that we saw last week,
and encoders, and
then encoder-decoders.
And in each of
these three cases,
we're going to talk a
little bit about sort
of what things you
could be doing,
and then popular models that
are in use across research
and in industry.
Then we're going to
talk a little bit about,
what do we think
pretraining is teaching?
This going to be very brief.
Actually a lot of the
interpretability and analysis
lecture in two weeks
is going to talk more
about sort of the mystery
and the scientific problem
of figuring out what
these models are learning
about language through
pretraining objectives,
but we'll sort of get a peek.
And then we'll talk
about very large models
and in-context learning.
So if you've heard of
GPT3, for example, we're
going to just briefly
touch on that here,
and I think we'll
discuss more about it
in the course later on as well.
OK.
So we've got a lot to
do, let's jump right in.
So word structure
and subword models.
Lets think about sort
of the assumptions
we've been making in
this course so far.
When we give you
an assignment, when
we talk about training
Word2vec for example,
we made this assumption about
a language's vocabulary.
In particular, we've
made the assumption
that it has a fixed
vocabulary of something
like tens of thousands,
maybe 100,000,
I don't know, a number of yeah.
Some relatively large, it
seems, number of words, and that
seems sort of like pretty
good so far at least,
and what we've done.
And we build this
vocabulary from the set
that we train say, Word2vec on.
And then, here's
the crucial thing.
Any novel word, any
word that you did not
see at training time, is sort
of mapped to a single UNK token.
And there are other
ways to handle this,
but you sort of
have to do something
and a frequent method is
to map them all to UNK.
So let's walk through what
this sort of means in English.
You learn in embeddings,
you map them, it all works.
Then you have a variation
on a word, like "taaaaasty."
With a bunch of As.
Right, and your model
isn't smart enough
to that sort of means
like very tasty maybe.
And so it maps it
to UNK because it's
just a dictionary look up miss.
And then, you have a typo
like "laern," and that maps
to UNK as well potentially, if
it wasn't in your training set.
Some people make typos
but not all of them
will be seen at training time.
And then you'll have
novel items, right?
So this could be the first
time that you've ever seen,
you as the students
in 224N have seen
the word, "transformerify."
But I get the feeling you
sort of have a notion of what
it's supposed to mean, right?
Like maybe add
transformers to, or turn
into using transformers,
or turn into a transformer,
or something like that.
And this is also going
to be mapped to UNK.
Even though you've seen
"transformer," and "ify."
OK.
And so somehow, the
conclusion we have to come to
is that, looking
at words as just
like the individual
sequences of characters
uniquely identifies
that word, and that's
sort of how we should
parameterize things
is just wrong.
And so, not only is this true in
English, but in many languages,
this finite
vocabulary assumption
makes even less sense.
So already it doesn't
make sense in English.
But English is-- it's not
the worst for English.
So morphology is the study
of the structure of words.
And English is known to have
pretty simple morphology
in kind of specific ways.
And when languages have
complex morphology,
it means you have longer
words, more complex words that
get modified more, and each one
of them occurs less frequently.
And that should sound
like a problem, right?
If a word occurs
less frequently,
it will be less likely to
show up in your training set,
and maybe it'll show
up in your test set,
never in your training set.
Now it's mapped to UNK, and
you don't know what to do.
So an example, Swahili verbs can
have hundreds of conjugations.
So each conjugation encodes
important information
about the sentence that in
English might be represented
through say, more words.
But in Swahili it's mapped
onto the verb as prefixes
and suffixes, and the like.
This is called
inflectional morphology.
And so you can have
hundreds of conjugations.
I have just sort of pasted
this Wiktionary block just
to give you a small sample
of just the huge number
of conjugations there
are-- and so trying
to memorize
independently a meaning
of each one of these words
is just not the right answer.
So this is going to be
a very brief overview.
And so what we're
going to do, is
take one, let's say a class of
algorithms for subword modeling
that have been kind
of developed to try
to take a middle ground
between two options.
One option is saying, everything
is just like individual words--
either I know the word and
I saw it at training time,
or I don't know the
word and it's like UNK.
And then sort of another
extreme option is to say,
it's just characters.
Right?
So like I get the
sequence of characters,
and then my neural
network on top
of my sequence of
characters has to learn
everything-- has to learn how
to combine words and stuff.
So subword models
in general just
means looking at the sort of
internal structure of words,
somehow looking
below the word level.
But this group of
models is going
to try to meet a middle ground.
So byte-pair encoding.
What we're going to
do is we're going
to learn a vocabulary from
a training data set again.
So now we have a training data
set, instead of just saying,
oh, everything that was split
by my heuristic word splitter
like spaces in
English for example,
is going to be a word
in my vocabulary,
we're going to learn
the vocabulary using
a greedy algorithm in this case.
So here's what
we're going to do.
We start with a vocabulary
containing only characters.
So that's our extreme, right?
That's our-- at the
very least, if you've
seen all the characters,
then you know that you can--
you'll never have an UNK.
Right? 'Cause you see a word,
you've never seen it before,
you just split it
into its characters,
and then you try to
deal with it that way.
And then also an
end of word symbol.
And then we'll iterate
over this algorithm
we'll say, use the
corpus of text,
find common adjacent letters--
so maybe a and b are
very frequently adjacent.
Add the pair of them
together as a single subword
into your vocabulary.
Now replace instances
of that character pair
with the new subword, repeat
until your desired vocabulary
size.
So maybe you start with a
small character vocabulary,
and then you end up with
that same small character
vocabulary plus a bunch
of sort of entire words
or parts of words.
So notice how "apple," an
entire word, looks like "apple."
But then, "app," maybe this
is sort of the first part,
the first subword of
application or "app."
Yeah, and then "ly,"
I guess I should
have not put the hash there.
But maybe you learned "ly"
as like the end of a word,
for example.
And so, what you end up
with is a vocabulary where
common things, you get
to map to themselves,
and then rare sequences
of characters,
you kind of split as
little as possible.
And it doesn't always
end up so nicely
that you learn like
morphologically relevant
suffixes like "ly," but you can
try to split things somewhat
reasonably and if
you have enough data,
the subword vocabulary
you learn tends to be OK.
So this is originally used
in machine translation,
and now a similar
method, WordPiece,
which we won't go
over in this lecture
is used in pretrained models,
but the idea is effectively
the same and you end
up with vocabularies
that look a lot like this.
So if we go back to our--
if we go back to our examples
of where word level NLP was
failing us, then you
have "hat" mapping
to "hat," OK that's good.
We've "hat" mapping
to "hat," because that
was a common enough
sequence of characters
that it was actually
incorporated
into our subword vocabulary.
Right?
And then you have "learn"
mapping to "learn."
So common words, good.
And that means that the model,
the neural network that you're
going to process this
text with, does not
need to say, combine the
letters of "learn" and "hat"
in order to try to derive
the meaning of these words
from the letters,
because you can imagine
that might be
difficult. But then
when you get a word that
you have not seen before,
you are able to decompose it.
And so, if you've seen
tasty with varying numbers
of As at training
time, maybe you
actually get some of the same
subwords, or similar subwords
that you're splitting it
into at evaluation time.
So we never saw tasty enough
to work with however many
As in order to add it into
our subword vocabulary.
But we're still able to
split it into things,
and then the neural
network that runs
on top of these
subword embeddings
could be able to sort
of induce that oh, yeah.
This is one of those things
where people chain letters
together, chain vowels together
in English for emphasis.
So misspellings still
pretty much mess you up.
So now, "laern,"
this misspelling
might be mapped to two subwords.
But if you saw misspellings
like this frequently enough,
maybe you could learn
sort of to handle it.
It still messes up
the model though.
And-- but at the very least,
it's not just an UNK, right?
It seems clearly
better than that.
And then, "transformerify,"
may be in the best,
this is sort of optimistic,
but maybe in the best case,
right, you were able
to say, oh, yes this
is "transformer," and "ify."
Again, the subwords
that you learn
don't actually tend to be this
well morphologically motivated,
I think.
So "ify" is like a clear
like suffix in English that
has a very common and replicable
meaning when you apply it
to nouns, that's
derivational morphology.
But you're able to sort of
compose the word of tran--
the meaning of "transformerify"
possibly from its two
subword constituents.
And so, when we talk
about words being
input to transformer models,
pretrained to transformer
models, throughout the
entirety of this lecture,
we will be talking
about subwords.
So I might say a
word, and what I mean
is possibly a full word,
also possibly a subword.
OK, so when we say a sequence
of words, the transformer,
the pretrained
transformer has no idea,
sort of whether it's dealing
with words or subwords, when
it's doing its
self-attention operations.
And so, this can be a problem.
You can imagine if you
have really weird sequences
of characters, you can actually
have an individual single word
mapped to as many words
as it has characters.
That can be a problem,
because suddenly you
have a 10-word sentence
but one of the words
is mapped to 20
subwords, and now you
have a 30-word sentence.
Where 20 of the 30 words
are just one real word.
So keep this in
mind, but I think
it's important for sort of this
open vocabulary assumption,
it's important in English,
and it's even more important
in many other languages.
And the actual
algorithm, I mean,
you can go into the actual
algorithms done for this,
byte-pair encoding is sort of my
favorite for going over briefly
word piece you can
also take a look at.
OK.
Any questions on subwords?
I guess, John,
somebody was asking,
what does the hashtag mean?
Oh great, great point.
So this means that you should
be combining this subword.
So this subword it is
not the end of a word.
"taa##" is sort of
telling the model.
So if I had "taa"
with no hashes,
that's a separate
subword that means
there's an entire word that is
"taa," or at the very least,
it's not the end of the word.
See how here, I don't have
the hashes at the end,
it's because this is
indicating that this
is at the end of the word.
Different subword
schemes differ on
whether you should put something
at the beginning of the word,
if it does begin a word, or
if you should put something
at the end of the word if
it doesn't end the word.
Right, so when the tokenizer
is running over your data,
so you've got something that's
tokenizing this sentence,
"in the worst case--" Oh!
Yeah.
"In the worst case--"
it says like, "in,"
that's a whole word.
Give it just the
word "in," no hashes.
That's a whole word.
Give it just the word
"the," no hashes.
And then, maybe over
here at subwords, right,
we've got this
weird word subwords,
and it splits it
into sub and words.
And so, "sub," it's going
to give it the subword with
S-U-B-#-# to indicate that
it's part of this larger word,
subwords, as opposed to the
word "sub," like "submarine,"
which would be different.
That was a great question.
OK, great.
So that was our note on
subword modeling, and you can--
subwords are
important for example
in a lot of translation
applications, that's
why we gave you subwords on
the translation assignment.
Now let's talk about
model pretraining and word
embeddings.
So I love--
I love being able
to go to this slide.
So we saw this quote at
the beginning of the class.
"You shall know a word
by the company it keeps."
And this was sort
of one of the things
that we used to summarize
distributional semantics.
This idea that Word2vec was sort
of well motivated in some way,
because the meaning of
a word can be thought
of as being derived
from the kind
of co-occurrence statistics of
words that co-occur around it,
and that was just fascinatingly
effective, I think.
But there's this other quote
actually from the same person.
So we have J.R.
Firth 1935 compared
to our quote before from 1957.
And the second quote says,
"the complete meaning of a word
is always contextual,
and no study
of meaning apart from
a complete context
can be taken seriously."
Now again, these are just
things that we can sort of
think about and chew on.
But it comes to
mind, right, when
you embed words with
Word2vec, one of the issues
is that, you don't actually
look at its neighbors
as you're giving
it an embedding.
So if I have the sentence,
"I record the record."
The two instances of "rec,"
"ord" mean different things,
but they're given the
same Word2vec embedding.
Right?
Because in Word2vec, you take
the string, you map it to,
oh I've seen the
word "record" before.
You get that sort of vector
from your learned matrix,
and you give it the same
thing in both cases.
And so, what we're
going to be doing today,
is actually not conceptually
all that different
from training Word2vec.
Word2vec training you can
think of as pretraining
just a very simple
model that only assigns
an individual vector
to each unique word
type, each unique element
in your vocabulary.
Today, we'll be going a
lot further than that.
But the idea is very similar.
So back in 2017, we would
start with pretrained word
embeddings.
And again, remember,
no context there.
So you give a word an embedding
independent of the context
that it shows up in.
And then, you learn how to
incorporate the context.
It's not like our NLP models
never used context, right?
Instead, you would learn to
incorporate the context using
your LSTM, or if it's
later in 2017, you know,
your transformer.
And you will learn to
incorporate context while
training on the task.
So you have some supervision.
Maybe it's machine
translation supervision,
maybe sentiment, maybe
question answering.
And you would learn how
to incorporate context
in your LSTM or otherwise
through the signal
of the training, instead of say,
through the Word2vec signal.
And so, sort of
pictographically,
you have these word
embeddings here.
So the red are sort of
your Word2vec embeddings
and those are pretrained.
And those take up some of the
parameters of your network.
And then, you've got
your contextualization.
Now, this looks like an LSTM
but it could be whatever.
So this maybe
bidirectional encoder thing
here is not pretrained.
And now that's a
lot of parameters
that are not pretrained,
and then maybe you
have some sort of readout
function at the end, right?
To predict whatever thing
you're trying to predict again.
Maybe it's sentiment, maybe
you're doing, I don't know,
topic labeling.
Whatever you want to do,
this is sort of the paradigm,
like you set some
code of architecture
and you only pretrained
the word embeddings.
And so, this isn't
actually conceptually
necessarily the biggest
problem, because we
like to think in
deep learning stuff
that we have a lot of training
data for our objectives.
I mean one of the things that
we motivated big deep neural
networks for, is that they
can take a lot of data,
and then we can learn
patterns from it.
But it does put the onus
on our downstream data
to be sort of sufficient to
teach the contextual aspects
of language.
So you can imagine
if you only have
a little bit of labeled
data for fine tuning,
you're putting a pretty big
role on that data to say,
"hey, maybe here's some
pretrained embeddings."
But how you handle
like sentences,
and how they compose, and all
that stuff, that's up to you.
So if you don't have
a lot of labeled data
for your downstream
task, you're asking
it to do a lot with a large
number of parameters that
have been initialized randomly.
OK, so like a small
portion of the parameters
have been pretrained
OK.
So where we're going is
pretraining whole models.
I mean, conceptually we're
pretty close to there.
So nowadays, almost
all parameters
in your neural
network, and let's say
a lot of research settings,
and increasingly in industry,
are initialized via pretraining.
Just like Word2vec
parameters were initialized.
And pretraining
methods in general,
hide parts of the input
from the model itself,
and then train the model
to reconstruct those parts.
How does this
connect to Word2vec?
In Word2vec people don't
usually make this connection,
but it's the following.
You have an individual word,
and it knows itself, right?
Because you have the
embedding for the center word.
Right?
From assignment 2.
You have the embedding
for the center word
and it knows itself,
and you've masked
out all of its neighbors.
You've hidden all of
its neighbors from it.
Right?
All of its window neighbors,
you've hidden from it.
You ask the center words
to predict its neighbors.
Right?
And so, this falls under
the category of pretraining.
All of these methods
look similar.
You hide parts of the
input from the model,
and train the model to
reconstruct those parts.
The differences with
full model pretraining
is that you don't give the
model just the individual word
and have it learn an
embedding of that word,
you give it much
more of the sequence
and have that predict held
out parts of the sequence.
And we'll get into
the details there.
But the takeaway is
that, everything here
is pretrained jointly.
Possibly with the exception
of the very last layer
that predicts the label.
OK.
And this has just
been exceptionally
effective at building
representations of language.
That just maps similar
things in language,
to similar representations
in these encoders,
just like how Word2vec
maps similar words
to similar vectors.
That's been exceptionally
effective at making parameter
initializations, where you
start with these parameters that
have been pretrained,
and then you fine
tune them on your labeled data.
And then third, they've
been exceptionally
effective at defining
probability distributions
over language, like
in language modeling.
They are actually
really useful to sample
from in certain cases.
So these are three ways
in which we interact
with pretrained models.
We use the representations
just to compute similarities,
we use them for parameter
initializations,
and we actually just use them
as probability distributions.
Sort of how we trained them.
OK.
So lets-- we're going to get
into some technical parts here,
but I sort of want to
think broad thoughts
about what we could
do with pretraining,
and what kind of things we could
expect to potentially learn
from this general method
of hide part of the input,
and then see other
parts of the input,
and then try to predict
the parts that you hid.
OK.
So Stanford University is
located in blank California.
If we gave a model everything
that was not blanked out here,
and asked to predict
the middle, right?
The loss function
would train the model
to predict Palo
Alto here, I expect.
OK.
So this is an
instance of something
that you could imagine being
a pretraining objective.
You take in a sentence,
you remove part of it,
and you say, recreate
the part that I removed.
And in this case, if I just
gave a bunch of examples
that looked like this, it might
learn this sort of trivia thing
here.
OK.
Here's another one I put
blank fork down on the table.
This one is under-specified.
Right?
So this could be "the fork," "my
fork," "his fork," "her fork,"
"some fork," "a fork."
So this is specifying the
kinds of syntactic categories
of things that can sort
of appear in this context.
So this is another
thing that you
might be able to learn
from such an objective.
Here-- so you have, the woman
walked across the street,
checking for traffic
over blank shoulder.
One of the things that
could go over here
is, "her," that's a
co-reference statement.
So you could learn sort of
connections between entities
in a text, where one
word, woman can also
co-refer to the same entity
in the world, as this word,
this pronoun her.
Here, you could think
about, I went to the ocean
to see the fish, turtles,
seals, and blank.
Now here, I don't think there's
a single correct answer,
as to what we could see
going into that blank.
But a model could
learn a distribution
of the kinds of
things that people
might be talking about when
they-- one go to the ocean,
and two are excited
to see marine life.
Right?
So this is sort of
a semantic category.
A lexical semantic
category of things
that might sort of be in the
same set of interest as fish,
turtles, and seals
in the context
of, "I went to the ocean."
OK?
So and you know, I
expect that there
would be examples of this in
a large corpus of text, maybe
maybe a book.
OK, here's another example.
Overall, the value I got from
the two hours watching it
was the sum total of the
popcorn and the drink.
The movie was blank.
Right?
And this is when I was
sort of like, look out
into the audience and say,
was the movie bad or good?
But the movie was bad,
is my prediction here.
Right?
And so, this is teaching you
something about sentiment.
About how people express
sentiment in language.
And so, this is--
even looks like a task itself.
Like do sentiment
analysis, is sort
of what you need to do
in order to figure out
whether the movie
was bad or good.
Or maybe the word is
neither bad or good,
the movie was over or
something like that.
But like, if you
had to, if you had
to choose between is
bad or good more likely,
right, you sort of
have to figure out
the sentiment of the text.
Now that's really fascinating.
OK.
Here's another one.
Iroh went into the
kitchen to make some tea.
Standing next to Iroh,
Zuko pondered his destiny.
Zuko left the blank.
OK.
So this is a little easy because
we really only show one place.
So I guess we have
another noun, destiny.
But this is sort of reasoning
about spatial location,
and the movement of sort of
agents in an imagined world.
We could imagine text
that has lines like this,
person went into
the place and was
next to so-and-so,
who left and did that,
and so you have
these relationships.
So here, Zuko left the kitchen,
is the most likely thing
that I think would go here.
And it sort of indicates
that in order for a model
to learn to perform this,
fill in the missing part task,
it might need to, in
general, figure out sort
of where things are, and
whether statements mean or imply
that locality.
So standing next to.
Iroh went into the kitchen.
Now Iroh is in the kitchen.
And then, standing
next to Iroh, means
Zuko is now in the kitchen.
Right?
And then, Zuko now leaves where?
Well, he was in
the kitchen before.
So this is sort of a very
basic sense of reasoning.
Now, this one.
Here's the sentence.
I was thinking about
the sequence that goes,
1, 1, 2, 3, 5, 8, 13, 21, blank.
Right?
So I don't know.
I can imagine people
writing stuff.
So this is the
Fibonacci sequence.
And sort of you sum these
two to get the next one,
sum these two to get the next
one, sum these two, right?
And so, you have
this running sum,
it's a famous
sequence that shows up
in a lot of text
on the internet.
And in general, you have to
learn the algorithm, or just
the formula, I guess that
defines the Fibonacci sequence
in order to keep going.
Do models learn
this in practice?
Wait and find out.
But you would have
to learn it in order
to get the sequence to keep
going, and going, and going.
OK.
So we're going to get into
specific pretrained models,
specific methods
of pretraining now.
So I'm going to go over a brief
review of transformer encoders,
decoders, and
encoder-decoders, because we're
going to get into the sort
of technical bits now.
So before I do that,
I'm going to pause,
are there any questions?
Oh, yeah.
There's an important
question asked about,
the risk of overfitting our
model on our input training
data when they're
doing pretraining.
Then you could also
answer this question
in the light of the
huge pretrained models
that we're seeing nowadays.
Sorry the first part
of that question,
was it are we overfitting
our models to what?
The risk of overfitting model
on our input training data
when they're doing pretraining.
Got it.
Yeah, so that's a good point.
So we're using
very large models,
and we might imagine that
there's a risk of overfitting.
And in practice,
yeah, it's actually
one of the more crucial things
to do to make training work.
So that turns out that you need
to have a lot, a lot, a lot
of data, like a lot of data.
And in fact, we'll
show results later on,
where people built
a pretrained model.
Pretrained it on a lot of data,
and then like six months later,
someone else came along
and was like, hey,
if you pretrained on
it 10 months later,
and changed almost nothing else,
it would have gone even better.
Now was it overfitting?
I mean, you can sort of hold out
some text during pretraining,
right?
And sort of evaluate
the perplexity, right?
The language modeling
performance on that
held out text,
and it tends to be
the case that actually these
models are underfitting, right?
That we need even
larger and larger models
to express the complex
interactions that
allow us to fit these
data sets better,
and so we'll talk about that
when we talk about BERT.
And one of the really
interesting results
is that BERT is underfit, not
overfit, but in principle,
yes, it's a problem to--
It's potentially a
problem to overfit,
but we end up having a ton
of text in English at least,
although not in every language.
And so, yeah, it's
important to scale them,
but currently our models
don't seem overfit
to their pretraining text.
OK.
Any other questions?
All right.
So we saw this figure
before, right here.
We saw this figure of a
transformer encoder-decoder,
from this paper Attention
Is All You Need.
And so we have a
couple of things.
We're not going to go over
the form of attention again
today, because we
have a lot to go over,
but I'm happy to chat
about it more on Ed.
But so in our encoder, we
have some input sequence.
Remember this is a
sequence of subwords now.
If subword gets a
word embeddding,
and each index in
the transformer
gets a position
embedding, now, remember
that we have a finite length
that our sequence can possibly
be, like 512 tokens.
That was that capital
T from last lecture.
So you have some
finite length, so you
have one embedding of a position
for every index for all 512
indices, and then you have
all your word embeddings.
And then the transformer
encoder, right,
was this combination
of sort of submodules
that we walked through
line by line on Tuesday.
Multi-headed attention was sort
of the core building block.
And then, we had
residual and LayerNorm,
right, to help with
passing gradients,
and to help make training
go better and faster.
We had that feed-forward
layer to process
sort of the result of the
multi-headed attention,
another residual and
LayerNorm, and then
pass to an identical
transformer encoder block here.
And these will be stacked.
We'll see a number of
different configurations here,
but I think 6, 12, of these
sort of stack together.
OK, so that's a
transformer encoder.
And we're actually going to
see whole models today that
are just transformer encoders.
OK.
So when we talked about
machine translation,
when we talked about
the transformer
itself, the transformer
encoder-decoder,
we talked about
this whole thing.
But you could actually
just have this left column,
and you could actually just
have this right column as well.
Although the right
column changes a little
bit if you just have it.
So remember the
right column, we had
this masked multi-head
self-attention, right,
so where you can't
look at the future.
And someone asked
actually about how
we decode from
transformers, given
that you have this sort
of big chunking operation.
It's a great
question, I won't be
able to get into
it in detail today,
but you have to run it once
during the decoding process.
For every time that
you decode to sort of
predict the next word.
I'll write out something
on Ed for this.
So in the masked
multi-head self-attention,
you're not allowed to
look at the future,
so that you sort of have
this well defined objective
of trying to do
language modeling,
then we have residual
and LayerNorm,
the multi-head
cross-attention remember
goes back to the last layer
of the transformer encoder,
or the last transformer
encoder block.
And then, more
residual LayerNorm,
another feed-foward layer,
more residual LayerNorm.
Now, if we don't have
an encoder here, right?
Then we get rid of the
cross-attention and residual
and LayerNorm here, right?
So if we didn't have
this stack of encoders,
the decoders get
simpler, because you
don't have to attend to them.
But then again, you also
have these word embeddings
at the bottom and
position representations
for the output sequence.
OK.
So that's been review.
Let's talk about pretraining
through language modeling.
So we've actually talked maybe
a little bit about this before,
and we've seen language
modeling in the context of maybe
just wanting to do it apriori.
So language models were
useful, for example,
in automatic speech
recognition systems.
They were useful in statistical
machine translation systems.
So let's recall the
language modeling task.
You can say it's
defined as modeling
the probability of a
word at a given index
T, of any word at
any given index.
Given all the words before it.
And this probability
distribution--
this is a distribution of words
given their past contexts.
And so this is just saying,
for any prefix here,
Iroh goes to make--
I want a probability of whatever
the next word should be.
So the observed
next word is tasty,
but maybe this goes to
make tea, goes to make
hot water, et cetera.
You can have a distribution
of what the next word should
be in this decoder,
and remember that,
because of the masked
self-attention,
"make" can look back to
the word "to," or "goes,"
or "Iroh," but it can't
look forward to "tasty."
So there's a lot
of data for this.
Right, you just
have text and voila!
You have language modeling data.
It's free.
Once you have the text,
it's freely available.
You don't need to label it.
And in English you
have a lot of it.
Right, this is not true of
every language by any means,
but in English you have a
lot of pretraining data.
And so, the simple thing
about sort of pretraining is,
well what we're
going to do, is we're
going to train a neural
network to do language
modeling on a large
amount of text,
and we'll just
save the parameters
of our trained network to disk.
So conceptually,
it's not actually
different from the things
that we've done before.
It's just sort of the intent.
Right?
We're training these
parameters to start
using them for something
else later down the line.
But the language modeling
itself doesn't change,
the decoder here
doesn't change, right?
It's a transformer in
pretrained models in a modern,
because this is sort of
a newly popular concept.
Although back in 2015, was
sort of when this, I think,
was first effectively
tried out and got
some interesting results.
But this could be anything here.
Today it's mostly going to
be transformers in the models
that we actually observe
OK.
So once you have your
pretrained network,
what's the sort of
the default thing
you do to take to use it, right?
And if you take anything away
from this lecture in terms
of just like
engineering practices
that will be broadly
useful to you as you go off
and build things and
study things maybe
as a machine learning engineer,
or a computational social
scientist or et cetera,
what people tend to do,
is you pretrain your network
on just a lot of data.
Lots of text, learn
very general things.
And then, you adapt the network
to whatever you wanted to do.
So we had a bunch
of pretraining data,
and then maybe this
is a movie review
that we're taking as
input here, and we just
apply the decoder that we
sort of pretrained right.
Start the parameters
there, and then
fine tune it on whatever we
were sort of wanting to do.
Maybe this is a
sentiment analysis task,
so we run the whole sequence
through the decoder, right?
Get a hidden state at the
end of the very last thing,
and then we predict maybe
plus or minus sentiment.
And this is sort of adapting the
pretrained network to the task.
So this pretrain, fine tune
paradigm is wildly successful
and you should really try it
whenever you're doing any NLP
task nowadays effectively.
Because this tends to be what--
some variant of this tends
to be what works best.
OK, so we've got a
technical note now.
So if you don't like to think
about optimization, or gradient
descent, maybe take
a pass on this slide,
but I encourage you to just
think for a second about,
like why should this help?
Training neural nets, we're
using gradient descent
to try to find some
global minimum, right,
of this optimism-- of
this loss function,
and we're sort of doing
this in two steps.
And the first step is we
have-- we get some parameters,
theta hat, by approximating
min over our--
sorry theta is the parameters
of the neural network.
So all of the KQV vectors
in our transformer,
right, the word embeddings,
the position embeddings,
it's just all of the parameters
of our neural network.
And so, we're doing min over
all the parameters of our theta
we're trying to approximate,
min over the parameters
of our neural network of
our pretraining loss, which
here was language modeling
of our parameters.
And we just get this
sort of estimate
of some parameters theta hat.
And then we fine
tune by approximating
this, min over theta of the
fine tune loss, maybe that's
sentiment, right?
Starting at theta hat.
So we initialize our gradient
descent at theta hat.
And then we just sort of
like let it do what it wants.
And it's just like,
it just works.
In part it has to
be, because something
about where we start
is so important,
not just in terms of sort of
gradient flow, although that
is a big part of it, but also it
seems like stochastic gradient
descent sticks relatively
close to that pretraining
initialization
during fine tuning.
This is something that we seem
to observe in practice, right,
that somehow the locality of
stochastic gradient descent,
finding local minima that are
close to this theta hat that
was good for such a general
problem of language modeling.
It seems like, yeah, the local
minima of the fine tuning loss,
because we don't find--
oh, yeah.
The local minima of
the fine tuning loss
tend to generalize well, when
they're near to this theta hat
that we pretrained.
And this is sort of a mystery
that we're still trying
to figure out more about.
And then also, yeah,
maybe the gradients.
Right, the gradients of the
fine tuning loss near theta
propagate nicely so our
network training goes really
well as well.
OK.
So this is something to chew
on, but in practice it works.
I think it's just still
fascinating that it works.
OK.
So we've talked about mainly
the transformer encoder-decoder.
And in fact, right,
I said that we
could have just sort
of the left hand
side encoders to be
pretrained, or just
decoders to be pretrained,
or encoder-decoders.
And there are actually
really popular sort
of famous models in each
of these three categories.
The kinds of
pretraining you can do,
and the kinds of applications or
uses of those pretrained models
that are most natural,
actually depend strongly
on whether you choose to
pretrain an encoder, a decoder,
or an encoder-decoder.
And so, I think
it's useful as we
go through some of these
popular sort of model names
that you need to know,
and what the sort of, what
their innovations were
to actually split it up
into these categories.
So we've already--
so here's the thing.
We're going to go
through these three,
and they all have sort of
benefits, and in some sense
drawbacks.
So for the decoders, right?
Really what we're talking about
here mainly is language models.
And we've seen
this so far, we've
talked about
pretrained decoders,
and these are nice
to generate from.
Right?
So you can just sample from
your pretrained language model,
and get things that
look like the text
that you were pretraining on.
But one problem
is that you can't
condition on future words.
Right?
So we mentioned in our
modeling with LSTMs,
that just like if you could--
when you can do it, we said that
having a bidirectional LSTM,
was actually just way more
useful than having a one
directional LSTM.
Well, it's sort of true
for transformers as well.
So if you can see how the
arrows are pointing here,
the arrows are pointing
up and to the right.
So this word is sort of looking
back at its past history,
but this word can't see, can't
contextualize with the future.
Whereas in the encoder block
here in blue just below it,
you sort of have all
pairs of interactions.
And so, when you're
building representations,
that can actually be
super useful to know
what the future words are.
So so that's what
encoders get you, right?
You get bidirectional context.
So you can condition
on the future, maybe
that helps you build up better
representations of language,
but the question that will
actually go through here
is, well, how do
you pretrain them?
You can't pretrain them
as language models,
because you have
access to the future.
So if you try to do that, the
loss will just immediately be
0, because you can just
see what the future is,
that's not useful.
And then, we'll talk about
pretrained encoder-decoders,
which like may be the
best of both worlds.
But also maybe unclear what's
the best way to pretrain them,
they definitely have
benefits for both.
So let's get into
sort of some general--
a more-- yeah, let's
get into decoders first,
we'll go through all three.
OK.
So when we're pretraining
a language model,
right, we're pretraining
it on this objective,
we're trying to make it
approximate this probability
of a word given all
of its previous words.
What we end up
doing, and I showed
this sort of pictographically,
but that's some math, right?
We get a hidden state,
h1 to hT for each
of the words in
the input w1 to wT,
and remember words again
mean subwords here.
OK.
And then, when we're
fine tuning this,
right, we can take
the representation--
this should be hT
Aht plus b, and then
the picture here is right here.
So hT, it's the very
last encoder state.
And now, this has sort of the--
it's seen all of
its history, right,
and so, you can apply a linear
layer here maybe multiplying it
by some parameters A and B,
that were not pretrained,
and then you're predicting
sentiment maybe.
Plus or minus
sentiment, perhaps.
And so, look at the
red and the gray,
so most of the parameters
of my neural network
have now been pretrained,
the very last layer that's
learning the sentiment
say decision has not
been pretrained.
So those have been
randomly initialized.
And when you take the loss
of the sentiment loss,
right, you train not just
the linear layer here,
but you actually back
propagate the gradients
all the way through the
entire pretrained network,
and fine tune all
of those parameters.
Right?
So it's not like you're
just training this,
at fine tuning time,
this linear layer.
You're training
the whole network
as a function of this
fine tuning loss.
And maybe it's bad that the
linear layer wasn't pretrained,
in the grand scheme of things,
it's not that many parameters
also.
So this is useful,
this is just one way
to interact with
pretrained models, right?
And so, what I want you
to take away from this
is that, there was
a contract that we
had with the original model.
Right?
The contract was
that it was defining
probability distributions.
But when we're fine
tuning, when we're
interacting with the pretrained
model, what we also have
are just like the trained
weights, and the network
architecture.
We don't need to use
it as a language model,
we don't need to use it as
a probability distribution.
When we're actually fine tuning
it, we're really just using it
for its initialization of
its parameters, and saying,
oh, this is just a
transformer decoder
that was pretrained by--
and it happens to
be really great,
in that when you fine tune
on some sentiment data
it does a really good job.
OK, but there's a second way
to interact with decoder--
with pretrained decoders.
Which is in some sense
even more natural,
it actually is closer to the
contract that we started with.
So we don't have to just
ignore the fact that it
was a probability
distribution entirely,
we can make use of it
while still fine tuning it.
So here's what
we're going to do.
So we can use them as a
generator at fine tuning time.
By generator, I mean, it's going
to define this distribution
of words given their contexts.
And then we'll
actually just fine tune
that probability distribution.
So in a task like some kind
of turn-based dialogue,
we might encode the dialogue
history as your past context.
Right, so you have a dialogue
history of some things
that people are saying back
and forth to each other,
you encode it as
words, and you try
to predict the next
words in the dialogue.
Right, and maybe your
pretraining objective,
you looked at very general
purpose text from I don't know,
Wikipedia, or
books, or something.
And you're fine tuning
it as a language model,
but you're fine tuning
as a language model
on this sort of domain-specific
distribution of text,
like dialogue, or maybe
summarization, where
you paste in the whole
document and then say
a specific word, and
then the summary,
and say predict the summary.
And so what this
looks like is, again,
at fine tuning time here.
You have your h1 to hT is equal
to the decoder of the words.
And then, you have
this distribution
that you're fine tuning, of wT
is Ah, there's a typo again,
ht minus 1 plus b.
So now, every time I have this--
I'm predicting these
words-- from word 1
I predict word 2, word 2 I
predict word 3, et cetera,
right?
The actual last
layer of the network
unlike before, the last
has been pretrained.
But I'm still fine
tuning the whole thing.
Right, so A and B
here are mapping
to sort of a
probability distribution
over my vocabulary, or the
logits of a probability
distribution.
And I just get to sort
of like tweak them now.
In order to have
the distribution
that I'm going to use, reflect
the thing like dialogue
that I want it to reflect.
OK.
So those are two
ways of interacting
with a pretrained decoder.
Now, here's an example
of what is ended up
being the first of
your line of wildly
successful, or at least talked
about, pretrained decoders.
So the generative
pretrained decoder, GPT,
was a huge success
in some sense,
or at least it
got a lot of buzz.
So it's a transformer decoder,
no encoder, with 12 layers.
I'm giving you
the details so you
can start to get a feeling
for how the size of things
changes over the years as we'll
continue to progress here.
Had each of-- each of the hidden
states with dimensionality 768.
So if you remember
back to last lecture,
we had a term D, which was our
dimensionality, so D is 768.
And then, an
interesting statement
that you should keep in mind
for the engineering-minded folks
is that, the actual
feed-forward layers, right.
You've got a hidden
layer in the feed--
excuse me, in the
feed-forward layer,
and this is actually very large.
So you had these
sort of position
wise feed-forward layers, right?
And the feed-forward layer
would take the 768 dimensional
vector, sort of like project
it to 3,000 dimensional space
through the sort
of non-linearity,
and then project it back to 768.
This ends up being
because you can squash
a lot more parameters
in, for not too much more
compute in this way
but-- so that's curious.
OK, and then,
byte-pair encoding.
It's actually-- was this
one byte-pair encoding?
Was a subword vocabulary
with 40,000 merges.
So 40,000 merges, so that's
not the size of the vocabulary,
because you started with
a bunch of characters,
and I don't remember how many
characters they started with.
But so it's a relatively small
vocabulary you can see, right?
And compared to if
you tried to say,
have every word have a
unique representation.
Now, it's going to be
trained on BooksCorpus.
It's got 7,000 unique
books, and it contains
long spans of contiguous text.
So you have, instead
of say training it
on individual sentences,
just small short sentences,
the model is able to learn
long distance dependencies,
because you haven't split like
a book into random sentences,
and shuffled them all around.
You've sort of
kept it contiguous.
So it can have that
sort of consistency.
And then, a little
treat here, yeah.
So GPT never showed up
in the original paper,
or in the original blog
post like as an acronym.
And it could actually
sort of refer
to like, Generative
PreTraining, just
sort of what the title of
the paper would suggest,
or Generative
PreTrained Transformer.
And I sort of decided to
say, Generative PreTrained
Transformer because this
seemed like way too general.
So, GPT.
OK.
So they pretrained this huge
language model transformer,
this huge transformer
decoder, just on 7,000 books.
And they fine tuned it on a
number of different tasks.
And I want to talk a little
bit about the details about how
they fine tuned it.
And so, they fine tuned it on
one particular task, or family
of tasks, called Natural
Language Inference.
So in Natural
Language Inference,
we're labeling
pairs of sentences
as entailing, or contradictory
to each other or neutral.
So you have a premise,
and you hold the premise
that's sort of true.
"The man is in the doorway,"
and you have a hypothesis,
"the person is near the door."
If this person is
referring to that man,
then it's sort of
like, Oh, yeah.
So this is sort of entailed,
because there's a person,
because a man is a person.
And they're in the doorway,
then they are near the door.
So you have this sort of logical
reasoning that you're doing,
or you're supposed to
be able to be doing,
and you're labeling
these sentences.
So it's a labeled "task."
You've got sort of an input
that's cut into two parts,
and then one of three outputs.
OK.
So the GPT paper
evaluates on this task.
But what they've got is
a transformer decoder.
So what do they do?
This is sort of one of the
earlier examples of taking--
instead of changing your
neural network architecture
to adapt to the kind
of task you're doing,
you're going to just format the
task as like a bunch of tokens
and not change
your architecture.
Because the pretraining
was so useful.
It's probably better to
keep the architecture fixed,
pretrain it, and
then change the task
specification to sort of fit
the pretrained architecture.
So what they did right,
they put this token "START,"
this is a special token.
"The man is in the doorway."
Some delimiter token, right?
So this is just a linear
sequence of tokens
that we're giving as
one big prefix to GPT.
And then, "the person
is near the door,"
and then some extra token here.
Like "EXTRACT."
And then, the linear
classifier that we talked about
in sort of the first way
to interact with models,
with decoder models, it's
applied to the represent
of the EXTRACT token, right?
So you have the last hidden
state on top of extract,
and then you fine
tune the whole network
to predict these labels.
And so this sort
of input formatting
is increasingly used to keep
the model architecture the same,
and allow for a variety
of different problems
to be solved with it.
OK, and so, did it work?
On Natural Language
Inference, the answer is yes.
So there's a number of
different numbers here,
I wouldn't worry
too much about it.
The fine tuned
transformer language model
is sort of what you
should pay attention to.
There's a lot of effort that
went into the other models,
right?
And sort of, this is the
story of pretraining.
People put a lot of
effort into models
that do various sort
of careful things,
and then you take a
single transformer
and you say, I'm going to
pretrain it on a ton of text,
and not worry too much
about anything else,
and just fine tune it, and you
end up doing super, super well.
Sometimes not too much
better in the GPT case
than sort of the best known
state of the art methods,
but usually a little bit better.
And again, the amount
of effort, the amount
of task-specific effort that
you have to put into it,
is very low.
OK.
And so, what about the other way
of interacting with decoders?
Right, so we said that we
could interact with the code
just by sampling from
them, just by saying,
well, they're probability
distributions.
So we can use them in their
capacities as language models.
And so, GPT-2, this is just,
really just a bigger GPT.
Don't worry too much about it.
With larger hidden
units, more layers.
When it was trained
on more data,
it was shown to produce sort of
relatively convincing samples
of natural language.
So this is something that
went around Twitter a lot.
Right, so you have this
sort of contrived example
that probably didn't show
up in the training data that
has scientists discovering
a herd of unicorns,
and then they sort of sample
from almost the distribution
of the model.
They sort of give that model
some extra credit here.
They do something
called, truncating
the distribution of
the language models,
to sort of cut out
noise in GPT-2.
So it's not exactly
a perfect sample,
but more or less
GPT-2 generated this.
And so, you have the scientists
discovering unicorns.
And then, you have this
consistency, OK, there's
the scientist, you have
them giving it a name.
You have-- you refer
back to this well--
yeah, you refer back to
the scientist's name,
you sort of have these like
topic consistency things,
also the syntax is really good.
It looks vaguely like
English, and so this is sort
of continuing to be a trend.
As we get larger and
larger language models,
we actually sample
from them, even when
we give them prompts
that look sort of odd,
and they seem to be
increasingly convincing.
OK.
So pretraining encoders.
OK, pretraining encoders.
Let's take another second
because I need some more water
here.
If there's another
question, let me know.
All right.
So the benefit of encoders
that we talked about
was that, they get this
bidirectional context.
So you can-- while you're
building representations
of your sentence, of
your parts of sentences,
you can look to the
future, and that
can help you build a better
representation of the word
that you're looking
at right now.
But the big problem is that we
can't do language modeling now.
So we've pretty
much only said we
like we've relied on these
tasks that we already
knew about language modeling
to do our pretraining.
But now we want to
pretrain encoders,
and so, we can't use it.
So what are we going to do?
Here's the solution
that was come up
with in a paper that introduced
the language model of the model
called BERT.
It's called masked
language modeling.
So here's the idea.
We get the sentence
and then we just
take a fraction of the
words, and we replace them
with a sort of a masked token.
A token that's-- that means you
don't know what this is right
now.
And then you
predict these words.
Some details we'll get
into in the next slide.
But so here's what
it looks like, right?
We have the sentence,
I mask to the mask.
We get some hidden states
for all of them, right?
So we haven't trained-- we
haven't changed the transformer
encoder at all.
We've just said, OK, here
is like this sequence.
You get to see
everything, right?
Look at all the arrows
going everywhere.
But then, we have
this prediction layer,
that we were pretraining, right?
And we're using it, we
only have loss on the words
where we had masks here.
So I had this masked,
and then I have
to predict that
it was "went" that
went here, and "store"
that went here.
And now, this is a lot
like language modeling
you might say.
But now you don't need to have
this sort of left to right
decomposition,
you're saying, I'm
going to remove
some of the words,
and you have to
predict what they are.
So this is called masked
language modeling.
And it's been very, very, very
effective with a quick caveat,
it gets a little
more complicated.
So what did they actually do?
They proposed masked
language modeling,
and they released the weights
of this pretrained transformer,
but with a little
bit more complexity
so we get masked language
modeling to work.
So you are going to
take a random 15%
of the subword tokens.
So that was true.
But you're not always going
to replace them with mask.
You can think of it like, if
the model sees a mask token,
it gets a guarantee that it
needs to predict something,
and if the model doesn't
see a mask token,
it gets a guarantee
that it doesn't
need to predict anything.
So why should it bother
building strong representations
of the words that aren't masked?
And I want my model to
build strong representations
of everything.
So we're going to add some sort
of uncertainty to the model.
So what we're going to do
is, for those 15% of tokens,
80% of the time, we're going
to replace it with a mask.
That was our original idea
of masked language modeling.
Then 10% of the
time, we're actually
going to replace the word
with just a random token, just
a random vocabulary
item, can be anything.
And then the other
10% of the time, we're
going to leave the
word unchanged.
So now, when it sees a word,
it could be a random token,
or it could be unchanged.
Then if I see a mask, I
know I need to predict it.
So what these two
things do here is say,
you have to sort
of be doing this--
you have to be on your
toes for every word
in your representation.
So here, "I pizza to the mask."
Right?
It turns out, and the
model didn't know this,
but it's getting three loss
terms for the sentence.
It only has one
mask, but it's going
to be penalized for predicting
three different things.
It needs to predict that this
word is actually, "went," so I
replaced this one.
It needs to predict that this
word is "to," is in fact,
the word "to,"
and then, it needs
to predict that this
word is in fact "store."
Now as a short interlude,
you might be thinking,
maybe thinking, John, there's no
way the model could know this,
it's so under-specified.
OK.
"I pizza," is a
little weird, I admit.
But there's just no way to know
that there's a store, and went,
and to, I mean, the same thing
is true of language modeling,
right?
So it's going to end up learning
these average statistics
about what things tend
to be in a given context,
and it's going to sort
of hedge its bets,
and try to build a distribution
of what things could appear
there.
So for the people who are
thinking that if there was any,
that's what you
should be thinking.
It has to sort of know
what kinds of things
will end up in these slots, it
has other uncertainty, right,
because it can't be sure
that any of the other words
are necessarily right.
And then, it's predicting
these three words.
OK.
And so, that's-- you can see why
it's important to not just have
masks potentially, to have these
sort of token randomization
things, because again we don't
actually care about its ability
to predict the masks.
Right?
Like I'm not going
to usually, I'm
not going to actually sample
from the models distribution
over what should go here.
Instead, I am going
to use the parameters
of the neural
network, and expect
that it built strong
representations of language.
So I don't want it
to think it's got
a free pass for
representing something,
if it doesn't have a mask there.
OK.
So there was one extra thing
with the BERT pretraining,
which is a next sentence
prediction objective.
So the inputs of
BERT looks like this.
This is straight
from the BERT paper.
You have a label here
before your first sentence.
And then a separation, and
then a second sentence.
So you had all these two
contiguous chunks of text.
You had the first chunk of
text here, "my dog is cute."
And then a second chunk of
text, "he likes playing."
Right?
And you see the subwords there.
And now, these would actually
be both be much longer, right?
So this whole thing
would be 512 words,
this would be about half,
and that would be about half,
and they'd be contiguous
chunks of text.
But here is the deal.
What they wanted to
do was they wanted
to try to teach the
system to understand
sort of relationships between
different whole pieces of text.
In order to better
pretrain for objectives--
for downstream applications,
like question answering,
where you have two pretty
different pieces of text,
and you need to know how
they relate to each other.
So the objective they came up
with was, you should sometimes,
have the second chunk of text.
The actual chunk of text
that directly follows
the first in your data
set, and sometimes
have the second check of
text be randomly sampled
from somewhere else.
So unrelated.
And the model should
predict whether it's
the first case or the second
in order, again, to sort of,
have to reason about the
relationships between the two
chunks of text.
So this is next
sentence prediction.
I think it's important to think
about, because again, it's
a very different idea
of pretraining objective
than language modeling and
masked language modeling.
Even though, later
work sort of argued
that in the case of BERT,
it's not necessary or useful.
And one of the
arguments is actually
because it's actually way better
to have a single context that's
twice as long.
So you can learn even
longer distance dependencies
and things.
And so, whether the
objective itself
would be useful if you could
always just double the context
size, I'm not sure if anyone's
done research on that.
But again, it's like a
different kind of objective.
And it's still noising something
about the input, right?
The input was this
big chunk of text.
And you've noised it
to say like, now you
don't know whether
it really was that,
or whether you sort of replaced
it with a bunch of garbage.
This sort of second
portion here.
Whether the second portion has
been replaced with something,
yeah.
Has been replaced with
something that didn't actually
come from the same sequence.
OK.
So let's talk some
details about BERT.
So BERT had 12 or
24 layers depending
on BERT-base or BERT-large.
You'll probably use
one of these models
or one of the sort of
descendants of these models,
if you choose to do something
with the custom final project
potentially, or if you choose
the version of the default
final project.
And you had 600 or 1,000
dimension hidden states,
a bunch of attention heads.
So this is that multi-headed
attention you remember,
had a bunch of them.
So you're splitting all your
dimensions into those 16 heads,
and we're talking on the
order of a couple 100
million parameters.
At the time, right in
2018, we were like, whoa!
That's a lot of parameters.
How do you-- that's
a lot of parameters.
And now, models are way,
way, way, way bigger.
So let's keep track of
sort of the model sizes
as we're going through this.
And let's come back now to
the corpus sizes as well.
So we have BooksCorpus, this
is the number of words there.
This is the same
thing that GPT-2--
GPT-1 was trained on,
800 million words.
Now we're going to train
on also English Wikipedia.
It's 250, sorry
that's 2,500 million.
So that's 2.5 billion words.
And again, to give
you an idea of what
is done in practice, right?
Pretraining is expensive and
impractical for most users,
let's say.
So if you are a researcher
with the GPU, or five GPUs,
or something like that.
You tend to not really be
pretraining your whole own BERT
model unless you're willing
to spend a long time doing it.
BERT itself was pretrained
with 64 TPU chips.
A TPU is a special kind
of hardware accelerator
that accelerates the tensor
operations effectively,
it was developed by Google.
So TPUs are just fast,
and can hold a lot.
And for four days,
they had 64 chips.
So if you have
one GPU, which you
can think of as less
than a single TPU,
you're going to be waiting
a long time to pretrain.
But fine tuning actually.
Fine tuning is so fast.
It's so fast and practical,
it's common on a single GPU.
You'll see how much faster
fine tuning is than pretraining
in assignment 5.
And so, this becomes, I think
like a refrain of the field.
You pretrain once or
a handful of times.
Like a couple of people
release big pretrained models,
and then you fine tune
many times, right?
So you you save those parameters
from pretraining, you fine
tune on all kinds of
different problems.
And that paradigm, right?
Taking something like
BERT, or whatever
the best descendant of BERT
is, and taking it pretrained
and then fine tuning it and what
you want, is pretty close to--
it's a very, very strong
baseline in NLP right now.
Right?
So and the simplicity
is pretty fascinating,
and there's one code
base called Transformers
from a company called
Hugging Face, that
makes this just really, just
a couple of lines of Python
to try out as well.
So it's sort of opened
up very strong baselines
without too, too much
effort for a lot of tasks
OK.
So let's talk about evaluation.
So pretraining is
pitched as requiring
all this different kind
of language understanding.
And the field is--
the field of NLP has a
hard time doing evaluation.
But we try our best,
and we build datasets
that we think are hard
for various reasons,
because they require
you to know stuff
about language, and about the
world, and about reasoning.
And so, when we evaluate
whether retraining
is getting you a lot of
sort of general knowledge,
we evaluate on a
lot of these tasks.
So we evaluate on things
like-- paraphrase detection,
on Quora Questions, natural
language inference we saw,
we have hard sentiment
analysis datasets, or what
were hard sentiment analysis
datasets a couple of years ago.
Actually figuring out if
sentences are grammatical
tends to be hard.
Determining the
textual similarity,
the semantic similarity
of text can be hard.
Paraphrasing again,
natural language inference
on a very, very small data set.
So this is this--
this pretraining help
you train on smaller
data sets, the answer is
yes, sort of thing.
And so, right, so
the BERT folks,
released their paper
after GPT was released,
and there were a lot of sort
of state of the art results
that came from various
things that you
were supposed to be doing.
And the results that you get
sort of with pretraining.
So here's OpenAI's GPT,
here is BERT-base and large.
The last three rows
are all pretrained.
ELMo is sort of in the middle.
It's sort of in the
middle between pretraining
the whole model, and just
having word embeddings,
that's what this is.
And the numbers
you get are just,
I think to the field were
quite astounding actually.
We were all surprised
that there was that much
left to even be gotten on
some of these datasets.
And taking here, so
this line in the table
is unmarked, which is actually
the number of training
examples.
This dataset has 2.5
thousand training examples.
And before sort of the big
transformers came around
we had 60% accuracy on it.
We run transformers on
it, we get 10 points
just by pretraining.
And this has been a trend
that is just continued.
So why do anything,
but pretrain encoders?
But like we know
encoders are good,
and we like the fact that you
have bidirectional context.
We also saw that BERT
did better than GPT.
But it has-- if you
want to actually get
it to do things, right?
You can't just generate it--
generate sequences
from it the same way
that you would from a model
like GPT, a pretrained decoder,
right?
You can sort of sample what
things should go in a mask.
So here's a mask, you
can put a mask somewhere,
sample the words
that should go there.
But if you want to
sample the whole context,
right, if you want to get
that story about the unicorns,
for example, the encoder
is not what you want to do.
So they have sort of
different contracts in there.
It can be used naturally
at least in different ways.
OK.
So let's talk very briefly
about extensions of BERT.
So there are variants
like RoBERTa and SpanBERT,
and there's just
a bunch of papers
with the word BERT in the
title, that did various things.
Two very strong takeaways.
RoBERTa, train BERT
longer, BERT is under fit.
Train it on more data,
train it four more steps.
SpanBERT, mask contiguous
spans of subwords--
of words makes a harder,
more useful pretraining task.
So this is the idea
that we can come up
with better ways of noising
the input, of hiding stuff
in the input, or breaking stuff
in the input for our model
to correct.
So, for example, if
you have the sentence,
"Mask irr esi mask good."
It's just not that
hard to know that this
is "irresistibly," right?
Because like what
could this possibly
be after these subwords?
So this is "irresisti--"
something's got to come here,
and it's probably
the end of that word.
Whereas if you mask a
long sequence of things.
Right, now this is much
harder, and actually you're
getting a useful signal
that it's irresistibly good.
And you sort of need
to mask all of them
to make the task interesting.
So SpanBERT was like
oh, we should do this.
So this was super
useful as well.
So RoBERTa-- just to
point you at the fact
that RoBERTa showed
that BERT was under fit,
said BERT was trained on
about 13 gigabytes of text,
it got some accuracies.
You can get above
the amazing results
of BERT, four extra
points or so here,
right, just by taking
the identical model
and training it on more
data, with a larger batch
size for a long time.
And if you train it,
yeah, on even longer
without sort of more data,
you don't get any better.
Very briefly OK, so--
very briefly on the
encoder-decoders.
So we've seen,
decoders can be good
because we get to play with the
contracts that they gave us,
we get to play with
them as language models,
encoders give us that
bidirectional context.
So encoder-decoders
maybe we get both.
In practice they're actually,
yeah, pretty, pretty strong.
So there was a--
right, we could-- so but I
guess one of the questions
is like, what do we
do to pre-train them?
So we could do something
like language modeling,
right, where we take a sequence
of words, word 1 to word 2T,
instead of T. Right,
and instead of word 1
here, dot, dot, dot,
word T, we provide those
all through our encoder, and
we predict on none of them.
And then we have, word
T plus 1 to word 2T,
here in our decoder, right?
And we predict on these.
So we're doing language
modeling on half the sequence,
and we're taking the
other half to have
our bidirectional
encoder, right?
So we're building strong
representations on the encoder
side, not predicting language
modeling on any of this,
and then we on the other
half of the tokens,
we predict as a
language model would do.
And the hope is that you sort
of pretrained both of these well
through the one language
modeling loss up here.
And this is actually-- so
this works pretty well.
The encoder benefits from
bidirectionality, the decoder,
you can use to train the model.
But what-- this paper showed
that introduced the Model T5
Raffel et al., found to work
best was actually a very--
well, at least a somewhat
different objective.
And this should keep in
your mind sort of that we
have different ways of
specifying the pretraining
objectives, and they will
really work differently
from each other.
So what they said,
let's say you have
an original text like this.
Thank you for inviting me
to your party last week.
We're going to define variable
length spans in the text,
to replace with a
unique symbol that
says something is missing here.
And then we'll replace,
and then we'll remove that.
So now our input
to our encoder is,
Thank you, symbol 1, me to your
party, symbol 2, week, right?
So we've noised the input,
we've hidden stuff in the input.
Also really
interestingly, right, this
doesn't say how long
this is supposed to be.
That's different from BERT.
Right?
BERT said, "Oh, you masked
this many subwords."
This says, well I got
some token that says,
Something's missing here.
And I don't know what
it is, I don't even
know how many subwords it is.
And then, so you have
this in your encoder,
and then your decoder predicts
the first special word,
this X here, and then what
was missing, for inviting.
So, "Thank you X,
X for inviting,"
and then it predicts
Y, here's this Y here.
And then what was missing
from the Y, "last."
"Last week."
This is called span
corruption, and it's
really interesting to
me because, in terms
of the actual
encoder-decoder, we
don't have to change it
compared to whether we--
if we were just doing
language modeling pretraining.
Because I just do
language modeling
on all of these things.
I just predict these words
as if I'm a language model.
I've just done a text
pre-processing step.
Right?
So the actual--
I've just pre-processed the
text to look like, oh, yeah.
Take the input, make
it look like this.
Then make an output that
looks like that up there.
And the model gets to do what is
effectively language modeling,
but it actually works better.
So these are a lot of
numbers I realize, but take
a look at the star here.
This encoder-decoder with
a denoising objective
that tends to work the best.
And they tried similar models
like a prefix language model,
that was sort of the
first try that we had at
defining a pretraining
objective for language models,
sorry, for encoder-decoders.
And then they had another--
a number of other options,
but what worked best for
the encoder-decoders.
And one of the fascinating
things about T5
is that you could pretrain it
and fine tune it on questions.
Like, When was Franklin
D, Roosevelt born?
And fine tune it to
produce the answer.
And then, you could ask it
new questions at test time.
And then it would retrieve
the answer from its parameters
with some accuracy.
And it would do so
relatively well actually.
And it would do so maybe 25% of
the time on some of these data
sets with 220
million parameters.
Then at 11 billion
parameters, this
is way bigger than BERT-large,
it would do so even better,
sometimes even doing
as well as systems
that were allowed to
look at stuff other
than their own parameters.
So again, this is just
making this answer
come from its parameters.
Yeah, we have to skip this.
So if you look back at
this slide after class,
I have each of the
examples of the things
that we could imagine
learning from pretraining,
with the label of what
you might be learning.
So this example is, Stanford
University is located in blank.
You might learn trivia.
In all these cases, there's
all these things you can learn.
One thing I will say, is that
models also learn and can
make even worse--
racism, sexism, all
manner of bad biases
that are encoded in our text.
When I say-- yeah, they do this.
And so, we'll learn more about
this in our later lectures,
but it's important to keep
in mind that when you're
doing pretraining, you're
learning a lot of stuff
and not all of it is good.
So with GPT-3, the
last thing here
is that there's this
third way of interacting
with models that's
related to treating them
as language models.
So GPT-3 is this
very, very large model
that was released
by OpenAI, and it
seems to be able to learn from
examples in their contexts--
their decoder contexts,
without gradient steps.
Simply by looking sort
of within their history.
And now, GPT-3 has 175
billion parameters, right?
The last T5 model we saw
was 11 billion parameters.
And it seems to be sort
of the canonical example
of this working.
And so what it
looks like is, you
give it as part of its prefix--
"thanks" goes to "merci,"
"hello" goes to--
"mint" goes to-- so you've got
these translation examples.
You ask it for the last
one, and it comes up
with the correct translation.
Seemingly because it's learned
something about the task
that you're sort of telling
it to do through its prefix.
And so, you might do the
same thing with addition.
So something plus something--
5 plus 8 is 13.
Give it addition examples,
it might do the next addition
example for you.
Or maybe trying to figure out
grammatical or spelling errors,
for example.
And here is the French
to English-- the English
to French case.
So again, you're learning
just to do pretraining.
But when you're evaluating
it, you don't even
fine tune the model, you
just provide prefixes.
And so, this especially
is not well understood
and there's a lot
of research is going
into sort of what
the limitations
of this so-called
in-context learning are.
But it's a fascinating
direction for future work.
In total, these models
are not well understood.
However, "small," in air
quotes, models like BERT
have become general tools
in a wide range of settings,
and they do have these issues
about learning all these biases
about the world.
That will go into and further
lectures in this course,
and so, yeah.
What you've learned this week,
transformers and pretraining
form the basis, or at
least the baselines
for much of natural
language processing today.
And assignment 5
is out, and you'll
be able to look more into it.
And I'm over time, all right.
Yeah.
I guess, I can take a
question if there is any.
But people can
get going as well.
Well, I think there is
a question about T5.
Which was, how does the decoder
know that it's currently
predicting X or Y?
Could you repeat that?
Yeah.
About T5, there
was a question that
asking, how does the decoder
know that it's currently
predicting X or Y?
Its hierarchy of
I guess if you can
specify it sort of says,
how does it know that it's
currently predicting X or Y?
OK.
Yeah.
Yeah, that makes sense.
So what it does, right so,
it knows from the encoder,
that it has to at
some point predict X,
and at some point predict Y.
Because the encoder can just
remember that, oh, yeah,
there's two things missing.
And if there were
more spans replaced,
there would be a Z, and then an
A, and then a B, and whatever.
Just a bunch of
unique identifiers.
And then up here, it gets to
say, OK, I have attention,
I suppose.
I can look and I know that
first I have to predict this,
first masked thing.
So I'm going to generate
that in my decoder.
And then it gets
that symbol, right?
So we're doing training by
giving it the right symbol.
Now, it gets that X, and it
says OK, I'm predicting X now.
right?
Now it can predict, predict,
predict, predict, then
it gets Y. So we're doing
this teacher-forcing training
where we give it the right
answer after penalizing it
if it's wrong.
Now it gets this Y,
right, and says OK, now I
have to predict what should
go in Y, and it can attend
into the natural parts of this,
as well as what it's already
predicted here, because
the decoder has attention
within itself, and it can
see what should go there.
So what's fascinating here,
is you're doing something
like language modeling, but
when you're predicting Y,
right, you get to see
what came after it.
And that's, I think, one of the
benefits of span corruptions.
You're doing this thing where
you don't know how long you
should be predicting for,
like language modeling,
but you get to know what came
after the thing that's missing.