Welcome to CS224N lecture 15.
So I'm Megan.
And I'm one of the
CAs in this course.
And I'm also a PhD student
working at [INAUDIBLE]..
And today I'll be talking
about integrating knowledge
in language models.
So some quick reminders.
Your project milestones
were due today.
So hopefully, you
turned those in already
or will be turning them in
the next couple of days.
And we'll try to
give you feedback
on those as fast as possible.
So something to be aware of is
the change in grading basis.
And of course, withdrawal
deadline is this Friday.
So if you want to make
any change in your grade,
make sure you do that by then.
And we'll be getting you the
grades back on assignment 5
by then as well, in case
that's helpful in making
your decision.
And finally, your final
projects are due in two weeks so
hopefully, those
are going smoothly.
So the topic of the
day is integrating
knowledge in language models.
You've seen a bit about
this idea in a assignment 5
and also on Colin [INAUDIBLE]
lecture last class.
So in assignment
five, the task was
to train a model to predict the
birthplace of a person, given
their name.
And you saw that by pretraining
on a larger data set,
you're actually able to
do better on this task
since you could encode some
real knowledge into the language
model.
And then last lecture,
Colin [INAUDIBLE]
presented how T5 could actually
fine-tune for a closed domain
question answering task
such that you can give T5
a natural language question,
and it will return an answer.
So today we'll be
building on these threads
and looking at techniques
that researchers have recently
been developing to increase
the amount of knowledge
in language models.
So we're going to start with a
quick recap of language models
just to make sure we're
all on the same page.
Then we're going to talk
about what types of knowledge
language models
can already encode,
and what they might struggle on.
We'll also motivate
why researchers
are interested in increasing
the amount of knowledge
in language models and
what this could enable
for a future systems if we
have language models that
can actually reliably
recall knowledge.
We'll talk about three
broad classes of techniques
that researchers have been
using to add knowledge
to language models.
These include adding
pretrained entity embeddings,
using external memory
or key-value store,
or even just modifying
the training data.
And for each of
these techniques,
we'll talk about at
least one recent work
that used that technique.
So hopefully, it's clear to
see how to actually employ it
in practice.
And then finally, we'll
wrap up by talking
about how to evaluate the
knowledge in language models
and the challenges that come
up when trying to do this.
So let's dive right in.
We're going to start by talking
about standard language models.
You learned about these at
the beginning of the course.
And the task is to predict the
next word in a sequence a text
and to compute the
probability of a sequence.
So you may remember the
example, the students
opened their blank.
And we talked about
could be minds,
exams, bring those books here.
And the task of
standard language model
is to predict the most likely
next word in the sequence.
A couple of lectures
ago, John also
introduced the notion of
masked language models.
And so in predicting the next
word in a sequence of text,
the task is to predict
the masked token.
And this is done using
bidirectional context.
So you may remember the
example, I masked the mask.
And the goal of the
masked language model
is to make the most likely
token for each of the masked
out words.
So maybe I went to the store.
So while there are some
differences in these two
types of language models whether
you're predicting the next word
or whether you're predicting
the masked out token,
they're similar
and that they can
both be trained over large
amounts of unlabeled text.
And this is one
of the reasons why
they've been so widely adopted.
They don't require any
human annotated data.
So you've seen that
language models
can be used for a variety
of tasks from summarization
to dialogue to fluency
evaluation Tests involved would
be the generating
text or evaluating
the probability of text.
And more recently, we've seen
that language models can also
be used to generate pretrained
representations of text that
encode some notion of
language understanding
and has been shown to be widely
useful for different downstream
NLP tasks.
And then finally, today, we're
going to touch on this idea
that if language
models are trained
over massive amounts
of text, can they even
be used as a knowledge base?
So we're going to
start by looking
at what types of
factual knowledge
a language model
might already know.
And these examples
are taken from a paper
by Petroni, et al in EMNLP
a couple of years ago.
And the goal is to test
the factual or commonsense
knowledge in existing language
models such as BERT-Large.
So let's check out what
BERT-Large predicts.
iPod touch is produced by Apple.
London Jazz Festival
is located in London.
Dani Alves plays with Santos.
Carl III used to
communicate in German.
And ravens can fly.
So here, we have the
correct predictions
in green and incorrect
predictions in red.
And if you know
anything about sports,
you may know that Dani
Alves is a soccer player.
Santos is a soccer team.
Here they were hoping that
it would predict Barcelona.
Because at least at the
time of this data set,
apparently he played
for Barcelona.
And Carl III is actually used
to communicate in Swedish,
not German.
So what's good
about these examples
is the predictions are
generally reasonable.
If you didn't know the ground
truth, they all make sense.
When you want to produce--
when you want to
predict a language,
you do, in fact,
predict the language.
But of course, they're
not all factually correct.
So what made this happen?
Well, for one, the fact might
not have been seen in training.
And you can't expect
the language model
to do more than recall facts
that it has seen in training.
It can't make up facts about
the world, for instance.
It's also possible that the
fact is just really rare.
So maybe the language model has
seen the fact during training,
but it hasn't seen
it enough times
to actually memorize the fact.
And the last issue is
a little more subtle,
which a model might just be
very sensitive to the phrasing
of the fill in the
blank statement.
And so for example, you
might have statements
like x was created in
blank, that the model can't
predict correctly.
But if you change it
to x was made in blank,
suddenly, it can
predict it correctly.
And I will come
back to this and how
to actually evaluate the
knowledge in these language
models.
So it's inability to
reliably recall knowledge
is a key challenge facing
language models today.
And they will be the
focus of this talk.
Recent works have found that
language models can recover
some knowledge, including
the work that Colin presented
last class.
They've had very
encouraging results.
But there's still
a way to go as we
saw with the fill in
the blank statements
and with these challenges
that we just discussed above.
So as a result, the
past couple of years
have had a ton of rapid progress
in this area of research
in terms of trying to figure out
how do you actually encode more
knowledge in language models.
So I also want to
motivate why researchers
are interested in building
language models that can more
reliably recall knowledge.
And one of these reasons is that
the pretrained representations
are used in a variety
of downstream tasks.
And some of these downstream
tasks are knowledge intensive.
So for instance, you might
have a downstream task
to extract the relations between
two entities in a sentence.
And this is commonly known
as relation extraction.
And this is much
easier if you have
some knowledge of
the entities, which
could be potentially provided by
this pretrained language model
representation.
And when we talk
about evaluation,
we'll talk about
what types of tests
are most likely to benefit
from this knowledge
rich pretrained representations.
And then as a stretch
goal, some researchers
are starting to
propose the idea that,
can language models
actually ultimately be
used to replace traditional
knowledge bases?
So instead of querying a
knowledge base for a fact
like you might
right now with SQL,
you'd create a language model
with a natural language prompt.
And of course, this does
require the language model
to have high quality
on recalling facts.
So we might not be
there yet, but it's
an interesting direction
for us to be moving towards.
So I want to make
it super clear what
I mean by a knowledge base.
Here we're just talking
about a knowledge graph
where the nodes in the
graph would be entities,
and the edges are going to be
relations between the entities.
So for example, here
we have a subset
of a knowledge graph for
Franklin D. Roosevelt.
And you see the information
about his spouse,
his place of birth, his
date of birth, and so on.
An important thing
to note is this
is a structured way of storing
the knowledge since it's just
in a graph form.
And you can actually
describe these graphs
with knowledge
graph triples, which
will be an important vocabulary
word throughout this talk.
So knowledge graph
triple would be
consisting of a subject entity,
a relation, and an object
entity.
So for instance, here we might
have Franklin D. Roosevelt,
date of birth, January
30, 1882, and that would
form a knowledge graph triple.
We'll also refer to this as a
apparent entity, a relation,
and a tail entity.
So Wikidata is one
very popular knowledge
base you might come across if
you're working in this area.
It's a free
knowledge base that's
actually populated by humans.
So they're filling in these
relations and entities.
And it's also multilingual.
So if you want information from
this knowledge base, what you'd
do is you'd write a SQL query.
This is a simplified one.
But the idea is if
you'd want to figure out
the date of birth of
Franklin Roosevelt,
so you would write a
query like follows.
Now if instead you want
to create a language model
as the knowledge
base, you'll have
something like this diagram that
you've actually probably seen
in several lectures now.
And the idea is you're
training a language model
over this unstructured text.
And then you'll use
a language model
to just answer these natural
language query statements.
So here, this is the
work on T5, where they're
training T5 over natural
language over unstructured text
with the span corruption task.
And then they're asking T5, when
was Franklin D Roosevelt born?
And the idea is TD will
produce a textual answer.
So you can see this
contrast very much
with the old approach of
using a traditional knowledge
base where the knowledge
base is structured,
and you have these SQL
statements to query it.
So what are the advantages
of using language models
over traditional
knowledge bases?
And why might people think
this could be a good idea?
Well, for one, the
language models
are pretrained
over large amounts
of unstructured
and unlabeled text,
whereas traditional
knowledge bases require
manual annotation,
like with Wikidata,
people are actually
populating it,
or complex NLP pipelines to
extract from unstructured text
into a structured form that
forms the knowledge base.
Language models can also support
more flexible natural language
queries.
So if we take the example, what
is the final F in the song UFOF
stand for, a knowledge
base probably
won't have a feel for
final F. So it won't
be able to answer your query.
But there's a chance that a
language model could actually
learn and have a response for
this natural language query.
They also had a less
extreme example,
in this paper by
Petroni and others,
where maybe your
relation would be,
is works for in your knowledge
base, and then you ask for,
is working for, and
the knowledge base
doesn't have an exact
match on the field,
and so it returns
an empty response.
And as much-- it's reasonable
to believe that your language
model could figure out that
these relations are similar.
So if I know the
answer to one of them,
I probably know the
answer to the other.
Of course, it's
not all advantages.
There's also many open
challenges using language
models as knowledge bases.
So for one, it's
harder to interpret.
When a traditional knowledge
base produces an answer,
there's actually provenance
information associated with,
why did it return
that particular query?
But with a language model,
it's really not clear
why it might produce
a prediction.
The knowledge is just encoded
in the parameters of the model.
It's also harder to trust.
So you saw this
in assignment five
where the language model could
produce realistic predictions,
but they are incorrect.
So it's not easy to know when
the language model actually
knows a fact versus it's using
biases to make its prediction.
And in the case of the
traditional knowledge base,
if it doesn't know
a fact, it's just
going to have an empty response.
And then finally, knowledge
bases-- or language models
are harder to modify.
So in a knowledge base, if
you want to update a fact,
you just change
the fact directly
in the structured data.
But in a language model,
it's not quite clear
how you would do this.
You could fine-tune the model
longer on the updated data,
but how do if it still has some
memorization of the old fact?
So there are a lot
of open challenges
to this goal of actually
using language models
as traditional knowledge bases.
But hopefully, you'll
see why some people think
this could actually
be a good idea
and why researchers are
interested in training language
models that can actually
integrate more knowledge.
So that brings us to
section two of the talk.
So I want to pause here just in
case there's any questions OK?
I think that's OK.
Yeah.
OK.
Awesome.
So now we're going to be
talking about what techniques
researchers are using
to actually add more
knowledge to language models.
So we're going to talk
about three broad classes
of techniques.
This is by no means exhaustive.
But hopefully, it gives
you a good overview
so that if you want to
dive deeper, you can.
So we'll start by talking
about adding pretrained entity
embeddings.
And for each section, we'll
focus on the first work
that you see in the bullets.
But we'll also talk about,
briefly, some of the variants.
So you see how the works
within each class can differ
and what knobs you can turn.
So for adding
pretrained embeddings,
we first need to figure out
what pretrained embeddings would
actually be the
most useful to add
knowledge to language models.
And this can start
with the observation
that facts about the world are
usually in terms of entities.
So if we have a
fact like Washington
was the first president
of the United States,
we have the entities
Washington and United States.
But pretrained word
embeddings don't
have this notion of entities.
So we'd have different
word embeddings for USA,
United States of America, and
America even though these all
refer to the same entity.
And this makes it challenging
for the language model
to actually learn
any representations
over these entities since
they may be referred
to many ways in the text.
So what if instead, we have a
single embedding per entity?
And we'll refer to these
as entity embeddings.
So now you'd have a single
entity embedding for USA,
United States of
America, and America.
And whenever you see a phrase in
text referring to this entity,
you would use the
same entity embedding.
And these entity
embeddings can actually
be pretrained to encode
this factual knowledge
about the world.
And these first class
techniques we'll be looking at
will be how do you actually
best use these pretrained entity
embeddings in a language model.
So I need to make a quick
note that these entity
embeddings are only useful
to a language model.
So if you can do
another NLP task
called entity linking well.
So I'm going to take a
quick aside and explain
what is entity linking.
So a definition
of entity linking
is the link mentions in text
to entities in a knowledge
I like to think
about this in terms
of how we use word embeddings.
So if you want to
use word embeddings,
and you have a sentence,
you're going to first tokenize
that sentence into words.
And then for each
word, you're going
to look up their corresponding
ID in some word embedding
matrix.
And now, you have
your word embedding.
Well, for entity embeddings,
the dictionary lookup
isn't so easy.
You might have sentences
like Washington
is the first president
of United States.
Well, Washington has two
different candidates.
Are we talking about
George Washington?
Or are we talking
about Washington State?
And these are different entities
that have different entity
embeddings.
And the QIDs here would just be
their identifiers in Wikidata.
And then United States
just has a single entity.
So the task of entity linking
is to figure out correctly
these ambiguous mentions.
What entity do they actually
link to in a knowledge base?
And there's many different ways
you can do this entity linking.
So one way you
might be able to do
this is to figure out
that, oh, I see the context
word of president so
Washington probably
links to George Washington.
Just some more definitions.
We're going to
refer to Washington
as a mention, the United
States as a mention,
and then the things that
the mention could link to.
So the two options
for Washington
are going to be candidates.
So this is a whole
research area of its own.
And I encourage you check out
the resources at the bottom
if you're interested
in learning more.
But right now the most
important thing to understand
is that entity thinking is
what is going to tell us
which entity embeddings are
actually relevant to the text
and which ones you
want to use as you
iterate through a sequence.
Megan, there are a few
questions around here.
One of them is, so
that's entity linking,
but what about the relations?
Yeah.
So some of the works
we'll talk about
will only use the
entity embeddings.
Some of these have
been pretrained
with relation information.
But in the end, you only
have an entity embedding.
And so relation extraction
is yet another NLP task
you could also do.
But here, we're just talking
about entity linking.
Then if you have the knowledge
graph you showed earlier,
it had relations in it, right?
Do you get any connection
between that and the text?
I mean, that's the goal of
relation extraction, right?
It's to figure out,
given the entities, what
is the relation between
them, which would then
form the full triple of
head entity, tail entity,
and relation.
OK.
Then I think people want
to know more about how
this is going to be used.
Maybe you should go on
and show some examples
Yeah.
I will.
For sure.
OK.
So entity embeddings,
just to summarize,
they're like word
embeddings, but they're
for entities in
a knowledge base.
So you'll have some
vector associated
to George Washington.
And it should be meaningful
in embedding space such
that maybe the George
Washington vector
is close to the vectors
for other founding fathers.
So we're going to briefly talk
about some methods for training
entity embeddings.
There is knowledge
graph embedding methods.
You might have heard of the
TransE embedding method.
So this starts from the idea
of having these knowledge graph
triples.
And you want to learn pretrained
entity and pretrained relation
embeddings.
And you want it to be
the case that the subject
embedding and the
relation embedding,
the sum of those two,
is close to the object
embedding in vector space.
So it's an algorithm to
learn that constraint.
There's also word entity
co-occurrence methods.
So these build off of Word2Vec.
One of them's even
called Wikipedia2Vec.
And the idea is
given an entity, you
want to figure out
what words are most
likely to co-occur around it.
And then the last method, or
one of the other methods that
is common now is actually
just using the transformer
to learn representations
of an entity
by encoding the
entity description.
And so BLINK from Facebook is
an approach that does this.
So the methods we'll
talk about today
are actually agnostic to how
you train your pretrained entity
embedding.
But I think it's important
to know that there's actually
a wide variety of methods to
train these pretrained entity
embeddings.
And it's actually
not clear which
method is best for using them
downstream in language models.
So one of the key challenges
of using pretrained entity
embeddings in language
models is figuring out
how to incorporate
them when they're
from a different embeddings
space in the language model.
And so what we'll
do, or the approach
that we'll look at today
will learn a fusion layer
to combine this context
and entity information.
So we have entity
embeddings, and we
have the contextualized
word embeddings
from our language model.
So if we take a
sequence of text,
and we imagine that j indicates
the jth element in a sequence,
then the challenge
here is we want
to figure out how do we
combine some word embedding
wj with some aligned
entity embedding ek.
So here an alignment could
be like in the example where
we had, Washington was
the first President.
Washington would be
a word embedding,
and George Washington would be
the aligned entity embedding
there.
So you could imagine,
in this case,
let's say, your
wj is Washington,
and your ek is your
entity embedding
for George Washington, and you
want to align them together.
So what you can do is learn a
weight matrix, Wt for the text
and we for the entity to
project this embeddings
to the same dimension before
you sum them, and finally, take
an activation
function over them.
So the idea is that by
having some fusion layer
mechanism like this,
you can actually
use these entity embeddings
and these contextual word
embeddings that are in
different embedding spaces
and fuse them together
to have the single hidden
representation for the
element in the sequence.
So the approaches
we'll talk about today
all have some
mechanism either very
similar to this or
some variation of this
to do this combination of the
context and entity information.
So the first approach
we're talking about
is called ERNIE, Enhanced
Language Representation
with Informative Entities.
And so this just builds on
what we already talked about.
It uses pretrained
entity embeddings.
And it also uses this
notion of a fusion layer.
So the first block in
ERNIE is a text encoder
which is a multi-layer
bidirectional transformer
encoder.
For their experiments,
they use BERT.
But it doesn't have to be BERT.
And this is followed by
a knowledge encoder which
has stacked blocks composed of
two multi-headed attentions,
one is over the
entity embeddings
and one is over your token
or subword embeddings.
And then the output of these
contextualized entities
and token embeddings on
multi-headed attentions
are passed a fusion layer,
which looks very similar to what
we just looked at.
But now you also have new
word and entity embeddings
that you're producing as
output of your fusion layer.
So you see this wj
and it's ek, which
are produced as the next layer
of word and entity embeddings.
So the i here indicates
that it's the ith
block in the knowledge encoder.
So you'll actually have multiple
stacks of these knowledge
encoders, and you'll be doing
a fusion of the word entity
embedding, producing new
word and entity embeddings
and then passing this to the
next block of the knowledge
encoder.
So this is what the
architecture diagram looks like.
On the left side, we have the
T-encoder, or the text encoder,
followed by the K-encoder,
or the knowledge encoder.
And then on the
right side, you have
a zoomed in version of
your knowledge encoder.
So you see the
multi-headed attentions
over the tokens
in orange and then
over the entities in yellow.
And then you have this
alignment between the word
and entities with
the dashed lines.
So they had this example as, Bob
Dylan wrote Blowing in the Wind
in 1962.
The entities here are Bob
Dylan and Blowing in the Wind.
And they have a
simple alignment rule
where you want to align the
entity to the first word
in the entity phrase.
So you want to align
Bob Dylan to Bob.
That's what the dash
line's trying to indicate.
And you want to align
Blowing in the wind to blow.
Here this already assumes that
entity linking has been done.
And you know your
entities in advance.
So you can see that the
entities are actually input
into the model.
So after you have your
word entity alignment,
this goes to the
information fusion
layer in this light
purple gray color.
And then finally, it produces
these new word entities
embedded things as output.
And then remember that you
have multiple blocks of these,
so this will be passed onto the
next block of your knowledge
encoder.
So how do you
actually train this?
It's pretty similar to BERT.
You have a masked
language model loss,
and you have a next
sentence prediction loss.
And then they also introduce
a knowledge pretraining
task, which they refer
to as the DEA task.
It's named after a
denoising entity autoencoder
from an ICML paper in 2008.
And the idea is they're
going to randomly mask
these token entity alignments.
So the idea that Bob
goes to Bob Dylan,
they're going to mask that out
with some random percentage.
And then they're
going to predict
the corresponding
entity for a token are
the entities in the sequence.
So this looks like as follows.
The summation is over M
entities in the sequence.
So this would be over
Bob Dylan and Blowing
in the Wind in the
previous example.
And given a
particular word, they
want to figure out what entities
are most likely to align to
in that sequence.
So does Bob align to Bob Dylan?
Or does Bob align to
Blowing in the Wind?
And their motivation
for doing this
is that if you don't
have this task,
all you're ever going
to be predicting
is the token with the
masked language model loss.
And you really think that
knowledge should also probably
be predicting over entities.
So by adding this task,
they have some kind of task
that is actually
predicting the entity.
And they also suggest
that this might better
fuse the knowledge or the entity
and the word representations
than just using
the fusion layer.
Their final loss is
then the summation
of the masked language model
loss, the next sentence
prediction loss and this DEA
knowledge pretraining task
loss.
So they showed that
ablation experiment
that it's actually
very important
to have this knowledge
pretraining task.
So this has BERT on
the leftmost bar,
ERNIE has the second
bar from the left.
And so that's with all
the features of ERNIE.
And then they try removing the
pretrained identity embeddings
and removing this
knowledge pretraining task.
So you see that BERT
performs the worst--
this isn't very surprising-- and
that ERNIE performs the best.
But what's interesting is
that if you remove the entity
embeddings, or you remove
the pretraining task,
they only do a little
better than BERT.
And so it's really
necessary to actually use
this pretraining
task to get the most
use of your pretrained
entity embeddings.
So some strengths
of this work were
that they introduced some way
to combine entity and context
information through this
fusion layer and this knowledge
pretraining task.
And then they also showed
improved performance
on downstream tasks which
we'll come back to when
we talk about evaluation.
But of course, there's
also some limitations.
So it needs text data with the
entities annotated as input.
And this is even true
for downstream tasks.
So if you remember on
the architecture diagram,
we had the entity
information actually
input into the architecture.
But it's not very realistic
that you're necessarily
going to have a good entity
linker for any downstream task
that you want to use ERNIE on.
And the next challenge is
this requires more pretraining
of your language model.
So now you don't just
need to pretrain BERT,
but you also need to pretrain
your knowledge encoder on top.
For the first
challenge, we're going
to actually talk about a
work that presents a solution
to address this.
For the second challenge, I
encourage you to check out
the footnote on the bottom.
This introduces a work that
actually uses pretrained entity
embeddings, uses them
in a language model,
and doesn't require
any more pretraining.
So it's pretty cool.
I guess that's all
I have for ERNIE.
So I want a pause
here for questions.
Well, here's one that's up here.
So on the fusion
layer, it observed
that passing the entity
embedding into a fusion layer
to combine with
the word embedding
is more powerful than
just concatenating
the entity embedding onto
the end of the word embedding
question mark.
So I guess people are
still a little bit confused
as to the motivation
for that fusion layer.
And so I guess here is this,
the simplest strategy would be,
since you've got
the entity linking,
you could just concatenate
entity embeddings
onto the end of word
embeddings and do regular BERT.
Would that work just as well?
I think the idea is it wouldn't.
Because if you imagine
that, let's say,
your magnitudes
are very different,
you need some way to, I
guess, align the spaces
so that anything meaningful
in the entity embedding space
is still meaningful in
the word embedding space.
So if you're close in
the word embedding space,
you also would be-- you'd
want to be close to an entity
embedding space.
So I guess that's one argument.
Yeah.
I mean, I think the
question isn't--
it's a good question
as people say.
I mean, it's not
completely obvious
that it wouldn't
work to do that.
It seems like one, the potential
problem is some words have
the entity links to them
and some words don't.
And so you then, you
have zero vectors
for the ones that
don't have anything--
That's a good point.
Linked, and that might
act a bit weirdly.
But--
Yeah.
In this case, when they
don't have entities linked,
which is a great point,
yeah, the first equation
just simplifies to the
first term plus the bias.
So an obvious
solution in that case
when you're not
concatenating, that you just
don't add on the term.
Yeah.
That could be one reason to.
Are there any other questions?
I think you can go on.
OK.
Cool.
So now we're talking
about KnowBERT.
And this is from the same folks
that introduced the ELMo BERT.
And the idea here
is that they're
going to pretrain and
integrate an entity
linker as an extension to BERT.
And so their loss
function will now
be the summation of the
next sentence prediction,
the masked language model loss,
and its entity linking loss.
So instead, the knowledge
pretraining DEA task from ERNIE
will have an entity
linking loss.
And the idea of
the entity linker
is you'll now have just as
normal sequence as input.
And the integrated entity
linker will figure out
what are the entities
in the sentence
or what are the mentions
in the sentence, what
are the candidates
of those mentions,
and then what
should be the scores
of those entities
for the candidates,
given the context
of the sentence.
So this is all done now
as part of the model
rather than requiring it as
some external pipeline stage
before you could even
use ERNIE, for instance.
So now for downstream
tasks, you no longer
need this entity annotations.
Your integrated
entity linker will
figure out what the
correct entity is
and be able to use the
correct entity embedding.
So there's also this idea that
learning this entity linking
may actually better
encode knowledge
than this DEA pretraining
task because they
show that KnowBERT
actually outperforms
ERNIE on downstream tasks.
So one reason this may occur is
that if you think about the DEA
task, it's actually
a bit simpler
than just entity linking.
So you're trying to
predict, for instance,
what Bob linked to out of Bob
Dylan and Blowing in the Wind.
And it's much easier
even as a human
to see that Bob Dylan will
more likely link to-- or Bob
will more likely
link to Bob Dylan
than that Bob will link
to Blowing in the Wind.
In the entity linking
task, you actually
have a much harder set of
candidates to predict over.
You're not just looking
at the ones in a sentence.
So does Washington link to
George Washington or Washington
State, actually requires
you using more information
about the entity.
So given it's a harder task,
it's not too surprising
that it might perform
better than just this easier
knowledge pretraining task
that ERNIE introduced.
So otherwise, KnowBERT has a
lot of similarities to Ernie.
It uses a fusion layer
that combines this context
and entity information.
And it introduces some
knowledge pretraining task.
So I'd say the high
level takeaways
if you want to use pretrained
entity embeddings in a language
model, you probably
at least want
to consider both
of these components
in terms of actually going to
integrate the pretrained entity
embeddings and take the most
advantage of the knowledge
in them as possible.
So that brings us to the next
class of techniques which
is using an external memory.
And here, we'll mainly focus
on this work called KGLM.
And then we'll also
briefly talk about kNN-LM.
So the previous methods
I've talked about
have relied on pretrained
entity embeddings
to encode the factual
knowledge from knowledge bases.
And the one problem
with this, or one
of the problems with this,
is if you want to, let's say,
modify your knowledge
base, you now
need to retrain your
entity embeddings
and then retrain your language
model on top of these entity
embeddings.
So this begs the
question, are there
more direct ways in
pretrained entity embeddings
to provide the model
factual knowledge?
And so what we're
going to talk about
is how you can actually
use an external memory
or a key-value store
to give the model
access to either knowledge graph
triples or context information.
And a key thing about
this external memory
is that it's independent of
the learned model parameters.
So this means you can actually
support injecting and updating
factual knowledge.
You can do this directly to the
symbolic external memory by,
let's say, changing the
value for a particular key
or maybe adding another key.
And you don't have to
retrain, or pretrain,
your entity embeddings
when you make this change.
And the next part
we'll talk about today
can actually even have these
updates to the external memory
without more pretraining
of the language model.
So that's pretty neat.
And another benefit of
using external memory
over these pretrained
entity embedding approaches
is it can also be
more interpretable.
So if you have a bug, or not
a bug, an air in your model,
where it's not
predicting a fact fact,
it's very challenging to figure
out with pretrained embeddings
what the problem might be.
Was it the original
knowledge base?
Was it the encoding in
the entity embeddings?
Is it how the language model
is using the entity embeddings?
And here you have a
little more information
with an external
memory, and that you
can look in the external
memory and see what's
a fact in the external memory
with a not in external memory
and so on.
So it adds a little bit
more interpretabilability
than just using these
pretrained entity
embeddings as an indirect way
to encode the knowledge base.
So first, what we're going
to talk about is called KGLM.
And unlike the other approaches
we've talked about so far,
this actually uses LSTMs
and not transformers.
So the key idea here is to
condition the language model
on a knowledge graph.
So recall with the
standard language model,
we want to predict the next
word, given the previous words
in the sequence.
Well, now we also want to
predict the next entity, given
the previous words
in the sequence,
and given the previous
entities in the sentence,
or the entities that are
relevant to the sentence,
I should say.
So KGLM will be building
a local knowledge graph
as it iterates
over the sequence.
And a local knowledge
graph is just
a subset of a full
knowledge graph that
only has the entities
that are actually
relevant to the sequence.
So if we have this example
here, a simplified example
from the paper, that
Super Mario Land
is a game developed by blank.
And Super Mario Land
here is an entity.
You'd want a local
knowledge graph
as follows, where you see
that Super Mario Land is
in the local knowledge graph.
But we also have the
relation to Super Mario Land
to other entities that are
copied from the full knowledge
graph into this local
knowledge graph.
And you would build up
this local knowledge graph
as you iterate
over the sentence.
So whenever you
see an entity, you
would add it to the local
knowledge graph as well as
its relations to other entities.
So obviously, this is
a much smaller example
than when we would really
have all the relations
to Super Mario Land, just for
the purpose of the example.
But hopefully, it's
clear that all of these
are relevant to the sequence.
Something important
to note here is
that this does assume that
the entities are known
during training so that you do
have this entity annotated data
for training.
And therefore, your
local knowledge graph
is always the ground truth
as you iterate
over the sequence.
So why might this be a
good idea to do this?
Well, here, the next word we
want to predict is Nintendo.
And you may notice that Nintendo
isn't in your local knowledge
graph.
So sometimes, this
local knowledge graph
can actually serve as a very
strong signal for what you want
to predict for your next word.
Now you may be thinking,
well, this wouldn't always
be helpful, and
that's true as well.
So if you look at just the
third word in the sequence,
and you want to
predict that word, so
is a game, for
instance, well, if this
isn't in the local
knowledge graph,
this wouldn't be
necessarily that helpful.
You will just do a standard
language model prediction.
Or if you at the
beginning of a sequence,
your local knowledge
graph is empty,
so of course, you're not going
to get any signal from it.
So the first question they ask
in KGLM is how can a language
model know when to use
a local knowledge graph
and when it might actually
be useful for predicting
the next word?
So we're going to keep the same
example as a running example.
And we have our local
knowledge graph here.
We now have an LSTM that looks
similar to the representations
you've seen
throughout this class.
And normally, you've seen the
LSTM predicts the next word.
Well, now we're also going
to use the LSTM to predict
the next type of the word.
So is the next word going
to be a related entity,
meaning it's in the local
knowledge graph already?
Is it going to be a new
entity, meaning it's not
in the local knowledge graph?
Or is it going to be not an
entity, in which case, you just
revert to a normal
LSTM prediction.
And they're going to use
the LSTM hidden state to do
this prediction of the type of
the next word over this three
way-- three different
classes that they
might want to consider.
So in the case of
Super Mario Land
is a game developed
by Nintendo, we
saw that this would
be a related entity
case because you saw
that Nintendo was
in the local knowledge graph.
But in the other
cases, Super Mario Land
would be a new entity case
since the local knowledge
graph is empty at that point.
And then any of the
words between Super Mario
Land and Nintendo
would be non-entity
as they're just a standard LSTM
language model prediction that
doesn't involve any entities.
So now we need to talk
about what the language
model actually does in these
three different scenarios
to predict the next
entity and the next word.
So we're going to keep the
example up at the top in case
you want to go back to
the three different cases.
And we're going to start
with a related entity case.
So here we assume that the
next word or entity is actually
in your local knowledge graph.
And remember that we can
describe a knowledge graph
in terms of triples,
so in terms of pairs
of parent entities,
relations, and tail entities.
And in the case of predicting
the next word as Nintendo,
there's only one
possible parent entity
in the local knowledge graph,
which is Super Mario Land.
And the goal is you
want to figure out
what is the most relevant triple
that will be useful in helping
to predict the next word.
So in this case, you could
have the triple Super Mario
Land, publisher, Nintendo.
You might have the triple
Super Mario Land, genre,
platform game, which
of these is actually
helpful in predicting
that Nintendo
should be the next word.
So here what you
would want KGLM to do
is predict that the
top scoring parent
entity is Super Mario Land.
And the top scoring
relation is publisher.
And you can see
there are actually
contextual cues
in a sentence that
could help you figure out which
triple you're talking about.
And then, given that
your top scoring
parent entity is Super Mario
Land, and your top scoring
relation is publisher,
you can figure out
that using knowledge graph
triples, the tail entity
he has to be Nintendo.
And therefore, this
gives you a strong signal
that the next word
will be Nintendo.
So the goal is you're going
to find the top scoring
parent entity and the
top scoring relation
using the nodes in your
local knowledge graph.
And you can do this by using
the LSTM hidden state combined
with pretrained entity
and relation embeddings.
So I do admit I cheated
here a little bit,
and that this does use
pretrained embeddings.
But hopefully, you'll see by
the end of this discussion
why I think it fits a bit better
in this external memory use
case as well.
So what I'm going
to do here is take
a softmax using LSTM hidden
state and the entity embeddings
for each of the potential
parent entities.
And they will take the top
scoring one as a parent entity.
And they'll do the same thing
for the relation embeddings.
The next entity is then
just this tail entity
from the knowledge graph triple.
So it's relatively
trivial to figure out
what the next entity
should be once you've
figured out the top
scoring parent entity
and your top scoring relation.
And then finally, to
predict the next word,
they take the
vocabulary, and they
expand it to include
different aliases that
could refer to that entity.
So what I mean by
aliases here are
phrases that could refer
to the entity and text.
So you might not just
call it Nintendo.
You might also say
Nintendo company or Koppai.
And you want any of these
to be possible words they
could predict as the next word.
So the goal of this
vocabulary expansion
is to increase the probability
that the next where you predict
will actually be related
to this next entity
So a new entity case
is a bit simpler.
This means that the entity
that you're predicting
is not in the local
knowledge graph.
So you're not getting any signal
from this local knowledge graph
that you've been building
up, and all you want to do
is find the top scoring entity
in the full knowledge graph.
And you can do this using
the LSTM hidden state
and pretrained
entity embeddings,
similar to how we found the
score for the top parent
entity.
Your next entity will just
be the top scoring entity out
of the full knowledge graph.
And then your next
word is once again
this vocabulary expanded to
include aliases of that entity.
The not an entity
case is as simple
as you just revert
to normal LSTM.
You don't have a next
entity to predict.
And your next word is just
the most likely next token
of your normal vocabulary.
So here's a diagram
from their paper
that hopefully summarizes and
makes even clear what I just
went over.
So they have a longer
example than the one
we are looking at but
the same prediction
as Nintendo is the next word.
And they have their
predictions in red.
So this is what they
want KGLM to predict.
The three different cases
are in the horizontals.
And we see that here, you're
in the related entity case
since Nintendo is in your
local knowledge graph.
So they want KGLM to
predict that Nintendo should
be a related entity
type of word,
that Super Mario Land
should be its parent
entity, that publisher should
be the relevant relation.
And as a result, the
next entity is Nintendo.
And then they expand
their vocabulary.
You see the aliases of
Nintendo at the bottom.
And then finally,
they actually predict
Nintendo is the next word.
And the other cases
just summarize
what we also already went over.
So you find that KGLM actually
outperforms GPT-2 and AWD-LSTM,
which is a strong LSTM language
model on a fast completion
task similar to the fill
in the blank examples
that we looked at the
beginning of the talk.
They also find qualitatively
that compared to GPT-2,
KGLM tends to predict more
specific tokens since it
can predict these
tokens from just copying
from the local knowledge
graph, whereas GPT-2 will tend
to predict more generic tokens.
So if you want to predict
the birthplace of someone,
GPT-2 is more likely to
predict New York, for example,
and KGLM might predict
some obscure place.
And then they have
these really cool set
of experiments where they showed
that KGLM actually supports
modifying or updating facts.
So they made a direct change
in the knowledge graph,
and then they saw what is the
change in KGLM's predictions.
So they have this example
where the sequence was,
Barack Obama was born on blank.
They had their knowledge
graph triple as Barack Obama's
original birth date, and then
the most likely next tokens,
whereas expected,
August 4th 1961.
And then they just changed
their knowledge graph.
So they changed the
birthday of Obama.
They said, OK,
he's now born 2013.
And they looked to see what the
next predictions were for KGLM,
and it changed its
predictions to match what was
in the local knowledge graph.
So this is something
that's pretty cool,
and that really only external
memory approaches can
do compared to the original
pretrained entity embedding
approaches we talked about.
And I think it's
one of the reasons
that KGLM, at least my
opinion, fits better
in these external
memory use cases.
Right.
So the next slide
is a different paper
so I guess I'll take questions
about KGLM, if there are any.
It's a pretty complex method.
So feel free to have questions.
Yeah.
Can you, one more
time, explain what
the definition of the
local knowledge graph
is in relationship to the
global knowledge graph?
Yep.
So local knowledge
graph is supposed
to be a subset of the
full knowledge graph.
And it's only
supposed to consist
of entities that
have actually been
seen in the sequence as well
as their relevant entities.
OK.
All right.
So here, you see
that Super Mario Land
is in the local knowledge
graph because Super Mario
Land is an entity that
is seen in the sequence.
And then you also want to
copy over all the edges
from Super Mario Land that would
be in the full knowledge graph.
So this is just a subset of them
for the purpose of the example.
But you see that
Super Mario Land
has an edge to Nintendo to
Game Boy to platform game.
And so you would copy all
edges that Super Mario
Land has to another node in
the full knowledge graph.
And they know in advance like,
they have the labels here
for what the entities
are during training.
So that's how they can actually
create this ground truth
knowledge graph.
Then briefly, a student
asked why we can't just
use the whole knowledge graph?
And I gave an answer but
maybe you know better.
Yeah, I think the
idea is the signal
be much stronger if you just
use local knowledge graph.
So in the softmax for
the related entity case,
you would just be predicting
over the potential parent
entities in your local
knowledge graph, which
is a much smaller set than
what's in your full knowledge
graph.
So I guess it's more
likely that you're
going to predict
something that is
correct in that case than
when you have 5 million
or so entities in your
full knowledge graph.
It's also much
cheaper to compute.
In this case, there's only
a single parent entity,
but you could have
multiple parent entities
that you're trying to compute
which ones the most likely
over.
Is that what you were
also thinking, John?
Yeah.
I mainly just said
the efficiency.
So the signal thing is cool too.
Here's an exciting question.
What about queries that
require more than one step
in the knowledge graph such as
the location of the publisher
of Super Mario Land?
Yeah.
That's a good question.
So the idea is it can
support those types?
Like, does it support
multi-hop, kind of,
building of the knowledge graph?
Yeah.
How does KGLM perform
in those cases?
Yeah.
I don't know.
That's a very good question.
They built up the
knowledge graph
so that is just a single
hop as far as I know.
But if you saw the
other entities, if you
were to see the
entities along the hops,
that it would have them in the
local knowledge graph, yeah,
that's a good question.
I don't if they support that.
Great.
OK.
Let's move along then.
So the next piece of
we're going to talk about,
you guys, have actually briefly
seen in the language generation
lecture.
But I'm going to go over
it again quickly here.
So unlike the other works
that we talked about that use
knowledge graph triples,
this is actually
going to take a looser notion of
knowledge in that the knowledge
will just be encoded in the
text in the training data set.
So this is called kNN-LM.
And the idea is that--
or it's brilliant idea
is language models
not only learn to predict
the next word in text,
but they also learn these
representations of text.
And the author suggests that
it might actually be easier
to learn similarities
between text sequences
than it is to predict the
next word in the text.
So you have this example that
Dickens is the author of blank,
and Dickens wrote blank.
And they argue that it's
easier to tell for a human
but also for a model that
these sequences are similar,
and they should probably
have the same next word
even if you don't know
what the next word is.
So that's suggesting
that it's easier
to learn these similarities
than it is to actually predict
the next word.
And they argue that this is
even more true for long tail
patterns, where it's very
challenging for the model
to predict that the next word
is some rarely seen token
or rare entity, than it is to
find another similar sequence
that it's already seen and
just copy the next word
from that sequence.
So what they proposed to do
is store all representations
of text sequences in the
nearest neighbor datastore.
And then an inference,
what you want to do
is you find the k most
similar sequences of text,
you then retrieve their
corresponding values,
so you just peek
at the sequences
and see what were
their next words.
And then you combine
the probability
from this nearest neighbor
datastore with just
a typical language
model prediction.
And so they call this
an interpolation step
in that they're weighting
how much to pay attention
to the probability
from this kNN approach
and how much to pay attention
to this language model approach.
And the lambda here is just
a hyperparameter they tune.
So I have this diagram
from their paper
where they want to predict
the next word in the sequence,
Shakespeare's play blank.
So what they do is they have
all the training context already
encoded in their datastore.
So they have representations
of all of the training context.
And then they compute
the representation
of the text context.
And they want to figure
out which representations
in the training context are most
similar to this task context
representation.
And so here, an external
memory view of things, the keys
would be the representations
of the training context,
and the values would
be the next words.
So to get the k nearest
training representations,
they then copy
over their values.
That's what you see with
this Macbeth, Hamlet, Macbeth
example.
They have a normalization
step where they convert this
to probability space.
And then finally, they
have an aggregation step.
So if a word is seen as
the next word in several
of these k nearest
neighbors, then they
want to count more for that.
So that's why they aggregate.
So if they see Macbeth twice,
it means Macbeth is more likely.
And then finally, they have
this interpolation step
where they try to balance
between the classification
probabilities from
the language model
and from the kNN-LM approach.
So some immediate observation
you might have is this
seems really expensive.
They do propose ways
to try to minimize
the expense of actually having
to store all the training
contexts in this datastore
because they actually store it
for every single window of next
word in the training context.
And you can do quantization
on some nearest neighbor
approaches to try to
make this less expensive.
But I imagine this would still
be pretty expensive for really
large training data sets.
They also have some
cool experiments
that show that this is very
good for domain adaptation.
So if you take your
language model,
and you have a new domain that
you want a higher language
model too, you could just create
a nearest neighbor datastore
of your new domain.
So you encode all
the representations
of that new domain.
You stick it in a datastore.
And then, you can just
use your language model
with these kNN probabilities
as well just immediately
on this new domain
without actually
having to further train
your language model.
So I thought that
was a pretty cool use
case of this external
memory approach.
So while it doesn't leverage
knowledge bases directly,
it does have this
loose knowledge of--
or a loose idea of
encoding knowledge
that is in a textual
representation
form into some external
memory that the model can then
take advantage of.
That's all I have
for this approach.
Are there any questions
on this approach?
Well, suddenly, one
person is asking,
how does the kNN make
predictions for the next word?
The k neighbors
are for the context
instead of the next word.
Oh, OK.
That wasn't clear.
So the keys are the
representations of the context.
The values in your external
memory are the next words.
So when you figure out,
you figure out your nearest
neighbors using your
keys, and then you
copy over their values.
So it does actually know what
the next words are for each
of those representations.
Yeah OK so finally, we're going
to talk about how you can just
modify the training
data to better encode
knowledge in language models.
So the approaches we've
talked about so far
are actually incorporating
knowledge explicitly
by using the
pretrained embeddings
or an external memory.
We also want to talk
about how can you just
incorporate knowledge implicitly
through the unstructured text?
So what we're going to do
is either mask or corrupt
the data to introduce
additional training tasks that
require factual knowledge
to figure out what
data was masked, for instance.
So this has some
clear advantages.
It doesn't have any additional
memory or computation
requirements, you
don't have a datastore
to deal with, you don't
have extra knowledge encoded
layers to train.
All you do is modify
the training data.
And you don't have to modify
your architecture either
so you can continue using
your favorite BERT model
and just make these changes
to the training data.
So the first work
we're going to look at
is called WKLM,
Weakly Supervised
Knowledge-Pretraining Language
Model, or Pretrained Language
Model.
And the key idea here
is to train the model
to distinguish between
true and false knowledge.
So they're going to corrupt
the data by replacing mentions
in the text with
mentions that refer
to different entities
of the same type
to create what they refer to as
negative knowledge statements.
And then the model
will just predict
has the entity been
replaced or corrupted.
This type constraint is
necessary to make sure that--
or to encourage the model to
actually use factual knowledge
to figure out that this
corruption is taking place.
So you can imagine
if you replace it
with something that's
not realistic at all,
the model could just be basing
its prediction based on,
is this sentence
linguistically correct?
So as an example, we have
a true knowledge statement
as JK Rowling is the
author of Harry Potter.
And then we want to
modify this to replace it
with another author.
So let's say we change
this to J.R.R. Tolkien
is the author of Harry Potter.
So you can see
that this requires
some amount of knowledge,
background knowledge,
to actually be able to figure
out which statement is true
and which statement is false.
And the idea is
that the model will
be able to predict for
each of these mentions
whether it's a true
or false mention.
So this diagram here
is from the paper.
And hopefully, it explains
this a bit better.
They have the original
article on the left.
And then they have
the replaced article
with the corruptions
on the right,
and the entities are in blue.
So what they do is
for a given entity,
they first look up its type.
They find other
entities of that type,
and then they randomly
sample the entity
and get an alias of it
to replace in the text.
So they're going to replace
Stan Lee, for instance,
with Bryan Johnson, and
Marvel Comics with DC Comics.
And the replacements
are in red on the right.
And then the idea
is that the model
will be able to predict
for each of these mentions,
was it replaced or not.
So in the case of
Bryan Johnson, they
have the red X for this
is a false mention.
And in the case of
the true mention,
they have the checkmark.
So it's a pretty
simple approach.
But they actually
show that it can
help a model increase the
amount of knowledge that's
encoded as parameters.
So WKLM uses an entity
replacement loss
to train the model
to distinguish
between these true
and false mentions.
And this just looks like a
binary classification loss
where your true mentions
are on the left,
and your false mentions
are on the right.
And you want to
increase the probability
that this P of e given C, so
the probability of entity given
the context, you
want to increase
that for the true mentions
and decrease it for the false
mentions.
The total loss is then
just a combination
of the masked language
model loss and this entity
replacement loss.
The masked language loss--
the masked language model loss
is defined at the token level.
And the entity replacement loss
is defined at the entity level,
meaning it's not
just over subwords,
it's even potentially
over words,
if you have multi-word
entities, phrases, for instance.
And this is an important
point, or an important theme,
that we really see occurring
throughout these works
that we look at
in that modifying
the data at the
entity level seems
to be an important component
of actually increasing
the amount of knowledge that
a language model can encode.
So they find that WKLM
improves over BERT and GPT-2,
in fact, completion
tasks like the fill
in the blank statements that
we looked at the beginning.
They also find that it
improves over the ERNIE paper
that we talked about
on a downstream task.
And then they had a set
of ablation experiments
where they looked at,
can you just remove
this masked language
model off now.
And if you just train
BERT for longer,
do you really need this
entity replacement loss?
So that's what the table
here is looking at.
The second row is looking at if
we remove the masked language
model loss, what happens?
We see that it
performs much worse
without the masked
language model loss.
So you really need both losses.
The intuition there was
the masked language model
loss helps to encode just
general language understanding.
And then training
BERT for longer
performs much worse than using
its entity replacement loss.
So that motivates even further
that you really do need--
or the entity replacement
loss is actually
really helping encode more
knowledge in these language
models.
So in addition to
corrupting the data,
we're also going
to look at, can we
just mask the data differently?
Can we be more clever about
how we do the masking?
And this is a thread in
several recent works.
So there's actually
another paper called ERNIE.
So this is different than the
one I talked about before.
And this is an
Enhanced Representation
through Knowledge Integration.
And what they do is
show improvements
on downstream Chinese
NLP tasks by doing
phrase-level and
entity-level masking.
So instead of just
masking out subwords,
they're going to
mask out phrases
that have multiple words.
And entities-- the full phrase
of an entity which corresponds
to--
entity and text that
they might find that
are like NER
techniques, for example.
And then the second
work is actually
something you heard about
in the last lecture, which
is the idea of using
salient span masking
to mask out salient spans.
And a salient span is just
a named entity or a date.
So you can see this is pretty
similar to what ERNIE is doing.
And they found that using
salient span masking actually
significantly helped
T5 performance
on these closed domain
question and answering tasks.
So just to make sure
we're all on the same page
with the different
masking techniques,
this diagram from
the ERNIE paper
is comparing to what BERT
does versus what ERNIE does.
The top shows that ERNIE
masked up the subword tokens,
or that BERT masked up the
subword tokens, whereas ERNIE
masked up phrases like a
series of, as well as entities
like JK Rowling.
There's some interesting results
on showing that salient span
masking is helping
encode more knowledge
in these representations.
So on the left, we're
looking at the results
of the original paper that
proposed salient span masking.
So this is the REALM work.
And the idea here was that
they were training a knowledge
retriever.
So it's actually more
of an external memory
class of techniques,
but they find
that by using the salient
span masking technique,
they could actually train a
much better knowledge retriever.
So that's a good example
of how these techniques are
really complementary.
So while I presented three
classes of techniques,
you can definitely get benefits
by doing multiple techniques
together.
And they found that doing
salient span masking compared
to using masking
from BERT, which
would be the random
uniform masks,
or doing random masking spans
from a paper called SpanBERT,
it performs much better to
do salient span masking.
So you see a 38 exact match
score versus a 32 exact match
score, for instance.
And on the right,
we have results
from fine-tuning T5
with either salient span
masking or the span
corruption task
that you saw on assignment 5.
And you can see that on
these different QA data sets,
salient span masking does
significantly better than just
using the span
corruption technique.
So this really suggests that
doing the salient span masking
and masking out these salient
spans of these entities
is, in fact, helping to
encode more knowledge
in these language models.
So to recap, we talked about
three different classes
of techniques to add
knowledge of language models.
We talked about using
pretrained entity embeddings.
These weren't too difficult to
apply to existing architectures
and is a way to leverage this
knowledge graph pretraining.
But it's a rather indirect way
of incorporating knowledge,
and it could be
hard to interpret.
We also talked about approaches
to add an external memory.
This could support modifying
the knowledge base.
It was also easier to interpret.
But they tended to be more
complex in implementation
like we saw in KGLM.
And they also
required more memory
like we saw at the
kNN-LM approach.
And then, finally, we talked
about modifying the training
data.
So this requires
no model changes
or additional computation.
It also might be the easiest
to theoretically analyze.
So this is actually an active
area of research right now.
But it's still an open question
if modifying the training data
is always as effective
as model changes
and what the trade-offs are in
terms amount of data required
versus doing one of these
other knowledge enhancement
approaches.
So that leads us to section 3.
So I guess I'll pause
again for questions.
[INAUDIBLE] may be good.
Awesome.
OK.
So section 3 is about how
researchers are actually
going about evaluating the
knowledge in language models
and, I guess, how
some of the techniques
we actually just talked about
stand up in this evaluation.
So first, we're going
to talk about probes
which don't require any
fine-tuning of the language
model.
And then we're going to talk
about downstream tasks which
look at how well do these
pretrained representations
actually transfer their
knowledge to other tasks.
So one of the initial works
in this area was called LAMA.
And this really started
a series of works
to look into how much
knowledge is already encoded
in these language models.
So their question was how
much relational common sense
and factual knowledge is in
off-the-shelf language models?
So this is just taking
pretrained language models
and evaluating the
knowledge in them.
And this is without
any additional training
or fine-tuning.
So they mainly constructed
a set of what they
refer to as closed statements.
And these are just the fill
in the blank statements
that we actually drew from
at the beginning of the talk.
And we have some
more examples here.
And they manually
created these templates
of closed statements using
knowledge graph triples
and question-answer pairs
from existing data sets.
They wanted to compare
pretrained language models
to supervised relation
extraction and question
and answering systems to see how
do these language models that
were trained in an
unsupervised fashion
compare to these baseline
systems that are not
only supervised
but really targeted
for this task of
knowledge extraction
And their goal was to evaluate
the knowledge in existing
pretrained language models.
And a key point about
this is they're just
using the language
models as they
are available to researchers.
So this means there could be
differences in the pretraining
corpora, for example.
So when you look at
the following table,
and you're comparing
language models,
also keep in mind
that these don't
account for the differences
in the pretrained corpora.
So a lot of these
language models
probably look familiar to you
either from previous lectures
or maybe your final projects.
And what we see is
that overall, BERT-base
and BERT-Large pretrained
models are performing
much better than the previous
language or the other language
models here.
I guess I forgot to mention
what mean precision at one is.
This a pretty simple metric.
The idea is if you
look at the blank,
and you look at the
top predictions,
or the top prediction, for the
blank, is it correct or not.
That's what precision
at one means.
Precision at 10 would be, let's
look at the top 10 predictions,
is the correct
prediction in the top 10?
So in addition to
BERT-Large and BERT-base
performing well overall, we do
see that in the T-REx data set,
their relation extraction
baseline is performing
a bit better than BERT.
One thing they notice here
that's pretty interesting
is that this data set has
a lot of different types
of relations.
And relations can be
classified in terms of,
are they one-to-one relation,
are they n-to-one relation,
are they n-to-n relation?
An example of a
one-to-one relation
would be your
student ID relation.
So you have a unique student ID.
An example of an n-to-n would
be the enrolled in relation.
So there's lots of students
enrolled in lots of classes.
So this would be
an n-to-n relation.
And they find that
BERT really struggles
on these n-to-n relations.
So while it performs better than
relation extraction baseline
on some types of
relations, overall, it
does pretty terribly on
these n-to-n relations.
So overall, it does a bit
worse than the baseline
on this T-REx data set.
They also compared
to SQuAD on DrQA.
And they find that it
does a fair amount worse.
They note that the language
model is not fine-tuned here.
And also, it has no access to
an information retrieval system.
And then when they look
at the precision at 10,
they find that this gap between
DrQA's performance and BERT
actually closes
quite a bit, which
suggests that these
language models do have
some amount of knowledge
encoded in them
and that they're
even competitive
with these knowledge extraction
supervised baselines.
So you can also try out
examples on their GitHub repo
for the LAMA probe.
We have an example that was
from their repo that was,
the cat is on the mask.
You can see what the top
10 predictions are to fill
in the closed statement.
Here, they have the
cat is on the phone.
So this can be a fun
way to figure out
what factual and
common sense knowledge
is in existing language models.
And it's pretty easy to use
with this interactive prompt.
So some limitations
of the LAMA probe
are that it can be
hard to understand
why the models performed
well when they do.
So for instance, BERT might
just be the most popular token,
and this happens to be right.
Maybe it's just memorizing
co-occurrence patterns
and doesn't really understand
the knowledge statement
and doesn't understand
what the fact is.
It might also just
be identifying
similarities between
surface forms of the subject
and object.
So for instance,
in this example,
Pope Clement VII has
a position of blank.
Even if you don't know anything
about Pope Clement VII,
you might be able to
figure out that Pope
is the likely next word for this
triple, or for this template.
So the problem with this
is if the model is just
making these predictions
based on these surface
forms or co-occurrence
patterns, it's
difficult to know if
we're actually evaluating
the knowledge in the model.
Maybe it's just making correct
predictions for other reasons.
And the more subtle issue
that we've brought up
is that language
models might be just
be sensitive to the
phrasing of the statement.
So for each triple in their
data set, or for each relation
their data set, they just had
one mainly defined template.
And qualitatively, they
found that if they just
make small changes
to this template,
it could actually change whether
or not the model could recall
the correct prediction or not.
And so this means
that the probe results
are really a lower bound
on the knowledge that's
encoded in the language model.
So if you change
your phrasing, it's
possible that the model
might show that actually, it
does have the knowledge
encoded in it.
So the next lines of
work we'll talk about
are really building on
these two limitations
of this original LAMA probe.
So the first one is called
LAMA-UHN, or LAMA-Unhelpful
Names.
And the key idea is to
remove these examples
from LAMA that can be answered
without the relational
knowledge.
So this is just addressing
the first limitation
on the left side.
So they observed that BERT
relies on the surface forms
entities, might not
be using knowledge
to make these predictions.
This includes a
string match situation
that we talked
about with the pope.
This also is dealing with the
revealing person name issue
that you saw on assignment 5.
So this is where
the name could be
an incorrect prior
for the native
language of someone, their place
of birth, their nationality.
They have this example
from the table,
or from the paper, where they
looked at different people
names or person's
names, and then they
looked at BERT's prediction
for their native language.
And these are all
French-speaking actors.
And BERT just predicts very
biased and stereotypical
languages for these
particular names.
So this can really
work both ways.
It can lead BERT to make
incorrect predictions sometimes
or in some cases.
But it could also work
to make-- or to let
BERT make correct
predictions, even
if it has no factual
knowledge of those people.
So that's the issue they're
trying to get at here
is do we know that BERT
actually knows this fact,
or is it just using some
bias to make its prediction?
So what they do
is they introduce
a couple of heuristics to
basically just filter out
these examples from the
LAMA probe that can either
be solved by the
string match setting
or this revealing
person name setting.
So they make a harder subset
of the data set, essentially.
They find that when they test
BERT on this harder subset,
that its performance
drops about 8%.
But when they test
their knowledge
on the enhanced model,
which they call E-BERT,
the score only drops about 1%.
So it's possible that as you
make harder knowledge probes,
we'll actually see even bigger
differences in the performance
of knowledge-enhanced models to
models without these knowledge
enhancements.
The next piece of work
we'll talk about is actually
getting at this issue of
the phrasing of the prompt
might actually trigger
different responses
from the language model.
So the language model
might know the fact,
but it might fail on the
task due to the phrasing.
One reason this might
happen is the pretraining
is on different
contexts and sentence
structures in the query.
So for example, you might have
in your pretraining corpus,
the birthplace of Barack
Obama is Honolulu, Hawaii.
And this might be something you
see in Wikipedia, for instance.
That's a common
training data set.
And then as a
researcher, you write,
Barack Obama was born in blank.
And you can see that
this sentence structures
are pretty different.
So the model might have
seen the first fact.
But the sentence
structure difference
is actually enough to confuse it
so it can't answer this query.
So what they do is they
generate a lot more
of these prompts by mining
templates from Wikipedia.
One of the techniques
actually uses
dependency parsing and also
generating paraphrase prompts
by taking inspiration from the
machine translation literature
and using back translation.
So you generate a
lot more prompts
to try to query the
language models and figure
out do small variations
in the prompt trigger
the correct prediction
from the language model.
They also experimented
ensembling prompts.
So if we give the model
multiple prompts and then
take some probability averaged
over these different prompts,
can we improve the performance
on the model returning
the correct prediction?
So we give it a higher
chance of seeing a context
that it might have actually
seen during pretraining.
They find that the
performance on LAMA
increases when they either
use a top performing prompt
or when they use this
ensembling approach.
So this suggests that
the original LAMA really
was a lower bound on the
amount of knowledge encoded
in these language models.
And changing the
phrasing can actually
help the model recall
the correct answer.
This table's a bit frightening.
But they find that small
changes in the query
can lead to really large
gains on performance.
So if you just have a query
like x plays in y position,
and then you change that
to x plays that y position,
this can actually lead
to a 23% accuracy gain
on this particular relation
in terms of the model
actually being able to
call the correct answer.
Or even just x was created in y
to x is created in y, 10% gain.
So I think this motivates a need
to not only develop better ways
to query these models
but probably also build
language models that
are actually more
robust to the query itself.
So in addition to
probes, another way
to evaluate these
language models
is by looking at how
well they transfer
from the pretrained
representation
to downstream tasks.
And so the idea here
is you're actually
going to fine-tune the
pretrained representation
on different downstream tasks
similar to how you would
evaluate BERT on GLUE tasks.
So common tasks that
are used for this
are relation extraction,
entity typing,
and question and answering.
Relation extraction
is where you want
to predict the relation
between two entities.
So this is getting back at
one of the questions earlier
in the talk in
terms of, well, how
do you get the relation that's
in the edges in these knowledge
bases.
So
Given two entities,
you learn a model
to predict what is the
relation between then.
Entity typing is
the task of given
an entity, what is the
type of the entity.
So here, Alice robbed the bank.
You want to predict
here as a criminal.
And then, you guys, are
very familiar with question
and answering.
So the idea of these
common-- of these tasks,
is that they're knowledge
intensive so they're
good candidates
to see how do all
of these pretrained
representations
actually transfer the knowledge
to these downstream tasks.
Here we look at the performance
on a relation extraction
benchmark called TACRED.
And all the models that we
show here were at one point,
state-of-the-art on TACRED.
So this C-GCN is a graph
convolutional neural network
over dependency trees.
The BERT-LSTM-base is ONE of
the first works that showed that
you could actually get
state-of-the-art performance
with BERT on
relation extraction.
And this is just putting LSTM
layer over BERT's output.
ERNIE is the work
that we talked about
with the pretrained
entity embeddings.
Matching the Blanks,
we didn't get to today.
But it's a really
interesting work
about learning meaningful
relational representations.
And it falls more into the
training data modification
approaches and that
they are actually
masking out entities again.
And then KnowBERT is
what we talked about.
The W and W here means they
actually encode two knowledge
bases in KnowBERT.
So they're encoding BERT
Net, and they're also
encoding Wikipedia.
And the high level takeaway from
this table is that you can see
that the recent knowledge
enhanced models have achieved
state-of-the-art over the
original models that once
performed very well on TACRED.
And we have about
five F1 gains here.
Another interesting
takeaway from this table
is there seems to be a trade-off
in the size of the language
model that's necessary to
get a certain performance.
So if you just consider the
size of the language model,
then KnowBERT performs the best.
But if you don't
consider that, then it
ties with Matching the Blanks.
So overall, this is
pretty good evidence
that these knowledge-enhanced
methods are, in fact,
transferring to these
knowledge-intensive downstream
tasks that can
really take advantage
of these pretrained
representations.
We also have results
on entity typing.
So here we're comparing
a slightly different set
of models.
Some of the baselines
are LSTM models
that were designed
for entity typing.
And we have ERNIE and
KnowBERT leading the, I guess,
leaderboard here on the entity
typing task of open entity.
And we see gains of about 15 F1
points with ERNIE and KnowBERT.
So once again, we
really do see that
these knowledge-rich
pretrained representations are
transferring and helping on
these knowledge-intensive
downstream tasks.
So just to recap, we
talked about probes
which evaluate the knowledge
already present in models.
These don't require
any more training.
But it can be challenging
to construct benchmarks
to actually make
sure you're testing
the knowledge in
these language models.
It can also be
challenging to construct
the queries using the probe.
We then talked about
downstream tasks.
These are a bit of an indirect
way to evaluate knowledge
and that they have this extra
component of fine-tuning.
But it's a good
way to evaluate how
useful is this knowledge-rich
pretrained representation
in actual applications.
So I just touched on the
exciting work in this area,
but there's many
other directions
if you want to dive
more into this.
So there's retrieval-augmented
language models
which learn knowledge
retrievers to figure out
what documents might be relevant
for predicting the next word.
There's work in modifying the
knowledge in language models.
So I talked about
how this is one
of the obstacles and
challenges to using language
models as knowledge bases.
So there's been recent
work in this area.
We also saw how important the
knowledge pretraining task was.
Although there's
many papers that
are proposing different tasks
to do the knowledge pretraining,
so it's still an open
question in terms
of what tasks are best to
add to encode more knowledge.
There's also been work on more
efficient knowledge systems,
so at NeuIPRS
efficient QA challenge
which aims at building
the smallest QA system.
And then finally,
there's been work
on building better
knowledge benchmarks that
build on the benchmarks
that we saw today.
So that's all I have for today.
And I hope your final
projects are going well.