Welcome to CS224N, lecture 17,
Model Analysis and Explanation.
OK, look at us.
We're here.
Let's start with some
course logistics.
We have updated the policy on
the guest lecture reactions.
They're all due Friday,
all at 11:59 PM.
You can't use late days for
this, so please get them in.
Watch the lectures.
They're awesome lectures.
They're awesome guests,
and you get something
like half a point
for each of them.
And yeah, all three can be
submitted up through Friday.
OK, so final projects, remember
that the due date is Tuesday.
It's Tuesday at
4:30 PM, March 16th.
And let me emphasize that
there's a hard deadline
on the three days from then.
Friday, we won't be accepting
for additional points
off assignments--
sorry, final projects that
are submitted after the 4:30
deadline on Friday.
We need to get these
graded and get grades in.
So whew, it's the
end stretch, week 9.
Week 10 is really the
lectures are us giving
you help on the final projects.
So this is really the
last week of lectures.
Thanks for all your
hard work and for asking
awesome questions in lecture,
and in office hours and on Ed.
And let's get right into it.
So today, we get to talk about
one of my favorite subjects
in natural language processing.
It's model analysis
and explanation.
So first, we're going to
do what I love doing, which
is motivating why we want to
talk about the topic at all.
We'll talk about how we can look
at a model at different levels
of abstraction to perform
different kinds of analysis
on it.
We'll talk about out of
domain evaluation sets.
So this will feel familiar
to the RobustQA folks.
Then we'll talk about sort
of trying to figure out,
for a given example, why did it
make the decision that it made?
It had some input, it
produced some output.
Can we come up with some sort
of interpretable explanation
for it?
And then we'll look at,
actually, the representations
of the models.
So these are the sort of
hidden states, the vectors that
are being built throughout
the processing of the model,
try to figure out if
we can understand some
of the representations
and mechanisms
that the model is performing.
And then we'll actually
come back to sort
of one of the kind
of default states
that we've been in
this course, which
is trying to look at
model improvements,
removing things from models,
seeing how it performs,
and relate that to the
analysis that we're
doing in this lecture, show how
it's not all that different.
OK, so if you haven't seen
this xkcd, now you have.
And it's one of my favorites.
I'm going to say all the words.
So person A says, this is
your machine learning system?
Person B says, yep,
you pour the data
into this big pile
of linear algebra
and then collect the
answers on the other side.
Person A, what if the
answers are wrong?
Then person B,
just stir the pile
until they start looking right.
And I feel like at its
worst, deep learning can feel
like this from time to time.
You have a model.
Maybe it works for
some things, maybe
it doesn't work
for other things.
You're not sure why it
works for some things
and doesn't work for others.
And the changes that
we make to our models,
they're based on intuition, but
frequently-- what are the TAs
told?
Everyone in office
hours, sometimes you just
have to try it and see
if it's going to work out
because it's very hard to tell.
It's very, very difficult
to understand our models
on sort of any level.
And so today we'll
go through a number
of ways we're trying
to sort of carve out
little bits of understanding
here and there.
So beyond it being important
because it's an xkcd comic,
why should we care about
understanding our models?
One, is that we want to know
what our models are doing.
So here you have a black box.
Black box functions
are sort of this idea
that you can't look
into them and interpret
what they're doing.
You have an input sentence,
say, and then some output
prediction.
Maybe this black box is actually
your final project model,
and it gets some accuracy.
Now, we summarize our models.
And in your final projects
you'll summarize your model
with sort of one or a handful
of summary metrics of accuracy,
or F1 score, or BLEU
score or something,
but it's a lot of model
to explain with just
a small number of metrics.
So what do they learn?
Why do they succeed?
And why do they fail?
What's another motivation?
So we want to sort of know
what our models are doing, OK,
but maybe that's
because we want to be
able to make tomorrow's model.
So today, when you're
building models in this class,
at a company, you start out
with some kind of recipe
that is known to work
either at the company
or because you have
experience from this class,
and it's not perfect, right?
It makes mistakes.
You look at the errors.
And then over time, you
take what works, maybe,
and then you find
what needs changing.
So it seems like maybe
adding another layer
to the model helped.
And maybe that's a nice tweak
and the model performance
gets better, et cetera.
And incremental progress
doesn't always feel exciting,
but I want to pitch to
you that it's actually
very important for
us to understand
how much incremental progress
can kind of get us towards some
of our goals so that we can have
a better job of evaluating when
we need when we need big leaps,
when we need major changes,
because there are problems
that we're attacking
with our incremental
sort of progress
and we're not getting very far.
OK, so we want to
make tomorrow's model.
Another thing that's, I think,
very related to and sort
of both a part of and bigger
than this field of analysis
is model biases.
So let's say you take your
Word2vec analogies solver
from GloVe or Word2vec
that is from assignment 1,
and you give it the analogy,
man is to computer programmer
as woman is to, and it gives
you the output, homemaker--
this is a real example
from the paper below--
you should be like, wow.
Well, I'm glad I know that now.
And of course, you saw the
lecture from Yulia Tsvetkov
last week.
You say, wow, I'm
glad I know that now,
and that's a huge problem.
What did the model
use in its decision?
What biases is it
learning from data
and possibly making even worse?
So that's the kind of
thing that you can also
do with model analysis, beyond
just making models better
according to some sort of
summary metric as well.
And then another
thing, we don't just
want to make tomorrow's model.
And this is something that
I think is super important.
We don't just want to
look at that time scale.
We want to say, what about
10, 15, 25 years from now?
What kinds of things
will we be doing?
What are the limits?
What can be learned by
language model pretraining?
What's the model that will
replace the transformer?
What's the model that
will replace that model?
What does deep learning
struggle to do?
What are we sort of attacking
over and over again and failing
to make significant progress on?
What do neural models tell us
about language, potentially?
There's some people
who are primarily
interested in understanding
language better using
neural networks.
Cool.
How are our models
affecting people,
transferring power
between groups of people,
governments, et cetera?
That's an excellent
type of analysis.
What can't be learned via
language model pretraining?
So that's sort of the
complementary question there.
If you sort of come
to the edge of what
you can learn via language
model pretraining,
is there stuff that we need
total paradigm shifts in order
to do well?
So all of this falls
under some category
of trying to really
deeply understand
our models and
their capabilities.
And there's a lot
of different methods
here that we'll go over today.
And one thing that I want
you to take away from it
is that they're all
going to tell us
some aspect of the model,
elucidate some kind
of intuition or something.
But none of them are
we going to say, aha,
I really understand 100% about
what this model is doing now.
So they're going to
provide some clarity,
but never total clarity.
And one way, if you're
trying to decide
how you want to understand
your model more,
the thing you should sort of
start out by thinking about
is, at what level
of abstraction do I
want to be looking at my model?
So the sort of very
high level abstraction--
let's say you've trained
a QA model to estimate
the probabilities of
start and end indices
in a reading
comprehension problem,
or you've trained
a language model
that assigns probabilities
to words in context.
You can just look at the
model as that object.
So it's just a
probability distribution
defined by your model.
You are not looking
into it any further
than the fact that you can
sort of give it inputs and see
what outputs it provides.
So that's not even--
who even cares if
it's a neural network.
It could be anything, but it's a
way to understand its behavior.
Another level of abstraction
that you can look at,
you can dig a little
deeper, you can say,
well, I know that my
network is a bunch
of layers that are kind of
stacked on top of each other.
You've got sort of maybe
your transformer encoder
with one layer, two
layer, three layer.
You can try to see what
it's doing as it goes deeper
in the layers.
So maybe your neural model is
the sequence of these vector
representations.
A third option of
sort of specificity
is to look at as much
detail as you can.
You've got these
parameters in there,
you've got the connections
in the computation graph.
So now you're sort of trying to
remove all of the abstraction
that you can and look at as
many details as possible.
And all three of these sort of
ways of looking at your model
and performing analysis
are going to be useful
and will actually sort of
travel slowly from 1 to 2 to 3
as we go through this lecture.
OK, so we haven't actually
talked about any analyses yet,
so we're going to get
started on that now.
And we're starting with
the sort of testing
our model's behaviors.
So would we want to see,
will my model perform well?
I mean, the natural
thing to ask is,
how does it behave on some
sort of test set, right?
And so we don't really
care about mechanisms
yet, why is it performing
this, by what method
is it making its decision.
Instead, we're just
interested in sort
of the more higher
level of abstraction
of, does it perform the
way I want it to perform?
So let's take our model
evaluation that we are already
doing and sort of recast it
in the framework of analysis.
So you've trained your
model on some samples
from some distribution.
So you've got input/output
pairs of some kind.
So how does the model
behave on samples
from the same distribution?
It's a simple question
and it's sort of known
as in-domain
accuracy, or you can
say that the samples are IID and
that's what you're testing on.
And this is just what we've
been doing this whole time.
It's your test set accuracy
or F1 or BLEU score.
And so you've got some
model with some accuracy,
and maybe it's better than some
model with some other accuracy
on this test set, r ight?
So this is what
you're doing is you're
iterating on your models and
your final project as well.
You say, well, on
my test set, which
is what I've decided
to care about for now,
model A does better.
They both seem pretty good.
And so maybe I'll choose
model A to keep working on.
Maybe I'll choose it if
you were putting something
into production.
But remember back to
this idea that it's
just one number to summarize
a very complex system.
It's not going to be
sufficient to tell you
how it's going to perform in
a wide variety of settings.
OK, so we've been doing this.
This is model evaluation
as model analysis.
Now we are going to
say, what if we are not
testing on exactly the same
type of data that we trained on?
So now we're asking, did the
model learn something such
that it's able to
sort of extrapolate
or perform how I
want it to on data
that looks a little
bit different from what
it was trained on?
And we're going to take the
example of natural language
inference.
So to recall the test of
natural language inference,
and this is through the
Multi-NLI data set that we're
just pulling our definition.
You have a premise.
He turned and saw Jon
sleeping in his half-tent
And you have a hypothesis,
he saw Jon was asleep.
And then you give
them both to a model,
and this is the model
that we had before that
had some good accuracy.
And the model is
supposed to tell
whether the hypothesis
is sort of implied
by the premise or contradicting.
So it could be
contradicting, maybe,
if the hypothesis is John
was awake, for example,
or he saw John was awake.
Maybe that'd be contradiction.
Neutral if sort of both could
be true at the same time,
so to speak.
And then entailment,
in this case,
it seems like you're saying
that the premise implies
the hypothesis.
And so you would
say, probably, this
is likely to get
the right answer
since the accuracy
of the model is 95%.
95% of the time, it
gets the right answer.
And we're going to
dig deeper into that.
What if the model
is not doing what
we think we want it to be
doing in order to perform
natural language inference?
So in a data set like
Multi-NLI, the authors
who gathered the data set
will have asked humans
to perform the task
and gotten the accuracy
that the humans achieved.
And models nowadays are
achieving accuracies
that are around where
humans are achieving,
which sounds great at first.
But as we'll see, it's
not the same as actually
performing the task more
broadly in the right way.
So what if the model's not doing
something smart, effectively?
We're going to use
a diagnostic test
set of carefully
constructed examples that
seem like things
the models should
be able to do to test for a
specific skill or capacity.
In this case, we'll use HANS.
So HANS is the Heuristic
Analysis for NLI Systems
data set, and it's
intended to take systems
that do natural
language inference
and test whether they're
using some simple syntactic
heuristics.
What we'll have in
each of these cases,
we'll have some heuristic.
We'll talk through
the definition.
We'll get an example.
So the first thing
is lexical overlap.
So the model might
do this thing where
it assumes that
a premise entails
all hypotheses constructed
from words in the premise.
So in this example,
you have the premise,
the doctor was
paid by the actor.
And then the hypothesis is,
the doctor paid the actor.
And you'll notice that
in bold here, the doctor,
OK, and then paid, and
then the actor, right?
And so if you use
this heuristic,
you will think that "the
doctor was paid by the actor"
implies the doctor
paid the actor.
That does not imply
it, of course.
And so you could
expect the model--
you want the model to
be able to do this.
It's somewhat simple.
But if it's using
this heuristic,
it won't get this example right.
Next is subsequence heuristics.
So here, if the model assumes
that the premise entails
all of its continuous
subsequences,
it will get this
one wrong as well.
So this example is, "the
doctor near the actor danced."
That's the premise.
The hypothesis is,
"the actor danced."
Now, this is a simple
syntactic thing.
The doctor is doing the
dancing near the actor.
It's this prepositional phrase.
And so the model sort
of uses this heuristic,
oh, look, the actor danced.
That's a subsequence,
entailed, awesome.
And it'll get this
one wrong as well.
And here's another one that's
a lot like subsequence.
But so if the model thinks
that the premise entails all
complete subtrees, so this is
sort of fully formed phrases.
So the artist slept here is a
fully formed sort of subtree.
"If the artist slept,
the actor ran."
And then that's the premise.
Does it entail the
hypothesis, the actor slept?
No.
Sorry, the artist slept.
That does not entail it because
this is in that conditional.
OK, now let me pause
here for some questions
before I move on to see
how these models do.
Anyone unclear about how
this sort of evaluation
is being set up?
No?
Cool.
OK, so how do models perform?
That's sort of the
question of the hour.
What we'll do is we'll
look at these results
from the same paper that
released the dataset.
So they took four
strong Multi-NLI models
with the following accuracies.
So the accuracies here
are something between 60
and 80 something, 80%.
BERT over here is
doing the best, OK.
And in-domain, right,
in that first sort
of setting that we
talked about, you
get these reasonable accuracies.
And that is sort of what
we said before about it
like looking pretty good.
And when we evaluate on
HANS, in this setting here,
we have examples
where the heuristics
we talked about actually work.
So if the model's
using the heuristic,
it will get this right.
And it gets very
high accuracies.
And then if we evaluate the
model in the settings where
if it uses the heuristic,
it gets the examples wrong,
maybe BERT's doing
epsilon better than some
of the other stuff here.
But it's a very different story.
OK, and you saw those examples.
They're not complex in our
sort of own idea of complexity.
And so this is why it sort
of feels like a clear failure
of the system.
Now, you can say, though,
that, well, maybe the training
data sort of didn't have any
of those sort of phenomena,
so the model couldn't have
learned not to do that.
And that's sort of a reasonable
argument, except, well,
BERT is pretrained on a
bunch of language text.
So you might hope,
you might expect,
you might hope that
it does better.
OK, so we saw that example
of models performing well
on examples that are like
those that it was trained on,
and then performing
not very well at all
on examples that seem reasonable
but are sort of a little bit
tricky.
Now we're going to take
this idea of having
a test set that we've
carefully crafted
and go in a slightly
different direction.
So we're to have,
what does it mean
to try to understand the
linguistic properties
of our models?
So that syntactic
heuristics question
was one thing for natural
language inference,
but can we sort of test how
the models, whether they
think certain things are sort
of right or wrong as language
models?
And the first way that
we'll do this is we'll
ask, well, how do we
think about what humans
think of as good language?
How do we evaluate their sort
of preferences about language?
And one answer is minimal pairs.
And the idea of
a minimal pair is
that you've got one sentence
that sounds OK to a speaker.
So this sentence is, the chef
who made the pizzas is here.
It's called it's an acceptable
sentence, at least to me.
And then with a small
change, a minimal change,
the sentence is no
longer OK to the speaker.
So the chef who made
the pizzas are here.
And this-- oops.
This should be
present tense verbs.
In English, present tense
verbs agree a number
with their subject when
they are third person.
So chef, pizzas, OK.
And this is sort of a
pretty general thing.
Most people don't like this.
It's a misconjugated verb,
and so the syntax here
looks like you have the
chef who made the pizzas.
And then this arc of
agreement in number
is requiring the word "is"
here to be singular "is"
instead of plural
"are," despite the fact
that there's this
noun, pizzas, which
is plural, closer linearly.
Comes back to
dependency parsing.
We're back, OK?
And what this looks like
in the tree structure,
right, is, well, "chef" and
"is" are attached in the tree.
"Chef" is the subject
of "is," "pizzas"
is down here in
this subtree, and
so that subject-verb
relationship has
this sort of agreement thing.
So this is a pretty sort of
basic and interesting property
of language that also
reflects the syntactic, sort
of hierarchical
structure of language.
So we've been training these
language models sampling
from them, seeing that they
get interesting things.
And they tend to seem to
generate syntactic content.
But does it really
understand or does
it behave as if it understands
this idea of agreement
more broadly?
And does it sort
of get the syntax
right so that it matches
the subjects and the verbs?
But language models
can't tell us exactly
whether they think that a
sentence is good or bad.
They just tell us the
probability of a sentence.
So before, we had
acceptable and unacceptable.
That's what we get from humans.
And the language
model's analog is just,
does it assign
higher probability
to the acceptable sentence
in the minimal pair, right?
So you have the probability
under the model of the chef who
made the pizzas is
here, and then you
have the probability under
the model of the chef who
made the pizzas are here.
And you want this probability
here to be higher.
And if it is, that's
sort of like a simple way
to test whether the model
got it right effectively.
And just like in
HANS, we can develop
a test set with very carefully
chosen properties, right?
So most sentences in English
don't have terribly complex
subject-verb agreement
structure with a lot of words
in the middle, like "pizzas,"
that are going to make it
difficult. So if I
say, the dog runs,
sort of no way to get it
wrong because there's no--
the syntax is very simple.
So we can create or we
can look for sentences
that have these things called
attractors in the sentence.
So "pizzas" is an
attractor because the model
might be attracted
to the plurality here
and get the conjugation wrong.
So this is our question.
Can language models sort of very
generally handle these examples
with attractors?
So we can take examples
with zero attractors,
see whether the model gets the
minimal pairs evaluation right.
We can take examples with
one attractor, to attractors,
you can see how people would
still reasonably understand
these sentences, right?
Chef who made the pizzas and
prepped the ingredients is--
it's still the chef who is,
and then on and on and on.
It gets rarer,
obviously, but you can
have more and more attractors.
And so now we've
created this test set
that's intended to
evaluate this very
specific linguistic phenomenon.
So in this paper here, Kuncoro
et al trained an LSTM language
model on a subset of
Wikipedia back in 2018,
and they evaluate it sort
of in these buckets that
are specified by the paper
that sort of introduce
subject-verb agreement
to the NLP field,
more recently at least.
And they evaluate
it in buckets based
on the number of attractors.
And so in this table here
that you're about to see,
the numbers are
sort of the percent
of times that you
get this-- assign
higher probability to
the correct sentence
in the minimal pair.
So if you were just to do
random or majority class,
you get these errors.
Oh, sorry.
It's the percent of times
that you get it wrong.
Sorry about that.
So lower is better.
And so with no attractors,
you get very low error rates.
So this is 1.3 error rate
with a 350 dimensional LSTM.
And with one attractor,
your error rate is higher.
But actually, humans
start to get errors
with more attractors, too.
So zero attractors is easy.
The larger the LSTM, it looks
like, in general, the better
you're doing, right?
So the smaller model's
doing worse, OK.
And then even on sort
of very difficult
examples with four
attractors, which--
try to think of an
example in your head.
The chef made the pizzas
and took out the trash and--
sort of has to be
this long sentence.
The error rate is
definitely higher,
so it gets more difficult.
But it's still relatively low.
And so even on these
very hard examples,
models are actually performing
subject-verb number agreement
relatively well.
Very cool.
OK, here's some examples
that our model got wrong.
This is actually a worse model
than the ones from the paper
that was just there.
But I think, actually, the
errors are quite interesting.
So here's the sentence.
The ship that the player
drives has a very high speed.
Now, this model thought
that was less probable than,
the ship that the player
drives have a very high speed.
My hypothesis, right, is that
it sort of mis-analyzes drives
as a plural noun, for example.
It's sort of a difficult
construction there.
I think it's pretty interesting.
Likewise, here, this one is fun.
The lead is also rather long.
5 paragraphs is pretty lengthy.
So here, "5 paragraphs" is
a singular noun together
because it's a unit
of length, I guess.
But the model
thought that it was
more likely to say, five
paragraphs are pretty
lengthy, because it's
referring to this sort of five
paragraphs as the five
actual paragraphs themselves,
as opposed to a single unit
of length describing the lead.
Fascinating, OK.
Maybe questions again?
So I guess there are a couple.
Can we do the similar heuristic
analysis for other tasks,
such as Q&A classification?
Yes.
I think that it's easier
to do this kind of analysis
for the HANS style analysis
with question answering
and other sorts of tasks because
you can construct examples that
similarly have these heuristics
and then have the answer depend
on the syntax or not.
The actual probability
of one sentence
is higher than the
other, of course,
is sort of a language
model dependent thing.
But the idea that you can sort
of develop kind of bespoke test
sets for various tasks, I
think, is very, very general
and something I think is
actually quite interesting.
Yes, so I won't go
on further, but I
think the answer's just yes.
So there's another one.
How do you know where to
find these failure cases?
Maybe that's the right time to
advertise linguistics classes.
Sorry.
You're still very
quiet over here.
How do we find what?
How do you know where to
find these failure cases?
Oh, interesting.
Yes.
How do we know where to
find the failure cases?
That's a good question.
I think I agree with Chris,
that actually thinking
about what is interesting
about things in language
is one way to do it.
Kind of the heuristics that
we saw in our language model--
sorry, in our NLI
models with HANS,
you can kind of imagine
that if the model was
sort of ignoring facts
about language and sort
of just doing this sort
of rough bag of words
with some extra magic, then
it would do well about as bad
as it's doing here.
And these sorts of ideas
about understanding
that this statement, if the
artist slept, the actor ran,
does not imply the artist
slept, is the kind of thing
that maybe you'd
think up on your own,
but also you'd spend time
pondering about and thinking
broad thoughts about in
linguistics curricula as well.
So anything else, Chris?
So there's also-- well, I
guess someone is also saying--
I think it's about the sort
of intervening verbs example,
or intervening nouns--
sorry-- example.
But the data set itself
probably includes mistakes
with higher attractors.
Yeah.
Yeah, that's a good point.
Yeah, because humans make more
and more mistakes as the number
of attractors gets larger.
On the other hand, I
think that the mistakes
are fewer in written
text than in spoken.
Maybe I'm just making that up.
That's what I think.
But yeah, it would be
interesting to actually go
through that test set and
see how many of the errors
the really strong model
makes are actually
due to be sort of observed
form being incorrect.
I'd be super curious.
OK, should I move on?
Yeah.
Great.
OK, so what does
it feel like we're
doing when we are
kind of constructing
these sort of bespoke,
small, careful test sets
for various phenomena?
Well, it is sort of
feels like unit testing.
And in fact, this sort of idea
has been brought to the fore,
you might say, in
NLP unit tests,
but for these NLP
neural networks.
In particular, the paper here
that I'm citing at the bottom
suggests this minimum
functionality test.
You want a small test set that
targets a specific behavior.
That should sound like
some of the things
that we've already talked about.
But in this case, we're going
to get even more specific.
So here's a single test case.
We're going to have an
expected label, what
was actually predicted, whether
the model passed this unit
test.
And the labels are going to
be sentiment analysis here.
So negative label,
positive label, or neutral
are the three options.
And the unit test is going to
consist simply of sentences
that follow this template.
I, then a negation, the positive
verb, and then the thing.
So if you negation
positive verb,
it means a negative verb, right?
And so here's an example.
I can't say I
recommend the food.
The expected label is negative.
The answer that the model
provided-- and this is,
I think, a commercial
sentiment analysis system--
so it predicted positive.
And then, I didn't
love the flight.
The expected label was negative,
and then the predicted answer
was neutral.
And this commercial
sentiment analysis system
gets a lot of what
you could imagine
are pretty reasonably
simple examples wrong.
And so what Ribeiro
et al 2020 showed
is that they could actually
provide a system that
sort of had this framework of
building test cases for NLP
models to ML engineers
working on these products
and give them that interface,
and they would actually
find bugs, bugs being
categories of high error,
right, find bugs in their
models that they could then kind
try to go and fix,
and that this was
kind of an efficient
way of trying
to find things that
were simple and still
wrong with what should be pretty
sophisticated neural systems.
So I really like
this, and it's sort
of a nice way of thinking
more specifically about what
are the capabilities in sort
of precise terms of our models.
And all together now,
you've seen problems
in natural language inference.
You've seen language
models actually
perform pretty well at the
language modeling objective.
But then you just saw an example
of a commercial sentiment
analysis system that sort of
should do better and doesn't.
And this comes to this really,
I think, broad and important
takeaway, which is, if
you get high accuracy
on the in-domain
test set, you are not
guaranteed high
accuracy on even what
you might consider to be
reasonable out-of-domain
evaluations.
And life is always
out of domain,
and if you're building a system
that will be given to users,
it's immediately out of
domain, at the very least
because it's trained
on text that's
now older than the things
that the users are now saying.
So it's a really,
really important take
away that your sort
of benchmark accuracy
is a single number that does
not guarantee good performance
on a wide variety of things.
And from a what are our neural
networks doing perspective,
one way to think about
it is that models
seem to be learning the
data set, fitting sort
of the fine-grained sort
of heuristic and statistics
that help it fit
this one data set,
as opposed to learning the task.
So humans can perform
natural language inference.
If you give them examples
from whatever data set,
once you've told them
how to do the task,
they'll be very
generally strong at it.
But you take your MNLI model
and you test it on HANS,
and it got whatever that
was below chance accuracy.
That's not the kind of
thing that you want to see.
So it definitely learns
the data set well
because the accuracy
in domain is high.
But our models are seemingly
not frequently learning
sort of the mechanisms that we
would like them to be learning.
Last week, we heard about
language models and sort
of the implicit knowledge that
they encode about the world
through pretraining.
And one of the ways that we saw
the interactive language models
was providing them
with a prompt,
like, Dante was born in
mask, and then seeing
if it puts high probability on
the correct continuation, which
requires you to access knowledge
about where Dante was born.
And we didn't frame
it this way last week,
but this fits into the
set of behavioral studies
that we've done so far.
This is a specific
kind of input.
You could ask this
for multiple people.
We could swap out
Dante for other people.
We could have swapped out born
in for, I don't know, died in
or something.
And then there are
test suites again.
And so it's all connected.
OK, so I won't go too deep
into the knowledge of language
models in terms
of world knowledge
because we've gone over
it some, but when you're
thinking about ways of
interacting with your models,
this sort of behavioral study
can be very, very general,
even though, remember,
we're at still this highest
level of abstraction where we're
just looking at the probability
distributions that are defined.
All right, so now
we'll go into--
so we've sort of
looked at understanding
in fine-grained areas what
our model is actually doing.
What about sort of why,
for an individual input,
is it getting the
answer right or wrong?
And then are there
changes to the inputs
that look fine to
humans but actually
make the models do a bad job?
So one study that I love to
reference that really draws
back into our original
motivation of using
LSTM networks instead of simple
recurrent neural networks
was that they could
use long context.
But how long is your long-
and short-term memory?
And the idea of
Khandelwal et al 2018
was shuffle or remove contexts
that are farther than some k
words away, changing k.
And if your accuracy, if
the predictive ability
of your language model,
the perplexity, right,
doesn't change once
you do that, it
means the model wasn't
actually using that context.
I think this is so cool.
So on the x-axis,
we've got how far away
from the word that you're trying
to predict are you actually
sort of corrupting,
shuffling, or removing stuff
from the sequence?
And then on the y-axis
is the increase in loss.
So if the increase
in loss is 0, it
means that the model was not
using the thing that you just
removed because if
it was using it,
it would now do worse
without it, right?
And so if you shuffle,
in the blue line
here, if you shuffle
the history that's
farther away from 50 words,
the model does not even notice.
I think that's
really interesting.
One, it says everything past
50 words of this LSTM language
model, you could have
given it in random order
and it wouldn't have noticed.
And then, two, it says that
if you're closer than that,
it actually is making
use of the word order.
That's a pretty long memory.
OK, that's really interesting.
And then if you actually
remove the words entirely,
you can kind of notice
that the words are
missing up to 200 words away.
So you don't know the order--
you don't care about
the order they're in,
but you care whether
they're there or not.
And so this is an
evaluation of, well,
do LSTMs have long-term memory?
Well, this one at least
has effectively no longer
than 200 words of
memory, but also no less.
So very cool.
So that's a general
study for a single model.
It talks about its sort
of average behavior
over a wide range of examples.
But we want to talk about
individual predictions
on individual inputs.
So let's talk about that.
So one way of interpreting,
why did my model
make this decision,
that's very popular is,
for a single example,
what parts of the input
actually led to the decision?
And this is where we come
in with saliency map.
So saliency map provides a
score for each word indicating
its importance to the
model's prediction.
So you've got something
like BERT here.
You've got BERT.
BERT Is making a
prediction for this mask.
The mask rushed to the emergency
room to see her patient.
And the predictions that
the model is making is
thinks with 47% it's
going to be nurse that's
here in the mask instead,
or maybe woman or doctor,
or mother, or girl, OK.
And then the saliency map
is being visualized here
in orange.
According to this
method of saliency
called simple gradients,
which we'll get into,
"emergency," "her,"
and the SEP token--
let's not worry about
the SEP token for now,
but "emergency" and "her"
are the important words,
apparently.
And the SEP token shows
up in every sentence,
so I'm not going to--
right.
And so these two together
are, according to this method,
what's important for
the model to make
this prediction to mask.
And you can see maybe some
statistics, biases, et cetera
that it's picked up
in the predictions
and then have it mapped
out onto the sentence.
And this is-- well, it
seems like it's really
helping interpretability.
And yeah, I think that this
is sort of a very useful tool.
Actually, this is part
of a demo from AllenNLP
that allows you to do this
yourself for any sentence
that you want.
So what's this way of
making saliency maps?
We're not going to go--
there's so many ways to do it.
We're going to take
a very simple one
and work through why
it sort of makes sense.
So the sort of issue is, how do
you define importance, right?
What does it mean to be
important to the model's
prediction?
And here's one way
of thinking about it.
It's called the simple
gradient method.
Let's get a little formal.
You've got words x1
to xn, OK, and then
you've got a model's score
for a given output class.
So maybe you've got, in the
BERT example, each output
class with each output word
that you could possibly predict.
And then you take the norm
of the gradient of the score
with respect to each word.
OK, so what we're
saying here is the score
is sort of the un-normalized
probability for that class, OK?
So you've got a single class,
you're taking the score.
It's, like, how
likely it is, not yet
normalized by how likely
everything else is sort of.
Gradient, how much
is it going to change
if I move it a little bit
in one direction or another?
And then you take the norm to
get a scalar from a vector.
So it looks like this.
So salience of
word "I," you have
the norm bars on the outside,
gradient with respect to xi.
So that's, if I change
a little bit locally xi,
how much does my score change?
So the idea is that
a high gradient norm
means that if I were
to change it locally,
I'd affect the score a lot.
And that means it was very
important to the decision.
Let's visualize
this a little bit.
So here on the y-axis,
we've got loss, just
the loss of the model.
Sorry, this should be
score, should be score.
And on the x-axis,
you've got word space.
The word space is like sort
of a flattening of the ability
to move your word embedding
in 1,000-dimensional space.
I've just plotted it
here in one dimension.
And now a high
saliency thing, you
can see that the relationship
between what should be score
and moving the
word in word space,
you move it a little
bit on the x-axis,
and the score changes a lot.
That's that derivative,
that's the gradient.
Awesome, love it.
Low saliency, you move
the word around locally,
and the score doesn't change.
So the interpretation
is that means
that the actual
identity of this word
wasn't that important
to the prediction
because I could have changed
it and the score wouldn't
have changed.
Now, why are there
more methods than this?
Because, honestly,
reading that, I was like,
that sounds awesome.
That sounds great.
There are sort of lots of
issues with this kind of method,
and lots of ways of
getting around them.
Here's one issue.
It's not perfect
because, well, maybe
your linear approximation that
the gradient gives you holds
only very, very locally, right?
So here the gradient is 0,
so this is a low saliency
word because I'm at the
bottom of this parabola.
But if I were to move it even a
little bit in either direction,
the score would shoot up.
So is this not an
important word?
It seems important to be
right there, as opposed
to anywhere else, even sort of
nearby, in order for the score
not to go up.
But the simple gradients
method won't capture this
because it just looks
at the gradient, which
is that 0 right there, OK?
But if you want
to look into more,
there's a bunch of
different methods
that are sort of
applied in these papers.
And I think that it's a good
tool for the toolbox, OK?
So that is one way of
explaining a prediction.
And it has some issues, like
why are individual words being
scored, as opposed to phrases
or something like that.
But for now, we're going
to move on to another type
of explanation, and I'm
going to check the time.
OK, cool.
Actually, yeah, let
me pause for a second.
Any questions about this?
Earlier on, there were
a couple of questions.
One of them was, what
are your thoughts
on whether looking
at attention weights
is a methodologically
rigorous way of determining
the importance that the model
places on certain tokens?
It seems like there's some back
and forth in the literature.
That is a great
question, and I probably
won't engage with
that question as much
as I could if we had a
second lecture on this.
I actually will provide some
attention analyses and tell you
they're interesting, and then
I'll sort of say a little bit
about why they can be
interesting without being sort
of the end-all of analysis of
where information is flowing
in a transformer, for example.
I think the debate
is something that we
would have to get into in a
much longer period of time.
But look at the slides
that I show about attention
and the caveats that
I provide, and let
me know if that answers
your question first,
because we have quite a
number of slides on it.
And if not, please,
please, ask again,
and we can chat more about it.
Then maybe you can go on.
Great, OK.
So I think this is a really
fascinating question, which
also gets what was
important about the input,
but it actually kind of an
even more direct way, which is,
could I just keep some
minimal part of the input
and get the same answer?
So here's an example from SQuAD.
You have this passage,
in 1899 John Jacob Astor
IV invested $100,000 for Tesla.
OK, and then the answer that
is being predicted by the model
is going to always be in blue,
in these examples, Colorado
Springs experiments.
So you've got this passage.
And the question is, what did
Tesla spend Astor's money on?
That's why the prediction is
Colorado Springs experiments.
The model gets the answer
right, which is nice.
And we would like to
think it's because it's
doing some kind of
reading comprehension.
But here's the issue.
It turns out, based on
this fascinating paper,
that if you just reduced
the question to, did,
you actually get
exactly the same answer.
In fact, with the
original question,
the model had sort of a
0.78 confidence probability
in that answer.
And with the reduced
question, did,
you get even higher confidence.
And that, if you
give a human this,
they would not be
able to know really
what you're trying to ask about,
so it seems like something
is going really wonky here.
So here's sort of a very high
level overview of the method.
In fact, it actually references
our input saliency methods.
Ah, nice, it's connected.
So you iteratively remove
non-salient or unimportant
words.
So here's a passage again
talking about football,
I think.
Yeah, oh, nice.
So the question is,
where did the Broncos
practice for the Super Bowl?
Has the prediction of
Stanford University.
And that is correct.
So again, seems nice.
And now we're not actually
going to get the model
to be incorrect.
We're just going to say, how
can I change this question such
that it'll still get
the answer right?
So I'm going to remove the
word that was least important
according to the
saliency method.
So now it's, where did the
practice for the Super Bowl?
Already, this is
sort of unanswerable
because you've got
two teams practicing.
You don't even know which
one you're asking about.
So why the model still thinks
it's so confident in Stanford
University makes no sense.
But you can just
sort of keep going.
And now I think
here the model stops
being confident in the
answer Stanford University.
But I think this is
really interesting
just to show that
if the model is
able to do this with
very high confidence,
it's not reflecting the
uncertainty that really should
be there because you can't know
what you're even asking about.
OK, so what was important
to make this answer?
Well, at least these
parts were important
because you could
keep just those parts
and get the same answer.
Fascinating.
All right, so that's
sort of the end
of the admittedly
brief talk section
on thinking about input saliency
methods and similar things.
Now we're going to talk
about actually breaking
models and understanding
models by breaking them.
OK, cool.
So if we have a passage
here, Peyton Manning
became the first
quarterback something
Super Bowl, age 39, past
record held by John Elway.
Again, we're doing
question answering.
We've got this
question, what was
the name of the quarterback
who was 38 in the Super Bowl?
The prediction is
correct, looks good.
Now we're not going
to change the question
to try to sort of make
the question nonsensical
while keeping the same answer.
Instead, we're going
to change the passage
by adding this sentence at the
end, which really shouldn't
distract anyone.
This is well-known
quarterback Jeff Dean.
Had jersey number
37 in Champ Bowl.
So this just doesn't--
it's really not even related,
but now the prediction
is Jeff Dean for
our nice QA model.
And so this shows as well that
it seems like maybe there's
this end of the passage bias as
to where the answer should be,
for example.
And so this is an
adversarial example
where we flipped the
prediction by adding something
that is innocuous to humans.
And so sort of the
higher level take away
is, oh, it seems
like the QA model
that we had that seemed good
is not actually performing
QA how we want it to, even
though its in-domain accuracy
was good.
And here's another example.
So you've got this
paragraph with the question,
what has been the result
of this publicity?
The answer is, increased
scrutiny on teacher misconduct.
Now, instead of
changing the paragraph,
we're going to change
the question in really,
really seemingly insignificant
ways to change the model's
prediction.
So first, what H-A and then
I've got this typo L been
the result of this publicity.
The answer changes to
teacher misconduct.
Likely a human would sort of
ignore this typo or something
and answer the right answer.
And then this is really nuts.
Instead of asking, what has been
the result of this publicity,
if you ask, what's been the
result of this publicity,
the answer also changes.
And the authors call this
a semantically equivalent
adversary.
This is pretty rough.
And in general, swapping "what"
for "what's" in this QA model
breaks it pretty frequently.
And so, again, when you go
back and sort of re-tinker
how to build your
model, you're going
to be thinking about
these things, not just
the sort of average accuracy.
So that's sort of
talking about noise.
Are models robust to
noise in their inputs?
Are humans robust to noise is
another question we can ask.
And so you can kind of go
to this popular sort of meme
passed around the
internet from time
to time, where you have all
the letters in these words
scrambled.
You say, according to research
at Cambridge University,
it doesn't matter in what order
the letters in a word are,
right?
And so it seems like--
I think I did a pretty
good job there--
seemingly, right,
we've got this noise.
That's a specific kind of noise.
And we can be robust as humans
to reading and processing
the language without actually
all that much of a difficulty.
So that's maybe something
that we might want our models
to also be robust to.
And it's very practical as well.
Noise is a part of all NLP
systems inputs at all times.
There's just no such
thing effectively as
having users, for example,
and not having any noise.
And so there's a study
that was performed
on some popular machine
translation models where you
train machine translation models
in French, German, and Czech,
I think all to English,
and you get BLEU scores.
These BLEU scores
will look a lot better
than the ones in
your Assignment 4
because much, much
more training data.
The idea is these are
actually pretty strong machine
translation systems, and
that's in in-domain clean text.
Now, if you add character
swaps, like the ones
we saw in that sentence
about Cambridge,
the BLEU scores take
a pretty harsh dive.
Not very good.
And even if you take a somewhat
more natural sort of typo noise
distribution here, you'll
see that you're still
getting 20-ish very
high drops in BLEU score
through simply natural noise.
And so maybe you'll go
back and retrain the model
on more types of noise,
and then you ask, oh,
if I do that is it robust to
even different kinds of noise?
These are the questions that are
going to be really important.
And it's important
to know that you're
able to break your model really
easily so that you can then go
and try to make it more robust.
Now, let's see, 20
minutes, awesome.
Now we're going to, I guess--
so now we're going to look
at the representations
of our neural networks.
We've talked about
sort of their behavior
and then whether we
could sort of change
or observe reasons
behind their behavior.
Now we'll go into
less abstraction,
look more at the actual
vector representations that
are being built
by models, and we
can answer a different kind of
question, at the very least,
than with the other studies.
The first thing is
related to the question
I was asked about
attention, which
is that some modeling components
lend themselves to inspection.
Now, this is a sentence that
I chose somewhat carefully,
actually, because in part
of this debate, right,
are they interpretable
components?
We'll see, but they
lend themselves
to inspection in
the following way.
You can visualize them well and
you can correlate them easily
with various properties.
So let's say you have
attention heads in BERT.
This is from a really nice
study that was done here
where you look at
attention heads of BERT
and you say, on most sentences,
this attention head had 1,
1, seems to do this very sort of
global aggregation, simple kind
of operation, does this
pretty consistently.
That's cool.
Is it interpretable?
Well, maybe, right?
So it's the first layer, which
means that this word, "found,"
is sort of uncontextualized.
But in deeper
layers, the problem
is that once you do some
rounds of attention,
you've had information mixing
and flowing between words.
And how do you know exactly what
information you're combining,
what you're attending to, even?
It's a little hard to tell.
And saliency methods
more directly
sort of evaluate the
importance of models.
But it's still
interesting to see
at sort of a local
mechanistic point of view
what kinds of things
are being attended to.
So let's take another example.
Some attention heads seemed
to perform simple operations.
So you have the
global aggregation
here that we saw already.
Others seem to attend pretty
robustly to the next token,
cool.
Next token is a great signal.
Some heads attend
to the SEP token,
so here you have it
attending to SEP.
And then maybe some
attended periods.
Maybe that's sort of a
splitting sentences together
and things like that, not
things that are hard to do,
but things that
some attention heads
seemed to pretty
robustly perform.
Again, now, though,
deep in the network,
what's actually represented
at this period at layer 11?
Little unclear,
little unclear, OK?
So some heads,
though, are correlated
with really interesting
linguistic properties.
So this head is actually
attending to noun modifiers.
So you've got this, the
complicated language
in the huge new law, right?
That's pretty fascinating.
Even if the model is not doing
this as a causal mechanism
to do syntax
necessarily, the fact
that these things so
strongly correlate
is actually pretty cool.
And so what we have in
all of these studies is
we've got an approximate
interpretation
and quantitative analysis
relating, allowing
us to reason about very
complicated model behavior.
They're all approximations, but
they're definitely interesting.
One other example is
that of coreference.
So we saw some work
on coreference,
and it seems like this
head does a pretty OK job
of actually matching
up coreferent entities.
These are in red--
talks, negotiations, she, her.
And that's not obvious
how to do that.
This is a difficult
task, and so it does so
with some percentage
of the time.
And again, it's sort of
connecting very complex model
behavior to these sort of
interpretable summaries
of correlating properties.
Other cases, you can have
individual hidden units
that lend themselves
to interpretation.
So here you've got a character
level LSTM language model.
Each row here is a sentence.
If you can't read it,
that's totally OK.
The interpretation
that you should take
is that, as we walk
along the sentence,
this single unit is
going from, I think,
very negative to very
positive or very positive
to very negative.
I don't really remember.
But it's tracking the
position in the line.
So it's just a linear
positioning unit,
and pretty robustly doing so
across all of these sentences.
So this is from a nice
visualization study
way back in 2016, way back.
Here's another cell from
that same LSTM language model
that seems to sort of
turn on inside quotes.
So here's a quote,
and then it turns on.
So I guess that's
positive in the blue.
End quote here, and
then it's negative.
Here you start with no
quote, negative in the red,
see a quote, and then blue.
Seems, again, very
interpretable,
also potentially a very useful
feature to keep in mind.
And this is just an
individual unit in the LSTM
that you can just look at
and see that it does this.
Very, very interesting.
Even further on this,
and this is actually
a study by some AI and
neuroscience researchers,
is we saw that LSTMs were
good at subject-verb number
agreement.
Can we figure out the
mechanisms by which
the LSTM is solving the task?
Can we actually get
some insight into that?
And so we have a
word-level language model.
And the word-level
language model
is going to be a little small,
but you have a sentence,
the boy gently and
kindly greets the.
And this cell that's
being tracked here,
so it's an individual
hidden unit, one dimension,
right, is actually,
after it sees "boy,"
it sort of starts to go higher.
And then it goes down
to something very small
once it sees "greets."
And this cell seems to
correlate with the scope
of a subject-verb number
agreement instance effectively.
So here, the boy that watches
the dog that watches the cat
greets, you've got that
cell again staying high,
maintaining the scope of subject
until "greets," at which point
it stops.
What allows it to do that?
Probably some complex other
dynamics in the network,
but it's still a fascinating,
I think, insight.
And yeah, this is just
neuron 1,150 in this LSTM.
So those are sort of all
observational studies
that you could do by picking
out individual components
of the model, that you can
sort of just take each one of
and correlating them
with some behavior.
Now we'll look at a general
class of methods called
probing by which we still sort
of use supervised knowledge,
like knowledge of the
type of coreference
that we're looking for.
But instead of seeing if it
correlates with something
that's immediately
interpretable,
like a attention
head, we're going
to look into the vector
representations of the model
and see if these
properties can be read out
by some simple function
to say, oh, maybe
this property was
made very easily
accessible by my neural network.
So let's dig into this.
So the general
paradigm is that you've
got language data that goes into
some big pretrained transformer
with fine tuning, and you
get state of the art results.
SOTA means State
Of The Art, right?
And so the question for the
probing sort of methodology
is, if it's providing these
general purpose language
representations, what does it
actually encode about language?
Can we quantify this?
Can we figure out
what kinds of things
it's learning about language
that we seemingly now
don't have to tell it?
And so you might have
something like a sentence,
like, I record the record.
That's an interesting sentence.
And you put it into your
transformer model with its word
embeddings at the
beginning, maybe
some layers of self
attention and stuff,
and you make some predictions.
And now our objects
of study are going
to be these intermediate
layers, right?
So it's a vector per word
or subword for every layer.
And the question is, can we use
these linguistic properties,
like the dependency
parsing that we
had way back in the
early part of the course,
to understand sort of
correlations between properties
and the vectors and these
things that we can interpret?
We can interpret
dependency parses.
So there are a couple
of things that we
might want to look for here.
We might want to
look for semantics.
So here in the sentence,
"I record the record,"
I am an agent.
That's a semantics thing.
Record is a patient.
It's the thing
I'm recording, OK?
You might have syntax, so you
might have the syntax tree
that you're interested in,
that's the dependency parse
tree.
Maybe you're interested
in part of speech,
right, because you have
"record" and "record,"
and the first one's a verb,
the second one is a noun,
they're identical strings.
Does the model sort of
encode that one is one
and the other is the other?
So how do we do
this kind of study?
So we're going to decide on a
layer that we want to analyze
and we're going to freeze BERT.
So we're not going
to fine tune BERT.
All the parameters are frozen.
So we decide on layer 2 of BERT.
We're going to pass
in some sentences.
We decide on what's
called a probe family.
And the question
I'm asking is, can I
use a model from my
family, say linear,
to decode a property that
I'm interested in really
well from this layer?
So it's indicating that
this property is easily
accessible to linear
models, effectively.
So maybe I train the model,
I train a linear classifier,
right, on top of BERT, and I
get a really high accuracy.
And that's sort of
interesting already
because you know from prior
work in part of speech
tagging that if you run a
linear classifier on simpler
features that aren't
BERT, you probably
don't get as high an accuracy.
So that's an interesting
sort of takeaway.
But then you can
also take a baseline.
So I want to compare
two layers now.
So I've got layer 1 here, I
want to compare it to layer 2.
I train a probe on it as well.
Maybe the accuracy
isn't as good,
and now I can say,
oh, wow, look.
By layer 2, part of
speech is more easily
accessible to linear functions
than it was at layer 1.
So what did that?
Well, the self-attention
and feed forward stuff
made it more easily accessible.
That's interesting
because it's a statement
about sort of the information
processing of the model.
OK, so we're going to
analyze these layers.
Let's take a second
more to think about it
and just really--
give me just a second.
So if you have the model's
representations h1 to ht,
and you have a
function family f,
that's the subset linear models,
or maybe you have like a feed
forward neural network, some
fixed set of hyperparameters,
freeze the model,
train the probe.
So you get some
predictions for part
of speech tagging or whatever.
That's just the probe applied to
the hidden state of the model.
The probe is a member
of the probe family.
And then the extent
that we can predict y
is a measure of accessibility.
So that's just kind of written
out not as pictorially, OK?
So I'm not going to stay on
this for too much longer.
And it may help in the
search for causal mechanisms,
but it sort of just gives
us a rough understanding
of processing of the
model and what things
are accessible at what layer.
So what are some results here?
So one result is that BERT, if
you run linear probes on it,
does really, really
well on things
that require syntax
and part of speech
and named entity recognition,
actually, in some cases,
approximately as well as just
doing the very best thing you
could possibly do without BERT.
So it just makes easily
accessible amazingly strong
features for these
properties, and that's
an interesting sort of emergent
quality of BERT, you might say.
It seems like as well
that the layers of BERT
have this property
where, so if you
look at the columns of this plot
here, each column is a task.
You've got input words at the
sort of layer 0 of BERT here.
Layer 24 is the last
layer of BERT-large.
Lower performance is yellow,
higher performance is blue.
And I know the
resolution isn't perfect,
but consistently the best place
to read out these properties
is somewhere a bit
past the middle
of the model, which is it's
a very consistent rule, which
is fascinating.
And then it seems
as well, if you
look at this function
of increasingly
abstract or increasingly
difficult to compute
linguistic properties on
this axis, and increasing
depth in the network
on that axis, so
the deeper you go
in the network,
it seems like the more
easily you can access more
and more abstract
linguistic properties,
suggesting that that
accessibility is
being constructed over time
by the layers of processing
of BERT.
So it's building more
and more abstract
features, which I
think is, again, sort
of a really interesting result.
And now I think--
one thing that I
think comes to mind
that really brings us
back right to day one
is we built intuitions
around Word2vec.
We were asking, what does each
dimension of Word2vec mean?
And the answer was
not really anything.
But we could build
intuitions about it
and think about properties
of it through sort
of these connections between
simple mathematical properties
of Word2vec and
linguistic properties
that we could sort
of understand.
So we had this approximation,
which is not 100% true,
but some approximation
that says,
cosine similarity is
effectively correlated
with semantic similarity.
Think about even
if all we're going
to do at the end
of the day is fine
tune these word
embeddings anyway,
likewise we had
this sort of idea
about the analogies being
encoded by linear offsets.
So some relationships
are linear in space,
and they didn't have to be.
That's fascinating.
It's this emergent
property that we've now
been able to study since
we discovered this.
Why is that the
case in Word2vec?
And in general, even
though you can't interpret
the individual
dimensions of Word2vec,
these sort of emergent,
interpretable connections
between approximate
linguistic ideas
and sort of simple math on
these objects is fascinating.
And so one piece of work that
sort of extends this idea
comes back to
dependency parse trees.
So they describe the
syntax of sentences.
And in a paper that
I did with Chris,
we showed that,
actually, BERT and models
like it make the dependency
parse tree structure
emergent, sort of more easily
accessible than one might
imagine in its vector space.
So if you've got
a tree right here,
the chef who ran to the
store was out of food, what
you can sort of do is think
about the tree in terms
of distances between words.
So you've got the number
of edges in the tree.
Between two words is
their path distance.
So you've got the distance
between "chef" and "was" is 1.
And we're going to use this
interpretation of a tree
as a distance to make a
connection with BERT's
embedding space.
And what we were
able to show is that
under a single linear
transformation,
the squared Euclidean
distance between BERT vectors
for the same sentence
actually correlates well,
if you choose the
B matrix right,
with the distances in the tree.
So here in this Euclidean
space that we've transformed,
the approximate distance between
"chef" and "was" is also 1.
Likewise, the difference
between "was" and "store"
is 4 in the tree.
And in my simple sort of
transformation of BERT space,
the distance between "store" and
"was" is also approximately 4,
and this is true across a
wide range of sentences.
And this is, to me, a
fascinating example of, again,
emergent approximate structure
in these very nonlinear models
that don't necessarily need
to encode things so simply.
OK, all right, great.
So probing studies and
correlation studies are,
I think, interesting and
point us in directions
to build intuitions
about models.
But they're not arguments
that the model is actually
using the thing that you're
finding to make a decision.
They're not causal studies.
And this is for probing
and correlation studies.
So in some work that I
did around the same time,
we showed, actually, that
certain conditions on probes
allow you to achieve high
accuracy on a task that's
effectively just
fitting random labels.
And so there's a
difficulty of interpreting
what the model
could or could not
be doing with this thing that
is somehow easily accessible.
It's interesting that this
property is easily accessible,
but the model might not
be doing anything with it,
for example, because
it's totally random.
Likewise, another
paper showed that you
can achieve high
accuracy with a probe,
even if the model is trained
to know that thing that you're
probing for is not useful.
And there's causal
studies that sort of
try to extend this work.
It's much more difficult,
but read this paper,
and it's a fascinating
line of future work.
Now in my last two
minutes, I want
to talk about
recasting model tweaks
and ablations as analysis.
So we had this
improvement process
where we had a network
that was going to work OK,
and we would see whether we
could tweak it in simple ways
to improve it.
And then you could
see whether you
could remove anything
and have it still be OK,
and that's kind
of like analysis.
I have my network.
Do I want it to--
is it going to be better
if it's more complicated?
Is it going to be
better if it's simpler?
Can I get away with
it being simpler?
And so one example of some
folks who did this is they
took this idea of multiheaded
attention and said,
oh, so many heads.
Are all the heads important?
And what they showed
is that if you
train a system with
multiheaded attention,
and then just remove
the heads at test time
and not use them at
all, you can actually
do pretty well on
the original task,
not retraining, at all without
some of the attention heads,
showing that they
weren't important.
You could just get rid
of them after training.
And likewise, you can
do the same thing for--
this is on machine translation,
this is on Multi-NLI.
You can actually
get away without
a large, large percentage
of your attention heads.
Let's see.
Yeah, so another thing
that you could think about
is questioning sort of
the basics of the models
that we're building.
So we have transformer
models that
are sort of self-attention,
feed forward, self-attention,
feed forward.
But why in that order, with
some of the things omitted here?
And this paper
asked this question
and said, if this is my
transformer, self-attention,
feed forward, self-attention,
feed forward, et cetera,
et cetera, et cetera, what
if I just reordered it
so that I had a bunch of
self-attentions at the head
and a bunch of feed
forwards at the back?
And they tried a bunch
of these orderings,
and this one
actually does better.
So this achieves a lower
perplexity on a benchmark.
And this is a way
of analyzing what's
important about the
architectures that I'm building
and how can they be changed
in order to perform better.
So neural models
are very complex,
and they're difficult
to characterize
and impossible to characterize
with a single sort
of statistic, I think, for your
test set accuracy, especially
in domain.
And we want to find intuitive
descriptions of model
behaviors, but we should look at
multiple levels of abstraction.
And none of them are
going to be complete.
When someone tells you that
their neural network is
interpretable, I encourage you
to engage critically with that.
It's not necessarily false, but
the levels of interpretability
and what you can interpret,
these are the questions
that you should be
asking because it's
going to be opaque in some
ways, almost definitely.
And then bringing this-- this
lens to your model building
as you try to think about
how to build better models,
even if you're not going to be
doing analysis as sort of one
of your main driving goals.
And with that, good luck
on your final projects.
I realize we're at time.
The teaching staff is really
appreciative of your efforts
over this difficult quarter.
And yeah, I guess there's
a lecture left on Thursday,
but yeah, this is my last
one, so thanks, everyone.