For today, I'm really delighted, um,
to introduce our third guest speaker, who's Marc'Aurelio Ranzato.
So he's originally from Italy and then worked at NYU with Yann LeCun,
and then has a post-doc with Geoffrey Hinton.
So he's a very dyed in the wool deep learning researcher.
A lot of his original work was in the areas like feature learning and vision,
but over the last few years he's really
turned his interests to natural language processing.
And in particular, um,
in the last few years,
he's worked a huge amount in looking at machine translation in general and in
particular machine translation for languages for which less resources are available.
So I saw a talk of his about six months ago on this topic.
And, um, through him and his team at Facebook,
they've really got a lot of exciting new work in ways to
bring neural machine translation up to the next level.
And so I hope that this would be a really great opportunity for everyone to
see some of the latest and most exciting techniques in neural machine translation.
That's sort of - of a next level beyond what we talked
about, and you guys all did on assignments 4 and 5 of the class.
Um, so take it away, Marc'Aurelio.
Okay. Thank you so much,
Chris, for inviting me.
Um, let me just put my face.
I'm here. [LAUGHTER] Hi everybody.
I'm gonna disable it now so you can focus on the presentation.
Um, so share.
I hope you should be able to see my presentation now.
Okay. So I'm very excited to
tell you a little bit about low resource machine translation.
And let's start by, uh,
revisiting, uh, the machine translation problems.
So let's say that we want to translate between English and French.
And, uh, we started with a big, uh,
training set where we have a collection of sentences,
uh, in English with their corresponding translation in French.
And this is what we call a parallel data set.
And in particular the sentences in English,
we call them source sentences, right?
And the corresponding sentences in French are,
uh, what we call the target sentences.
And now, uh, the learning problem is about for a given,
uh, sentence in English,
you want to predict the corresponding,
uh, sentence in French.
And, uh, the way that we do that is by minimizing the cross-entropy loss,
which maximizes the low probability of
the reference human translation given the input source sentence.
And we do this by stochastic gradient descent, using, uh,
as architecture a sequence to sequence with attention that as far as I know,
you started and- and- and you had a homework on a few weeks ago.
And then after you train this, at this time,
you are given a normal English sentence
and you want to produce the corresponding translation.
And in order to do that, um,
we usually, uh, employ a heuristic, uh,
search method like beam that tries to find, uh,
approximately the target sentence that maximizes the low probability given the- uh,
the given, uh, source sentence.
So this is at the high level how machine translation works.
And let's think about the assumptions that,
uh, we have been making,
uh, through this discussion.
So the first assumption is that we are working with two,
uh, fairly related languages like English and French.
And the second, uh,
assumptions is that we have at our disposal,
a large data set of parallel sentences.
Because here we are essentially doing,
uh, supervised learning, right?
And it is a beautiful example of end-to-end supervised learning,
that relies on the availability of a large parallel dataset.
And so in the world there are more than 6,000 languages.
Um, and needless to say,
most of these languages don't belong to the European family for
which much of the recent research on machine translation has been focusing on.
And even if you look at English,
English is spoken by less than 5% of- as
native languages speak- is spoken by less than 5% of the world population.
And so, uh, if you were
to count how many people speak a certain language and you look at that histogram,
it's a very heavy tailed distribution.
So even if you take the top 10 spoken languages,
you find that this accounts for less than 50%of the people in the world.
And, um, now if you look at the very far right of the tail,
those are languages for which there are very few speakers and essentially there
is no digitized data material for you to train anything.
So for- for those I think it's almost hopeless, I would say.
But in the middle of this tail,
we have a lot of languages for which there is some,
uh, digital data and for which, uh,
we don't have good ways to translate nowadays,
if you think about major providers like Google, Yandex,
Baidu, Facebook, and so on, and so forth,
they provide translation for the top 100 languages.
So we are still very much at the far right of this normal distribution.
And so, uh, if- if we're able to, uh, um,.
Improve machine translation in the middle,
I think we could do- uh,
it would be very impactful, right?
But so what happens as we walk down these tails?
So what happens is that the amount of data or parallel data decreases and,
uh, that correlates very much with the quality of
the automatic machine translation systems that we have.
And particularly as you can see here,
at some point there is actually a drastic drop
in accuracy of your machine translation system.
So, um, so perhaps the initial,
um, picture that we had in mind is a little different.
So now if we take a fairly low resource language like Nepali,
which is the language spoken in Nepal,
a lovely country northeast of India,
um, with more than 25 million people.
So it's not as handful of people.
Uh, first of all, the amount of training data is not as much as English.
French is much, much less than that.
And here, uh, let's use a different visual representation.
So let's use, um, uh,
few rectangles with a color that corresponds to the language.
So the blue rectangle is English data and the red rectangle is Nepali data.
Now, in practice, the parallel dataset is not
just such a monolithic thing because some part
originates in English and some parts originates in Nepali.
And now let's represent the Nepali translations of English data
with an empty rectangle where the color
corresponds to the language and whether you fill
it or not depends whether this is translation is,
so whether this is a human translation or whether it is,
uh, um, data originating in- in the language.
So in this case, we take, uh,
data that originates in English and we translate it into Nepali.
And so this is the empty red rectangle
and the same for when you go from Nepali to English.
Now, in general, the data that originates in English and
the data that originates in Nepali come from different- may come from different domains.
So here on the y-axis you have the domain.
And so in this example that I totally made up,
but it's pretty, um,
uh, indicative of what happens in practice.
You may have that English sentences may come from, let say Bible.
And so the Nepali here are translations from, uh, the Bible.
And, uh, the Nepali sentences may come from parliamentary data, okay?
So you may agree with me that translating a normal sentence from
the Bible is not
a super interesting task because the Bible is a pretty static dataset, right?
And so maybe we want to translate news data.
And, uh, but so, uh,
in practice we don't have any,
uh, parallel data in the news domain,
perhaps what we have,
so what we really want to do at the end is translate sentences from this test set,
that is English news into Nepali.
But all we have in the news domain is at
most monolingual data both in English and in Nepali.
So these are English sentences that are not aligned at all with the Nepali,
uh, sentences over here.
Here it just happened to be just data that you got from new sources.
Okay? And so this is a pretty complicated learning setting because you
have a little bit of parallel sentences and,
uh, that are in a different domain from the test set,
and, uh, all you have in the domain of interest is monolingual data.
And in fact, you may have also some other parallel data but in another language,
let's say Hindi that is in the same family as
Nepali but maybe these parallel data is in a different domain, let say books.
And perhaps you have also monolingual data in Hindi that is also in the book domain.
So in fact, what you really- [LAUGHTER] in- in practice,
what you'll find is that you may have a lot of languages
here from which you could learn and- and a lot of domains.
And all you want to do at the end is to be
able to translate news data in English into Nepali.
But you don't have any supervision for that.
You don't have any labeled data,
any parallel data for that.
All you have is a bunch of data in different domains and in different languages.
And so the question is,
how can you leverage all these data in order to perform your original translation task?
And so this is a- a Mondrian like learning setting,
which is pretty tricky.
And this is going to be the topic of this lecture.
And so, um, there is not a very, um,
clear definition of what Low Resource Machine Translation is but, loosely speaking, uh,
a language pair can be consider low-resource when the number of
parallel sentences in domain is less than 10,000. Okay?
And as, uh, order of magnitude.
And, uh, and this is very little,
particularly if you think
that modern neural machine translation systems
have easily hundreds of millions of parameters.
And so there are several challenges.
There are challenges that pertain to data and
challenges that pertain to the model design.
So in terms of the data,
it is very hard to get data to train, right?
It is very hard to figure out where to get the data to train,
data that is in- in a domain similar to
the domain that you are interested in eventually translating.
Uh, if that doesn't exist,
how to get data in similar languages on
other domains and even how to get data to evaluate your system on.
And on the modeling side, uh,
there is the question of, of course,
how to learn with,
uh, so little supervision,
so little direct supervision at the very least,
and how to operate in this,
um, framework for which you have so many languages and so many domains.
So, uh, so as,
uh, Chris mentioned at the very beginning,
my background is not really NMT.
My, um, I've always been interested in learning with less supervision.
And I think working low resource machine translation is,
at least personally, a very unique opportunity.
It's a very rare case in which my research agenda is aligned
with an application [LAUGHTER] because, um,
in low resource machine translation you don't have much level data and you need to make
the best use of auxiliary tasks and au- auxiliary data in order to, uh, perform well.
And this is a general problem.
And at the same time,
machine translation is a real application,
it's something that if we improve we can really, uh,
have a chance to improve, uh,
a lot of applications and- and- and the life of a lot of people.
So, uh, this concludes my introduction about low resource machine translation and,
um, the issues that we face when working on these languages.
Before, uh, and let me just,
uh, pause for a second,
seeing the- the outline of this talk goes around three pillars that in a way define,
uh, the cycle of research.
So the first pillar is data.
So, um, I'm going to review,
uh, how we can get data in particular for evaluation.
So, uh, data is the prerequisite to do
anything in our life as machine learner practitioners, right?
And then, uh, afterwards I'm gonna move to the modeling, so, uh,
describing some, uh, algorithms to, uh,
learn, um, on low resource languages.
And finally, I will conclude with some work on analyzing,
uh, what a model does when we train on low resource languages.
And in practice, like, uh, throughout my, um,
work here, I keep going around the circle because as I figured out,
uh, the issues that we have with the data, with the model,
then I make a mark with a dataset
that better fits the kinds of problems that I'm interested in,
and then I may, uh,
go back to the modeling side to improve the models and- and so on and so forth, okay?
And here I'm giving some references of the works that I'm presenting, not all of them.
And just so- uh, and just to be clear,
these are- this is not meant to be a chronological survey,
so these are not necessarily the works that introduce a certain- a- a certain idea,
but it's just, I would say,
the most accessible entry points on the topic,
and then you can go on the related work sections to figure out,
uh, if there was, eh,
some seminal paper that led to- to- to that line of research.
And of course, there is quite a bit of presenter bias because most of these, uh,
works are- are being co-authored by me,
so, uh, be mindful of that.
That said, do you have any questions so far?
Uh, I have a quick question about, uh,
I- I see people posting the model about Phrase-based and Neural Unsupervised MT.
I was wondering if you could talk about
the different approaches about unsupervised learning,
and also, uh, a- algorithms like GLoVe and Word2vec are possible in low resource languages.
Yeah, yeah, so, um,
Yuri, I- I- in this lecture I'm gonna focus on neural more.
Actually I'm not even going into details of the architecture,
I'm more talking about algorithms actually.
And so these algorithms are applicable both to
neural machine translation system as
well as through statistical machine translation systems.
Uh, when I go over this part I can,
um, uh, address a little bit your question and tell you
a little bit about the differences between the- these two.
Um, uh, and then in terms of, um, uh,
methods to learn word embeddings and- and- and sentence embeddings,
I'm gonna touch very briefly on that.
So at the end of the, er,
lecture, I'm gonna, uh,
refer to some recent work on filtering where people use,
um, sentence embedding methods.
It's not GloVe but it's,
uh, something, uh, similar in the way.
Um, in practice, uh, for word embeddings,
um, it's kind of,
I would say, um,
a prerequisite for machine translation because if you can
align word embeddings, you learn a dictionary,
and that's, uh, a primitive way to do machine translation.
So oftentimes we look at those things as a, um,
good sanity check or as a simplified machine translation task.
Whenever you have a reference dictionary for which you can then,
um, check the accuracy of your alignment.
But- so if you- let me get back to you when,
uh, we talk about, uh, uh, this paper, okay?
So let's talk about data then.
So, uh, let's go back to, uh, our English,
Nepali, um, um, translation task.
So there is, um, er, um,
a resource called OPUS,
which is a very nice, uh,
which hosts a very nice collection of datasets,
all publically available in- in lots of languages.
And, uh, when you go to this website,
the OPUS website, you find that for English,
Nepali, actually there are 1 million parallel sentences.
So maybe I lied to you,
telling you that this is a low resource language.
But if actually- if you look at what this corpus are,
you realize that pretty much half a million of these sentences come from,
uh, JW 300, uh, and, uh,
which is a religious magazine,
and then you have 60,000 sentences from the Bible,
and the rest come from GNOME, KDE, Ubuntu,
so these are computer related, um, materials, right?
And so again, unless you're interesting in translating novel sentences from the Bible,
uh, this is not,
um, super useful, I would say.
Um, and, uh, so one thing to notice that all this data originates from English,
we have nothing that originates from Nepali, first of all.
And second of all, if you are interested in,
let's say translating Wikipedia,
all you have is Wikipedia monolingual data both in English and Nepali,
and Nepali is not even very much.
And then of course you can add some monolingual data in another domain like Common Crawl,
which is just a dump of the Internet.
Uh, but again, uh,
translating between English and Nepali using publicly available data is going to be
a challenge because you don't have any in domain parallel dataset, okay?
All you have is at most some in domain monolingual data.
But there is an even bigger problem,
which is that there is no test data, right?
So here we don't have reference translations in
Nepali to measure the quality of our machine translation system.
And this is a big problem because if you don't have
a high-quality or you don't have at all, er, the set,
it's very hard to compare models and it's very hard
to do model selection to compare algorithms and- and our,
uh, field is crippled.
We need, uh, strong evaluation, uh, benchmarks.
And so this motivator,
a project that's called FloRes,
that stands for Facebook low resource- low resource, um,
evaluation benchmark for machine translation,
uh, where we took, uh,
Wikipedia sentences in English and translated them into Nepali and Sinhala,
and then we took, uh, Wikipedia.
We - we took sentences from Nepali Wikipedia and translating them
into English as well as from Sinhala Wikipedia and translated them into English.
Okay. So you may say this is a little bit boring because what's hard about it?
And [LAUGHTER] and tell me about,
um, you know, tricks to do better modeling.
But actually, you'd be surprised that this data collection process
was harder and more interesting also than we thought.
So it is hard because there are very few, ah,
fluent professional translators in
these languages and this is not even super low resource, right?
And so, since, ah, so, ah,
we dealt with a translator agency and typically there are not enough people,
ah, for which you can do kind of AB testing to
test the translation of one person with another one.
That's number one. Number two in general,
it's very hard to assess automatically the quality of the translation
because we don't have enough parallel data to train machine translation system, right?
And so we need to rely on other methods
than a well-trained machine translation system to assess the quality.
And so, ah, we build a pipeline where we would have,
ah, we would send the sentences to the translators.
Once the translations are back, we would, um,
do several checks like fluency checks,
ah, using, ah, a language model.
We would check for transliteration to make sure that
a sentence is not translated by simply transliterating.
We would check that, ah,
the language is the desired one, right?
And so we will have a lot of checks like that.
And then, if and of course here there are thresholds that you need to set somehow.
And then, ah, for those sentences that would fail, ah, this,
ah, this step we would send them back to, ah, re-translation.
And so after a few iterations of this,
then eventually we do also a human evaluation.
And then, ah, the sentences in this evaluation benchmark are those that are,
that have passed, that I've, um,
passed all the automatic and human assessment checks.
Now, um, it turns out that
there is not even very good literature that tells you how to collect data.
And in particular, for low-resource languages,
there are a lot of issues related to the quality of the translations.
And so this was a process that we thought would take us a couple of months,
but instead it took us more than six months.
Um, and, but that said, eventually we got a validation set, a test set,
and also a hidden test set because we used
this data for a WMT competition and, um, for that,
they needed to have a test set that was not
available to people to make sure that people were not,
ah, cross-validating on the test set.
And, um, here are some examples of sentences: So
this is from a sentence from the Sinhala Wikipedia,
translating into English a couple of sentences here,
and this from English Wikipedia translating into Sinhala.
I don't know how many people in the audience come from Sri Lanka,
ah, that could appreciate [LAUGHTER] this set.
But, um, one interesting thing that you can already see is that,
if you, although this is totally anecdotal,
because it's just a couple of sentences from,
for Sinhala and English,
you can see that - the topic,
kind of the topic distribution is different.
And - and here you have things that,
ah, would be a little unlikely in English Wikipedia.
And the same is for, ah,
Nepali English and - and English Nepali.
So, ah, we have a GitHub repository where we
host the data and also baseline models that we train on,
ah, publicly available data and then tested on this FloRes benchmark.
And, uh, last week we released
another couple of languages: English Pashto and English Timor,
and we are adding more and more languages,
uh, in the coming months.
So, um, the point of this, ah,
section is just to say that data is oftentime more
important than designing a model because without data in particular,
without a good evaluation benchmark it's
essentially impossible to do research in - in this area.
And collecting data is not trivial.
It's not trivial.
The process the - that you use is - is not, ah,
well-established and, ah, and in practice,
it - it is hard to do.
And another, ah, thing to consider, sorry,
is to, ah, look at the data,
look at the data when you collect it,
and also before you start training your model because you may realize
some issues with the quality of the translations if you speak the language,
oftentimes, English is on one side.
And, or may, you may discover biases or you may discover, ah, interesting things.
So always look at the data, ah,
as opposed to just apply your matter in a black box way.
Um, that concludes my, ah,
little, um, discussion of the data part.
Are there any questions on this?
Why don't people talk about building a language model for low resource languages?
Yeah, yeah, yeah. So in this case what we did, ah,
actually we took, ah,
the Common Crawl data.
And I think I actually don't remember exactly.
So for Nepali I think we had to, ah,
concatenate the Wikipedia data and
the Common Crawl data because the Wikipedia data was just too small.
And we simply train a count-based n-gram.
And then, the count-based n-gram gives you,
I don't know if you study this,
but it gives you the probability of one word given some fixed window of context.
And then, ah, for a given sentence,
we put like, let's say, what is it?
For a given sentence, you would, um,
compute a score for every board,
and then the score of a sentence is simply the average,
ah, low-probability score, ah,
across all the words in the sentence and that will give you a score and
then we will simply have a threshold on that.
And so all the sentences that would score too low,
that would be deemed not fluent enough,
would be sent for rework.
But, of course, um,
whenever you have an entity,
whenever you have, ah, you know,
it's not super reliable and if you go on
languages that are even lower resource than Sinhala than you have,
you don't even have really in domain data like Wikipedia is not in all the languages,
and then it becomes even harder.
And so, oftentimes,
so now that we are scaling this up,
we are looking at, um, language models,
neural language models that are trained in
a multilingual way and that are fine tuned on a small,
ah, in domain, ah,
limiting what they decide if available.
But yeah. Also this type is not particularly,
um, obvious how to do it.
Yeah, sure. So thank you for like this amazing result.
But, I just wanna comment because like,
I've noticed that like Wikipedia actually will have like
different content with different language you choose.
So for example, they'll have like very detailed,
like description of some like basically topic.
And then in other languages,
even if with like really commonly used language like Chinese,
they'll actually just have completely different content or basically simplified content.
So I'm like pretty sure this also gonna happen with like rarely used languages.
So yeah, I - I just,
I just generally think that like Wikipedia might not be like basically.
[OVERLAPPING] You might not be like
very direct reference to the tran - translation. Yeah.
Yeah, yeah, so it - it's an excellent point and this is
something that I'm going to discuss more in the third part of the lecture.
And, um, in a way,
ah, this is the translation problem, right?
So we need to accept the fact that content that is originated in
a certain language may have
a different topic distribution than content that originates in another language.
And what you want to translate is really a content that
originates in - in the source language.
Right? And so you need to - to live with it,
that that's, ah, that's what it is.
[LAUGHTER] So oftentimes in, um,
in the public benchmarks in - in the literature,
you find that people assume that corpora are comparable.
So everything that originates in English,
and - and let's see, Nepali essentially comes from the same kind of sources.
So it's news and it's all news,
talking about similar things.
But in practice, this is not true,
it's not true for Wikipedia,
as you correctly said,
but it's also true for news, right?
Because if - if local news in, ah,
Nepal and local news over here,
ah, it's quite different, right?
So this is a general problem, yeah, and this has
implications in terms of the matters that we are going to use as we will discuss later.
Other questions? Or- I'm not sure if I was clear.
It's really hard to [LAUGHTER] speak without seeing [LAUGHTER] without feedback.
[LAUGHTER] Uh, please- please let me know if- if- if anything is- is not clear.
Okay. Let's talk about modeling.
And this is going to be, um, most of,
uh, our- uh, where we are going to spend most of our time.
So remember that we have this, uh,
funky chart where we have domain and languages
and it's a pretty complicated learning setting.
And here for simplicity,
we are going to focus just on English and Nepali languages.
Um, and we start with the simplest setting ever,
which is Supervised Learning.
Assuming that all data is in the same domain.
So perhaps you have a small training set
and the test set is in the same domain
as the training set- as the parallel training set, okay?
So we denote as x,
the source sentence as y,
the target sentence d. So d is, uh,
the parallel dataset that collects all these sentence pairs, right?
And so this is the typical empirical risk minimization framework
whereby you, uh, you know,
you do supervised learning, in this case,p
you minimize the cross-entropy loss and you want to maximize
the probability of the target sentence given the source sentence.
And so a way to visualize this is to say that,
uh, x, uh, is my English sentence.
It goes to my encoder,
decoder NMT system that produces a prediction,
and then we have a loss that measure the discrepancy between the human reference that,
you know, you took the sentence x, you asked, uh,
your translator that gave you the human reference.
And so the cross-entropy loss measures the discrepancy
between the model prediction and the human reference, right?
Um, now, uh, notice that here I'm denoting with boxes.
Uh, [LAUGHTER] now, uh,
model components, in this case,
the blue box is the encoder that processes English, er, sentences,
and the red box is the decoder that,
uh, operates in Nepali.
And, uh, I just wanted to add one more thing,
which is that if you don't have a lot of parallel data,
you need to regularize.
And so you can do a word k,
uh, which is pretty standard.
So you kind of minimize the L2 norm or the parameters,
but there are also other methods that I think, uh,
in the machine learning class,
you may have seen like dropout where you set to zero at random,
uh, hidden units in your encoder decoder.
Or you can do label smoothing whereby you, um,
uh, in your cross-entropy loss instead of- actually it should be more more over here.
Uh, instead of setting, uh,
um, as a target,
uh, for the correct word.
So this is, uh,
the probability over the whole sequence which you can factorize over,
uh, each individual word by the product, uh, rule.
Uh, so for every word,
you- you- you have the correct,
uh, word that you want- sorry.
At every timestamp, you want to predict the next word.
And now instead of assigning 100% of probability on the, uh, next word,
you- let's say you assign 90% of the probability and the remaining 10%
you evenly distribute across
all the remaining words so that the model is not too overly confident.
So the combinations of these two things are usually good ways to,
um, regularize the system, okay?
So that's the simplest setting.
Now let's see what happens when we have also some source side, uh, monolingual data.
So here now we have a- an additional dataset that has only,
uh, sentences in the source- in the source language, English.
So in addition to d,
now we have also, uh,
M_s, which is the monolingual data on the source, uh, side.
And so we have a bunch of X's.
So typically, M is much greater than N, right?
And now, a typical way to use, uh, uh,
this data is to model the marginal distribution of the data of x, right?
And so there are many ways to do that.
One way that has proven to be pretty effective
in machine translation is to do denoising autoencoding.
And so here the idea is that, um,
you have something similar to what we had before,
except that now the input is taken from this monolingual dataset, okay?
And you add noise to it,
and I'm going to describe the noise in a- in a second.
And then the, er, job, uh,
of the encoder decoder is simply to denoise the noisy input.
And the cross-entropy loss measure the discrepancy
between the cle- the prediction and the actual clean input.
But now notice that the decoder is not
this red decoder because the decoder now is a decoder that operates in English,
but the encoder does not.
The encoder is- uh,
is, uh, the same that you have seen here.
So again, the- uh,
the loss function here is,
er, very similar to before, except that,
uh, the target is the clean input x,
and the input is,
uh, a noisifed version of x.
So in this case,
we are not predicting something in Nepali but something in English.
So this is a, uh,
if you want the limitation of- of this work,
but this is useful because you are anyway,
doing some good modeling of,
uh, the input sentences,
and you're gonna train the encoder parameters that are going to
be shared with your supervised system.
So the encoder is shared between,
um, uh, the translation task on parallel data, right?
And the denoising auto-encoder task.
So essentially you have an encoder and two decoders.
One that operates in Nepali,
one that operates in English.
And, um, so in terms of noise,
there are essentially two types of noise that we have been using in our work.
Others are possible, but, uh,
in the simplest case, you can drop words or swap words.
So assume that the input sentence is,
"The cat sat on the mat."
Then if you swap words, you may, uh,
provide at the input "The cat the on sat mat."
And so here the encoder decoder needs to understand a little bit of the- the syntax,
the grammatical rules in order to reorder.
If you drop- let's say you drop the last word,
"The cat sat on the," then, uh,
the model needs to understand a little bit of the semantics because it needs to assign,
a higher probability to mat now, right?
And so you can see that there is a little bit of,
uh, so there are two hyperparameters here.
So one- actually, there are several ways to use denoising auto-encoding.
So you can use denoising auto-encoding as a way to pre-train the encoder.
Or you can use it, uh,
as auxiliary loss when you do supervised learning.
So you can have this term plus Lambda, this term, okay?
So both ways are fine.
And, uh, so there is a very critical hyperparameter here,
which is the level of noise.
If you don't have any noise or if the noise level is too low,
then this task is trivial because of the attention,
you can simply copy the input.
And so the encoder and the decoder don't need to learn anything.
If the noise level is too high,
then you destroy the input here.
So the encoder is not useful and you just do language modeling using the decoder.
But remember that this decoder is then, uh,
not use- used for translation because, uh,
what you use for- in machine translation system is- is the encoder box, right?
The encoder module. Okay, so,
uh, there are other ways to use source-side monolingual data.
In addition to denoising of encoding,
you could also do, uh,
self-training, which is a method that comes from the '90s, if not earlier.
And the idea is very simple.
So again, you take a sentence from
your source-side monolingual dataset and you add noise to it,
and then you have an encoder decoder that tries to
this time translate from this noisy input, okay?
And now what's the reference?
The reference is given by a stale version of your machine translation system, okay?
Where the reference is produced by, let's say beam.
And so, uh, the cross-entropy loss is then going to measure the discrepancy between
your prediction and what the prediction from- from a stale version of your system gave.
And the reason why this works is that when you do beam,
you actually typically, um,
produce better quality, uh, outputs.
And so when you train,
now this encoder-decoder by cross-entropy loss,
you're going to learn the decoding process, okay?
And so this is something good for you.
In addition, when you train,
you inject noise and,
and the noise is regularizing,
it's kind of smoothing out your prediction space.
And so if you're predicting correctly one sentence now also nearby sentences,
and by nearby I mean sentences that are similar phrases
so they have a good overlap with the current sentence,
are gonna be more likely predicted correctly.
And so we have this paper where we analyze a little bit, uh, these aspects.
And so the algorithm is very simple.
And so first you train your machine translation system on the parallel data,
and then you repeat the following process.
So first you decode your monolingual dataset using your current,
uh, machine translation system.
And you make a new, uh,
parallel data set of sentences from your monolingual dataset with,
sorry, with the, ah,
translations from your current system.
And then you retrain the model,
this p of y- p of y given x on the union of
your original parallel data plus this, uh, auxiliary dataset.
And so here you have two hyperparameters.
One is the noise level and the other is
the hyperparameters that weight this, ah, auxiliary dataset.
So this is set training loss, okay?
Now let's- so that's- that concludes how we can use a source-side monolingual data.
Let me say a word about how we can use target-side monolingual data.
So you could use the target-side monolingual data, uh,
to train a language model and then train
the machine translation system in the residual space.
So this language model.
But it turns out that there is a much more effective way to leverage this data,
and that's called back translation.
So at the high level,
it works as follows.
So you take a sentence from your target-side monolingual data set, y_t here.
And on the parallel dataset,
you train also backward machine translation system
that goes from Nepali to English, okay?
So that's- so now you have a red encoder that takes Nepali and,
and the blue decoder that was in
the English space and so you map the sentence into English,
this Nepali sentence into English.
And now this may not be a correct translation but it's
a noisy input that you feed to your encoder-decoder that you want to train, right?
And so now the input is noisy,
but the target here is clean because it
comes from the original target-side monolingual dataset.
And so this is a very powerful algorithm because, um,
unlike cell training, here the targets are clean but the input is a little noisy,
and that's usually much better than having clean inputs but noisy targets, right?
Because the targets affect
essentially all the other signals that you backpropagate through the NMT systems.
And this is- and you can see back translation is
a way to do data augmentation because you
produce noisy version of inputs, ah,
for a given target,
a little bit like in vision where they do,
uh, well, I guess this is not the right audience to,
to do this analogy,
but it should work on vision you- you will do scaling,
rotation, different cropping, and that's a little bit similar to what we are doing here.
And so the algorithm again is,
you train, er, backward and then forward machine translation system on the parallel data.
And then you use your backward model to decode
the target-side monolingual dataset to produce an auxiliary parallel dataset.
And then you concatenate the,
the, the two datasets,
the original parallel data set and the auxiliary one
to train the new foreword model, okay?
Of course you can combine set training and back translation.
So if you have both source monolingual dataset and target monolingual dataset,
you can do the following.
So, uh, you can use the parallel data to train the forward and
the backward machine translation system and then at step two you
can use the forward model to decode- to
translate the source-side monolingual dataset into, uh, this data.
And you can use the backward machine translation system to
translate the target-side monolingual dataset into these, uh, translations, okay?
And then you treat these parallel sentences as
real data and you concatenate them to the parallel dataset.
And now you retrain both the forward and the backward machine translation systems.
And now as long as these two improve,
then you can go and do another iteration whereby you, again,
you read the code,
retranslate the source and the target-side monolingual dataset and then you go,
ah, and you retrain them.
And this is as far as I know,
the most effective way to leverage monolingual data in low-resource languages nowadays.
Lemme talk a little bit about how we can do multilingual training.
So in this case we have parallel datasets on different language pairs.
And, uh, so you have a parallel dataset for English-Nepali,
one for English-Hindi, one for Hindi-English,
or Nepali-Hindi, or any subset of these.
And this is super simple.
So the way that it works is that,
you have a single encoder and a single decoder, okay?
And you train by supervised learning.
The only change that needs to be made is that,
at the input of the encoder you concatenate also a
token that specifies the language in which you want to translate.
And so the encoder will learn to process multiple languages.
The decoder will learn to the- to produce
multiple languages as one and it will pick
the language based on the token specified by the encoder input.
And so training is just minimizing the cross-entropy loss for
all the parallel datasets that you have where you simply add an extra token,
ah, in the source sentence that specifies the target,
uh, language that you want to translate.
And the only thing that I wanted to add on this is that often
times it helps if you pre-process the data
by- I'm not sure if you learn about bipolar encoding sentence pieces,  essentially ways
to segment words into syllables or frequent, um, character n-grams.
And so if you concatenate this data in order to learn these ways to segment the data,
then it's also possible that for
many languages there is a good fraction of the dictionary that is shared.
And so this also helps,
making sure that you can do a good job translating multiple languages at one- at once.
And so my- the conclusion so far is that even without domain effect,
there are a lot of training paradigms depending on the available data that you have.
A priori, it's very hard to tell which method works
best nowadays because it really depends on how much data you have,
how different are the domains and-
and what is the language pair that you are working with.
For instance, the domains may be very different,
but if you have a lot of data,
maybe, um, it doesn't matter much.
In practice, we have keen regions denoising with encoding by translation,
multilingual training that we're pretty wide.
And nowadays, the field is
at the stage in which we are trying to figure out the best way to combine them.
And right now there is a lot of what I would say,
craftsmanship to figure out how to best combine them.
And, um, but hopefully we can
find- and I think there is a lot of
effort in trying to automate this process because right now,
um, there is a lot of cross-validation I would
say to figure out all these hyperparameters.
So the open challenges here is- are,
dealing with a diversity of domain or domains,
dealing with datasets that have very wildly different translation quality,
some are very noisy, some are very clean,
dealing with different- with datasets of
different size and very different language pairs.
And yeah.
And so I would say that in general,
it may be counter-intuitive,
but working low-resource machine translation doesn't
mean training small models on small data.
But actually means training even bigger models on
even more data because you need to compensate for the lack of supervision that you have,
of direct supervision that you have.
Very good. Before I go on,
are there any questions?
Um, yeah. I just had a quick question regarding,
um- in the- in a few of the previous algorithms that you described,
is it necessary to retrain entirely,
um, like retrain the model entirely,
or is there some way to augment the model or fine-tune it on the,
um, on the generated-
So actually what usually happens is that as you iterate,
you can make the model bigger.
So when you train on the parallel data set,
usually this is not much data and so you need to train in something small.
Otherwise, you over- overfit too much.
But once you add, uh,
the monolingual data that you- this,
uh, A_t data set,
then this model can be much bigger than the original model.
Now, it's not super obvious how to,
uh, you know, initialize a bigger model from a smaller model.
[LAUGHTER] And so that's why people usually initialize from random.
At the next iterations, you can,
um, initialize from the model at the previous iteration.
Uh, what we usually find is that initializing at random usually works as well.
Gotcha. Thank you.
Thank you. Okay. Any other question?
When you say, uh, usually the model launch, ah,
I was wondering do you mean that you add, ah,
more layers with more parameters,
ah, as the model keeps training?
Uh, usually you just make it bigger.
Yeah. Um, yeah, the more layers, more parameter.
So whether it is wider or- or deeper,
um, I think usually, um- yeah.
I'm not entirely sure there is a definite answer on that.
Um, usually making the encoder deeper is a good thing.
[LAUGHTER] Making the decoder deeper doesn't buy you much.
Um, so usually we play with the encoder, I would say.
And, um- but yeah, uh,
there is not so much difference in practice,
uh, I would say. Um, yeah.
So you can imagine just double the size of your hidden state, that would work.
Okay? Okay. So let's see how
this- so I- I didn't speak about models but I spoke about algorithms.
So you can turn these algorithms into models a little
bit and talk about joint distribution, marginal distribution.
But in my view,
it's just simpler to think in terms of algorithms because also the way that,
uh, we implement them.
And so let's see how these algorithms can be put
together in some interesting case studies.
So actually I realize that I'm really going slow.
So let's see the case where you only have monolingual data and no parallel data.
So this is what we call unsupervised machine translation.
So let's say that you have an English and a French data set, uh,
this is not a typical use-case of
unsupervised machine translation but this is where it works really well.
So let's focus for this for now.
And so you take a sentence from the target monolingual data set,
you go through your encoder-decoder,
and you produce an English translation.
Obviously, you don't have the reference here.
So what you could do is to feed this to a machine translation system
that goes from English to French so that
you kind of reconstruct the original French sentence.
And now you have- you can have another signal
to back-propagate through your machine translation system.
And you can do the same going from English to French to English.
This is very much what people have done in vision.
They call it, uh, cycle consistency.
You can see this as an auto-encoder where the intermediate representation is uh,
er, you know, er, is a language in- in English.
The problem is that, the- as it is,
the model is not constrained to produce something that is,
uh, a fluent English sentence.
So in the vision domain,
people use adversarial training,
but in NLP it's kinda tricky because this is a discrete sequence.
And so in order to make sure that this decoder
produces English- fluent English sentences,
you could imagine to do denoising auto-encoding, all right?
So you could take a no- you could take an English sentence,
noisify it, go through your denoising auto-encoding.
Now, this decoder is the same block that you have here,
it's gonna be forced to learn the statistics and the regularities of the English language.
The problem is that if you look at this decoder,
this decoder is, in the denoising auto-encoding game,
it is operating on the output of this encoder that takes English as input,
while here, encoder takes French as input.
It could be very well be the case that
the representation produced by these two encoders is different.
So this decoder may work very well in this setting,
but not in this setting.
And so in other ways,
how can we make sure that these red and blue blocks are interchangeable?
How can we make sure that there is good modularity?
And so- so one way to do this is to use the trick that we use for multilingual training,
whereby we have a single encoder and a single decoder.
So the decoder is shared across French and English,
and the encoder is shared across English and French.
And we specify the target language by an extra token, ah, at the input.
And so in particular,
if you learn, ah,
common VPs and if you share parameters,
then this process- sorry,
this process really works well and- and you have
an- a decoder that operates well with an- ah,
whenever it is fed with a hidden state that comes from
an encoder operating on English or French.
And so again, the ke- key ingredients are iterative backtranslation,
denoising auto-encoding and multi-lingual training.
And for unsupervised machine translation,
we do, uh, back translation in an
online manner whereby for a given mini-batch,
we do, uh, back translation.
We don't do it, uh,
with the stale version on the model but you could do that, well, that works less well.
And so when you do this on English-French, you find,
uh- actually you can get pretty good performance.
A BLEU of 30 usually gives you pretty fluent translations that are, uh, also adequate.
And, uh, if you compare that to what you got with the, er,
supervised baseline that is trained on the parallel data set,
you find that training on
10 million monolingual sentences
in English and 10 million French gives you the same, uh,
translation accuracy than training a supervised baseline,
that is this, um,
uh, red curve- actually this red curve- this blue curve and this red curve.
This is the neural version,
this is the phrase-based version with 100,000 parallel sentences.
So in other words,
each parallel sentence pair is equivalent to 100 monolinguals sentences.
Equivalent in the sense that they give you a machine translation system
of similar, uh, um, accuracy.
And so now the more the domains are different,
and the more the languages are different from each other, the worse it gets.
And so that's why when you do low-resource machine translation,
this is the extreme case of unsupervised machine translation,
you need to learn from lots of data in order to
compensate for the lack of direct supervision. Um-
I'm gonna, um, maybe give you, uh,
an example on FloRes where for the FloRes,
as we have seen there was no in-domain parallel data.
There was some monolingual data that was in domain.
But not very much,
and there was quite a bit of auto- auto domain parallel data,
you remember the one we used sentences from,
um, Bible and Ubuntu.
And then we have quite a bit of monolingual data that is auto domain.
And so this is the supervised baseline.
Unsupervised machine translation here didn't work at all because very much like was
mentioning the- the Wikipedia domains are not quite, uh, aligned.
And so this doesn't have unsupervised machine translation.
If you do back translation,
if you do iterative back-translation,
you do quite a bit better than the supervised baseline,
which is quite good.
But now if you add those, so English-Hindi,
parallel data, you do quite a bit better.
And now also the unsupervised machine translation works.
It's unsupervised for English- English-Nepali,
but you do have supervision for English-Hindi.
And so the combination of backtranslation and,
um, multilingual training is here, the winning combination.
And this is something that we see, uh, through in general.
Okay? So I'm gonna skip the results on English-Burmese.
Actually I had a nice demo.
But I'm going to show it to you later if there is time.
Um, and so, as I said,
we have quite a few good components which we can combine pretty easily.
Right now the research is about how to best combine them,
how to best weigh datasets,
how to best weigh the examples in order to automate
the current cross-validation based process, I would say.
And the other message here is that
it's- low-resource machine translation is a big data problem.
It- it requires big compute,
it's a pretty big engineering feat.
Uh, in order to, uh,
compensate for the lack of parallel data.
Are there any questions on this?
I- I was just wondering when you mentioned that the parallel to, um,
vision in cycle consistency, um,
you mentioned that we can't do adversarial training-
Yeah.
-and I was just wondering if you could flesh that out and wh we couldn't just
use say like an LSTM that performs adversarial training better.
Yeah. Yes. So there are actually a bunch of papers trying to do, um,
adversarial training or, uh,
dense style training for, uh, text generation.
I must say that it's a pretty active research area.
I haven't seen a very compelling demonstration
that these methods work very well with, we've tried.
And it's a little difficult to backpropagate.
So when this produces a sentence,
you need to produce a,
you know, a sentence and that's discrete.
And so you could backpropagate using reinforce kind of methods.
You could do a lot of these things but essentially-
it's just a little hard to make it work and it's very finicky.
So it may work on simple datasets,
but at scale, it's very hard to.
So another thing- another consideration is that
anything that you do has to work at scale.
Because again, the value- the amount of
information that you get from a monolingual sentence is not very much.
And now if you do a lot of compute,
if you- or if your gradients have a lot of noise, uh,
like when you train with reinforce,
then, uh, it's not going to work.
But it's possible that people may come up with ways to make it work.
I don't think this is true at present,
but it could be in the future.
So let me spend five minutes on the analysis, um,
and then you will have the slides so you can,
uh, go over the remaining details.
So here, uh, we- so the- the starting point is to say, well,
if I want to simulate
low-resource machine translation with a high resource language like French to English.
Let's say you take EuroParl data, you have,
let's say 20,000 parallel sentences and 100,000 monolingual target sentences,
and you apply backtranslation,
you get a very nice improvement.
Now, if you come here to Facebook,
[LAUGHTER] and- and you try this on Facebook data,
you find that the improvement is actually very, very minimal.
And that relates to the discussion that we had at the very beginning,
that what people talk about in different parts of the world is very different.
And so now you- you need- it's like you need to align two, uh,
point clouds, but the distribution in these two point clouds is very,
very different from each other,
and so it's very difficult to align them.
And so here I was making the example that
even for English speaking countries, if you look at
topics on- on sports,
you have that- in America people may
talk more about Football and Baseball while in the UK,
more about Cricket and Soccer, right?
And so for the same topic,
you have different distribution words,
but you also have a different distribution of topics.
And so this is what we call the source target domain mismatch.
So you may have several kinds of domain mismatch.
Typically, you have a mismatch
between the training distribution and the test distribution.
Here I'm talking also about the mismatch between the source domain,
the source language, the source domain,
and the target domain.
Okay? And so there is a hypothesis that this may make backtranslation
less effective because even if you were to
perfectly translate target side monolingual data,
once you translate it,
it's going to be out of domain, uh,
with respect to the data that you really want to translate,
which originates in the source domain.
And so we had a very,
uh, nice controlled setting,
to study this problem.
Um, where, uh, we create
a syntactic dataset where the source domain comes from EuroParl data,
and the target domain counts from OpenSubtitles,
which are movie captions.
And now, by creating the target domain as a mixture of the two,
you can precisely control the amount of,
uh, in-domainess between the source and the target domain.
And by varying Alpha,
you can vary that.
And so the major result is this figure,
where Alpha measures how much is the target domain,
uh, similar to the source domain.
So if Alpha is equal to 1,
they are all, uh, in the same domain.
If Alpha is equal to 0, they are very different.
One is EuroParl and the other is OpenSubtitles.
And so it turns out that in these extreme regime,
actually set training, which is this red line,
works better than backtranslation.
But as you make the domains more and more similar,
backtranslation is much better than set training.
And both of them are much better than,
um, just if you were to use the parallel data.
Um, so I'm going to skip all of this.
You can look at the paper,
uh, and the slides.
I want to conclude that there are other things that I didn't talk about, like filtering.
This is one of the most exciting things nowadays,
and the idea is to, uh,
essentially learn a joint embedding space for sentences
by simply training a multilingual system on lots of public available data,
and then you use this in order to do nearest neighbor retrieval
of a sentence for what the corresponding translation would be in other languages.
And they found that- they collected
a large data set and they were able to beat the performance of
state of the art machine translation system
on high-resource languages like English-German, English-Russian.
And the idea is that by using much more data, although noisy,
you can do better than using a curated,
high-quality dataset, and this is something that we see over and over.
And again, the idea here is that we need to figure out
how to best combine backtranslation, this filtering, multilingual,
and pretraining in order to, uh, uh, get, uh,
the best combination ever for solving or for improving low-resource machine translation.
And so I just want to- maybe I should conclude here,
uh, by thanking my collaborators and by, uh,
telling you that, um, uh,
if you have any questions about this lecture,
you can always e-mail me,
drop me a line, I'd be happy to follow up.
And also, in my lab,
we have a lot of opportunities,
from internships to full-time positions as a research scientist, research engineer.
So if you're interested or are curious,
just also, uh, drop me an e-mail. Okay. Thank you.
Thanks a lot, Marc'Aurelio.
Um, so- so maybe there's still a few people that might have questions.
And we are happy to stay a few more minutes for questions.
Happy to answer questions.
Yes.
Uh, I'd love to learn more about the models that you used.
Uh, actually, should we- should we go back to the model that you first talked
about- spoke about, right, before back-translation?
Uh, in order to understand, uh,
you have a pipeline from English to English, right?
In this one, uh, you want something like, uh,
you- the data augmentation techniques
like in vision such as dropping the word or switching,
uh, switching words to be able to make an augmented dataset, is that right?
That's right.
So the analogy that I made is,
for back-translation were, yes,
all these methods, essentially,
you don't have x and y- golden x and y pairs,
and so for set training,
what you do, you,
uh, fantasize the target.
For back-translation, you fantasize the input.
And so you can see all these methods as a way in particular, back-translation,
is very similar to the data augmentation that people do in vision in the sense that here,
the transformation is not, uh, rule-based,
it's produced by a backward machine translation system,
but it does the same objective of regularizing by adding a lot of noisy,
uh, uh, labeled data.
So if you go back to the previous slide,
when you say you fantasize the- the target.
So in this case, you have, uh,
one where you- where you predict the goal target and one
where you- where you change the input and then predict the target,
is that how it is?
Yeah. So in- for set training,
the way that it works is that you take the clean input,
you pass it through your machine translation system at the previous iteration.
And, uh, you decode with beam or with other methods,
and you got a prediction for what the label should be.
And that- that's now your reference.
But the way that you train your machine translation system is by noisifying the input.
So you add noise to your input and the noise is you drop words,
you swap words, and then you try to predict the,
uh, target that you fantasize.
And the idea is that the- that the two targets should be the same?
Yeah. So the prediction and- and these targets,
when you train with cross-entropy loss,
you- you try to tie them together as much as possible.
Okay. Thanks so much. I have a followup question, later.
Yeah. This is a very- this is one of the first semi-supervised learning methods that,
uh, you find in the machine learning community.
There are a lot of variants of this where they have perhaps, er, uh, uh,
a community of experts that produces the, uh- the label.
Um, there are a lot of variants of this and, um,
it's something that makes a lot of sense,
particularly for asymmetric tasks.
Like if you do, image speci- if you do text classification,
if you do summarization,
then back-translation is not really applicable because,
uh, you know, if you go from a label category- from a categorical,
uh, uh, input to a whole sentence,
that's a very difficult task, right?
So back-translation works really well for symmetric tasks like, uh, machine translation.
But for, uh, things that are,
uh- for many-to-one mapping,
self-training is definitely- definitely works better.
Uh, self-training works well also in machine translation when
there is a lot of domain mismatch between the source and the target as we're seeing.
Yeah. So unfortunately, these algorithms- so it's hard to
say in general what works best because it really depends on the application,
it really depends on the kind of data that you have.
Dose anyone else have a question they'd like to ask?
Well, it seems like we're maybe not getting another immediate question.
And I guess we have gone through the end of the time,
that we're, uh, meant to do.
So maybe we should call it and bring it to a close,
but thank you so much, Marc'Aurelio.
I mean, I hope everyone really enjoyed that.
And I, you know, speaking as someone who did work in machine translation for a decade,
though I haven't so much for the last few years,
I mean, you know,
it actually still seems to me just amazing how successfully you can build things,
um, with these, um,
building with monolingual data and using ideas like the back-translation.
I mean, it's just actually incredible that that's providing such competitive,
um, machine translation systems now.
And, you know, obviously,
this is something that isn't just of academic interest,
as you might have realized if you've thought about it, right?
If you're at a company like Facebook, right?
Being able- actually able to translate well data on domains that are very
far from news data or the Bible [LAUGHTER]
and in languages of smaller communities of speakers,
it's just actually super-duper important, um,
to people being happy users of and members of communities.
Yeah. And- and I just want to add,
uh, the kind of- these methods are pretty general,
so we apply them to summarization,
Q&A, uh, style transfer.
So, you know, it's really beautiful that- it's a set of
tools that you can use them in many places and it's all about,
you know, in a way, um,
aligning domains with little, uh,
supervision or correspondences, right?
So, yeah.
Okay. Thank you very much.
Thank you. Thank you. Bye. Bye-bye.
Bye.