OK, so what are we
going to do for today?
So the main content
for today is to go
through sort of more
stuff about word vectors,
including touching
on word senses
and then introducing the notion
of neural network classifiers.
So our biggest goal is that
by the end of today's class
you should feel like
you could confidently
look at one of the
word embeddings papers,
such as the Google word2vec
paper or the GLoVe paper
or Sanjeev Arora's paper
that we'll come to later.
And feel like yeah, I
can understand this.
I know what they're
doing and it makes sense.
So let's go back
to where we were.
So this was introducing
this model of word2vec
and [AUDIO OUT] idea was that
we started with random word
vectors and then
we're going to--
we have a big corpus
of text and we're
going to iterate through each
word in the whole corpus.
And for each
position we're going
to try and predict what words
surround our center word.
And we're going to do that
with a probability distribution
that's defined in terms of the
dot product between the word
vectors for the center
word and the context words.
And so that will
give a probability
estimate of a word appearing
in the context of into.
Well actual words did
occur in the context
of into on this occasion.
So what we're
going to want to do
is sort of make it more likely
that turning problems, banking,
and crises will turn up
in the context of into.
And so that's learning,
updating the word vectors
so that they can predict actual
surrounding words better.
And then the thing
that's almost magical
is that doing no more than
this simple algorithm,
this allows us to
learn word vectors that
capture well word similarity
and meaningful directions
in a wordspace.
So more precisely, right,
for this model the only
parameters of this model
are the word vectors.
So we have outside word
vectors and center word vectors
for each word.
And then we're taking
their dot product
to get a probability--
well, we're
taking a dot product
to get a score
of how likely a
particular outside word is
to occur with the center word.
And then we're using the
softmax transformation
to convert those scores into
probabilities as I discussed
last time, and I kind of come
back to at the end this time.
A couple of things
to note, this model
is what we call in NLP,
a bag of words model.
So bag of words
models are models
that don't actually pay
any attention to word order
or position.
It doesn't matter if you're
next to the center word
or a bit further away
on the left or right.
The probability estimate
would be the same.
And that seems like a very
crude model of language
that will offend any linguist.
And it is a very crude
model of language.
And we'll move on to better
models of language as we go on.
But even that crude
model of language
is enough to learn quite a
lot about the probabilities--
sorry, quite a lot about
the properties of words.
And then the second
note is well,
with this model we
wanted to give reasonably
high probabilities
to the words that
do occur in the context
of the center word,
at least if they
do so at all often.
But obviously lots of
different words can occur.
So we're not talking about
probabilities like 0.3 and 0.5.
We're more likely
going to be talking
about probabilities like
0.01 and numbers like that.
Well, how do we achieve that?
And well, the way that the
word2vec model achieves this--
and this is the learning
phase of the model--
is to place words that
are similar in meaning
close to each other in this
high dimensional vector space.
So again, you can't
read this one.
But if we scroll
into this one we
see lots of words that are
similar in meaning grouped
close together in the space.
So here are days of the week
like Tuesday, Thursday, Sunday,
and also Christmas over.
What else do we have, we
have Samsung and Nokia,
this is a diagram I made
quite a few years ago.
So that's when Nokia was
still an important maker
of cell phones.
We have various sort of fields
like mathematics and economics
over here.
So we group words that
are similar in meaning.
Actually one more note I wanted
to make on this, I mean again,
this is a two
dimensional picture,
which is all I can
show you on a slide.
And it's done with the
principal components projection
that you also used
in the assignment.
Something important to
remember but hard to remember
is that high dimensional spaces
have very different properties
to the two dimensional
spaces that we can look at.
And so in particular,
word vector
can be close to
many other things
in a high dimensional
space but close to them
on different dimensions.
OK, so I've mentioned
doing learning.
So the next question
is, well how
do we learn good word vectors?
And this was the bit that
I didn't quite hook up
at the end of last class.
So for a while in the last
I said oh gee, calculus.
And we have to work out the
gradient of the loss function
with respect to
the parameters that
will allow us to make progress.
But I didn't sort of
altogether put that together.
So what we're going
to do is we start off
with random word vectors.
We initialize them
to small numbers,
near 0 in each dimension.
We've defined our
loss function J,
which we looked at last time.
And then we're going to
use a gradient descent
algorithm, which is an
iterative algorithm that
learns to maximize J of
theta by changing theta.
And so the idea
of this algorithm
is that from the
current values of theta
you calculate the
gradient j of theta.
And then what you're going
to do is make a small step
in the direction of
the negative gradient.
So the gradient is
pointing upwards.
And we're taking a small
step in the direction
of the negative of the
gradient to gradually move down
towards the minimum.
And so one of the
parameters of neural nets
that you can fiddle in
your software package
is what is the step size.
So if you take a really,
really itsy bitsy step,
it might take you a long time
to minimize the function.
You do a lot of
wasted computation.
On the other hand, if your
step size is much too big, well
then you can actually
diverge and start
going to worse places.
Or even if you are going
downhill a little bit,
then what's going to
happen is you're then
going to end up
bouncing back and forth.
And it'll take you much
longer to get to the minimum.
OK, in this picture I
have a beautiful quadratic
and it's easy to minimize it.
Something that you might
know about neural networks
is that in general
they're not convex.
So you could think that this
is just all going to go awry.
But the truth is in practice
life works out to be OK.
But I think I won't get
into that more right
now and come back to
that in the later class.
So this is our gradient descent.
So we have the current values
of the parameters theta.
We then walk a little bit
in the negative direction
of the gradient using
our learning rate or step
size alpha.
And that gives us
new parameter values
where that means that
these are vectors
but for each
individual parameter
we're updating it a
little bit by working out
the partial derivative of j
with respect to that parameter.
So that's the simple
gradient descent algorithm.
Nobody uses it and
you shouldn't use it.
The problem is that
our j is a function
of all windows in the corpus.
Remember we're doing this
sum over every center
word in the entire corpus.
And we'll often have billions
of words in the corpus.
So actually working
out J of theta
or the gradient of J of theta
would be extremely, extremely
expensive.
Because we have to iterate
over our entire corpus.
So you'd wait a very
long time before you
made a single gradient update.
And so optimization
would be extremely slow.
And so basically 100% of the
time in neural network land
we don't use gradient descent.
We instead use what's called
stochastic gradient descent.
And stochastic gradient descent
is a very simple modification
of this.
So rather than working out
an estimate of the gradient
based on the entire
corpus, you simply
take one center word or a small
batch like 32 center words
and you work out an estimate
of the gradient based on them.
Now that estimate
of the gradient
will be noisy and bad
because you've only
looked at a small fraction
of the corpus rather
than the whole corpus.
But nevertheless, you can use
that estimate of the gradient
to update your theta parameters
in exactly the same way.
And so this is the
algorithm that we can do.
And so then if we have
a billion word corpus
we can if we do it
on each center word.
We can make a billion
updates to the parameters
we pass through the corpus
once rather than only making
one more accurate
update to the parameters
once you've been
through the corpus.
So overall, we can learn
several orders of magnitude
more quickly.
And so this is the
algorithm that you'll
be using everywhere, including
right from the beginning,
from our assignments.
Again, just an extra
comment of more complicated
stuff we'll come back to.
[AUDIO OUT] the gradient descent
is a sort of performance hack
that lets you learn
much more quickly.
It turns out it's not
only a performance hack.
Neural nets have some quite
counter intuitive properties.
And actually the fact that
stochastic gradient descent
is kind of noisy and bounces
around as it does its thing.
It actually means that
in complex networks
it learns better
solutions than if you
were to run plain gradient
descent very slowly.
So you can both compute
much more quickly
and do a better job.
OK, one final note on running
stochastic gradients with word
vectors, this is an aside.
But something to
note is that if we're
doing a stochastic gradient
update based on one window,
then actually in
that window we'll
have seen almost none
of our parameters.
Because if we have a window
of something like five words
to either side of
the center word,
we've seen at most 11
distinct word types.
So we will have gradient
information for those 11 words
but the other 100,000 odd
words in our vocabulary
will have no gradient
update information.
So this will be a very,
very sparse gradient update.
So if you're only
thinking math, you
can just have your
entire gradient
and use the equation
that I showed before.
But if you're thinking
systems optimization,
then you'd want to
think, well actually I
only want to update the
parameters for a few words.
And there have to be and there
are much more efficient ways
that I could do that.
And so this is
another aside but it
will be useful for your
assignment so I will say it.
Up until now when I
presented word vectors,
I presented them
as column vectors.
And that makes the most
sense if you think about it
as a piece of math.
Whereas actually in all
common deep learning
packages including
PyTorch that we're using,
word vectors are actually
represented as row vectors.
And if you remember back to
the representation of matrices
in CS107 or something
like that, that you'll
know that that's then obviously
efficient for representing
words.
Because then you can access
an entire word vector
as a continuous range of memory,
different if you're in Fortran.
Anyway, so actually
our word vectors
will be row vectors when you
look at those inside PyTorch.
OK, now I wanted
to say a bit more
about the word2vec
algorithm family.
And also what you're
going to do in homework 2.
So if you're still meant to be
working on homework 1, which
remember is due
next Tuesday, that
really actually
with today's content
we're starting into homework 2.
And I'll kind of go through the
first part of homework 2 today
and the other stuff you
need to know for homework 2.
So I mentioned briefly
the idea that we
have two separate vectors
for each word type.
The center vector and
the outside vectors.
And we just average
them both at the end.
They're similar but not
identical for multiple reasons,
including the random
initialization
and the stochastic
gradient descent.
You can implement a
word2vec algorithm
with just one vector per word.
And actually, if you do
it works slightly better.
But it makes the algorithm
much more complicated.
And the reason for
that is sometimes you
will have the same word type as
the center word and the context
word.
And that means that when
you're doing your calculus
at that point, you've then
got this sort of messy case
that just for that word
you're getting a dot product--
you're getting a
dot product of x
dot x term, which makes it sort
of much messier to work out.
And so that's why we use
this simple optimization
of having two vectors per word.
OK, so for the word2vec model as
introduced in the Mikolov et al
paper in 2013, it wasn't
really just one algorithm.
It was a family of algorithms.
So there were two
basic model variants.
One was called the
skip-gram model,
which is the one that
I've explained to you.
That [AUDIO OUT] outside
words position independent
given the center word in a
bag of words style model.
The other one was called the
Continuous Bag of Words model,
CBOW.
And in this one you
predict the center word
from a bag of context words.
Both of these give
similar results.
The skip-gram one is more
natural in various ways.
So it's sort of normally the
one that people have gravitated
to in subsequent work.
But then as to how
you train this model.
What I've presented so far is
the naive softmax equation,
which is a simple but relatively
expensive training method.
And so that isn't
really what they
suggest using in the paper.
They suggest using
a method that's
called negative sampling.
So an acronym
you'll see sometimes
is SGNS, which means
skip-grams negative sampling.
So let me just say a little
bit about what this is.
But actually, doing
the skip-gram model
with negative sampling is
the part of homework 2.
So you'll get to
know this model well.
So the point is that if
you use this naive softmax
even though people commonly
do use this naive softmax
in various neural net models.
That working out the
denominator is pretty expensive.
And that's because you
have to iterate over
every word in the vocabulary
and work out these dot products.
So if you have a
100,000 word vocabulary,
you have to do
100,000 dot products
to work out the denominator.
And that seems a
little bit of a shame.
And so instead of that, the
idea of negative sampling
is instead of using
this softmax we're
going to train binary logistic
regression models for both the
the true pair of center word and
the context word versus noise
pairs where we keep the
true center word and we just
randomly sample words
from the vocabulary.
So as presented in the
paper, the idea is like this.
So overall what we
want to optimize
is still an average of the
loss for each particular center
word.
But for when we're
working out the loss
for each particular center
word, we're going to work out--
sorry, the loss for
each particular center
word in each particular
window, we're
going to take the dot product
as before of the center
word and the outside word.
And that's sort of
the main quantity.
But now instead of using
that inside the softmax,
we're going to put it through
the logistic function, which
is sometimes often also
called the sigmoid function,
the name logistic
is more precise
so that's this function here.
So the logistic function
is a handy function
that will map any real number
to a probability between 0 and 1
open interval.
So basically if the
dot product is large,
the logistic of the dot
product will be virtually 1.
OK, so we want this to be large.
And then what we'd
like is on average we'd
like the dot product between
the center word and words
that we just chose
randomly, i.e.
they most likely didn't
actually occur in the context
of the center word to be small.
And there's just
one little trick
of how this is done, which
is this sigmoid function is
symmetric and so if we want
this probability to be small,
we can take the negative
of the dot product.
So we're wanting
it to be over here.
The dot product of a random
word and the center word
is a negative number.
And so then we're going to
take the negation of that
and then again once we put
that through the sigmoid,
we'd like a big number.
OK, so the way they're
presenting things,
they're actually
maximizing this quantity.
But if I go back to making it
a bit more similar to the way
we had written
things, we'd worked
with minimizing the
negative log likelihood.
So it looks like this.
So we're taking the negative
log likelihood of the sigmoid
of the dot product.
Again, negative log
likelihood, we're
using the same negated dot
product through the sigmoid.
And then we're going to
work out this quantity
for a handful of random words.
We k-negative samples and
how likely they are to sample
a word depends on
their probability.
And where this loss
function is going
to be minimized given this
negation by making these dot
products large, and these dot
products small means negative.
So there's just then one
other trick that they use.
Actually there's more
than one other trick
that's used in
the word2vec paper
to get it to perform well.
But I'll only mention one
of their other tricks here.
When they sample the
words, they don't simply
just sample the words based on
their probability of occurrence
in the corpus or uniformly.
What they do is they start
with what we call the unigram
distribution of words.
So that is how
often words actually
occur in our big corpus.
So if you have a
billion word corpus
and a particular word
occurred 90 times in it,
you're taking 90
divided by a billion.
And so that's the unigram
probability of the word.
But what they then do
is that they take that
to the three-quarters power.
And the effect of that
three-quarters power,
which is then renormalized
to make a probability
distribution with z like we saw
the last time with the softmax.
By taking the
three-quarters power,
that has the effect of
dampening the difference
between common and rare words.
So that less frequent words are
sampled somewhat more often,
but still not nearly as much
as they would be if you just
use something like a
uniform distribution
over the vocabulary.
OK, so that's
basically everything
to say about the basics
of how we have this very
simple neural network
algorithm word2vec
and how we can train it
and learn word vectors.
So for the next bit what I
want to do is step back a bit
and say, well,
here's an algorithm
that I've shown you
that works great.
What else could we have done.
And what can we say about that.
And the first thing that
you might think about
is, well here's this
funny iterative algorithm
to give you word vectors.
If we have a lot of
words in a corpus,
seems like a more obvious
thing that we could do
is just look at the counts of
how words occur with each other
and build a matrix of counts,
a co-occurrence matrix.
So here's the idea of
So I've got a teeny
little corpus.
I like deep learning.
I like NLP, I enjoy flying.
And I can define a window size.
I made my window
simply size one to make
it easy to fill in
my matrix symmetric
just like our
word2vec algorithm.
And so then the
counts in these cells
are simply how often
things co-occur
in the window of size 1.
So "I like" occurs twice.
So we get twos in these
cells because it's symmetric.
"Deep learning" occurs
once so we get 1 here.
And lots of other
things occur 0.
So we can build up a
co-occurrence matrix like this.
And well, these actually
give us a representation
of words as
co-occurrence vectors.
So I can take the word "I" with
either a row or a column vector
since it's symmetric and say OK,
my representation of the word
"I" is this row vector.
And that is a representation
of the word "I".
And I think you can
maybe convince yourself
that to the extent that words
have similar meaning and usage,
you'd sort of expect them to
have somewhat similar vectors,
right?
So if I had the word "you"
as well on a larger corpus,
you might expect "I" and
"you" to have similar vectors.
Because I like, you
like, I enjoy, you enjoy.
You'd see the same
kinds of possibilities.
Hey Chris?
Yeah?
Do you think you can
answer some questions?
Sure.
All right.
So we've got some questions from
sort of the negative sampling
slides.
In particular can you
give some intuition
for negative sampling?
What is the negative
sampling doing?
And why do we only take
one positive example?
These are two questions
if you can answer.
OK.
That's a good question.
OK, I'll try and
give more intuition.
So one is to work out something
like what the softmax did
in a much more efficient way.
So in the softmax
well, you wanted
to give high probability
in predicting
a context word that actually
did appear with the center word.
And well, the way you
do that is by having
the dot product
between those two words
be as big as possible.
And part of how--
you're going to be sort of--
it's more than that
because in the denominator
we were also working out the dot
product with every other word
in the vocabulary.
So as well as wanting the dot
product with the actual word
that you see in the
context to be big.
You maximize your
likelihood by making
the dot products of other words
that weren't in the context
smaller.
Because that's shrinking your
denominator and therefore
you've got a bigger
number coming out
and you're maximizing the loss.
So even for the softmax,
the general thing
that you want to do
to maximize that is
have a dot product with words
actually in the context big.
Dot products with words
not in the context
be small to the extent possible.
And obviously you
have to average
this as best you can over all
kinds of different contexts.
Because sometimes
different words
appear in different
contexts obviously.
So the negative sampling is
a way of therefore trying
to maximize the same objective.
Now, you only have one positive
term because you're actually
wanting to use the actual data.
So you're not wanting
to invent data.
So for working out
the entire J, we
do work this quantity
out for every center
word and every context word.
So we are iterating over the
different words in the context
window.
And then we're moving through
positions in the corpus.
So we're doing different
VCs, so gradually we do this.
But for one particular center
word and one particular context
word, we only have one real
piece of data that's positive.
So that's all we
use because we don't
know what other words should
be counted as positive words.
Now for the negative
words you could just
sample one negative word and
that would probably work.
But if you want a sort of a
slightly better more stable
sense of, OK we'd like to
in general have other words,
have low probability.
That seems like you might
be able to get better more
stable results if you instead
say let's have 10 or 15 sample
negative words.
And indeed that's
been found to be true.
And for the negative
words, well, it's
easy to sample any number
of random words you want.
And at that point it's kind
of a probabilistic argument.
The words that you're sampling
might not be actually bad words
to appear in the context.
They might actually be other
words that are in the context.
But 99.9% of the
time they will be
unlikely words to
occur in the context.
And so they're good ones to use.
And yes you only sample
10 or 15 of them.
But that's enough
to make progress.
Because the center word is going
to turn up on other occasions.
And when it does, you'll
sample different words over
here so that you
gradually sample
different parts of the
space and start to learn.
We had this co-occurrence
matrix and it
gives a representation of
words as co-occurrence vectors.
And just one more
note on that, I
mean there are actually two ways
that people have commonly made
these co-occurrence matrices.
One corresponds to what
we've seen already,
that you use a window
around the word, which
is similar to word2vec.
And that allows you to
capture some locality
and some of the sort of
syntactic and semantic
proximity that's
more fine grained.
The other way these co-occurence
matrices have been made
is that normally documents
have some structure,
whether it's paragraphs or
just the actual web pages
sort of size documents.
So you can just make your
window size a paragraph
or a whole web page and
count co-occurrence in those.
And this is the kind
of method that's
often been used in
information retrieval,
in methods like latent
semantic analysis.
OK, so the question then is
are these kind of count word
vectors good things to use?
Well, people have used them.
They're not terrible.
But they have certain problems.
The kind of problems
that they have,
well, firstly they're
huge though very sparse.
So this is back
where I said before,
if we had a vocabulary
of half a million words
and then we have half a
million dimensional vector
for each word, which
is much, much bigger
than the word vectors
that we typically use.
And it also means
that because we
have these very high
dimensional vectors
that we have a lot of sparsity
and a lot of randomness.
So the results that you get tend
to be noisier and less robust
depending on what particular
stuff was in the corpus.
And so in general
people have found
that you can get much
better results by working
with low dimensional vectors.
So then the idea is
we can store most
of the important information
about the distribution of words
and the context of other
words in a fixed small number
of dimensions, giving
a dense vector.
And in practice
the dimensionality
of the vectors that
are used are normally
somewhere between 25 and 1,000.
And so at that point,
we need to use some way
to reduce the dimensionality
of our count co-occurrence
vectors.
So if you have a good memory
from a linear algebra class,
you hopefully saw singular
value decomposition.
And it has various
mathematical properties
that I'm not going to talk
about here of singular value
projection giving you an optimal
way under a certain definition
of optimality of producing
a reduced dimensionality
matrix that maximally, or
sorry, a pair of matrices
that maximally well lets you
recover the original matrix.
But the idea of the
singular value decomposition
is you can take any matrix
such as our count matrix.
And you can decompose
that into three matrices.
U, a diagonal matrix sigma,
and a V transpose matrix.
And this works for any shape.
Now in these matrices, some
parts of it are never used.
Because since this
matrix is rectangular
there's nothing over here.
And so this part of the V
transpose matrix gets ignored.
But if you're wanting to
get smaller dimensional
representations, what you do
is take advantage of the fact
that the singular values inside
the diagonal sigma matrix
are ordered from largest
down to smallest.
So what we can do is just
delete out more of the matrix.
Delete out some singular
values which effectively
means that in this product,
some of U and some of V
is also not used.
And so then as a
result of that, we're
getting lower dimensional
representations for our words,
if we're wanting to
have word vectors.
Which still do as
good as possible
a job within the
given dimensionality
of enabling you to recover the
original co-occurrence matrix.
So from a linear
algebra background,
this is the obvious
thing to use.
So how does that work?
Well, if you just build a raw
count co-occurrence matrix
and run SVD on that and try
and use those as word vectors,
it actually works poorly.
And it works poorly
because if you
get into the mathematical
assumptions of SVD,
you're expecting to have these
normally distributed errors.
And what you're getting
with word counts
looked not at all like
someone's normal [INAUDIBLE]
because you have exceedingly
common words like "a," "the,"
and "and".
And you have a very large
number of rare words.
So that doesn't work very well.
But you can actually
get something
that works a lot better if you
scale the counts in the cells.
So to deal with this problem
of extremely frequent words,
there are some things we can do.
We could just take the
log of the raw counts.
We could kind of cap
the maximum count.
We could throw away
the function words.
And any of these ideas
that you build then
have an co-occurrence matrix
that you get more useful word
vectors from running
something like SVD.
And indeed these kind of models
were explored in the 1990s
and in the 2000s.
And in particular, Doug
Rohde explored a number
of these ideas as
to how to improve
the co-occurrence
matrix in a model
that he built that
was called COALS.
And actually in his COALS
model, he observed the fact
that you could get the same
kind of linear components
that our semantic components
that we saw yesterday
when talking about analogies.
So for example, this is
a figure from his paper
and you can see that we seem to
have a meaning component going
from a verb to the
person who does the verb.
So drive to driver, swim to
swimmer, teach to teacher,
marry to priest.
And that these vector
components are not perfectly
but are roughly parallel
and roughly the same size.
And so we have a
meaning component
there that we could
add on to another word
just like we did for
previously, for analogies.
We could say drive is to
driver as marry is to what,
and we add on this screen
vector component, which is
roughly the same as this one.
And we'd say oh, priest.
So that this space could
actually get some word
vectors analogies right as well.
And so that seemed
really interesting to us
around the time
word2vec came out,
of wanting to understand better
what the iterative updating
algorithm of word2vec did.
And how it related to these
more linear algebra based
methods that had been explored
in the couple of decades
previously.
And so for the next bit I
want to tell you a little bit
about the GLoVe algorithm,
which was an algorithm for word
vectors that was made by
Jeffrey Pennington, Richard
Socher, and me, in 2014.
And so the starting
point of this
was to try to connect together
the linear algebra based
methods on co-occurrence
matrices like LSA and COALS
with the models like skip-gram,
CBOW and their other friends,
which were iterative
neural updating algorithms.
So on the one hand, the linear
algebra methods actually
seemed like they had
advantages for fast training
and efficient usage
of statistics.
But although there had been work
on capturing words similarities
with them, by and
large the results
weren't as good perhaps because
of disproportionate importance
given to large
counts in the main.
Conversely, the
neural models it seems
like if you're just doing these
gradient updates on Windows,
you're somehow
inefficiently using
statistics versus the
co-occurrence matrix.
But on the other hand,
it's actually easier
to scale to a very large corpus
by trading time for space.
And at that time, it seemed
like the neural methods just
worked better for people.
That they generated improved
performance on many tasks,
not just on word similarity.
And that they could
capture complex patterns,
such as the analogies that
went beyond word similarity.
And so what we wanted to
do was understand a bit
more as to what
properties you need
to have these analogies work
out as I showed last time.
And so what we realized
was that if you'd
like to have these sort
of vector subtractions
and additions work
for an analogy,
the property that you want
is for meaning components.
So a meaning
component is something
like going from male to
female, queen to king.
Or going from a verb to
its agent, truck to driver.
That those meaning
components should
be represented as ratios of
co-occurrence probabilities.
So here's an example
that shows that.
OK, so suppose the
meaning component
that we want to get out is
the spectrum from solid to gas
as in physics.
Well, you'd think that you
can get the solid part of it
perhaps by saying does the
word co-occur with ice?
And the word "solid" occurs
with ice so that looks hopeful.
And gas doesn't occur with ice
much, so that looks hopeful.
But the problem is the
word "water" will also
occur a lot with ice.
And if you just take
some other random word
like the word
"random", it probably
doesn't occur with ice much.
In contrast, if you look at
words co-occurring with steam,
solid won't occur with
steam much, but gas will.
The water will again and
random will be small.
So to get out the
meaning component
we want of going from gas to
solid, what's actually really
useful is to look at the
ratio of these co-occurrence
probabilities.
Because then we get a
spectrum from large to small
between solid and gas.
Whereas for water
and a random word,
it basically cancels
out and gives you 1.
I just wrote these numbers in.
But if you count them
up in a large corpus
it is basically what you get.
So here are actual
co-occurrence probabilities.
And that for water and my random
word which was "fashion" here,
these are approximately 1.
Whereas for the
ratio of probability
of co-occurrence of solid
with ice or steam is about 10.
And for gas it's about a 10th.
So how can we
capture these ratios
of co-occurrence probabilities
as linear meaning components?
So that within our
word vector space,
we can just add and subtract
linear meaning components.
Well, it seems
like the way we can
achieve that is if we
build a log-bilinear model.
So that the dot product
between two word vectors
attempts to approximate
the log of the probability
of co-occurrence.
So if you do that, you
then get this property
that the difference
between two vectors,
its similarity to
another word corresponds
to the log of the
probability ratio shown
on the previous slide.
So the GloVe model
wanted to try and unify
the thinking between
the co-occurrence matrix
models and the neural
models by being
in some way similar
to a neural model.
But actually calculated on
top of a co-occurrence matrix
count.
So we had an explicit
loss function.
And our explicit
loss function is
that we wanted the
dot product to be
similar to the log
of the co-occurrence.
We actually added in
some bias terms here
but I'll ignore
those for the moment.
And we wanted to not have
very common words dominate.
And so we capped the
effect of high word
counts using this f
function that's shown here.
And then we could optimize
this j function directly
on the co-occurrence
count matrix.
So that gave us fast training
scalable to huge corpora.
And so this algorithm
worked very well.
So if you run this
algorithm, ask what
are the nearest words to frog?
You get "frogs",
"toad", and then you
get some complicated words.
But it turns out
they are all frogs.
Until you get down to
lizards, so litoria's
that lovely tree frog there.
And so this actually seemed
to work out pretty well.
How well did it work out?
To discuss that a
bit more I now want
to say something about how
do we evaluate word vectors.
And are we good up to
there for questions?
We got some questions.
What do you mean by an
inefficient use of statistics
as a con for skip-gram?
Well, what I mean is
that for word2vec you're
just looking at one
center word at a time
and generating a few
negative samples.
And so it sort of seems
like [AUDIO OUT] doing
something really precise there.
Whereas if you're doing
an optimization algorithm
on the whole matrix at
once, well, you actually
know everything about
the matrix at once.
You're not just looking at
what other words occurred
in this one context
of the center word.
You've got the entire vector
of co-occurrence counts
of the center word
and another word.
And so therefore you can much
more efficiently and less
noisily work out how
to minimize your loss.
OK, I'll go on.
OK, so I've sort of said,
look at these word vectors,
they're great.
And I showed you a
few things at the end
of the last class, which
argued, hey, these are great.
They work out these analogies.
They show similarity
and things like this.
We want to make this
a bit more precise.
And indeed for natural
language processing
as in other areas
of machine learning,
a big part of what
people are doing
is working out good ways
to evaluate knowledge
that things have.
So how can we really
evaluate word vectors?
So in general for
an NLP evaluation,
people talk about two
ways of evaluation.
Intrinsic and extrinsic.
So an intrinsic evaluation
means that you evaluate directly
on the specific or intermediate
subtasks that you've
been working on.
So I want a measure where
I can directly score
how good my word vectors are.
And normally,
intrinsic evaluations
are fast to compute.
They help you to
understand the component
you've been working on.
But often, simply trying
to optimize that component
may or may not have a
very big good effect
on the overall system that
you're trying to build.
So people have also
been very interested
in extrinsic evaluations.
So an extrinsic evaluation is
that you take some real task
of interest to human beings.
Whether that's web search
or machine translation
or something like that,
and you say your goal
is to actually improve
performance on that task.
Well that's a real proof that
this is doing something useful.
So in some ways that's
just clearly better.
But on the other hand, it
also has some disadvantages.
It takes a lot longer to
evaluate on an extrinsic task
because it's a
much bigger system.
And sometimes when
you change things,
it's unclear whether the fact
that the numbers went down
was because you now
have worse word vectors
or whether it's just
somehow the other components
of the system interacted better
with your old word vectors.
And if you change the
other components as well,
things would get better again.
So in some ways it
can sometimes be
muddier to see if
you're making progress.
But I'll touch on both
of these methods here.
So for intrinsic
evaluation of word vectors,
one way which we
mentioned last time
was this word vector analogy.
So we could simply
give our models
a big collection of word
vector analogy problems.
So we could say man is to
woman as king is to what?
And ask the model to find
the word that is closest
using that sort of word
analogy computation
and hope that what comes
out there is queen.
And so that's something people
have done and have worked out
an accuracy score of how
often that you are right.
At this point I should just
mention one little trick
of these word vector
analogies that everyone uses
but not everyone talks about
a lot in the first instance.
I mean there's a little
trick which you can find
in the Jensen code if you look
at it that when it does man is
to woman as king is to what,
something that could often
happen is that
actually the word--
once you do your pluses
and your minuses--
that the word that will actually
be closest is still king.
So the way people
always do this is
that they don't allow
one of the three input
words in the selection process.
So you're choosing
the nearest word that
isn't one of the input words.
OK, so since here it's showing
results from the GloVe vectors.
So the GloVe vectors have
this strong linear component
property just like I
showed before for COALS.
So this is for the
male-female dimension.
And so because of this you'd
expect in a lot of cases
that word analogies would work.
Because I can take the vector
difference of man and woman
and then if I add that vector
difference onto brother,
I expect to get to
sister and king, queen,
and for many of these examples.
But of course, they may
not always work, right?
Because if I start from emperor,
it's sort of more of a lean.
And so it might turn out that I
get countess or duchess coming
out instead.
You can do this for
various different relations
or different semantic relations
So these word vectors actually
learn quite a bit of
just world knowledge.
So here's the company's CEO.
Or this is the company's
CEO around 2010 to 2014
when the data was taken
from word vectors.
And as well as semantic things
or pragmatic things like this,
they also learn
syntactic things.
So here are vectors
for positive,
comparative, and superlative
forms of adjectives.
And you can see those also move
in roughly linear components.
So the word2vec people built
a data set of analogies
so you could evaluate different
models on the accuracy
of their analogies.
And so here's how
you can do this
and this gives some numbers.
So there are semantic
and syntactic analogies.
I'll just look at the totals.
OK, so what I said
before is if you just
use unscaled
co-occurrence counts
and pass them through an
SVD, things work terribly.
And you see that there,
you only get 7.3.
But then as I also pointed
out if you do some scaling
you can actually get SVD
of a scaled count matrix
to work reasonably well.
So this SVD-L is similar
to the COALS model.
And now we're
getting up to 60.1,
which actually isn't
a bad score, right?
So you can actually do a decent
job without a neural network.
And then here are the two
variants of the word2vec model.
And here are our results
from the GloVe model.
And of course, at the time 2014,
we took this as absolute proof
that our model was better
and a more efficient use
of statistics was really
working in our favor.
With seven years of retrospect,
I think that's not really true,
it turns out.
I think the main part
of why we scored better
is that we actually
had better data.
And so there's a bit of evidence
about that on this next slide
here.
So this looks at the semantic,
syntactic and overall
performance on word
analogies of GloVe models
that were trained on
different subsets of data.
So in particular, the two on the
left are trained on Wikipedia.
And you can see that
training on Wikipedia
makes you do really well on
semantic analogies, which maybe
makes sense because
Wikipedia just tells you
a lot of semantic facts.
I mean that's kind of
what encyclopedias do.
And so one of the big
advantages we actually had
was that Wikipedia--
that the GloVe model was partly
trained on Wikipedia as well
as other text.
Whereas the word2vec
model that was released
was trained exclusively
on Google News.
So news wire data.
And if you only train on a
smallish amount of news wire
data, you can see
that for the semantics
it's just not as good as
even one quarter of the size
amount of Wikipedia data.
Though if you get a lot of data
you can compensate for that.
So here on the right
end, if you then
have Common Crawl Web data.
And so once there's a lot of web
data, so now 42 billion words,
you're then starting to
get good scores again
from the semantic side.
The graph on the
right then shows
how well do you do as you
increase the vector dimension.
And so what you can see there
is 25 dimensional vectors
aren't very good.
They go up to sort
of 50 and then 100.
And so 100 dimensional vectors
already work reasonably well.
So that's why I used 100
dimensional vectors when
I showed my example in class.
[AUDIO OUT] and working
reasonably well.
But you still get
significant gains
for 200 and somewhat to 300.
So at least back around
sort of 2013 to 2015,
everyone sort of
gravitated to the fact
that 300 dimensional
vectors is the sweet spot.
So almost freakily, if you look
through the best known sets
of word vectors that include the
word2vec vectors and the GloVe
vectors that
usually what you get
is 300 dimensional word vectors.
That's not the only intrinsic
evaluation you can do.
Another intrinsic
evaluation you can do
is see how these models
model human judgments of word
similarity.
So psychologists
for several decades
have actually taken human
judgments of word similarity.
Where literally you're asking
people for pairs of words
like "professor" and "doctor"
to give them a similarity
score that's being measured as
some continuous quantity giving
you a score between,
say 0 and 10.
And so there are
human judgments,
which are then averaged over
multiple human judgments
as to how similar
different words are.
So "tiger" and "cat"
is pretty similar.
"Computer and "internet"
"Plane and "cars" less similar.
"Stock" and "CD" aren't
very similar at all
but "stock" and "jaguar"
are even less similar.
So we could then
say for our models,
do they have the same
similarity judgments.
And in particular, we
can measure a correlation
coefficient of whether they give
the same ordering of similarity
judgments.
And so then we can
get data for that.
And so there are various
different data sets
of word similarities.
And we can score
different models
as to how well they
do on similarities.
And again, you see
here that plain SVD's
works comparatively better
here for similarities
than it did for analogies.
It's not great but it's
not completely terrible
because we no longer need
that linear property.
But again, scaled SVD's
work a lot better.
Word2vec works a bit
better than that.
And we got some of the same
kind of minor advantages
from the GloVe model.
Sorry to interrupt.
A lot of those students who are
asking if you could re-explain
the objective function for
the GloVe model and also
what log-bilinear means.
OK.
Sure, OK, here is my
objective function.
All right, if I go one
slide before that--
right, so the
property that we want
is that we want the dot
product to represent the log
probability of co-occurrence.
So that then gives me
my tricky log-bilinear.
So the "bi" is that
there's the wy and the wj
so that there are
two linear things.
And it's linear in
each one of them.
So this is sort of
like having and--
rather than having
a sort of an ax
where you just have
something that's
linear in x and is a constant.
It's bi-linear because
we have the wy, wj
and it's linear in both of them.
And that's then related to
the log of a probability.
And so that gives us
the log-bilinear model.
And so since we'd like
these things to be equal,
what we're doing here, if
you ignore these two center
terms is that we're
wanting to say
the difference between these
two is as small as possible.
So we're taking this difference
and we're squaring it
so it's always positive.
And we want that squared term
to be as small as possible.
And that's 90% of it.
And you can
basically stop there.
But the other bit
that's in here,
is a lot of the time when
you're building models
rather than simply having
sort of an ax model,
it seems useful to
have a bias term which
can move things up and down
for the word in general.
And so we added into
the model bias term
so that there's a bias
term for both words.
So if in general probabilities
are high for a certain word,
this bias term can model that.
And for the other word this
bias term can model it, okay?
So now I'll pop back and after--
oh actually I just
saw someone said
why multiplying by the f of--
sorry I did skip that last term.
OK, the y modifying
by this f of xij.
So this last bit
was to scale things
depending on the
frequency of a word
because you want to pay
more attention to words
that are more common or word
pairs that are more common.
Because if you think about
it in word2vec terms,
you're seeing if things have
a co-occurrence count of 50
versus three.
You want to do a
better job at modeling
the co-occurrence of the
things that occurred together
50 times.
And so you want to consider
in the count of co-occurrence.
But then the argument is that
that actually leads you astray
when you have extremely common
words like function words.
And so effectively you
paid more attention
to words that
co-occurred together up
until a certain point.
And then the curve
just went flat,
so it didn't matter if it
was an extremely, extremely
common word.
So then for extrinsic
word vector evaluation.
So at this point you're now
wanting to sort of say, well,
can we embed our word
vectors in some end-user task
and do they help?
And do different word
vectors work better or worse
than other word vectors?
So this is something that
we'll see a lot of later
in the class.
I mean, in particular
when you get on
to doing assignment three.
That assignment three you get
to build dependency parsers
and you can then
use word vectors
in the dependency parser
and see how much they help.
We don't actually make you
test out different sets of word
vectors, but you could.
Here's just one example of
this to give you a sense.
So the task of named
entity recognition
is going through a piece
of text and identifying
mentions of a person's name
or an organization name
like a company or a location.
And so if you have
good word vectors,
do they help you do named
entity recognition better?
And the answer to that is yes.
So if one starts off
with a model that simply
has discrete features, so it
uses word identity as features,
you can build a pretty good
named entity model doing that.
But if you add into
it word vectors
you get a better representation
of the meaning of words.
And so that you can have the
numbers go up quite a bit.
And then you can
compare different models
to see how much gain
they give you in terms
of this extrinsic task.
So skipping ahead,
this was a question
that was asked after class,
which was word senses.
Because so far we've had
just one particular string,
we've got some string house.
And we're going to say for
each of those strings there's
a word vector.
And if you think
about it a bit more,
that seems like it's very weird.
Because actually most words,
especially common words,
and especially words that
have existed for a long time
actually have many meanings
which are very different.
So how could that be
captured if you only have
one word vector for the word?
Because you can't
actually capture the fact
that you've got different
meanings for the word.
Because your
meaning for the word
is just one point in
space, one vector.
And so as an example of
that, here's the word "pike".
Now it's actually
a very common word
but it is an old Germanic word.
Well, what kind of meanings
does the word "pike" have?
So you can maybe just
think for a minute
and think what word meanings
the word "pike" has.
And it actually turns out it
has a lot of different meanings.
So perhaps the
most basic meaning
is if you did fantasy games or
something, medieval weapons,
a sharp pointed staff is a pike.
But there's a kind
of a fish that
has a similar elongated
shape that's a pike.
It was used for railroad lines.
Maybe that usage isn't
used much anymore.
But it's certainly still
survives in referring to roads.
So this is like when
you have turnpikes.
We have expressions where
"pike" means the future,
like coming down the pike.
It's a position in diving,
that divers do a pike.
Those are all noun uses.
There are also verbal uses.
So you can pike
somebody with your pike.
Different usages might
have different currency.
In Australia you can
also use "pike" to mean
that you pull out
of doing something,
like I reckon he's
going to pike.
I don't think that usage
is used in America.
But lots of meanings.
And actually for
words that are common
or if you start thinking of
words like "line" or "field",
I mean they just have even
more meanings than this.
So what are we actually
doing with just one
vector for a word?
And well, one way
you could go is
to say OK, up until now
what we've done is crazy.
"Pike" has, and
other words have all
of these different meanings.
So maybe what we should do is
have a different word vectors
for the different
meanings of "pike".
So we'd have one word vector
for the medieval pointy weapon.
Another word vector
for the kind of fish.
for the kind of road.
So that there'd then
be word sense vectors.
And you can do that.
I mean actually, we were working
on that in the early 2010s,
actually even before
word2vec came out.
So this picture is a
little bit small to see.
But what we were
doing was for words,
we were clustering
instances of a word hoping
that those clusters--
clustering the word tokens,
hoping those clusters
have similar represented senses.
And then for the
clusters of word tokens,
we were also treating them
like they were separate words.
And learning a word
vector for each.
And basically that
actually works.
So in green we have two
senses for the word "bank".
And so there's one sense for the
word "bank" that's over here,
where it's close to words
like "banking", "finance",
"transaction", and "laundering".
And then we have another sense
for the word "bank" over here,
where it's close to words like
"plateau", "boundary", "gap
territory", which is the river
bank sense of the word "bank".
And for the word "jaguar"
that's in purple.
Well, "jaguar" has
a number of senses
and so we have those as well.
So this sense down here
is close to "hunter"
so that's the big game
animals sense of "jaguar".
Up the top here it's
being shown close
to "luxury" and "convertibles",
This is the Jaguar car sense.
Then "jaguar" here is near
"string", "keyboard" and words
like that.
So jaguar's the name
of a kind of keyboard.
And then this final
"jaguar" over here
is close to "software"
and "Microsoft".
And then if you're
old enough, you'll
remember that there was an
old version of Mac OS that
was called Jaguar.
So that's then the
computer sense.
So basically this does work
and we can learn word vectors
for different senses of a word.
But actually this
isn't the majority way
that things have then
gone in practice.
And there are kind of a
couple of reasons for that.
I mean one is just simplicity.
If you do this,
it's kind of complex
because you first of all
have to learn word senses
and then start learning word
vectors in terms of the word
senses But the other reason is
although this model of having
word senses is traditional.
It's what you see
in dictionaries.
It's commonly what's been used
in natural language processing.
I mean it tends to be
imperfect in its own way
because we're trying to take
all the uses of the word "pike"
and sort of cut them up
into key different senses.
Where [AUDIO OUT] differences
kind of overlapping and it's
often not clear which
ones to count as distinct.
So for example here,
right, a railroad line
and a type of road,
well sort of that's
the same sense of "pike".
It's just that they're different
forms of transportation.
And so that this could be a
type of transportation line
and cover both of them.
So it's always sort
of very unclear
how you cut word meaning
into different senses.
And indeed, if you look
at different dictionaries
everyone does it differently.
So it actually turns
out that in practice you
can do rather well
by simply having
one word vector per word type.
And what happens if you do that?
Well, what you find is that--
what you learn is
the word vector
is what gets referred
to in fancy talk
as a superposition
of the word vectors
for the different
senses of a word.
Where the word "superposition"
means no more or less
than a weighted sum.
So the vector that
we learn for "pike"
will be a weighted
average of the vectors
that you would have learned
for the medieval weapons
sense, plus the fish
sense, plus the road sense,
plus whatever other
senses that you have.
Where the weighting that's
given to these different sense
vectors corresponds
to the frequencies
of use of the different senses.
So we end up with
the vector for "pike"
being a kind of
an average vector.
And so if you say
OK, you've just
added up several different
vectors into an average.
You might think
that that's useless
because you've lost the
real meanings of the word.
You've just got some kind
of funny average vector
that's in between them.
But actually it
turns out that if you
use this average
vector in applications,
it tends to sort of
self-disambiguate.
Because if you say is the word
"pike" similar to the word
for "fish" well, part of
this vector represents fish,
the fish sense of "pike".
And so in those components,
it will be kind of
similar to the fish vector.
And so yes you'll say there's
substantial similarity.
Whereas if in another
piece of text that says,
the men were armed with pikes,
and lances or pikes and maces,
or whatever other medieval
weapons you remember.
Well, actually some of that
meaning is in the "pike" vector
as well.
And so it'll say, yeah that's
good similarity with mace,
and staff and words
like that as well.
And in fact, we can work
out which sense of "pike"
is intended by just sort
of seeing which components
are similar to other words that
are used in the same context.
And indeed there's actually
a much more surprising result
than that.
And this is a result that's
due to Sanjeev Arora, Tengyu
Ma, who is now on the Stanford
faculty and others in 2018.
And that's the following
result, which I'm not actually
going to explain.
But so if you think that
the vector for "pike"
is just a sum of the vectors
for the different senses.
Well, it should be you'd think
that it's just completely
impossible to reconstruct the
sense vectors from the vector
for the word type.
Because normally, if I
say I've got two numbers,
the sum of them is 17, you just
have no information as to what
my two numbers are, right?
You can't resolve it.
And even worse, if I tell
you I've got three numbers
and they sum to 17.
But it turns out
that when we have
these high dimensional
vector spaces that things
are so sparse in those high
dimensional vector spaces
that you can use ideas from
sparse coding to actually
separate out the different
senses, providing they're
relatively common.
So they show in
their paper that you
can start with the
vector of say "pike"
and actually separate
out components
of that vector that correspond
to different senses of the word
"pike".
And so here's an example at
the bottom of this slide, which
is for the word "pike".
Separate out that vector
into five different senses.
And so the one sense
is close to the words
"trousers", "blouse",
"waistcoats",
and that's that sort of
clothing sense of "tie".
Another sense is close to
"wires", "cables", "wiring",
"electrical".
So that's the tie sense of a tie
used in the electrical stuff.
Then we have
"scoreline", "goalless",
"equalizer" this is the
sporting game sense of "tie".
This one also seems
to in a different way
evoke a sporting
game sense of "tie".
And then there's
finally this one here.
Maybe my music is
just really bad.
Maybe it's because you get ties
in music when you tie notes
together, I guess.
So you get these different
senses out of it.