Hi, everyone.
I'll get started.
OK, so we're now back to
the second week of CS224N
on Natural Language
Processing with Deep Learning.
OK, so for today's lecture what
we're going to be looking at
is all the math details of
doing neural net learning.
First of all, looking
at how we can work out
by hand gradients for
training neural networks,
and then looking
at how it's done
more algorithmically, which is
known as the back propagation
algorithm.
And correspondingly,
by you guys,
well, I hope you remember
that one minute ago
was when assignment one was due
and everyone has handed that
in.
If by some chance you
haven't handed it in,
really should hand it
in as soon as possible.
Best to preserve those late
days for the harder assignments.
So I mean, I actually forgot
to mention we actually
did make one change
for this year
to make it a bit easier
when occasionally people
joined the class a week late.
If you want to this
year in the grading,
assignment one can be
discounted and we'll just
use your other four assignments.
But if you've been in the class
so far, for that 98% of people,
well, since assignment one
is the easiest assignment,
again, it's silly not
to do it and have it
as part of your grade.
OK, so starting today
we've put out assignment 2.
And assignment 2 is all
about making sure you really
understand the math
of neural networks,
and then the software that
we use to do that math.
So this is going to be a bit
of a tough week for some.
So for some people
who are great on all
their math and
backgrounds, now feel
like this is stuff they know
well, nothing very difficult.
But I know there are
quite a few of you who
this lecture and week is the
biggest struggle of the course.
We really do want
people to actually
have an understanding of what
goes on in neural network
learning rather than viewing
it as some kind of deep magic.
And I hope that some of
the material we give today
and that you read up on and use
in the assignment will really
give you more of a sense of
what these neural networks are
doing, and how it
is just math that's
applied in a systematic
large scale that works out
the answers, and
that this will be
valuable in giving you a deeper
sense of what's going on.
But if this material seems
very scary and difficult,
you can take some
refuge in the fact
that there's first light
at the end of the tunnel
since this is really
the only lecture that's
heavily going through the math
details of neural networks.
After that, we'll be kind of
popping back up to a higher
level and by and
large, after this week
we'll be making use of
software to do a lot
of the complicated math for us.
But nevertheless, I
hope this is valuable.
I'll go through
everything quickly today,
but if this isn't stuff
that you know backwards,
I really do encourage
you to work through it
and get help as you need it.
So do come along to
our office hours.
There are also a number of
pieces of tutorial material
given in the syllabus.
So there's both
the lecture notes,
there's some
materials from CS231.
In the list of readings,
the very top reading
is some material put together
by Kevin Clark a couple of years
ago, and actually that
one's my favorite.
The presentation there
fairly closely follows
the presentation in
this lecture of going
through matrix calculus.
So personally, I'd recommend
starting with that one
but there are four
different ones
you can choose from if one of
them seems more helpful to you.
Two other things on
what's coming up.
Actually for our Thursday's
lecture, we make a big change.
And Thursday's
lecture is probably
the most linguistic
lecture of the whole class
where we go through the
details of dependency
grammar and dependency parsing.
Some people find that
tough as well, but at least
it will be tough
in a different way.
And then one other really good
opportunity is this Friday,
we have our second
tutorial at 10:00 AM, which
is an introduction to PyTorch,
which is the deep learning
framework that we'll be using
for the rest of the class
once we've gone through
these first two assignments
where you do things by yourself.
So this is a great chance
to get an intro to PyTorch,
it will be really useful
for later in the class.
OK, today's material
is really all
about sort of the math
of neural networks,
but just to introduce a setting
where we can work through this,
I'm going to
introduce a simple NLP
task and a simple
form of classifier
that we can use for it.
So the task of named
entity recognition
is a very common basic NLP task.
And the goal of this is you're
looking through pieces of text
and you're wanting to label
by labeling the words which
words belong to entity
categories like persons,
locations, products,
dates, times, et cetera.
So for this piece
of text, last night
Paris Hilton wowed
in a sequin gown.
Samuel Quinn was arrested
in the Hilton Hotel in Paris
in April 1989.
The-- some words
are being labeled
as named entities as shown.
These two sentences
don't actually
belong together in
the same article
but I chose those two sentences
to illustrate the basic point
that it's not that you can
just do this task by using
a dictionary.
Yes, a dictionary is helpful
to know that Paris can possibly
be a location, but Paris
can also be a person name.
So you have to
use context to get
named entity recognition right.
OK, well, how might we do
that with a neural network?
There are much more
advanced ways of doing this.
But a simple yet
already pretty good
way of doing named
entity recognition
with a simple neural
net is to say, well,
what we're going to do
is use the word vectors
that we've learned
about and we're
going to build up a context
window of word vectors.
And then we're going to put
those through a neural network
layer and then feed it through
a softmax classifier of the kind
that we, sorry, I
said that wrong,
and then we're going to feed it
through a logistic classifier
of the kind that
we saw when looking
at negative sampling,
which is going
to say for a particular
entity type, such as location,
is that high
probability location
or is that not a high
probability location?
So for a sentence like
the museums in Paris
are amazing to see, what we're
going to do is for each word,
say we're doing the
word Paris, we're
going to form a
window around that,
say a plus or minus
2 word window.
And so for those
five words, we're
going to get word
vectors for them
from the kind of Word2Vec
or GLoVe word vectors
we've learned.
And we're going to
make a long vector out
of the concatenation of
those five word vectors
so the word of interest
is in the middle.
And then we're going
to feed this vector
to a classifier
which is at the end
going to have a probability
of the word being a location.
And then we could have
another classifier
that says the probability of
the word being a person name.
And so once we've
done that, we're
then going to run it
at the next position.
So we then say, well, is
the word "a" a location?
And we'd feed a
window of five words,
it's then, in Paris
are amazing to,
and put it through the
same kind of classifier.
And so this is the
classifier that we'll use.
So its input will
be this word window.
So if we have D
dimensional word vectors,
this will be a 5D vector.
And then we're going to
put it through a layer
of a neural network.
So the layer of
the neural network
is going to multiply
this vector by a matrix,
add on a bias vector,
and then put that
through a non-linearity such
as the softmax transformation
that we've seen before.
And that will give
us a hidden vector
which might be of a smaller
dimensionality such as this one
here.
And so then with
that hidden vector,
we're then going to
take the dot product
of that with an extra
vector here, here it's u.
So we take u dot product h.
And so when we do that, we're
getting out a single number.
And that number can
be any real number.
And so then finally, we're
going to put that number
through a logistic
transform of the same kind
that we saw when doing
negative sampling.
The logistic transform
will take any real number,
and it'll transform
it into a probability
that that word is the location.
So its output is the
predicted probability
of the word belonging
to a particular class.
And so this could be
our location classifier
which could classify
each word in a window
as to what the probability is
that it's the location word.
And so this little
neural network
here is the neural network
I'm going to use today when
going through some of the math.
But actually, I'm going to
make it even easier on myself.
I'm going to throw away the
logistic function at the top,
and I'm really
just going to work
through the math of the
bottom three-quarters of this.
If you look at Kevin Clark's
handout that I just mentioned,
he includes when he
works through it, also
working through the
logistic function.
And we also saw working through
a softmax in the first lecture
when I was working through
some of the Word2Vec model.
OK, so the overall question
we want to be able to answer
is, so here's our stochastic
gradient descent equation,
that we have existing
parameters of our model,
and we want to update them
based on our current loss, which
is the j of theta.
So for getting our loss
here, that the true answer
as to whether a word
is a location or not
will be 1 if it is a location
or 0 if it isn't, our logistic
classifier will return
some number like 0.9,
and we'll use the distance
away from what it should
have been squared as our loss.
So we work out a loss and then
we're moving a little distance
in the negative of
the gradient, which
will be changing our parameter
estimates in such a way
that they reduce the loss.
And so this is
already being written
in terms of a whole
vector of parameters,
which is being updated as to
a new vector of parameters.
But you can also think about it,
for each individual parameter,
theta J, that we're working
out the partial derivative
of the loss with respect
to that parameter.
And then we're
moving a little bit
in the negative
direction of that.
That's going to give us a new
value for parameter theta J.
And we're going to update all
of the parameters of our model
as we learn.
I mean, in particular,
in contrast
to what commonly happens
in statistics, we also--
we update not only the sort
of parameters of our model
that are sort of weights
in the classifier,
but we also will update
our data representation.
So we'll also be changing
our word vectors as we learn.
OK, so to build
neural nets, i.e.,
to train neural
nets based on data,
what we need is to
be able to compute
this gradient of the parameters
so that we can then iteratively
update the weights of the
model and efficiently train
the model that has
good weights, i.e.
that has high accuracy.
And so how can we do that?
Well, what I'm going
to talk about today
is, first of all, how
you can do it by hand.
And so for doing it by
hand, this is basically
a review of matrix
calculus, and that will take
quite a bit of the lecture.
And then after we've talked
about that for a while,
I'll then shift gears and
introduce the back propagation
algorithm, which is the central
technology for neural networks.
And that technology
is essentially
the efficient application
of calculus on a large scale
as we'll come to
talking about soon.
So for computing gradients
by hand, what we're doing
is matrix calculus.
So we're working with
vectors and matrices
and working out gradients.
And this can seem like
pretty scary stuff.
And well, to the extent
that you're kind of scared
and don't know what's
going on, one choice
is to work out a non-vectorized
gradient by just working out
what the partial derivative
is for one parameter at a time
and I showed a little example
of that in the first lecture.
But it's much, much
faster and more useful
to actually be able to work
with vectorized gradients.
And in some sense, if
you're not very confident,
this is kind of almost
a leap of faith,
but it really is the case that
multivariable calculus is just
like single variable
calculus except you're
using vectors and matrices.
So providing you
remember some basics
of single variable
calculus, you really
should be able to do this
stuff and get it to work out.
Lots of other sources are
mentioned in the notes.
You can also look at
the textbook for Math 51
which also has quite a
lot of material on this.
I know some of you have
bad memories of Math 51.
OK, so let's go
through this and see
how it works ramping
up from the beginning.
So the beginning of calculus
is, we have a function
with one input and one output.
f(x) equals x cubed.
And so then its gradient
is its slope, right?
So its derivative.
So its derivative is 3x squared.
And the way to
think about this is
how much will the output
change if we change
the input a little bit, right?
So what we're wanting to
do in our neural net models
is change what they output
so that they do a better
job of predicting the
correct answers when we're
doing supervised learning.
And so what we want to
know is if we fiddle
different parameters of the
model, how much of an effect
will that have on the output?
Because then we can choose how
to fiddle them in the right way
to move things down, right?
So when we're saying that the
derivative here is 3x squared,
well, what we're saying is
that if you're at x equals 1,
if you fiddle the
input a little bit,
the output will change 3 times
as much, 3 times 1 squared,
and it does.
So if I say what's the value
at 1.01, it's about 1.03.
It's changed three times as
much, and that's its slope.
But at x equals 4, the
derivative is 16 times 348.
So if we fiddle
the input a little,
it will change 48 times
as much, and that's
roughly what happens,
4.01 cubed is 64.48.
Now, of course,
this is just sort
of showing it for a small fiddle
but that's an approximation
to the actual truth.
Okay, so then we sort of ramp
up to the more complex cases,
which are more
reflective of what we
do with neural networks.
So if we have a function
with one output and n inputs,
then we have a gradient.
So a gradient is a vector
of partial derivatives
with respect to each input.
So we've got n inputs x1 to
xn, and we're working out
the partial derivative
of f with respect
to x1, the partial derivative
of f with respect to x2,
et cetera, and we then get a
vector of partial derivatives
where each element
of this vector
is just like a simple derivative
with respect to one variable.
OK, so from that
point, we just keep
on ramping up for what we
do with neural networks.
So commonly, when
we have something
like layer in a
neural network, we'll
have a function
within n inputs that
will be like our
word vectors, then
we do something like
multiply by a matrix,
and then we'll have m outputs.
So we have a function now
which is taking n inputs
and is producing m outputs.
So at this point, what
we're calculating for
the gradient is what's
called a Jacobian matrix.
So for m inputs and n
outputs, the Jacobian
is an m by n matrix
of every combination
of partial derivatives.
So function f splits up into
these different sub functions
f1 through fm, which generate
each of the m outputs.
And so then we're taking
the partial derivative of f1
with respect to x1 through
with respect to xn,
then heading down,
we can make it up to the partial
derivative of fm with respect
to x1, et cetera.
So we have every possible
partial derivative
of an output
variable with respect
to one of the input variables.
OK, so in simple calculus,
when you have a composition
of one variable functions.
So that if you have y equals x
squared, and then z equals 3y,
that's--
then z is a composition
of two functions of--
or you're composing
two functions,
to get z as a function of x.
Then you can work out
the derivative of z
with respect to x.
And the way you do that
is with the chain rule.
And so in the chain rule,
you multiply derivatives.
So dz dx equals
dz dy times dy dx.
So dz dy is just
3, and dy dx is 2x.
So we get 3 times 2x so that
overall, the derivative here
is 6x.
And since if we
multiply this together,
we're really saying that
z equals 3x squared.
You should trivially
be able to see again.
Aha, its derivative is 6x.
So that works.
OK, so once we move into vectors
and matrices and Jacobians,
it's actually the same game.
So when we're
working with those,
we can compose functions and
work out their derivatives
by simply multiplying Jacobians.
So if we start with an
input x and then put it
through the simplest form
of neural network layer
and say that z equals Wx plus b.
So we multiply the
x vector by matrix W
and then add on a bias vector b.
And then typically,
we put things
through a non-linearity f.
So f could be a
sigmoid function.
We'll then say h equals f(z).
So this is the composition
of two functions in terms
of vectors and matrices.
So we can use
Jacobians and we can
say the partial
of h with respect
to x is going to be the
product of the partial h
with respect to z, and the
partial z with respect to x.
And this all does work out.
So let's start going
through some examples of how
these things work
slightly more concretely.
First, just particular
Jacobians and then
composing them together.
So one case we look at
is the nonlinearities
that we put a vector
through, so this
is something like
putting a vector
through the sigmoid function f.
And so if we have an
intermediate vector z and we
turn into vector h by putting
it through a logistic function,
we can say what is dh / dz?.
Well, for this, formally
this is a function that
has n inputs and n outputs.
So at the end of the day, we're
computing an n by n Jacobian.
And so what that's meaning is
the elements of this n by n
Jacobian are going to take
the partial derivative
of each output with
respect to each input.
And well, what is that
going to be in this case?
Well, in this case,
because we are actually
just computing element
wise transformation,
such as a logistic
transform of each element zi
like the second equation
here, if i equals j,
we've got something to compute.
Whereas, if i doesn't
equal J, the input
has no influence on the output
and so the derivative is 0.
So if i doesn't equal j
we're going to get a 0,
and if i does equal
j, well, then we're
going to get the regular
one variable derivative
of the logistic function,
which if I remember correctly,
you were asked to compute--
now I can't remember
whether it's assignment, 1
or assignment 2, but one of the
two asked you to compute it.
So our Jacobian for this
case looks like this.
We have a diagonal matrix with
the derivatives of each element
element along the diagonal
and everything else is 0.
OK, so let's look at a
couple of other Jacobians.
So if we are asking, if we've
got this Wx plus b basic neural
network layer and we're asking
for the gradient with respect
to x, then what are we
going to have coming out
is that that's actually
going to be the matrix W.
So this is where--
what I hope you can do is
look at the notes at home
and work through this exactly,
and see that this is actually
the right answer.
But this is the way in which if
you just have faith and think,
this is just like
single variable calculus
except I've now got vectors
and matrices, the answer you
get is actually what
you expected to get.
Because this is just like
the derivative of ax plus b
with respect to x where it's a.
So similarly, if we take the
partial derivative with respect
to b of Wx plus b we get
out the identity matrix.
OK, then one other Jacobian that
we mentioned while in the first
lecture while working through
Word2Vec is if you have the dot
product of two vectors,
i.e., that's a number,
that what you get
coming out of it--
so the partial derivative
of uTh with respect to u
is h transpose.
And at this point,
there's some fine print
that I'm going to come
back to in a minute.
So this is the correct
Jacobian, right?
Because in this case, we have
the dimension of h inputs
and we have one output, and so
we want to have a row vector.
But there's a little
bit more to say on
that that I'll come back
to in about 20 slides,
but this is the
correct Jacobian.
OK, so if you are not familiar
with these kind of Jacobians,
do please look at some of
the notes that are available
and try and compute these
in more detail element wise
and convince yourself that
they really are right.
But I'm going to assume
these now and show you
what happens when we
actually then work out
gradients for at least a
mini little neural net.
OK, so here is most
of this neural net.
I mean, as I commented
that really we'd
be working out the partial
derivative of the loss
j with respect to these
variables, but for the example
I'm doing here, I just--
I've locked that off to keep
it a little simpler and more
manageable for the lecture.
And so we're going
to just work out
the partial derivative
of the score s, which
is a real number with respect
to the different parameters
of this model where the
parameters of this model
are going to be the W
and the b and the u,
and also the input because
we can update the weight
vectors of the word
vectors of different words
based on tuning them to better
predict the classification
outputs that we desire.
So let's start off
with a fairly easy one
where we want to update
the bias vector b to have
our system classify better.
So to be able to do that,
what we want to work out
is the partial derivatives
of s with respect
to b, so we know how to put that
into our stochastic gradient
update for the b parameters.
OK, so how do we go
about doing these things?
So the first step is we
want to sort of break things
up into different functions
of minimal complexity
that compose together.
So in particular,
this neural net layer
h equals f of Wx plus b, it's
still a little bit complex.
So let's decompose
that one further step.
So we have the input
x, we then calculate
the linear transformation
z equals Wx plus b
and then we put things
through the sort of element
wise non-linearity h
equals f(z) and then we
do the dot product with u.
And it's useful for
working these things out
to split into pieces like
this, have straight what
your different variables
are, and to know
what the dimensionality of
each of these variables is.
It's well worth just writing
out the dimensionality
of every variable
and making sure
that the answers
that you're computing
are of the right dimensionality.
So at this point though, what
we can see is that calculating s
is the product of three--
I'm sorry, it's the composition
of three functions around x.
So for working out the partials
of s with respect to b,
it's the composition
of the three
functions shown on the left.
And so therefore, the gradient
of x with respect to b we're
going to take the
product of these three
partial derivatives.
OK, so how do-- what do we--
so we've got the s equals uTh.
So that's sort of the
top corresponding partial
derivative, partial
derivative h with respect
to z, partial derivative
of z with respect
to b, which is the first
one that we're working out.
OK, so we want to work this out.
And if we're lucky, we
remember those Jacobians
I showed previously about
the Jacobian for a vector dot
product, the Jacobian
for the non-linearity
and the Jacobian for the
simple linear transformation.
And so we can use those.
So for the partials of s
with respect to h, well,
that's going to be uT
using the first one.
The partials of h
with respect to z, OK,
so that's the
non-linearity, and so that's
going to be the matrix
that's the diagonal matrix
with the element-wise derivative
f prime of z and 0 elsewhere.
And then for the Wx
plus b, when we're
taking the partials with respect
to b, that's just the identity
matrix.
So we can simplify
that down a little,
the identity matrix disappears
and since uT is a vector
and this is a
diagonal matrix, we
can rewrite this as uT Hadamard
product of f prime of z.
I think this is
the first time I've
used this little circle
for Hadamard product
but it's something
that you'll see
quite a bit in neural network
work since it's often used.
So when we have two vectors uT
and this vector here, sometimes
you want to do an
element wise product.
So the output of
this will be a vector
where you've taken the
first element of each
and multiplied them, the
second element of each
and multiplied them,
et cetera downwards.
And so that's called
the Hadamard product
and that's what
we're calculating
as to calculate a vector,
which is the gradient of s
with respect to b.
OK, so that's good.
So we now have a gradient
of s with respect
to b and we could use that
in our stochastic gradient.
But we don't stop
there, we also want
to work out the
gradient with respect
to others of our parameters.
So we might want to next go on
and work out the gradients of s
with respect to w.
Well, we can use the chain rule
just like we did before, right?
So we've got the same product
of functions and everything
is going to be the
same apart from me now
taking the derivatives with
respect to w rather than b.
So it's now going to be the
partial of s with respect to h,
h with respect to z,
and z with respect to w.
And the important thing to
notice here and this leads
into what we do with the
back propagation algorithm
is wait a minute, this is very
similar to what we've already
done.
So when we are working
out the gradients of s
with respect to b, the first
two terms were exactly the same,
it's only the last
one that differs.
So to be able to
build or to train
neural networks
efficiently, this
is what happens all the time
and it's absolutely essential
that we use an algorithm that
avoids repeated computation.
And so the idea we're
going to develop
is when we have
this equation stack
that this sort of stuff that's
above where we compute z,
and we're going to be sort of,
that'll be the same each time
and we want to compute something
from that that we can then
sort of feed downwards
when working out
the gradients with
respect to Wx or b.
And so we do that
by defining delta,
which is delta is the
partials composed that
are above the linear transform.
And that's referred
to as the local error
signal, that's
what's being passed
in from above to the
linear transform.
And we've already computed
the gradient of that
in the preceding slides.
And so the final form of the
partial with respect to b
will be delta times
the remaining part.
And well, we've seen
that for partial of s
with respect to b,
the partial of z
with respect to b is
just the identity,
so the end result was delta.
But in this time,
we're then going
to have to work out the
partial of z with respect
to w and multiply that by delta.
So that's the part that
we still haven't yet done.
So and this is where things
get in some sense, a little bit
hairier, and so
there's something
that's important to explain.
So what should we have for
the Jacobian of ds / dW?
Well, that's a function
that has one output,
the output is just a
score of real number,
and then it has n by m inputs.
So that Jacobian is a 1
by n by m matrix, i.e.
a very long low vector
but that's correct math.
But it turns out
that that's kind of
bad for our neural networks.
Because remember, what we want
to do with our neural networks
is do stochastic
gradient descent.
And we want to say theta
new equals theta old
minus a small multiplier
times the gradient.
And well, actually the W
matrix is an n by m matrix,
and so we couldn't
actually do the subtraction
if this gradient we calculate
is just a huge row vector.
We'd like to have it as the
same shape as the W matrix.
In neural network
land when we do this,
we depart from pure
math at this point
and we use what we call
the shape convention.
So what we're going
to say is and you're
meant to use this for
answers in the assignment,
that the shape of
the gradient we're
always going to make to be
the shape of the parameters.
And so therefore,
ds / dW, we are also
going to represent as an
n by m matrix just like W,
and we're going to reshape
the Jacobian to place it
into this matrix shape.
OK, so if we want to place it
into this matrix shape, what
are we going to want
to get for ds / dW?
Well, we know that it's
going to involve delta,
our local error signal and
then we have to work out
something for dz / dW.
Well, since z equals
Wx plus b, you'd
kind of expect that
the answer should be x.
And that's right.
So the answer to
ds / dW is going
to be delta transpose
times x transpose.
And so the form that we're
getting for this derivative is
going to be the product of
the local error signal that
comes from above versus what we
calculate from the local input
x.
So that shouldn't yet be
obvious why that is true.
So let me just go through
in a bit more detail
why that's true.
So when we want to
work out the ds / dW,
right, it's sort
of delta times dz /
dW where that's computing
for z is Wx plus b.
So let's just
consider for a moment
what the derivative
is with respect
to a single weight, Wij.
So Wij might be W23 that's shown
in my little neural network
here.
And so the first thing to
notice is that Wij only
contributes to zi, so
it's going into to z2,
which then computes h2 and it
has no effect whatsoever on h1.
OK, so when we're
working out dzi,
dWij, it's going to be
dWix that sort of row,
that row of the matrix plus
bi, which means that for--
we've got a kind of a
sum of Wik times xk.
And then for this sum, this
is like one variable calculus
that when we're taking the
derivative of this with respect
to Wij, every term in
the sum is going to be 0,
the derivative is going to
be 0 except for the one that
involves Wij.
And then the derivative
of that is just
like ax with respect
to a, it's going
to be x so you get
xj out as the answer.
And so the end result of that
is that when we're working out
what we want as the
answer is that we're
going to get these columns
where x1 is all that's left,
x2 is all that's left through
xm is all that's left.
And then that's multiplied by
the vectors of the local error
signal from above.
And what we want to compute is
this outer product matrix where
we're getting the different
combinations of the delta
and the x.
And so we can get
the n by m matrix
that we'd like to have
via our shape convention
by taking delta transpose,
which is n by 1 times
x transpose, which
is n1 by m and then
we get this out
of product matrix.
So like that's the kind of a
hacky argument that I've made.
It's certainly a
way of doing things
that the dimensions work out
and it sort of makes sense,
there's a more detailed
run through this that
appears on the lecture notes.
And I encourage
you to sort of also
look at the more
mathy version of that.
Here's a little bit
more information
about the shape convention.
So well, first of
all one more example
of this, so when you're working
ds / db that comes out as--
its Jacobian is a row vector.
But similarly, you know
according to the shape
convention we want our gradient
to be the same shape as b and b
is column vector, so
that's sort of again,
they're different shapes and
you have to transpose one
to get the other.
And so effectively, what
we have is a disagreement
between the Jacobian form.
So the Jacobian form makes
sense for calculus and math.
Because if you want to have
that like I claimed, that matrix
calculus is just like
single variable calculus
apart from using
vectors and matrices,
you can just multiply
together the parftials,
that only works out if
you're using Jacobians.
But on the other
hand, if you want
to do stochastic
gradient descent
and be able to sort of subtract
off a piece of the gradient,
that only works if you
have the same shape
matrix for the gradient as you
do for the original matrix.
And so this is a bit confusing,
but that's just the reality,
there are both of
these two things.
So the Jacobian form is
useful in doing the calculus.
But for the answers
in the assignment,
we want the answers to be
presented using the shape
convention so that
the gradient is shown
in the same shape
as the parameters
and therefore, you'll
be able to-- it's
the right shape for doing
a gradient update by just
subtracting a small
amount of the gradient.
So for working through things
there are then basically
two choices.
One choice is to work through
all the math using Jacobians
and then right at the end, to
reshape following the shape
convention to give the answer.
So that's what I did
when I worked out ds/ db.
We worked through
it using Jacobians,
we got an answer but it
turned out to be a row vector,
and so well then we
have to transpose that
at the end to get into the right
shape for the shape convention.
The alternative is to always
follow the shape convention.
And that's kind of what I did
when I was then working out
ds / dW, I didn't
fully use Jacobians.
I said, Oh, well, when we work
out whatever it was, dz / dW,
let's work out what
shape we want it to be
and what to fill
in the cells with.
And if you're sort of
trying to do it immediately
with the shape convention,
it's a little bit more hacky
in a way, since
you know you have
to look at the dimensions
for what you want and figure
out when to transpose
or to reshape the matrix
to be at the right shape.
But the kind of informal
reasoning that I gave
is what you do and what works.
And one way, and there are
sort of hints that you can use,
right, that you know that
your gradient should always
be the same shape
as your parameters
and you know that the
error message coming in
will always have the
same dimensionality
as that hidden layer, and
you can work it out always
following the shape convention.
OK, so that is hey, doing
this is all matrix calculus.
So after pausing for
breath for a second,
the rest of the
lecture is then OK.
Let's look at how our software
trains neural networks using
what's referred to as the
backpropagation algorithm.
So the short answer is
basically we've already done it.
The rest of the lecture is easy.
So essentially, I've just shown
you what the backpropagation
algorithm does.
So the backpropagation
algorithm is
judiciously taking and
propagating derivatives
using the matrix chain rule.
The rest of the back
propagation algorithm
is to say, OK, when we
have these neural networks,
we have a lot of shared
structure and shared
derivatives.
So what we want
to do is maximally
efficiently re-use
derivatives of higher layers
when we're computing
derivatives for lower layers
so that we minimize computation.
And I already pointed
that out in the first half
but we want to
systematically exploit that.
And so the way we do that
in our computational systems
is they construct
computation graphs.
So this maybe looks a
little bit like what
you saw in a compilers
class if you did one, right,
that you're creating--
I call it here computation graph
but it's really a tree, right?
So you're creating here
this tree of computations
in this case but in
a more general case
it's some kind of directed
graph of computations which has
source nodes, which are inputs.
Either inputs like x or
input parameters like W
and b and its interior
nodes are operations.
And so then once we've
constructed a graph,
and so this graph corresponds
to exactly the example
I did before, right?
That this was our little neural
net that's in the top right
and here's the corresponding
computation graph of computing
Wx plus b put it through
the sigmoid non-linearity f
multiply the resulting dot
product with the resulting
vector with u, gives
us our output score s.
OK, so what we do
to compute this
is we pass along the edges
the results of operations.
So this is Wx then z then
h and then our output is s.
And so the first
thing we want to be
able to do to compute
with neural networks
is to be able to compute
four different inputs, what
the output is.
And so that's referred to
as forward propagation.
And so we simply run
this expression much
like you standardly
do in a compiler
to compute the value
of s and that's
the forward propagation phase.
But the essential additional
element of neural networks
is that we then also want
to be able to send back
gradients which will
tell us how to update
the parameters of the model.
And so it's this ability to send
back gradients which gives us
the ability for these models
to learn once we have a loss
function at the
end, we can work out
how to change the
parameters of the model
so that they more accurately
produce the desired output,
i.e. they minimize the loss.
And so it's doing that part that
then is called backpropagation.
So we then-- once we
forward propagated a value
with our current
parameters, we then
head backwards reversing
the direction of the arrows
and pass along gradients down
to the different parameters
like b, and W, and
u that we can use
to change using stochastic
gradient descent what
the value of b is and
what the value of W is.
So we start off with ds
/ ds, which is just 1,
and then we run
our backpropagation
and we're using the sort
of same kind of composition
of Jacobian.
So we have ds / dh
here and ds / dz
and we progressively pass
back those gradients.
So we just need to work out how
to efficiently and cleanly do
this in a computational system.
And so let's sort of
work through again a few
of these cases.
So the general situation is
we have a particular node,
so a node is where some kind of
operation like multiplication
or a non-linearity happens.
And so the simplest
case is that we've
got one output and one input.
So we'll do that first.
So that's like h equals f of z.
So what we have is an
upstream gradient ds / dh
and what we want to do is
compute the downstream gradient
of ds / dz.
And the way we're going
to do that is say,
well for this function
f it's a function,
it's got a derivative
for a gradient.
So what we want to do is work
out that local gradient dh /
dz, and then that gives us
everything that we need to work
out ds/ dz because that's
precisely we're going to use
the chain rule.
We're going to say that ds / dz
equals the product of ds / dh
times dh / dz where this
is, again, using Jacobians.
OK, so the general principle
that we're going to use
is the downstream gradient
equals the upstream gradient
times the local gradient.
OK, sometimes it gets a
little bit more complicated.
So we might have multiple
inputs to a function.
So this is the matrix vector
multiply, so z equals Wx.
OK, when there are
multiple inputs,
we still have an upstream
gradient ds / dz,
but what we're going to do
is work out a local gradient
with respect to each input.
So we have dz / dw and dz / dx.
And so then at that point,
it's exactly the same
for each piece of it.
We're going to work out the
downstream gradients ds / dW
and ds / dx by using the
chain rule with respect
to the particular
local gradient.
So let's go through
an example of this.
I mean, this is kind
of a silly example,
it's not really an example that
looks like a typical neural net
but it's sort of a
simple example where
we can show some of the
components of what we do.
So what we're going
to do is we're
going to calculate
f of xyz, which
is being calculated as x plus
y times the max of y and z.
And we've got particular
values that we're
starting off with x equals 1,
y equals 2, and z equals 0.
So these are the current
values of our parameters.
And so we can say,
OK, well, we want
to build an expression
tree for that.
Here's our expression tree.
We're taking x plus y, we're
taking the max of y and z,
and then we're multiplying them.
And so our forward propagation
phase is just to run this.
So we take the values
of our parameters
and we simply start to
compute with them, right?
So we have 1, 2, 2, 0
and we add them as 3,
the max is 2 we multiply
them and that gives us 6.
OK, so then at
that point, we then
want to go and work out how to
do things for back propagation
and how these back
propagation steps work.
And so the first
part of that is sort
of working out what our local
gradients are going to be.
So this is a here
and this is x and y.
So da / dx since a equals x
plus y is just going to be 1.
And da / dy is
also going to be 1.
Then for b equals the max of
yz, so this is this max node,
So the local gradients for that
is it's going to depend on y--
where the y is greater than z.
So db / dy is going
to be 1 if and only
if y is greater than z, which
it is at our particular point
here.
So that's 1.
And dbdz is going to be 1
only if z is greater than y.
So for our particular values
here that one is going to be 0.
And then finally here
we are calculating
the product f equals ab.
So for that, we're going to--
wait, sorry, that slide
is a little imperfect.
OK, so for the product, the
derivative f with respect to a
is equal to b, which is
2, and the derivative
of f with respect
to b is a equals 3.
So that gives us all of the
local gradients at each node.
And so then to run
back propagation,
we start with df /
df, which is just 1,
and then we're going to work
out that the downstream equals
the upstream times the local.
OK, so the local--
so when you have a
product like this,
note that sort of
the gradients flip.
So we take upstream times
the local, which is 2, oops.
So the downstream is 2,
on this side df / db is 3.
So we're taking upstream
times local, that gives us 3,
and so that gives us--
that propagates values to
the plus and max nodes.
And so then we continue along.
So for the max node, the local
gradient db / dy equals 1.
So we're going to
take upstream is 3,
so it only takes 3 times
1 and that gives us 3.
db / dz is 0 because of the fact
that z value is not the max.
So we're taking 3 times 0 and
saying the gradient there is 0.
So finally, during
the plus node,
the local gradients for
both x and y there are 1.
So we're just getting
2 times 1 in both cases
and we're saying that the
gradients there are 2.
OK, and so again at
the end of the day,
the interpretation here is that
this is giving us information
as to if we wiggle the
values of x, y, and z,
how much of a difference
does it make to the output?
What is the slope, the gradient
with respect to the variable?
So what we've seen is that since
z isn't the max of y and z,
if I change the value of z a
little, like I make the z 0.1
or minus 0.1, it
makes no difference
at all to what I
compute as the output.
So therefore, the
gradient there is 0.
If I change the
value of x a little,
then that is going
to have an effect.
And it's going to affect
the output by twice as much
as the amount I change it.
Right, so and that's because
the df / dz equals 2.
So interestingly, so I mean we
can basically work that out.
So if we imagine
making sort of x 2.1,
well, then what we'd
calculate the max is 2--
I'm so sorry, if we make x 1.1,
we then get the max here is 2,
and we get 1.1 plus 2 is
3.1, so we get 3.1 times
2 so they'd be about 6.2.
So changing x by 0.1 has
added 0.2 to the value of f.
Conversely, for the value of
y, we find that df dy equals 5.
So, what we do when we've got
two things coming out here,
as I'll go through
again in a moment,
is we're summing the gradient.
So, again, 3 plus 2 equals 5.
And empirically
that's what happens.
So, if we consider fiddling
the value of y a little,
let's say we make
it a value of 2.1,
then the prediction is
they'll have 5 times
as big an effect on the
output value that we compute.
And, well, what do we compute?
So, we compute 1 plus 2.1.
So that's 3.1.
Then we compute the max
of 2.1 and 0, is 2.1.
So we'll take the
product of 2.1 and 3.1.
And I calculate that in
advance, since I can't really
do this arithmetic in my head.
And the product of
those two is 6.51.
So it has gone up about by 0.5.
So we've multiplied by
fiddling it by 0.1, by 5 times
to work out the magnitude
of the effect on the output.
OK.
So for this--
Before I did the case of when
we had one in and one out here,
and multiple ins
and one out here.
The case that I hadn't
actually dealt with
is the case of when you have
multiple outward branches, that
then turned up in
the computation of y.
So, once you have multiple
outward branches, what
you're doing is you're summing.
So that when you want
to work out the df dy,
you've got a local
gradient, you've
got two upstream
gradients, and you're
working it out with
respect to each of them
as in the chain rule.
And then you're
summing them together
to work out the
impact at the end.
So, we also saw some of the
other node intuitions, which
it's useful to have doing this.
So when you have
an addition, that
distributes the
upstream gradient
to each of the things below it.
When you have max, it's
like a routing node.
So when you have max, you
have the upstream gradient
and it goes to one of
the branches below it,
and the rest of them
get no gradient.
When you then have
a multiplication,
it has this effect of
switching the gradient.
So, if you're taking 3 by 2,
the gradient on the 2 side
is 3 and on the 3 side is 2.
And if you think about it in
terms of how much effect you
get from when you're doing this
sort of wiggling, that totally
makes sense, right?
Because if you're multiplying
another number by 3,
then any change here is
going to be multiplied by 3,
and vice versa.
OK.
So, this is the kind
of computation graph
that we want to use to work
out derivatives in an automated
computational fashion,
which is the basis
of the back
propagation algorithm.
But at that point, this
is what we're doing,
but there's still one
mistake that we can make.
It would be wrong for us to sort
of say, OK, well, first of all,
we want to work out ds / db.
So, look, we can start up here.
We can propagate
our upstream errors,
work out local gradients.
Upstream our local gradient
and keep all the way down,
and get the ds / db down here.
OK.
Next we want to
do it for ds / dw.
Let's just run it
all over again.
Because if we did that, we'd
be doing repeated computation,
as I showed in the first half.
That this term is
the same both times.
This term is the
same both times.
That only the bits
at the end differ.
So, what we want to do is
avoid duplicated computation
and compute all the
gradients that we're
going to need successively,
so that we only do them once.
And so that was
analogous to when
I introduced this delta variable
when we computed gradients
by hand.
So, starting off here from--
Starting off here
with ds / ds is 1.
We then want to one time compute
gradient in the green here.
One time compute the
gradient in green here.
That's all common work.
Then we're going to take the
local gradient for dz / db
and multiply that by
the upstream gradient
to have worked out ds / db.
And then we're going to take
the same upstream gradient,
and then work out the
local gradient here.
And then sort of propagate
that down to give us ds / dw.
So, the end result is, we
want to sort of systematically
work to forward
computation forward
in the graph, and
backward computation,
back propagation backward
in the graph in a way
that we do things efficiently.
So this is the general
form of the algorithm,
which works for an
arbitrary computation graph.
So, at the end of the day, we've
got a single scalar output, z.
And then we have inputs and
parameters, which compute z.
And so once we have
this computation graph--
And I added in this
funky extra arrow
here to make it a more
general computation graph.
Well, we can always say
that we can work out
a starting point, something
that doesn't depend on anything.
So in this case, both of
these bottom two nodes
don't depend on anything else.
So we can start
with them, and we
can start to compute forward.
We can compute values for
all of these second row
from the bottom nodes.
And then we're able to
compute the third ones up.
So, we can have a
topological sort
of the nodes based
on the dependencies
in this directed graph.
And we can compute the
value of each node,
given some subset
of its predecessors
which it depends on.
And so doing that is referred
to as the forward propagation
phase, and gives us a
computation of the scalar
output, z, using our
current parameters
and our current inputs.
And so then after that,
we run back propagation.
So for back propagation, we
initialize the output gradient,
dz / dz, as 1.
And then we visit nodes
in the reverse order
of the topological sort, and we
compute the gradients downward.
And so our recipe is that for
each node as we head down,
we're going to
compute the gradient
of the node with respect to
its successors the things
that it feeds into.
And how we compute that gradient
is using this chain rule
that we've looked at.
So this is sort of the
generalized form of the chain
rule where we have
multiple outputs.
And so we're summing over
the different outputs.
And then for each
output, we're computing
the product of the
upstream gradient
and the local gradient
with respect to that node.
And so we head downwards.
And we continue down the
reverse topological sort order,
and we work out the
gradient with respect
to each variable in this graph.
And so it hopefully
looks kind of intuitive
looking at this picture.
If you think of it like
this, the big O complexity
of forward propagation
and backward propagation
is the same, right?
In both cases, you're
doing a linear path
through all of these
nodes and calculating
values given predecessors, and
then values given successors.
I mean, you have to do a little
bit more work for working out
the gradients sort of as
shown by this chain rule,
but it's the same
big O complexity.
So, if somehow you're
implementing stuff for yourself
rather than relying
on the software,
and you're calculating the
gradients of a different order
of complexity of
forward propagation,
it means that you're
doing something wrong.
You're doing repeated work
that you shouldn't have to do.
OK.
So, this algorithm works
for a completely arbitrary
computation graph.
Any directed acyclic graph
you can apply this algorithm.
In general, what we find is that
we build neural networks that
have a regular layer structure.
So we have things like
a vector of inputs,
and then that's
multiplied by a matrix.
It's transformed into
another vector, which
might be multiplied
by another matrix,
or summed with another
matrix or something, right?
So, once we're using that kind
of regular layer structure,
we can then parallelize
the computation
by working out the gradients in
terms of Jacobians of vectors
and matrices, and do things in
parallel much more efficiently.
OK.
So, doing this is then
referred to as automatic
differentiation.
And so, essentially, if you
know the computation graph,
you should be able to have
your clever computer system
work out what the
derivatives of everything is,
and then apply back
propagation to work out
how to update the
parameters and learn.
And there's actually a
sort of an interesting sort
of thing of how history has gone
backwards here, which I'll just
note.
So, some of you
might be familiar
with symbolic
computation packages,
so those are things
like Mathematica.
So Mathematica, you can
give it a symbolic form
of a computation, and
then it can work out
derivatives for you.
So it should be the
case that if you
give a complete symbolic form
of a computation graph, then
it should be able to work out
all the derivatives for you.
And you never have to work out a
derivative by hand, whatsoever.
And that was actually attempted
in a famous deep learning
library called
Theano, which came out
of Yoshua Bengio's group at
the University of Montreal.
That it had a compiler
that did that kind
of symbolic manipulation.
But somehow, that
proved a little bit
too hard a road to follow.
I imagine that it actually might
come back again in the future.
And so, for modern deep
learning frameworks,
which includes both
TensorFlow, or PyTorch,
they do 90% of this computation
of automatic differentiation
for you, but they don't
actually symbolically compute
derivatives.
So, for each particular node
or layer of your deep learning
system, somebody,
either you or the person
who wrote that layer,
has handwritten
the local derivatives.
But then everything
from that point on,
the sort of the taking,
doing the chain rule
of combining upstream
gradients with local gradients
to work out downstream
gradients, that's then
all been done automatically
for back propagation
on the computation graph.
And so what that means is,
for a whole neural network,
you have a computation
graph, and it's
going to have a forward
pass and a backward pass.
And so for the
forward pass, you're
topologically sorting the nodes
based on their dependencies
in the computation graph.
And then for each node,
you're running forward
the forward computation
on that node.
And then for
backward propagation,
you're reversing the
topological sort of the graph.
And then for each
node in the graph,
you're running the
backward propagation,
which is the little bit
of back prop, the chain
rule at that node.
And then the result
of doing that is you
have gradients for your
inputs and parameters.
And so, this is--
The overall software
runs this for you.
And so what you want
to do is then actually
have stuff for particular
nodes or layers in the graph.
So, if I have a
multiply gate, it's
going to have a forward
algorithm, which
just computes that the
output is x times y
in terms of the two inputs.
And then I'm going to
want to tell it also
how to calculate the
local derivative.
So I want to say, what
is the local derivative.
So, dl / dx and dl / dy in
terms of the upstream gradient,
dl / dz.
And so, I will then manually
work out how to calculate that.
And normally what
I have to do is,
I assume the forward
pass is being run first.
And I'm going to shove into some
local variables for my class
the values that we used in
the forward computation.
So as well as computing
z equals x times y,
I'm going to sort of
remember what x and y were.
So that then when I'm asked
to compute the backward pass,
I'm then going to
have implemented here
what we saw earlier of--
That when it's xy, you're going
to sort of swap the y and the x
to work out the local gradients.
And so then I'm going
to multiply those
by the upstream gradient.
And I'm going to return--
I've just written it here
as a sort of a little list,
but really it's going to be a
NumPy vector of the gradients.
OK.
So that's 98% of what I
wanted to cover today.
Just a couple of
quick comments left.
So, that can and should
all be automated.
Sometimes you want to
just check if you're
computing the right gradients.
And so the standard
way of checking
that you're computing
the right gradients
is to manually work
out the gradient
by doing a numeric
calculation of the gradient.
And so, you can do that--
So you can work out what the
derivative of f with respect
to x should be, by choosing
some sort of small number,
like 10 to the minus 4, adding
it to x, subtracting it from x.
And then so the difference
between these numbers is 2h.
Dividing it through by 2h.
And you're simply
working out the rise
over the run, which is the
slope at that point with respect
to x.
And that's an approximation of
the gradient of f with respect
to x at that value of x.
So, this is so simple.
You can't make a
mistake implementing it.
And so therefore,
you can use this
to check whether your gradient
values are correct or not.
This isn't something that
you'd want to use much.
Because not only
is it approximate,
but it's extremely slow.
Because to work
this out, you have
to run the forward computation
for every parameter
of the model.
So, if you have a model
with a million parameters,
you're now doing a
million times as much work
to run back prop as you
would do if you're actually
using calculus.
So, calculus is a
good thing to know.
But it can be really useful to
check that the right values are
being calculated.
In the old days when we
handwrote everything,
this was kind of
the key unit test
that people used everywhere.
These days, most
of the time you're
reusing layers that
are built into PyTorch,
or some other deep
learning framework.
So it's much less needed.
But sometimes you're
implementing your own layer,
and you really do want
to check that things
are implemented correctly.
There's a fine point in
the way this is written.
If you saw this sort of in
high school calculus class,
you will have seen rise
over run of f(x) plus h
minus f(x) divided by h.
It turns out that doing this
two sided estimate like this,
is much, much more accurate
than doing a one sided estimate.
And so you're really
much encouraged to use
this approximation.
OK.
So at that point, we've
mastered the core technology
of neural nets.
Back propagation is recursively
and hence efficiently
applying the chain rule
along the computation graph,
with this key step that
downstream gradient equals
upstream gradient
times local gradient.
And so for calculating
with neural nets,
we do the forward
pass to work out
values with current parameters,
then run back propagation
to work out the
gradient of the loss,
currently computed loss with
respect to those parameters.
Now, to some extent, with
modern deep learning frameworks,
you don't actually have to know
how to do any of this, right?
It's the same as you
don't have to know
how to implement a C compiler.
You can just write C code and
say gcc, and it'll compile it
and it'll run the
right stuff for you.
And that's the kind
of functionality
you get from the
PyTorch framework.
So, do come along to the
PyTorch tutorial this Friday
and get a sense
about how easy it
is to write neural networks
using a framework like PyTorch
or TensorFlow.
And it's so easy,
that's why high school
students across
the nation are now
doing their science projects
training deep learning systems.
Because you don't actually
have to understand
very much to bung a few neural
network layers together and set
it computing on some data.
But we hope in this
class that you actually
are also learning how these
things are implemented.
So you have a deeper
understanding than that.
And it turns out that
sometimes you need
to have a deeper understanding.
So, back propagation doesn't
always work perfectly.
And so understanding
what it's really doing
can be crucial to
debugging things.
And so we'll actually
see an example of that
fairly soon when
we start looking
at recurrent models and some
of the problems that they have,
which will require us to think
a bit more deeply about what's
happening in our
gradient computations.
OK.
That's it for today.