Hello, everyone, and
welcome back into week four.
So for week four, it's
going to come in two halves.
So today, I'm going to talk
about machine translation
related topics.
And then in the second
half of the week,
we take a little bit of a break
from learning more and more
on neural network
topics, and talk
about final projects, but
also some practical tips
for building neural
network systems.
So for today's lecture,
this is an important content
full lecture.
So first of all, I'm going to
introduce a new task, machine
translation.
And it turns out that
our task is a major use
case of a new
architectural technique
to teach you about
deep learning, which
is sequence to sequence models.
And so we'll spend a
lot of time on those.
And then there's a
crucial way that's
been developed to
improve sequence
to sequence models, which
is the idea of attention.
And so that's what I'll
talk about in the final part
of the class.
I'm just checking
everyone's keeping up
with what's happening.
So first of all,
assignment 3 is due today.
So hopefully you've all got in
your neural dependency parses
parsing text well.
At the same time,
assignment 4 is out today.
And really today's lecture
is the primary content
for what you'll be using for
building your assignment 4
systems.
Switching it up for a little.
For assignment 4, we give
you a mighty two extra days.
So you get nine days for it.
And it's due on Thursday.
On the other hand,
do please be aware
that assignment 4
is bigger and harder
than the previous assignments.
So do make sure you get
started on it early.
And then as I mentioned Thursday
I'll turn to final projects.
OK.
So let's get straight into
this with machine translation.
So very quickly, I
wanted to tell you
a little bit about where we were
and what we did before we get
to neural machine translation.
And so let's do the prehistory
of machine translation.
So machine translation
is the task
of translating a sentence
x from one language
which is called
the source language
to another language, the target
language forming a sentence y.
So we start off with a
source language sentence x.
L'homme, and then we
translate it and we get out
the translation
man is born free,
but everywhere he is in chains.
OK.
So there's our
machine translation.
OK.
So in the early
1950s, there started
to be work on
machine translation.
And so it's actually a
thing about computer science
if you find things that
have machine in the name,
most of them are old things.
And this really kind of
came about in the US context
in the context of the Cold War.
So there was this
desire to keep tabs
on what the Russians were doing.
And people had the idea that
because some of the earliest
computers had been so successful
at doing code breaking
during the Second World War.
Then maybe we could
set early computers
to work during the Cold
War to do translation.
And hopefully this will play
and you'll be able to hear it.
Here's a little
video clip showing
some of the earliest work in
machine translation from 1954.
They hadn't reckoned
with ambiguity
when they set out
to use computers
to translate languages.
$500,000 simple calculator,
most versatile electronic brain
known, translates
Russian into English.
Instead of mathematical
wizardry, a sentence
in Russian, it could be--
One of the first non-numerical
applications of computers,
it was hyped as the
solution to the Cold War
obsession of keeping tabs on
what the Russians were doing.
Claims were made that
the computer would
replace most human translators.
Then of course, you're just
in the experimental stage.
When you go in for
full scale production
what will the capacity be?
We should be able
to do about with
a modern commercial
computer about one
to two million words an hour.
And this will be quite
an adequate speed
to cope with the whole
output of the Soviet Union
in just a few hours of
computer time a week.
When do you hope to be
able to achieve this speed?
I our experiments go well,
then perhaps within five years
or so.
And finally, Mr.
McDaniel, does this mean
the end of human translators?
I say yes for translators
of scientific and technical
material.
But as regards to
poetry and novels,
no, I don't think we'll
ever replace the translators
of that type of material.
Mr. McDaniel, thank
you very much.
But despite the hype it
ran into deep trouble.
Yeah.
So the experiments
did not go well.
And so in retrospect,
it's not very surprising
that the early work did
not work out very well.
I mean, this was in the
sort of really beginning
of the computer
age in the 1950s.
That it was also the
beginning of people starting
to understand the science
of human languages,
the field of linguistics.
So really people had
not much understanding
of either side of
what was happening.
So what you had was
people were trying
to write systems on really
incredibly primitive computers,
right?
It's probably the case that
now if you have a USB C power
brick, that it has more
computational capacity
inside it, than the
computers that they
were using to translate.
And so effectively,
what you were getting
were very simple rule based
systems and word lookup.
So it was sort like,
dictionary look up a word
and get its translation.
But that just didn't work well.
Because human languages are
much more complex than that.
Often words have many
meanings and different senses
as we've sort of
discussed about a bit.
Often there are idioms.
You need to
understand the grammar
to rewrite the sentences.
So for all sorts of reasons,
it didn't work well.
And this idea was
largely canned.
In particular, there was a
famous US government report
in the mid 1960s, the ALPAC
report, which basically
concluded this wasn't working.
Oops.
OK.
Work then did revive
in AI at doing
rule based methods of machine
translation in the 90s.
But when things
really became alive
was once you got
into the mid 90s,
and when they were in the
period of statistical NLP
that we've seen in other
places in the course.
And then the idea began,
can we start with just data
about translation i.e.
sentences and
their translations,
and learn a
probabilistic model that
can predict the translations
of fresh sentences?
So suppose we're translating
French into English.
So what we want to do is
build a probabilistic model
that given a French sentence.
We can say, what's
the probability
of different English
translations?
And then we'll choose the
most likely translation.
We can then found--
it was found felicitous to break
this down into two components
by just reversing
this with Bayes' rule.
So if instead we
had a probability
over English sentences
p of y, and then
a probability of
a French sentence
given an English
sentence, that people
were able to make more progress.
And it's not
immediately obvious as
to why this should
be because this
is sort of just a trivial
rewrite with Bayes' rule.
That allowed the problem to be
separated into two parts which
proved to be more tractable.
So on the left hand
side, you effectively
had a translation model
where you could just
give a probability
of words or phrases
being translated between
the two languages
without having to bother
about the structural word
order of the languages.
And then on the right hand,
you saw precisely what
we spent a long time with last
week, which is this is just
a probabilistic language model.
So if we have a very
good model of what
good fluent English
sentences sound like,
which we can build just
from monolingual data,
we can then get it to make sure
we're producing sentences that
sound good while the
translation model hopefully
puts the right words into them.
So how do we learn
the translation model
since we haven't covered that?
So the starting point
was to get a large amount
of parallel data, which is
human translated sentences.
At this point, it's
mandatory that I
show a picture of
the Rosetta Stone
which is the famous original
piece of parallel data
that allowed the decoding
of Egyptian hieroglyphs
because it had the same piece
of text in different languages.
In the modern world, there
are fortunately for people
who build natural language
processing systems quite
a few places, where
parallel data is
produced in large quantities.
So the European Union produces
a huge amount of parallel text
across European languages.
The French.
Sorry.
Not the French.
The Canadian
Parliament conveniently
produces parallel text
between French and English,
and even a limited amount in
Inuktitut, Canadian Eskimo.
And then the Hong
Kong parliament
produces English and Chinese.
So there's a fair availability
from different sources.
And we can use that
to build models.
So how do we do it though?
All we have is these sentences.
And it's not quite obvious how
to build a probabilistic model
out of those.
Well, as before, what we want to
do is break this problem down.
So in this case, what
we're going to do
is introduce an extra variable,
which is an alignment variable.
So a is the alignment
variable, which
is going to give a
word level or sometimes
phrase level correspondence
between parts
of the source sentence
and the target sentence.
So this is an example
of an alignment.
And so if we could induce
this alignment between the two
sentences, then we
can have probabilities
of pieces of how likely
a word or a short phrase
is translated in
a particular way.
And in general, alignment is
working out the correspondence
between words that is capturing
the grammatical differences
between languages.
So words will occur in different
orders in different languages
depending on whether
it's a language that
puts on the subject
before the verb,
or the subject after the
verb, or the verb before both
the subject and the object.
And the alignments will
also capture something
about differences about the ways
that work languages do things.
So what we find is that we get
every possibility of how words
can align between languages.
So you can have words
that don't get translated
at all in the other language.
So in French, you put a definite
article "the" before country
names like Japon.
So when that gets translated
to English, you just get Japan.
So there's no
translation of the "the".
So it just goes away.
On the other hand, you can get
many to one translations, where
one French word gets translated
as several English words.
So for the last
French word, it's
been translated as Aboriginal
people as multiple words.
You can get the
reverse, where you
can have several
French words that get
translated as one English word.
So mis en application is getting
translated as implemented.
And you can get even
more complicated ones.
So here we sort of have
four English words being
translated as two French words.
But they don't really break down
and translate each other well.
I mean, these things don't
only happen across languages.
They also happen
within the language
when you have different ways
of saying the same thing.
So another way you
might have expressed
the poor don't have any money is
to say the poor are moneyless.
And that's much more
similar to how the French is
being rendered here.
And so even English
to English, you
have the same kind
of alignment problem.
So probabilistic or
statistical machine translation
is more commonly known.
What we wanted to do is
learn these alignments.
And there's a bunch of sources
of information you could use.
If you start with
parallel sentences,
you can see how often
words and phrases
co-occur in parallel sentences.
You can look at their
positions in the sentence.
And figure out what
are good alignments.
But alignments are
a categorical thing.
They're not probabilistic and
so they are latent variables.
And so you need to use
special learning algorithms
like the expectation
maximization algorithm
for learning about
latent variables.
In the olden days of CS224N
before we start doing it
all with deep
learning, we spent tons
of CS224N dealing with
latent variable algorithms.
But these days, we
don't cover that at all.
And you're going to have to
go off and see CS228 if you
want to know more about that.
And we're not
really expecting you
to understand the details here.
But I did then want to
say a bit more about how
decoding was done in a
statistical machine translation
system.
And so what we wanted to do
is to say we had a translation
model and a language model.
And we want to pick
out the most likely
why there's the translation
of the sentence.
And what kind of process
could we use to do that?
Well, the naive thing
is to say, well,
let's just enumerate every
possible y and calculate
its probability.
But we can't possibly
do that because there's
a number of translation
sentences in the target
language.
That's exponential in the
length of the sentence.
So that's way too expensive.
So we need to have some
way to break it down more.
And while we had a simple
way for language models,
we just generated words one at a
time and laid out the sentence.
And so that seems a
reasonable thing to do.
But here we need to
deal with the fact
that things occur in different
orders in source languages
and in translations.
And so we do want to
break it into pieces
with an independence assumption
like the language model.
But then we want a
way of breaking things
apart and exploring it in what's
called a decoding process.
So this is the way it was done.
So we start with
a source sentence.
So this is a German sentence.
And as is standard in German.
You're getting this
second position verb.
So that's probably not
in the right position
for where the English
translation is going to be.
So we might need to
rearrange the words.
So what we have is based
on the translation model.
We have words or
phrases that are
reasonably likely translations
of each German word,
or sometimes a German phrase.
So these are effectively
the LEGO pieces out
of which we're going to want
to create the translation.
And so then inside that,
making use of this data,
we're going to generate
the translation piece
by piece kind of like we
did with our neural language
models.
So we going to start with
an empty translation.
And then we're
going to say, well,
we want to use one
of these LEGO pieces.
And so we could explore
different possible ones.
So there's a search process.
But one of the
possible pieces is
we could translate
"er" with "he",
or we could start the
sentence with "are"
translating the second word.
So we could explore various
likely possibilities.
And if we're guided
by our language model,
it's probably much more likely
to start the sentence with he
than it is to start the
sentence with "are" though "are"
is not impossible..
OK.
And then the other
thing we're doing
with these little blotches
of black up at the top,
we're sort of recording which
German words we've translated.
And so we explore forward
in the translation process.
And we could decide
that we could translate
next the second word
goes, or we could
translate the negation here,
and translate that as does not.
When we explore
various continuations.
And in the process, I'll
go through in more detail
later when we do the
neural equivalent.
We sort of do this search where
we explore likely translations
and prune.
And eventually, we've
translated the whole
of the input sentence.
And I've worked out a
fairly likely translation.
He does not go home.
And that's what we use
as the translation.
OK.
So in the period from
about 1997 to around 2013,
statistical machine translation
was a huge research field.
The best systems were
extremely complex.
And they had hundreds of
details that I certainly
haven't mentioned here.
The systems have lots of
separately designed and built
components.
So I mentioned language model
and the translation model.
But they had lots of other
components for reordering
models, and inflection
models, and other things.
There was lots of
feature engineering.
Typically, the models also made
use of lots of extra resources.
And they were lots of
human effort to maintain.
But nevertheless, they were
already fairly successful.
So Google Translate
launched in the mid 2000s.
And people thought
wow, this is amazing.
You could start to get sort
of semi-decent automatic
translations for
different web pages.
But that was chugging
along well enough.
And then we got to 2014.
And really with
enormous suddenness,
people then worked out ways
of doing machine translation
using a large neural network.
And these large
neural networks proved
to be just extremely successful,
and largely blew away
everything that preceded it.
So for the next big part of the
lecture, what I'd like to do
is tell you something about
neural machine translation.
Neural machine
translation, well, it
means you're using
a neural network
to do machine translation.
But in practice, it's meant
slightly more than that.
It has meant that
we're going to build
one very large neural
network, which completely
does translation end to end.
So we're going to have
a large neural network,
we're going to feed in the
source sentence into the input.
And what's going to
come out of the output
of the neural network is the
translation of the sentence.
We're going to
train that model end
to end on parallel sentences.
And it's the entire
system rather
than being lots of
separate components
as in an old fashioned
machine translation system.
And we'll see that in a bit.
So these neural
network architectures
are called sequence
to sequence models
or commonly abbreviated seq2seq.
And they involve
two neural networks.
Here it says two RNNs.
The version I'm presenting
now has two RNNs.
But more generally, they
involve two neural networks.
There's one neural
network that is going
to encode the source center.
So if we have a
source sentence here,
we are going to
encode that sentence.
And what we know about a
way that we can do that.
So using the kind of LSTMs
that we saw last class,
we can start at the beginning
and go through a sentence
and update the hidden
state each time.
And that will give us a
representation of the content
of the source sentence.
So that's the first
sequence model, which
encodes the source sentence.
And we'll use the idea
that the final hidden state
of the encode RNN is
going to for instance,
represent the source sentence.
And we're going to
feed it in directly
as the initial hidden state
for the decoder, or RNN.
So then on the other
side of the picture,
we have our decoder RNN.
And it's a language
model that's going
to generate a target
sentence conditioned
on the final hidden
state of the encoder RNN.
So we're going to start with
the input of start symbol.
We're going to feed in the
hidden state from the encoder
RNN.
And now this second green
RNN has completely separate
parameters.
I might just emphasize.
But we do the same kind
of LSTM computations
and generate a first word
of the sentence, "he."
And so then doing
LSTM generation just
like last class, we copy
that down as the next input.
We run the next
step of the LSTM,
generate another word here,
copy it down, and chug along.
And we've translated
the sentence, right?
So this is showing
the test time behavior
when we're generating
the next sentence.
For the training
time behavior, when
we have parallel
sentences, we're
still using the same kind of
sequence to sequence model.
But we're doing it
with the decoder part
just like training a
language model, where we're
wanting to do teacher forcing
and predict each word that's
actually found in the
source language sentence.
Sequence to sequence
models have been
an incredibly powerful,
widely used work force
in neural networks for NLP.
So although historically,
machine translation
was the first big
use of them, and it's
sort of the canonical
use, they're
used everywhere else as well.
So you can do many other
NLP tasks for them.
So you can do summarization.
You can think of
text summarization
as translating a long
text into a short text.
But you can use them
for other things
that are in no way a
translation whatsoever.
So they're commonly used
for neural dialogue systems.
So the encoder will encode the
previous two utterances, say.
And then you will
use the decoder
to generate a next utterance.
Some other uses
are even freakier
but have proven to
be quite successful.
So if you have any
way of representing
the parse of a
sentence as a string,
and if you sort
of think a little
it's fairly obvious how you can
turn the parse of a sentence
into a string by just
making use of extra syntax
like parentheses, or putting in
explicit words that are saying
left arc, right arc, shifts
like the transition system
that you used for assignment 3.
Well, then we could say
let's use the encoder.
Feed the input
sentence to the encoder
and let it output the
transition sequence
of our dependency parser.
And somewhat surprisingly
that actually
works well as another way
to build a dependency parser
or other kinds of parser.
These models have
also been applied
not just to natural
languages, but to other kinds
of languages, including
music, and also
programming language code.
So you can train
a seq2seq system,
where it reads in pseudocode
in natural language,
and it generates
out Python code.
And if you have a
good enough one,
it can do the
assignment for you.
So this central new idea
here with our sequence
to sequence models is we have an
example of conditional language
models.
So previously, the main
thing we were doing
was just to start at the
beginning of the sentence
and generate a sentence
based on nothing.
But here we have
something that is
going to determine or
partially determine
that is going to condition
what we should produce.
So we have a source sentence.
And that's going to
strongly determine
what is a good translation.
And so to achieve that,
what we're going to do
is have some way of transferring
information about the source
sentence from the
encoder to trigger
what the decoder should do.
And the two standard ways
of doing that are you
either feed in a hidden state
as the initial hidden state
to the decoder, or sometimes
you will feed something
in as the initial
input to the decoder.
And so in neural
machine translation
we are directly calculating this
conditional model probability
of target language sentence
given source language sentence.
And so at each step,
as we break down
the word by word generation,
that we're conditioning
not only on previous words
of the target language,
but also each time on our
source language sentence x.
Because of this,
we actually know
a ton more about what our
sentence that we generate
should be.
So if you look at
the perplexities
of these kind of
conditional language models,
you will find them like the
numbers I showed last time.
They usually have almost
freakily low perplexities,
that you will have
models with perplexities
that are something like 4
or even less, sometimes 2.5
because you get a lot of
information about what words
you should be generating.
OK.
So then we have
the same questions
as we had for language
models in general.
How to train a neural machine
translation system and then
how to use it at runtime?
So let's go through both of
those in a bit more detail.
So the first step is we get
a large parallel corpus.
So we run off to the
European Union, for example.
And we grab a lot of
parallel English French data
from the European
parliament proceedings.
So then once we have
our parallel sentences,
what we're going to do is take
batches of source sentences
and target sentences.
We'll encode the source
sentence with our encoder LSTM.
We'll feed its final hidden
state into a target LSTM.
And this one, we
are now then going
to train word by word by
comparing what it predicts
is the most likely
word to be produced,
versus what the actual
first word, and then
the actual second word is.
And to the extent
that we get it wrong,
we're going to suffer some loss.
So this is going to
be the negative log
probability of generating
the correct next word "he"
and so on along the sentence.
And so in the same way that
we saw last time for language
models, we can work
out our overall loss
for the sentence doing
this teacher forcing style,
generate one word at a
time, calculate a loss
relative to the word that
you should have produced.
And so that loss then
gives us information
that we can backpropagate
through the entire network.
And the crucial thing
about these sequence
to sequence models that
has made them extremely
successful in practice is that
the entire thing is optimized
as a single system end to end.
So starting with
our final loss, we
backpropagate it right
through the system.
So we not only update all
the parameters of the decoder
model, but we also update all
of the parameters of the encoder
model, which in turn will
influence what conditioning
gets passed over from the
encoder to the decoder.
So this moment is a
good moment for me
to return to the three
slides that I skipped.
I'm running out of time at
the end of last time, which
is to mention multilayer RNNs.
So the RNNs that
we've looked at so far
are already deep on one
dimension then unroll
horizontally over
many time steps.
But they've been shallow
in that there's just
been a single layer of recurrent
structure about our sentences.
We can also make them deep
in the other dimension
by applying multiple RNNs
on top of each other.
And this gives us
some multilayer RNN.
Often also called a step RNN.
And having a
multilayer RNN allows
us the network to compute
more complex representations.
So simply put the lower RNNs
tend to compute lower level
features, and the higher RNNs
should compute higher level
features.
And just like in
other neural networks,
whether it's feed
forward networks,
or the kind of networks
you see in vision systems,
you get much greater
power and success
by having a stack
on multiple layers
of recurrent neural
networks, right?
That you might think that
oh, there are two things
I could do.
I could have a single LSTM with
a hidden state of dimension
2000, or I could have
four layers of LSTMs
with a hidden state of 500 each.
And it shouldn't
make any difference
because I've got the same
number of parameters roughly.
But that's not true.
In practice, it does
make a big difference.
And multilayer or stacked
RNNs are more powerful.
Can I ask you, there's a
good student question here?
What would lower level
versus higher level features
mean in this context?
Sure.
Yeah.
So I mean, in some sense, these
are somewhat flimsy terms.
The meaning isn't precise.
But typically,
what that's meaning
is that lower level
features and knowing
sort of more basic things
about words and phrases.
So that commonly might be
things like what part of speech
is this word, or are these
words the name of a person,
or the name of a company?
Whereas higher level
features refer to things
that are at a higher
semantic level.
So knowing more about
the overall structure
of a sentence, knowing
something about what it means,
whether a phrase has positive
or negative connotations.
What its semantics are when
you put together several words
into an idiomatic phrase,
roughly the higher level
kinds of things.
OK.
Jump ahead.
So when we build
one of these end
to end neural machine
translation systems,
if we want them to work
well, single layer LSTM
encoder-decoder in neurals
machine translation systems
just don't work well.
But you can build
something that is
no more complex than the model
that I've just explained now.
That does work pretty well by
making it a multi-layer stacked
LSTM neural machine
translation system.
So therefore, the
picture looks like this.
So we've got this
multilayer LSTM
that's going through
the source sentence.
And so now, at
each point in time,
we calculate a new
hidden representation
that rather than stopping there,
we sort of feed it as the input
into another layer
of LSTM, and we
calculate in the standard way
its new hidden representation.
And the output of it, we feed
into a third layer of LSTM.
And so we run that right along.
And so our representation
of the source sentence
from our encoder is then this
stack of three hidden layers,
whoops.
And then that we
use to then feed
in as the initial, as
the initial hidden layer
into then sort of
generating translations,
or for training the model
of comparing the losses.
So this is what the
picture of a LSTM
encoder-decoder neural
machine translation system
really looks like.
So in particular, to give
you some idea of that.
So a 2017 paper by
Denny Britz and others,
that what they found was
that for the encoder RNN,
it worked best if it
had two to four layers.
And four layers was best
for the decoder RNN.
And the details here like
for a lot of neural nets
depend so much on what you're
doing, and how much data
you have, and things like that.
But as rules of thumb
to have in your head,
it's almost invariably
the case that
having a two layer LSTM works
a lot better than having a one
layer LSTM.
After that, things
become much less clear.
It's not so infrequent that
if you try three layers,
it's a fraction better than two.
But not really.
And if you try four layers, it's
actually getting worse again.
It depends on how much
data, et cetera you have.
At any rate, it's normally
very hard with the model
architecture that I
just showed back here
to get better results with
more than four layers of LSTM.
Normally to do
deeper LSTM models
and get even better results.
You have to be adding extra
skip connections of the kind
that I talked about at the
very end of the last class.
Next week, John is going
to talk about transformer
based networks.
In contrast, for fairly
fundamental reasons.
They're typically much deeper.
But we'll leave discussing
them until we get on further.
So that was how we
train the model.
So let's just go a bit more
through what the possibilities
are for decoding and explore a
more complex form of decoding
than we've looked at.
But the simplest way
to decode is the one
that we presented so far.
So that we have our LSTM, we
start, generate a hidden state.
It has a probability
distribution over words.
And you choose the most
probable one the argmax.
And you say "he", and you copy
it down and you repeat over.
So doing this is referred
to as greedy decoding.
Taking the most probable
word on each step.
And it's sort of the
obvious thing to do,
and doesn't seem like it
could be a bad thing to do.
But it turns out
that it actually
can be a fairly
problematic thing to do.
And the idea of that is
that with greedy decoding,
you're taking locally what
seems the best choice.
And then you're stuck with it.
And you have no way
to undo decisions.
So if these examples have been
using this sentence about,
he hit me with a pie
going from translating
from French to English.
So if you start
off, then you say,
OK, "il" the first word in
the translation, should be he.
That looks good.
But then you-- and then you say,
well, hit, I'll generate hit.
Then somehow the model thinks
that the most likely next word
after hit is "a".
And there are lots of
reasons it could think so.
Because after hit most commonly,
there's a direct object now
and then he hit a car, he
hit a roadblock, right?
So that sounds pretty likely.
But once you've generated it,
there's no way to go backwards.
And so you just have to
keep on going from there
and you may not be able to
generate the translation
you want.
At best you can generate,
he hit a pie, or something.
So we'd like to be able
to explore a bit more
in generating our translations.
And well, what could we do?
Well, I sort of mentioned
this before looking
at the statistical empty models.
Overall, what we'd like
to do is find translations
that maximize the
probability of y given
x, and at least if we know what
the length of that translation
is.
We can do that as a product of
generating a word at a time.
And so to have a full model.
We also have to
have a probability
distribution over how long the
translation length would be.
So we could say
this is the model.
And let's generate and score
all possible sequences y
using this model.
And that's where
that then requires
generating an exponential
number of translations.
And it's far, far too expensive.
So beyond greedy decoding,
the most important method
that is used.
And you'll see lots
of places is something
called beam search decoding.
And so this isn't
what neural, well,
any kind of machine
translation has one place
where it's commonly used.
That this isn't
a method specific
to machine translation.
You find lots of other places,
including all other kinds
of sequence to sequence models.
It's not the only
other decoding method.
Once when we got on to the
language generation class,
we'll see a couple more.
But this is sort of the next
one that you should know about.
So beam search's
idea is that you're
going to keep some hypotheses to
make it more likely that you'll
find a good generation while
keeping the search tractable.
So what we do is
choose a beam size.
And for neural MT, the beam
size is normally fairly small,
something like 5 to 10.
And at each step of
the decoder, we're
going to keep
track of the k most
probable partial translation.
So initial sub- sequences
of what we're generating,
which we call hypotheses.
So a hypothesis,
which is then sort
of the prefix of a
translation has a score
which is this log
probability up to what's
been generated so far.
So we can generate that
in the typical way using
our conditional language model.
So as written all of
the scores are negative.
And so the least negative one,
i.e., the highest probability
one is the best one.
So what we want to do is
search for high probability
hypotheses.
So this is a heuristic method.
It's not guaranteed to find the
highest probability decoding.
But at least, it gives
you more of a shot
than simply doing
greedy decoding.
So let's go through an
example to see how it works.
So in this case, so I
can fit it on a slide.
The size of our beam is just 2.
Though normally,
it would actually
be a bit bigger than that.
And the blue numbers are
the scores of the prefixes.
So these are these log
probabilities of a prefix.
So we start off with
our start symbol.
And we're going to say, OK.
What are the two
most likely words,
to generate first according
to our language model?
And so maybe the first two
most likely words are he and I.
And there are the
log probabilities.
Then what we do next is for
each of these k hypotheses,
we find what are likely
words to follow them?
In particular, we find what
are the k most likely words
to follow each of those.
So we might generate he hit,
he struck, I was, I got.
OK.
So at this point,
it sort of looks
like we're heading
down what will
turn into an exponential
size tree structure again.
But what we do
now is we work out
the scores of each of
these partial hypotheses.
So we have four
partial hypotheses.
He hit, he struck.
I was, I got.
And we can do that by taking
the previous score that we have
the partial
hypothesis and adding
on the log probability of
generating the next word here,
he, hit.
So this gives the scores
for each hypothesis.
And then we can say, which of
those two partial hypotheses?
Because our beam size, k equals
2, have the highest score?
And so they are,
I was, and he hit.
So we keep those two
and ignore the rest.
And so then for
those two, we are
going to generate k
hypotheses for the most
likely following word.
He hit a, he hit me, I
was hit, I was struck.
And again, now, we want to find
the k most likely hypotheses
out of this full set.
And so that's going
to be he struck me
and I was, I don't
know, he struck me.
And he hit a.
So we keep just those ones.
And then for each of
those, we generate
the k most likely next
words tart, pie, with, on.
And then again, we filter
back down to size k by saying,
OK, the two most likely
things here are pie or with.
So we continue working on
those, generate things,
find the two most
likely, generate things,
find the two most likely.
And at this point, we would
generate end of string.
And say, OK, we've got
a complete hypothesis.
He struck me with a pie.
And we could then trace
back through the tree
to obtain the full
hypothesis for this sentence.
So that's most of the algorithm.
There's one more detail, which
is the stopping criterion.
So in greedy
decoding, we usually
decode until the model
produces an end token.
And when it produces the end
token, we say we are done.
In beam search decoding,
different hypotheses
may produce end tokens
on different time steps.
And so we don't
want to stop as soon
as one path through the
search tree has generated end.
Because it could
turn out there's
a different path through
the search tree, which
will still prove to be better.
So what we do is sort of put it
aside as a complete hypothesis
and continue exploring other
hypotheses via our beam search.
And so usually, we
will then either stop
when we've hit a cut off
length, or when we've completed
n complete hypotheses.
And then we'll look through the
hypotheses that we've completed
and say which is the
best one of those.
And that's the one we'll use.
OK.
So at that point, we have our
list of completed hypotheses.
And we want to select the top
one with the highest score.
Well, that's exactly what
we've been computing.
Each one has a probability
that we've worked out.
But it turns out that
we might not want
to use that just so naively.
Because that turns out to be a
kind of a systematic problem,
which is not as a theorem.
But in general, longer
hypotheses have lower scores.
So if you think about this as
probabilities of successively
generating each word, that
basically at each step,
you're multiplying by
another chance of generating
the next word probability,
and commonly those
might be 10 to the minus
3, 10 to the minus 2.
So just from the
length of the sentence,
your probabilities are
getting much lower the longer
that they go on.
In a way that appears to
be unfair since although
in some sense extremely
long sentences
aren't as likely as short ones.
They're not less
likely by that much.
A lot of the time we
produce long sentences.
So for example, in a newspaper,
the median length of sentences
is over 20.
So you wouldn't want to
be having a decoding model
when translating news
articles that says,
huh, just generate
two word sentences.
They're just way
high probability
according to my language model.
So the commonest way
of dealing with that
is that we normalize by length.
So if we're working
in log probabilities,
that means taking
dividing through
by the length of the sentence.
And then you have a per
word log probability score.
And you can argue that
this isn't quite right.
In some theoretical
sense, but in practice
it works pretty well and
it's very commonly used.
Neural translation has proven
to be much, much better.
I'll show you a
couple of statistics
and about that in a moment.
It has many advantages.
It gives better performance.
The translations are better.
In particular,
they're more fluent
because neural language
models produce much more
fluent sentences.
But also, they much
better use context
because neural language
models, including
conditional neural
language models
give us a very good
way of conditioning
on a lot of contexts.
In particular, we can just run
a long encoder and condition
on the previous sentence,
or we can translate words
well in context by making
use of neural context.
Neural models better understand
phrase similarities and phrases
that mean approximately
the same thing.
And then the technique of
optimizing all parameters
of the model end to end in a
single large neural network
has just proved to be
a really powerful idea.
So previously, a
lot of the time,
people were building
separate components
and tuning them
individually, which
just meant that they weren't
actually optimal when
put into a much bigger system.
So really a hugely
powerful guiding idea
in neural network land
is if you can sort of
build one huge network,
and just optimize the
entire thing end to end,
that will give you
much better performance
than component-wise systems.
We'll come back to the costs
of that later in the course.
The models are also actually
great in other ways.
They actually require much
less human effort to build.
There's no feature engineering.
There's in general, no
language specific components.
You're using the same method
for all language pairs.
Of course, it's rare for things
to be perfect in every way.
So neural machine
translation systems
also have some
disadvantages compared
to the older statistical
machine translation systems.
They're less interpretable.
It's harder to see why they're
doing what they're doing,
where before you could
actually look at phrase tables
and they were useful.
So they're hard to debug.
They also tend to be sort
of difficult to control.
So compared to anything
like writing rules,
you can't really give
much specification
as if you like to say I'd like
my translations to be more
casual or something like that.
It's hard to know
what they'll generate.
So there are various
safety concerns.
I'll show a few examples
of that in just a minute.
But first, before doing
that, quickly how do we
evaluate machine translation?
The best way to evaluate
machine translation
is to show a human being who's
fluent in the source and target
languages the sentences, and
get them to give judgment on how
good a translation it is.
But that's expensive to
do, and might not even
be possible if you don't have
the right human beings around.
So a lot of work
was put into finding
automatic methods of
scoring translations that
were good enough.
And the most famous
method of doing that
is what's called BLEU.
And the way you do
BLEU is you have
a human translation or
several human translations
of the source sentence, and
you're comparing a machine
generated translation to
those pre-given human written
translations.
And you score them
for similarity
by calculating n-gram
precisions, i.e., words
that overlap between the
computer and human reason
translation, bi-grams,
tri-grams, and 4-grams.
And then working out
a geometric average
between overlaps of
n-grams, plus there's
a penalty for too short
system translations.
So BLEU has proven to be
a really useful measure.
But it's an imperfect measure.
That commonly there
are many valid ways
to translate a sentence.
And so there's some
luck as to whether
the human written
translations you have happened
to correspond to
which what might
be a good translation
from the system.
There's more to say
about the details of BLEU
and how it's implemented.
That you're going to see all
of that during assignment 4,
because you will be building
neural machine translation
systems, and evaluating
them with a BLEU algorithm.
And there are full details about
BLEU in the assignment handout.
But at the end of the day, BLEU
gives a score between 0 and 100
where your score is 100.
If you are exactly producing
one of the human written
translations, and 0 if there's
not even a single unigram that
overlaps between the two,
With that rather
brief intro, I wanted
to show you sort
of what happened
in machine translation.
So machine translation
with statistical models,
phrase-based statistical
machine translation
that I showed at the
beginning of the class
had been going on since
the mid 2000s decade.
And it had produced sort
of semi-good results
of the kind that are in Google
Translate in those days.
But by the time you entered
the 2010s, basically progress
in statistical machine
translation had stalled.
And you were getting barely
any increase over time.
And most of the increase
you were getting over time
was simply because you're
training your models
on more data.
In those years, around
the early 2010s,
the big hope that
most people had.
Someone asked what
is the y-axis here,
this y-axis is this BLEU
score that I told you
about on the previous slide.
In the early 2010s, the big hope
that most people in the machine
translation field had was, well,
if we built a more complex kind
of machine
translation model that
knows about the syntactic
structure of languages, that
makes use of tools like
dependency parsers,
we'll be able to build
much better translations.
And so those are the
purple systems here,
which I haven't
described at all.
But it's as the years went
by it was pretty obvious that
barely seemed to help.
And so then in the
mid 2010s, so in 2014
was the first modern attempt
to build a neural network
from machine translations
and encoded-decoder model.
And by the time it was sort of
evaluated in bake offs in 2015,
it wasn't as good as
what had been built up
over the preceding decade.
But it was already
getting pretty good.
But what was found was
that these new models just
really opened up a
whole new pathway
to start building much, much
better machine translation
systems.
And since then, things have
just sort of taken off.
And year by year, neural
machine translation systems
are getting much
better and far better
than anything we
had preceding that.
So for at least the early
part of the application
of deep learning and
natural language processing,
neural machine translation was
the huge big success story.
In the last few
years, when we've had
models like GPT2 and GPT3,
and other huge neural models
like BERT improving web search.
It's a bit more complex.
But this was the
first area where
there was a neural
network, which
was hugely better than what
had preceded, and was actually
solving a practical problem
that lots of people in the world
need.
And it was stunning
with the speed
at which success was achieved.
So 2014 were the
first what I call
here fringe research attempts
to build a neural machine
translation system.
Meaning that three
or four people who
are working on
neural network models
thought, oh, why don't we see
if we can use one of these
to translate, learn to translate
sentences, where there weren't
really people with a background
in machine translation at all?
But a success was
achieved so quickly
that within two
years' time, Google
had switched to using neural
machine translation for most
languages.
And by a couple of
years later, after that,
essentially anybody who
does machine translation
is now deploying live neural
machine translation systems
and getting much,
much better results.
So that was sort
of just an amazing
technological transition that
for the preceding decade,
the big statistical
machine translation
systems like the previous
generation of Google Translate
had literally been
built up by hundreds
of engineers over the years.
But a comparatively small
group of deep learning people
in a few months with a
small amount of code.
And hopefully, you'll
even get a sense
of this doing assignment 4, were
able to build neural machine
translation systems that
proved to work much better.
Does that mean that machine
translation is solved?
No.
There are still
lots of difficulties
which people continue to
work on very actively.
And you can see more about it in
the Skynet Today article that's
linked at the bottom.
But there are lots of problems
with out of vocabulary words.
There are domain mismatches
between the training and test
data.
So it might be trained
mainly on news wire data
but you want to translate
people's Facebook messages.
There are still problems
of maintaining context
over longer text.
We'd like to translate
languages for which we
don't have much data.
And so these methods work
by far the best when we have
huge amounts of parallel data.
Even our best
multilayer LSTMs aren't
that great of capturing
sentence meaning.
There are particular
problems such as interpreting
what pronouns refer
to, or in languages
like Chinese or Japanese,
where there's often no pronoun
present.
But there is an
implied reference
to some person working
out how to translate that.
For languages that have lots
of inflectional forms of nouns,
verbs, and adjectives.
These systems often
get them wrong.
So there's still
tons of stuff to do.
So here's just sort of quick
funny examples of the kind
of things that go wrong, right?
So if you asked to
translate paper jam.
Google Translate is
deciding that this is
a kind of jam just like this.
Raspberry jam and
strawberry jam.
And so this becomes
a jam of paper.
There are problems of
agreement and choice.
So if you have many languages
don't distinguish gender.
And so the sentences are
neutral between things masculine
or feminine, so Malay,
or Turkish are two well
known languages of that sort.
But what happens when that
gets translated into English
by Google Translate is
that the English language
model just kicks in and
applies stereotypical biases.
And so these gender neutral
sentences get translated into,
she works as a nurse.
He works as a programmer.
So if you want to help solve
this problem, all of you
can help by using singular
they in all contexts when
you're putting material online.
And that could then
change the distribution
of what's generated.
And people also work on
modeling improvements
to try and avoid this.
Here's one more example
that's kind of funny.
People noticed a
couple of years ago.
That if you choose one
of the rarer languages
that Google will
translate such as Somali,
and you just write in some
rubbish like ag ag ag ag.
Freakily, it had produced out of
nowhere prophetic and biblical
texts, as the name
of the Lord was
written in the Hebrew language.
It was written in the
language of the Hebrew nation,
which makes no sense at all.
Well, we're about to see a bit
more about why this happens.
But that was a bit worrying.
As far as I can see, this
problem is now fixed in 2021.
I couldn't actually get
Google Translate to generate
examples like this anymore.
So there are lots of ways
to keep on doing research.
NMT certainly is a flagship
task for NLP and deep learning.
And it was a place where
many of the innovations
of deep learning
NLP were pioneered,
and people continue
to work hard on it,
people have found many,
many improvements.
And actually for the last bit
of the class and the minute
I'm going to present one
huge improvement, which
is so important that
it's really come
to dominate the whole of the
recent field of neural networks
for NLP.
And that's the
idea of attention.
But before I get
onto attention, I
want to spend three minutes
on our assignment 4.
So for assignment
4 this year, we've
got a new version of
the assignment, which
we hope will be interesting.
But it's also a real challenge.
So for assignment
4 this year, we've
decided to do Cherokee
English machine translation.
So Cherokee is an endangered
Native American language that
has about 2000 fluent speakers.
It's an extremely low
resource language.
So it's just there
isn't much written
Cherokee data available period.
And particularly, there's not
a lot of parallel sentences
between Cherokee and English.
And here's the answer to
Google's freaky prophetic
translations.
For languages for which there
isn't much parallel data
available, commonly
the biggest place
where you can get parallel data
is from Bible translations.
So you can have your
own personal choice
wherever it is over
the map as to where you
stand with respect to religion.
But the fact of the
matter is if you
work on indigenous languages,
what you very, very quickly
find is that a lot of the work
that's done on collecting data
on indigenous languages, and
a lot of the material that
is available in written form
for many indigenous languages
is Bible translations.
Yeah.
OK.
So this is what
Cherokee looks like.
And so you can see that the
writing system has a mixture
of things that look like English
letters and then all sorts
of letters that don't.
And so here's the
initial bit of a story
long ago where
seven boys who used
to spend all their time
down by the townhouse.
So this is a piece of parallel
data that we can learn from.
So the Cherokee writing
system has 85 letters.
And the reason why it
has so many letters
is that each of these letters
actually represents a syllable.
So many languages
of the world have
strict consonant vowel
syllable structure.
So you have words
like right up here
or something like that
for Cherokee, right?
And another language
like that's Hawaiian.
And so each of the letters
represents a combination
of a consonant and a vowel.
And that's the set of those.
You then get 17 by 5
gives you 85 letters.
Yeah, so being able
to do this assignment.
Big thanks to people
from University
of North Carolina, Chapel Hill
who've provided the resources
were using for this assignment.
Although you can do
quite a lot of languages
on Google Translate.
Cherokee is not a
language that Google
offers on Google Translate.
So we can see how
far we can get.
But we have to be modest
in our expectations
because it's hard to
build a very good MT
system with only a fairly
limited amount of data.
So we'll see how far we can get.
There is a flipside, which
is for you students doing
the assignment.
The advantage of having
not too much data
is that your models will
train relatively quickly.
So we'll actually
have less trouble
than we did last year with
people's models taking hours
to train as the assignment
deadline closed in.
There's a couple more
words about Cherokee.
So we have some idea
what we're talking about.
So the Cherokee originally
lived in Western North Carolina
and Eastern Tennessee.
They then sort of got
shunted Southwest from that.
And then in particular,
for those of you who
went to American high
schools and paid attention,
you might remember discussion
of the Trail of Tears
when a lot of the
Native Americans
from the Southeast of
the US got forcibly
shoved a long way further West.
And so most Cherokee
now live in Oklahoma.
There are some that
are in North Carolina.
The writing system that I
showed on this previous slide,
it was invented by a
Cherokee man, Sequoyah.
That's a drawing of him there.
And that was actually kind
of an incredible thing.
So he started off
illiterate and worked
out how to produce a
writing system that
would be good for Cherokee.
And given that it has this
consonant-vowel structure,
he chose a syllabary which
turned out to be a good choice.
So here's a neat
historical fact.
So in the 1830s and
1840s, the percentage
of Cherokee that were literate
in Cherokee written like this
was actually higher than the
percentage of white people
in the southeastern United
States at that point in time.
OK.
Before time disappears, oops,
time has almost disappeared.
I was just starting
to say, oh no, I'll
have to do a bit more of this.
We'll have to do a bit
more of this next time.
That'll be OK, right?
So the final idea that's
really important for sequence
to sequence models is
the idea of attention.
And so we had this
model of doing sequence
to sequence models such as for
neural machine translation.
And the problem with
this architecture
is that we have this
one hidden state, which
has to encode all the
information about the source
sentence.
So it acts as a kind of
information bottleneck.
And that's all the information
that the generation
is conditioned on.
Well, I did already
mention one idea last time
of how to get more information
where I said look maybe
you could kind of average all
of the vectors of the source
to get a sentence
representation.
But that method turns
out to be better
for things like
sentiment analysis.
And not so good for
machine translation,
where the order of words is
very important to preserve.
So it seems like we would
do better, if somehow, we
could get more information
from the source sentence
while we're generating
the translation.
And in some sense, this
just corresponds to what
a human translator does, right?
If you're a human translator,
you read the sentence
that you're meant to translate.
And you maybe start
translating a few words.
But then you look back
at the source sentence
to see what else was in it
and translate some more words.
So very quickly after the first
neural machine translation
systems, people came up
with the idea of maybe
we could build a better
neural empty MT that did that.
And that's the
idea of attention.
So the core idea is on
each step of the decoder,
we're going to use a direct
link between the encoder
and the decoder
that will allow us
to focus on a particular word
or words in the source sequence
and use it to help us
generate what words come next.
I'll just go through
now showing you
the pictures of
what attention does
and then at the
start of next time
we'll go through the
equations in more detail.
So we use our encoder
just as before
and generate our
representations,
feed in our
conditioning as before,
and say we're starting
our translation.
But at this point, we take this
hidden representation, and say,
I'm going to use this hidden
representation to look back
at the source to get
information directly from it.
So what I will do
is I will compare
the hidden state of the
decoder with the hidden
state of the encoder
at each position
and generate an attention score,
which is a kind of similarity
score like a product.
And then based on
those attention scores,
I'm going to calculate a
probability distribution
as to by using a
softmax as usual to say
which of these encoder states
is most like my decoder state.
And so we'll be training
the model here to be saying,
well, probably you should
translate the first word
of the sentence
first, so that's where
the attention should be placed.
So then based on this
attention distribution, which
is a probability distribution
coming out of the softmax,
we're going to generate
a new attention output.
And so this attention
output is going
to be an average of the hidden
states of the encoder model.
That is going to be a weighted
average based on our attention
distribution.
And so we then kind of
take that attention output,
combine it with the hidden
state of the decoder RNN
and together, the
two of them are then
going to be used to predict via
a softmax what word to generate
first, and we hope
to generate he.
And then at that
point, we sort of
chug along and keep doing
the same kind of computations
at each position.
There's a little side note
here that says sometimes
we take the attention output
from the previous step,
and also feed into the decoder
along with the usual decoder
input.
So we're taking this
attention output
and actually feeding it
back in to the hidden state
calculation.
And that can sometimes
improve performance.
And we actually have that trick
in the assignment 4 system.
And you can try it out.
OK.
So we generate along and
generate our whole sentence
in this manner.
And that's proven to be a
very effective way of getting
more information from
the source sentence
more flexibly to allow us to
generate a good translation.
I'll stop here for now and
at the start of next time.
I'll finish this off by going
through the actual equations
for how attention works.