OK, so now we'd better get
going with the lecture.
OK so we're now at week
8, second half of week 4.
So the agenda today is
that I'm first of all going
to finish off the last
pieces of the attention
that I didn't talk
about last time.
But the main topic today is
to talk about final projects.
And that will consist of sort of
a grab bag of different things.
I'll talk about
the final projects
and finding research
topics, and finding data,
and doing research.
I'll give a very
brief introduction
to the reading comprehension
and question answering, which
is our default final project.
But we get a whole
lecture on that
at the beginning of week 6.
So this is just to give you a
little bit of what it's about,
and if you're
thinking about doing
the default final project.
In some sense, this
lecture is also
a rare chance in this
course to pause for breath,
because we are really,
we've had up until now
been having the fire hose going
full stream ahead, spraying you
with new facts, and approaches,
and algorithms, and models,
and linguistic things.
So this is a brief
respite from that.
So if you have any
questions that you've
been wondering about for
weeks, today's lecture
could be a good
time to ask them.
Because after today's
lecture, in week 5,
we'll turn the fire
hose right back on,
and we'll have a lot of new
information about transformers
and large pre-trained
language models
that have become a huge
part of modern neural NLP,
as I already mentioned a little
bit of, later into this class.
OK, so this is where we left
things last time, basically.
So I'd sort of talked
through the rough idea
that what we're going to do
for this new attention model
is that we are going to use
the encoder just as before.
And then once we're running
the decoder, at each time step,
we're going to compute a new
hidden representation using
the same kind of sequence
model as we had before.
But now we're going to use
that hidden representation
of the decoder to look
back at the encoder.
And it's going to then work
out respectively some kind
of function of similarity
between encoder hidden states
and decoder hidden states.
And based on those, it's
going to work out what
are called attention scores.
And attention scores are
actually probability weights,
as to how much it likes
different elements.
And based on those
attention scores,
we're going to compute an
attention distribution.
So this is our
probability distribution.
And then based on
that, what we do
is compute a weighted average
of the encoder RNN hidden states
weighted by the
attention distribution.
And so that's going to give
us a new attention output
vector, which is
like the hidden state
vector of the encoder that
is an extra hidden vector.
And so we're gonna
use both of them
to then generate our
next output, which
is going to be here, the word
pie at the end of the sequence.
So let's start off now by
doing that with some equations.
So--
Chris, before we move on,
there's a good question here,
sorry, which is why is the
encoder and decoder both
required, as opposed to
just the same RNN for both?
I think it-- yeah.
OK, I'll address that.
So, well, maybe
there are a couple
of still possible
interpretations for that.
But I'll say something about it.
So notice that the basic case
that we've been doing here
is this case of machine
translation, where we've
got a source encoder, which
is in the source language,
and we've got a
target decoder which
is in the target language.
So since these two [INAUDIBLE]
different languages.
It makes sense to have
separate sequence models
with different RNN
parameters for each one.
And at that point,
it's just a fact
about what we want to do with
machine translation, which
is that, well, we actually
want to look back at the source
to try and decide what
extra words to put
into the translation.
So it makes sense to
attend back from the source
to the translation.
But what you might be asking
is, why do we only do that?
Why don't we also consider
doing attention from here
back into the decoder RNN?
And if that's what you
are thinking about,
that's a great suggestion.
And actually, very quickly
after these attention models
were developed, that's exactly
what people started doing.
They decided that,
well, actually we
could start using more
forms of attention.
And we could also use
attention that looks back
in the decoder sequence.
And that often gets referred
to as self attention.
And self attention
has proven to be
an extremely powerful concept.
And, indeed, that then leads
into the transformer models
that we're going
to see next week.
Going in on things, I
think self attention
wasn't quite as much an
obviously needed idea.
From this initial
translation motivation,
which was where
attention was developed,
it seemed fairly clear that
when you're running the decoder
RNN that as a conditional
language model,
it will get some information
about the source fed
into its initial state.
And it seemed pretty
clear you were losing
a lot of information
about the details of what
was in the source
sentence, and therefore it
would be really, really useful
have this idea of attention,
so you could directly
look at it as you
perceive it to translate.
In a way, it's a
little bit less obvious
that you need that
for the decoder RNN.
Because after all, last week, we
introduced those really clever
LSTMs.
And the whole argument
of the LSTM was actually
they're pretty
good at maintaining
history of a sequence through
quite a bunch of time periods.
So to the extent that the
LSTM is doing a perfect job,
maybe you shouldn't really need
self attention in your decoder.
But actually, precisely
what's being shown
is that this
mechanism of attention
is a much more
effective method, again,
of selectively addressing
elements of your past state.
And it's sort of lighter weight.
Rather than having
to kind of cook up
the parameters for
your LSTM so it's
carrying just the right
information forward
all the time, provided you
carry only enough information
that the model knows
where to look back to.
You can then kind of grab more
information from past states
when you want to.
So that's actually
a great approach.
But I won't talk
about it more now,
and that will come
out more next week.
OK, the equations, hopefully
these won't actually
seem difficult.
So what we have is
we have our encoded hidden
states which are vectors,
on time step t, we have
the decoder hidden state,
which is also a vector of
the hidden state dimension.
And then what we want to
do is get attention scores
as to for st, how much attention
it pays to each of the hidden
states of the encoder.
And the easiest way
to do that is just
use dot products between
the source and the-- sorry,
not the source--
the dot products
between the decoder hidden state
s and the encoder hidden state
h.
So these give us
a bunch of numbers
that might be
negative or positive,
but they're attention scores.
And so have, just like we did
right from the first lecture
with word vectors,
we then put those
through a softmax distribution.
And then we get a
probability distribution
over the time steps
of the encoder.
Okay, so and now we've got
that probability distribution.
We can construct a
new vector by creating
a weighted sum of the
encoder hidden states
based on these attention
distribution probabilities.
And that [INAUDIBLE]
going to make
use of that in
generating the output.
We're going to concatenate
the attention output
with the decoder
hidden state st.
So now that's
something of size 2h.
And then we're
going to proceed as
with the non-attention model.
We then put that
through another softmax
to generate a probability
distribution of output words,
and then we'd sample a word.
And hopefully that's a
fairly obvious implementation
of what we have here.
So we've got our vectors
with encoder and decoder.
We're getting dot products
of st with each one.
Softmax turns that
into a probability.
We take the weighted
average of the ones in red
to get the attention output.
We combine that with the
st decoder's hidden state.
And then we put it
through another softmax,
and we can sample pie.
Okay, so I sort almost
can't stress enough
that attention is great.
So the very first modern neural
machine translation program
was done in 2014 at
Google by [INAUDIBLE]..
And they had a straightforward
encoder, decoder to LSTMs.
And by a bunch of
tricks of having
very deep LSTMs,
huge amount of data,
huge amount of training,
other tricks that I don't want
to go into now,
they were actually
able to get good results
by just putting together
a straight seq2seq neural
machine translation system.
But very soon after that, in
fact, later the same year,
a group from Montreal, Dzmitry
Bahdanau, Kyunghyun Cho,
and Yoshua Bengio introduced
sequence to sequence model
with attention.
And it was just
obviously better.
So attention significantly
improved neural machine
translation performance.
And that sort of makes sense.
It allows the decoder to
focus on parts of the source
sentence.
So I think that is giving you
a much more human-like model
of doing machine translation.
Because you know exactly
what a human translator would
do is you read the
source sentence,
you've got an idea
of what it's about,
you start writing the first
couple of words of translation.
And then what you
do is you look back
to see what exactly it said,
as that sort of modifiers
the noun to translate
the next few words.
Technically people think of
it as solving the bottleneck
problem, because attention
now allows us full access
to the entire
source hidden state,
and we can get any
information that we need.
It's not the case
that all information
has to be encoded in
the final hidden state.
It also helps with the
vanishing gradient problem.
So effectively, now,
we have shortcuts back
to every hidden
state of the encoder.
And so therefore there's
always a short path
with gradient flow, and that
greatly mitigates the vanishing
gradient problem.
A final neat thing
is that attention
provides some effective
interpretability to sequence
to sequence models.
Because by looking at the
attention distribution,
we can see what the
decoder was focusing on.
So in a stark
probabilistic way, we
get the [INAUDIBLE]
operation of the model
a soft alignment as to which
words translate which words.
So in this example of the
French sentence being translated
is he hit me with a pie, where
there's sort of a single verb
here in the French.
Which is kind of like
as in English sometimes
people imply they
use pied as a verb.
So it's sort of like
saying he, me, pied.
That the model is getting
that "il" is translated as he,
the "m'" is being translated as
me, and essentially "entarte"
is being translated
as hit with a pie.
So the amazing thing is,
the model was never told
about any of these alignments.
There was no explicit
separate model
which was trying to
learn these alignments,
as in the earlier statistical
phrase based systems.
We just built a sequence to
sequence model with attention,
and said, here are a lot
of translated sentences.
Start running back and
forth and try and get
[INAUDIBLE] sentences.
And it just learns by
itself in deciding where
it's best to pay attention.
What is a good alignment between
the source and the target
languages?
Okay, so that's the
basic idea of attention.
I want to go a bit more into
the complexity of attention
since it's such an
important idea that we'll
see a lot as we continue
now with the course, right?
So there are several
attention variants.
But first of all,
what's the common part?
So we have some
values, some vectors
that we're going to be sort
of using as our memory,
and we have a query vector.
So attention always involves
that we calculate the attention
scores and turn those
into a probability
distribution of the softmax.
And we use the
attention distribution
to calculate a weighted sum
of the elements in our memory,
giving us an attention output.
So the main place where you'll
immediately see variation
in the attention is, how do you
compute these attention scores?
And so let's go through some
of the ways that that's done.
So the simplest, most obvious
way to do it is to say, let's
just take the dot product
between the given--
the current hidden state of the
decoder, and all of the vectors
here, the source encoder vectors
that we are putting attention
over.
And that sort of
makes sense, right?
This is a dot product, it's our
most basic similarity score.
But it seems like there's
something wrong with this.
And that is, it
seems wrong for you
to want to think
that the entirety
of the source hidden states,
and the entirety of the target
hidden states is all
having information
about where to attend to.
Because really, these LSTMs
are doing multiple things.
So the LSTMs are carrying
forward information
along their own sequence
to help record information
about the past so it can
be used in the future.
They have information in
the hidden state to tell you
which output you
should generate next.
And perhaps, they're
encoding some information
that will serve as a kind of
a query key for getting out
information by attention from
the source hidden states.
So it seems like
probably we only want
to use some of the
information in them
to calculate our
attention score.
And so that's the
kind of approach
that was taken very
quickly in subsequent work.
So the next year, Thang
Luong, working with me,
explored this idea that
is now normally called
multiplicative attention.
So in a multiplicative
attention,
we put an extra matrix in the
middle of our dot product.
So this gives us a matrix
of learnable parameters.
And so effectively,
inside this matrix,
we can learn what parts
of s to pay attention to,
and what parts of
h to pay attention
to when calculating
the similarity,
and hence the attention score
between the source hidden
states and the
decoder's hidden state.
So that is a good thing, which
in general works much better.
But there's perhaps
a problem with that,
which is, maybe this W matrix
has too many parameters.
Because we've got these two
vectors, which in the simplest
case are both in
the same dimension
d, but they don't
have to be the same.
And we're now
putting in d squared,
new parameters for the
matrix W. And that's sort of
feels like it's too many.
Because arguably, it
seems like we should only
have about two d parameters,
one d saying how much attention
to pay to different parts of
s, and the other one how much
attention to pay to parts of h.
There's a reason for more.
By having a whole matrix
here, you're not only doing
the scoring
element-wise, right, you
can have any element
of s being combined
with any element
of the h vector,
and see that as a useful part
of your similarity score.
But there's still a
lot of parameters.
So a bit after that,
[INAUDIBLE] parameters.
So if you have a
matrix W and you'd
like it to have less parameters,
the obvious linear algebra
thing to do is to say,
OK, we can model W
as U transpose V. Where U and
V are low rank skinny matrices.
So we can choose some number k
for how skinny these matrices
are going to be.
And they can be k
times d matrices.
And then we're getting a
reduced rank matrix here.
And so we have a lot less-- we
end up with a d by d matrix,
but it has a lot less
parameters in it.
And so people explored that.
And at that point,
if you just do
a little bit of linear
algebra, what we
have here is exactly the
same, the source hidden vector
and the decoder hidden vector,
and projecting each of them
with a low rank
linear projection,
and then taking the dot
product of the projections.
And if you remember
this equation
here at all, next
Tuesday's lecture,
you'll see that that's actually
exactly what's happening
in transformer models.
But none of these were actually
the original form of attention
that was suggested
by Bahdanau et al.
But Bahdanau et al.
suggested is the way we
could calculate the attention
score is by taking
the two vector,
multiply each by a matrix,
adding them, putting them
through a tanh function, giving
us another vector which we then
dot product with
yet another vector,
and we get out a weight.
So in the literature that
compares attention variance,
this one is normally referred
to additive attention.
I've always thought that
that's a really lousy name,
or at least it never
made sense to me.
Because really what
you're doing here
is that you're using a
neural net layer to calculate
the attention score, right?
This looks just like the
kind of neural net layers
that we use when we wanted
to calculate scores,
such as when we were
doing simple sort
of feed-forward networks
at the beginning
when wanted to calculate scores.
OK, in assignment 4, which
you should look at really soon
if you haven't looked
at it yet, actually one
of the things in the written
problems of assignment 4
is thinking about these
different attention variants.
OK, yeah, so I've only
presented this idea of attention
as something good for
machine translation
to use between the source and
the target sequence models,
except for that when I tried
to answer the question.
But, really, this is a general
deep learning technique, right?
So it's not only great
for that application.
You can use it in many
architectures, not just
sequence to sequence.
And you can use
it for many tasks,
not just for
machine translation.
So any time that you have
a bunch of vector values
and you have sum of a vector
that you can regard as a query,
attention is a technique to
compute a value from them,
that you can have the
query attend to the values.
And so once you think
about it like that,
you can think about attention
as a kind of memory access
mechanism, that the weighted
sum that attention calculates
gives you a kind of
selective summary of some
of the information
contained in the values.
And the query tells you which
values to pay attention to.
So, on the one
hand, you could say
this is a good general
technique any time you
have a whole bunch of
vectors and you want
to just get one vector out.
Well, the dumbest thing you can
do is just average them all,
or do max pooling, take
the element-wise max
of each element.
But this gives you a
much more flexible way
to combine them together
into a single vector.
And so you can think of
that as actually giving us
an operation that's much more
like a conventional computer
and its memory access.
So the values we can
think of as like our RAM.
And [INAUDIBLE] memory, right?
We have a query vector,
and the query vector
acts as a sort of associative
memory pointer that
says how much weight to put
on different parts of RAM.
And then we sort
of proportionately
retrieve those bits of
RAM to get a new value.
Another cool thing
about attention
that I'll just mention here
is that attention is actually
a genuinely new deep learning
idea from the last decade,
developed in the last decade.
It's sort of a slightly
depressing fact
about deep learning
that a lot of what's
being done in deep
learning in recent years
wasn't actually new ideas.
They were ideas that were
developed in the 80s and 90s,
it's just people aren't
able to get much use of them
then, because their
computers were too small,
and the amount of data
they had was too small.
And they were sort
of reinvented--
well, not reinvented, but
they were given new life
in the 2010s.
But attention is a genuinely
new idea from the 2010s.
And we'll see sort of next
week how it sort of then
turns into this huge
idea that transforms NLP.
OK, so that's all I wanted
to tell you about attention,
and now I'm going to
get on and go and talk
about final projects and
all this stuff about that.
So am I good to start
doing other stuff?
Yes.
Yeah, OK, so this is a quick
reminder so you don't forget.
This is the coursework.
So you're right in the middle.
You're past half way almost of
going through the assignments.
And they're worth
about half the grade.
But the other half
of the grade comes
from the final project, which
I'm going to talk about today.
And that gets split up.
So there's a project proposal,
which we've handed out
instructions for today.
It's worth 5%.
There's a milestone that's
worth 5% in the middle.
And there's a report at the end,
which is the big part, which
is worth 30%.
And then we also want to have a
representation of your project
that people can easily browse.
So in normal years when
there were people on campus,
we had a poster session
for the class, which
just seems like we
just can't usefully
do in the current world.
We want to put up a
website where there's
some brief descriptions
of each project,
so a nice picture
of what you've done.
And then we can link to
your project write up.
And so you will also
then get 3% for that.
Just make sure you do it, when
it comes down to it, right?
And yeah, so I should just
mention again, as we go along.
The honor code, that's important
also for the final projects.
So just to be clear on that,
so for the final projects,
in a lot of cases, you'll get to
use a lot of stuff that already
exists, that you may well
be using some model that you
can just download
from the GitHub
repository or similar places.
You may well be
taking various ideas.
It's fine for the
final project to use
any amount of existing stuff.
But you have to make sure
that you acknowledge what
you're using and document it.
And in terms of evaluating
your projects, what we'll
be interested in is the value
add in terms of what you did,
not what you're able to
download from other people.
So for the final project,
you can have teams of 1 to 3.
In almost every case,
every member of the team
gets the same score.
But we do ask for a brief
statement of the work done
by each teammate.
And if it's clear
that there was sort
of some egregious imbalance,
in sort of 1 in 100 cases,
we do do something about that.
So for the final project, you've
essentially got two choices.
You can either do our default
final project where we give you
the scaffolding and send you
pointed in some direction,
or you can propose a custom
final project, which we then
need to approve as a suitable
final project for the course.
And I'm going to
talk a bit about both
of those in this class.
So you can work in
teams of 1 to 3.
If you have a bigger team
we expect you to do more.
Sometimes people use the same
project for multiple classes,
so that it might also use it
as [INAUDIBLE] allow that.
But it's sort of the
same general rule, right?
So that there are two
of you, and you're
using the project
for two classes each,
that's sort of like it should
be four persons worth of work
that is being done.
And so we expect projects
that are bigger, that--
if it's just one
of you, we can be
totally satisfied with
something compact and small.
It sort of has to be done, but
it can be compact and small.
Whereas if there are three
of you, we sort of feel like,
well, you really should
have had enough time
to actually implement
a variant model
and see if that works better.
You can use any
framework or language
you want for the final project,
but in practice, basically,
people go on using PyTorch.
And then, finally,
I've got to mention
on the default final project.
I'll get back to
this in a minute.
But actually this
year, new thing, we've
got two sub-variants of
the default final project,
and you can choose
one or the other.
So for custom
final projects, I'm
really happy to talk to
people about final projects.
But there's this problem.
And you'll be encouraged to
sign up for an office hour slot.
But there's this problem
that there's only one of me.
So also encourage you to talk
to the TAs about final projects.
Many of the TAs have experience
for all sorts of things.
And we've tried to
sort of summarize
some of what they
have experience
with on the office hours page.
So look at that and try
and get some ideas of who
might be good to talk about.
So for the final projects,
we make sure everyone
has some kind of mentor.
And the mentor can either be a
TA or instructor in this class,
or it could be somebody else.
And for the somebody
else option,
well, if there's someone
you know at Stanford,
and there's some cool
project they have,
whatever it is,
if it's something
on the political science
of understanding documents,
or in the med school
doing something,
you can have them
as your mentor.
Or we then also collected
some projects from people
in the Stanford NLP
group and community,
and we're going to be
distributing a list of those.
So you can try and
sort of sign up
to be doing one
of those projects,
and they can be a mentor.
So in that case,
the other person
we expect to be
the mentor that's
keeping an eye your project
and telling you to do
something sort of sensible.
But it's one of the
TAs in the class who
will be grading your various
pieces of work for the class.
OK, so these are the details of
the two default final projects,
and the handouts for them.
There are about 10
or so page handouts
for each one are
out on the web now.
So both of them involve
question answering, which
I'll mention a bit at the end.
And there are sort
of two variants.
One is for you to actually
build the question answering
architecture by yourself.
And I've described
this as from scratch,
but it's not really from
scratch, because we give you
a baseline question answering
system in the starter code.
But you're working,
doing all the work
of what else could I
add to the model, how
could I add extra layers for
attention and other things
to make that better,
using the SQuAD data set.
But one of the things
that's happened in NLP,
which has really been the
topic of next week's class,
is in the last few
years in NLP, there's
been this revolution in using
large, pre-trained language
models with names like
BERT, roBERTa, others,
which have just been
fantastically good for doing
natural language problems.
So the other choice is to
make use of those models.
And so then,
effectively, the model
and the model architecture as a
starting point is given to you.
And so then what we're hoping
to have people focus on
is how to build a robust
question answering
system, which works
across different data
sets and domains.
So a huge problem with
a lot of NLP models
is if you train them on
say, Wikipedia data, they
work great on Wikipedia data.
But then as soon as you try
and use them on something else,
whether it's customer
support questions or web
questions, that their
performance degrades greatly.
Despite the fact that
the human being it
seems like they're doing
[INAUDIBLE] and so the building
a robust QA system
track with them,
going to be sort
of training or fine
tuning pre-trained language
models on simple data sets.
And your goal is to produce
something that then performs
well on different data sets.
OK, so for this topic
of question answering,
I'm going to set a few
minutes on it at the end.
But on Tuesday of week
6, the entire lecture
is on question answering.
So there'll be a
lot of content there
on the different kinds of models
for really getting up to speed.
Good stuff to know
even if you're not
doing the default final
project, because it's
a major application of NLP.
But even better
stuff to know if you
are doing the final project.
So look out for that.
But just to give
you one example,
this is the kind
of thing we have
in question answering problems.
So question answering is
taking a paragraph of text.
But I only put one sentence
to keep my slide short.
Bill Aiken, adopted by Mexican
movie actress Lupe Mayorga,
grew up in the
neighboring town of Madera
and his song
chronicled the what?
The question is, in what
town did Bill Aiken grow up?
This stuff doesn't
actually seen so hard.
I presume all of
you could have done
this when you were in
sixth grade in school,
or something like that.
The answer should be Madera.
But somehow, Google's BERT
model fails to find that answer.
Perhaps it's partly
because there's
the extra stuff in the middle
there, adopted by Mexican movie
actress.
And so it says,
no, this sentence
doesn't answer the question.
So you can hope to
do better than that.
OK, so there's this choice
about doing either the default
or custom final project.
And the overall steps have
been that about half the people
do each.
So there's no sort of
clear winner of a choice.
In terms of thinking about
what you should choose,
I mean, I think the default
final project is great
if you have limited experience
with doing research,
if you don't have any
clear idea of what
you would want to do with
a custom final project,
if you think it would be good to
have guidance and a clear goal
to work towards--
indeed, we give
you a leaderboard
so you can compete against
the other people doing
the default final project--
then you should do the
default final project.
It gives you guidance,
scaffolding, clear goal posts.
I mean, and in particular,
just to sort of try and give
a sharper edge to this, I
mean, the fact of the matter
is every year there
are few people who
do a custom final project.
And when we're grading
them, we look at this custom
final project, and we
say, huh, this just
looks pretty lame compared
to what people are doing
in the default final project.
And that's a bad state to be in.
But if you're doing the
custom final project,
you want to have a
sort of a clear thing
that you thought out
that is interesting,
so it'll seem as or more
interesting than the default
final project.
And if you don't think
you've got such a thing,
you're actually better off
doing the default final project.
Why should you do the
custom final project?
Well, if you have some
research projects, possibly
something you've
already been working on,
or any rate, something
that you think,
oh, this would be
great to do, which
there are two requirements
for our project.
It has to substantively
involve human language,
and it has to substantively
involve neural networks.
So that doesn't mean it has
to be fully about those.
If you want to do a language
and vision project, that's fine.
Or if you want to compare neural
networks versus other machine
learning methods on some
problem, that's fine.
But you do have to, in your
project, substantively use
both of those things.
Yeah, so if you'd like to
sort of design your own thing
and come up with something
different on your own,
or just you don't like
question answering,
or if you basically want
more experience of going
through the whole process of
trying to find a good research
goal, finding data and
tools to explore it,
work it out on your own,
then doing the custom
final project is a great choice.
OK, either way, the
steps that you go through
are the following.
So the first thing, which
you've got until Feb 16 for,
is to write a project proposal,
which is 3 to [INAUDIBLE]
So some of the details vary
on the kind of project.
So you need to decide
on the research topic
for your project, which is
kind of easy if you're doing
the default final project.
It's either A or
B. But we then want
you to choose one
research paper that's
relevant to your final project,
read it, and then learn
some stuff from it that
you can write about.
And we want you to
write about what
your plan is as to
what you're going
to do about the final project.
And that will include
describing things as needed,
such as the data
and the evaluation.
And, again, this is especially
important for custom
final projects.
Might be kind of
obvious if you're
doing a default final project.
And so typically, if you're
doing a default final project,
this should be three pages.
And if you're doing a
custom final project,
this should be four pages.
So there are two parts of that.
The first part of it is writing
about the paper you read.
And so that part is two pages.
And so there are longer
form of the instructions.
But we want you to read
and think about this paper.
What are its novel
contributions?
Is that an idea that could
be employed in other ways?
Are there things that
didn't really do well?
How does it compare
to other ways
that people have
approached this problem?
Does it sort of--
even though it did
things one way,
does it actually
suggest ideas that
really could do things a
different way that might even
be better?
And so we want you to write
this 2 page paper summary,
which we will grade.
And, respectively, we're going
to grade that on how good a job
you do at thinking about
analyzing and having
critical comments on this paper.
So then the other half, which
might be longer or shorter,
depending on whether
it's custom or default,
is to propose what
you're going to do.
And, really, this
part is formative.
So formative means we're not
going to grade it harshly.
We want you to write
it so we can help you.
So we want you to sort of
bullet through what you're
going to do, and us
have an opportunity
to say, no, that's
unrealistically large,
or that sounds
insufficiently ambitious,
or this isn't going
to work unless you
can get more data than
you actually have,
and things like that.
So this is mainly
just the feedback.
But on the things
to think about,
project plans that
are lacking, they're
generally just lacking
concreteness in nuts and bolts
ways, which are
essential to being
able to do a good final project
in a short amount of time.
So you need to have
found good data,
or have a realistic
plan, so that
shouldn't be plant,
a realistic plan
to be able to collect that.
You need to have a
realistic way that you
can evaluate your work.
You need to have thought about
what kinds of experiments
you could run so you could show
whether your model is working
well or badly.
And we'll be sort of looking
to see whether you've
done these things.
OK, so then a couple
of weeks after that
is the project milestone,
which is, again, from everyone.
This is a progress report.
And this, again, just meant
to help keep you on track.
So you should be more
than halfway done.
You should have been able--
in nearly all cases,
I'll talk more
about this in a minute,
nearly all cases,
you should already have
been able to implement
some baseline system and have
some initial experimental
results to show.
You might still be
working on your main model
and have nothing to show
for it, but hopefully you
have at least set an
obvious simple baseline
to know how well it works.
It's this thing, and I built
that, and I have some numbers.
And then we want an
update on how you plan
to spend the rest of your time.
And, again, a lot of this
is about us giving you
more feedback as to
what are the best
things you can do for the
final two weeks of the class.
And then at the end, there's
writing a final project.
And for this, the
quality of your writeup
is really, really important
to your grade, right?
By and large, we're going to
evaluate how good your project
is by reading the writeup.
So make sure you
budget sufficient time
to actually do a good
job of [INAUDIBLE]
You can look at good projects
from past years that are
all up on the CS224N website.
2020 was kind of a mess because
of the start of the pandemic.
So, of course, we
should look at 2019.
So there's even better
models of what you should do.
So the details vary, but
this is sort of a picture
to have in mind, and normally
what the writeup looks like.
So eight pages, you want to have
an abstract and introduction
to the paper, you want to
talk about related prior work,
you want to present
the model you're
using, you want to talk
about the data you're using,
talk about your experiments,
what the results are,
what you learned about it.
The details may vary.
Some papers there's less
to say about the model
and there's more to say
about the experiment.
So you can sort of move
things around a bit,
but roughly something like this.
Okay, so I now want
to go on and say
a bit about research
and practical things
that we need to do.
A lot of these things are
relevant to everybody.
At any rate, there
are things that you
should know a little bit about.
So the very first one is
finding research topics,
which is sort of especially
vital to custom final projects.
Yeah, so really
for all of science,
there's sort of only
two ways that you
can have a research project.
That one way is doing
domain science, where
you start with a problem
of interest in the domain,
such as, how can I
build a decent Cherokee
to English machine
translation system?
And you work on
finding ways to be
able to do it better
than people currently
know how to do, or to understand
the problem better than people
currently understand it.
And the other way is to take a
methodological approach where
you start off with some method
or approach of interest,
and then you work out good
ways to extend or improve it,
or new ways to apply it.
And so basically you're
doing one of those.
So there are effectively
different kinds
of projects you can do.
This is not an exhaustive
list, but most projects sort of
fall into one of these
buckets, very non-uniformly.
So the most common type is you
find some application or task
of interest, and you explore
how to approach and solve
it as well as possible.
Often, that's using
existing models
and trying out different
options, and things like that.
A second kind is you can
take some relatively complex
neural architecture, i.e.
it has to be something more
complex than we've built
for assignments 1 through 5.
You implement it,
and get something
that works on some data.
And while you are doing
something fairly complex,
it's fine just to implement
it and get it to work.
But if there's some way that
you can tweak it, and try and do
something different, and
see if that makes that even
better, or maybe
it makes it worse,
and you can do
experiments either way,
that's sort of even better.
There are then other kinds
of projects that you can do.
So another kind of project
is an analysis project.
So you can take
some model that's
an existing model and
you can poke at it
and find out things
about what it knows.
So you could take anything,
even as simple as word vectors,
and poke at them.
And you can find out
things like, well,
how much do word vectors
know about word sensors?
Well, sometimes the same word
is both a noun and a verb.
Can you tell-- can
you sort of get
that difference similarities
out of the word vectors?
So analysis projects
are perfectly fine,
often interesting.
And then of these five kinds,
the rarest kind of project,
we've had a couple, is
a theoretical project.
So there's a lot of
interesting deep learning
theory is to how do these
things work and why,
and what would it take
to make it work better?
And so you can work
on sort of getting
any kind of non-trivial
property or understanding
of a deep learning model.
Here are just quickly a couple
of examples of some projects
from the past years of
224N just to give you
a couple of examples
of things like this.
So deep poetry, this
was doing generation
of Shakespearean sonnets.
So the way it was
being generated
was with [INAUDIBLE] word with
now for machine translation.
But it had interesting
differences,
because if you wanted
to generate poetry,
you need to know about
metrical structure, and rhyme,
and so they're working
out how to add components
to the model that could do that.
Here is someone who
was implementing
a complex neural model.
So there's been a line
of work at DeepMind
on trying to build
general purpose
computers with
neural architectures,
so there's first of all
neural Turing machines,
and then a subsequent
model called
the differential
[INAUDIBLE] neural computer.
And they haven't released the
code of those open source.
And so Carol decided
that she was going to--
she was going to implement
differential neural computers
and get them to work.
This was a very dangerous
idea, because we
were in week 10 of the
class, and she still
hadn't gotten them
to work at all.
But luckily, she got it
together at the last moment
and actually got
her model working,
and was able to run it and get
results on some of the problems
that DeepMind was also
showing results on.
And so she pulled the
rabbit out of the hat,
and had an enormous success.
And we were very impressed
that she managed to do that.
Here's-- so sometimes final
projects can become papers.
Here is a final
project that became
paper published at the top
machine learning conference.
This is from a few years
ago, this one from 2017.
It actually has a couple
of fairly simple ideas.
There are ideas that, at that
time, people weren't using,
and these two people proved
worked and improved things.
And they got a conference
paper out of it.
So I'll just mention
one of them now.
So if you think about our
current neural network language
models, they have both--
for words and encoding into
distributed vectors, where
at the other end, the
softmax matrix basically
hides inside it, just
like for our word
vectors, our word
vector for each word.
And then you are sort of
deciding the probabilities
of generating
different words based
on similarities between
the query vector
and each of those words.
So their idea was, look,
maybe we'd actually
be able to build better language
models if we tied together
the word-embedding
matrix and the matrix
used to project the RNN output.
And, actually, they showed that
you can get significant gains
by doing that.
And so now, it's basically
sort of now become standard,
if you're wanting to build
strong neural language models,
that you want to tie those two
sets of parameters together.
So that was pretty cool.
Here's some more
systems of the project.
So I'll mention
this again later,
but something people have been
interested in is how can you
squish neural nets
and make them small
so you can run them on a
regular laptop, or a smaller
device like a mobile phone.
And so these people
worked on, how
could you do quantization
of neural networks
down to sort of one or
two bits per parameter
and still get good results.
So this is sort
of an example, has
to involve neural nets
and human language,
it's sort of a way in
which you could say,
this didn't involve
human language at all,
because this was really
about quantizing neural nets.
But effectively, where
we draw the line is
we say you will be
allowed to do this,
providing the task
and the model you
use to demonstrate success or
failure as a natural language
task.
And so they did both
word similarity tasks,
and question answering
tasks of seeing
how well the system performed
after doing the compression
by quantization.
How can you find a good
place for a project
if you don't have a good idea?
One place is to sort of
look at recent papers.
So for most NLP papers, they
appear in the ACL anthology.
Also look at major machine
learning conferences.
Most past 224N projects are
up on the class website.
You can look through them.
It's just general
arXiv.org preprint servers.
But perhaps even
better is looking
for an interesting
problem in the world.
So Hal Varian is
an an economist.
Was it [INAUDIBLE] And he wrote
this cool paper that I often
recommend to students,
How to Build an Economic
Model in Your Spare Time.
And the paper isn't really
about economic models.
It's about how to do research.
And what he says right
at the beginning,
section 1 of the paper
is called Getting Ideas.
And he writes, "The way to get
ideas, that's the question.
Most graduate
students are convinced
that the way you get ideas
is to read journal papers.
In my experience,
journals really
have a very good source
of original ideas.
You can get lots of things
from journal papers, technique,
insight, even truth.
But most of the
time, you will only
get somebody else's ideas."
And so he talks further
about better ways
of getting ideas by thinking
about problems in the world.
So Arxiv is this huge
repository of papers.
It's hard to navigate.
There are various tools that
can make it easier to navigate.
One of them is Arxiv
Sanity Preserver,
which is a website that was
written by Andrej Karpahty, who
was the original person
who constructed and taught
the CS231N course, still
a good thing to use.
There are lots of leaderboards
for different tasks in NLP.
So a place you can find
tasks and work on tasks
is looking at leaderboards.
So Papers With Code
and NLPProgress
are two good general
sources of leaderboards.
There are also then lots
of more specialized ones
for particular tasks.
I wanted to then,
for research topics--
this material, these
next four slides,
are brand new for this year.
I wanted to sort of
just say a few words
about the funny,
somewhat different time
that we're in, where there's
sort of old Deep Learning NLP,
and new Deep Learning NLP.
So in the early days of
the Deep Learning revival--
which I'll call 2010 to 2018,
because 2010 is the year
I started doing Deep
Learning for NLP.
Most of the work was in
defining and exploring better
Deep Learning architectures.
So the typical paper was, I can
improve a summarization system
by not only using
the kind of attention
I just explained,
but I could add
an extra kind of
attention, which I'll
use as a copying mechanism.
So I'll do additional
attention calculations
to work out source words
which I could copy verbatim
to the output, rather than
having to regenerate them
through the standard
kind of softmax.
That's just one
example of millions.
But you were changing the
architecture of the model,
and make things better.
That's what a lot of good
CS224N projects did too.
And, in particular,
for one branch
of the default final
project, the one where
you start with the baseline
SQuAD question answering system
and work out ways
to make it better
by adding more
neural architecture,
it's essentially doing this.
But, actually, if you
look out in the research
world of the last
couple of years,
the sad truth is that
approach is dead.
It's not actually dead.
I mean, that's too strong.
But that's now much more
difficult and rarer to do.
If you look at the sort of
last three years of NLP--
and this is true both for people
who are implementing production
NLP systems at
companies and for people
who are doing research in NLP--
that most work is
more like this.
There are these enormously
good big pre-trained language
models, BERT, GPT-2,
roBERTa, XLNet,
T5, they exist on the web,
and you can download them
with one Python command, and
they give you a great basis
for doing most NLP tasks.
We'll learn all
about them next week.
So you're not actually
starting from scratch
defining your own
model architecture
and playing with variants.
You're saying, I'm going
to be using RoBERTa
[INAUDIBLE] further fine
tuning it for your task,
doing domain adaptation,
and things like that.
So this is still very
quickly of our 2021
NLP for all of your practical
projects and industry needs,
this is basically the formula
that which you should probably
use.
There's this enormously
great library
by the company Huggingface.
You install it, pip
install transformers.
And then that gives you
a great implementation
of the transformers we
learn about next week.
And then, effectively,
what you're doing
is something like my code below.
This code doesn't quite run.
It's missing some
pieces if you try it.
But the sort of pieces are, you
load a big pre-trained language
model.
So here I'm loading the
bert-base-uncased model.
It turns out these models all
have very special tokenizers.
You'll hear about those
next week, as well.
So we grab the tokenizer for it.
Then we are going to fine
tune it for our task.
Like maybe I'm going to be
working with legal data,
so I want to take
the general model
and fine tune it to
understand legal data better.
And then I've got
something I want to do,
like question answering,
or perhaps here I'm
using
BertForSequenceClassification.
Maybe the task I want
to do is label mentions
of sections of legal code.
So at that point, I'm
then going to sort
of fine tune for
that particular task,
and then run on that task.
And so this is kind
of what we're doing,
and we're just
sort of doing stuff
on top of a pre-existing model.
So a lot of what
is exciting now is
problems that work within
or around that world.
So and you might
think about that,
and look at recent
papers and things that
could be done about that world.
Well, one of them-- and this is
the other half of the default
final project--
is we still have this problem
of robustness to domain shift,
that these models are trained
on normally one kind of text,
but we often want to use it
for different kinds of text,
including often when you're
talking about problem
or application
specific questions,
there are domains for which
you don't have much data.
How can you do that well?
If you've got one of these big
models, well, in some sense
they're good.
But are they actually
robust that they
work for all of the different
things in the space you'd
like them to work on?
So you're not only interested in
basic accuracy, but robustness.
So this RobustnessGym was a
very recently announced project
by a PhD student at
Stanford, Karan Goel.
It's actually testing the
robustness of NLP models.
And they've got some
stuff built into it,
but there's lots of stuff
that isn't built into it.
If someone would like to sort
of choose some NLP problem,
whether it's dependency
parsing or something else
like summarization, and build
out robustness tests for it,
that could be kind
of interesting to do.
A bunch of other things,
you can look at issues
whether there's bias
embedded in these models.
How can you explain
what they're doing?
How can you use
data augmentation?
There's been an
enormous amount of work
on using data augmentation to
improve model resources, lots
of different areas.
I'll just mention two other
things and then I'll go on.
So there's been a ton of work
on scaling models up and down.
So these big, pre-trained
language models
are already big.
So the fact of the
matter is, it's just not
possible for the
time and resources
that you have in
224N to be thinking,
I'm going to be building by
myself big pre-trained models.
All you can do is use
ones that already exist.
But on the other hand, people
are actually interested in,
can you build very small models
that still work pretty well?
And there are lots of examples.
But actually one that was done
recently for question answering
was that there was a bake off
competition at the last NeurIPS
which was called Efficient QA.
And one of the
divisions of this bake
off was, can you build a
performant question answering
system that will
run [INAUDIBLE]..
And, well, that's actually
a reasonable thing
that you could attempt
for a final project.
Another thing people have
been very interested in
is wanting to explore more
advanced learning capabilities
in neural networks, ideas like
compositionality, systematic
generalization, fast learning,
such as meta learning work.
And a lot of the time,
people have investigated
these in small domains.
So here's a couple of examples
that you could go look at,
BabyAI and gSCAN.
So those could be
interesting places you
could look for a final project.
OK, other stuff to know
quickly, probably I
can't quite go through all of
these slides, and some of them
you could just take
home and look at.
You need data.
Now, we actually love it
if people feel like they
can collect their own data.
And sometimes there are good
ways to collect your own data.
But the reality is a lot of
the time, the easiest way
to get a fast start
on a final project
when you only have a few weeks
is to make use of an existing
data set.
And there are lots of
pre-existing data sets.
So this data from the
Linguistic Data Consortium,
which is a licensed data.
We have licenses at Stanford.
You can look through
their catalog
and find all the
things they have.
There are websites
that have lots of data.
So if you want to do
machine translation tasks,
you can find lots of
machine translation data
on this website.
Dependency parsing, if you're
keen on assignment 3, lots
of data on the Universal
Dependencies website.
There are now several
websites that are
collecting a lot of data sets.
So Huggingface has
also just recently
actually announced
Huggingface Datasets,
which is sort of an
index of datasets.
And the Paperswithcode
people also
have Paperswithcode Datasets,
so you can look at those.
There are many more.
Yeah, here's just
a quick summary
of thinking about
a research project.
So this is just
one example, right?
That suppose you
think summarization.
So that's going from
a longer piece of text
to a short summary of it.
So what you have to do, you
need to find the data set.
And, well, probably
the easiest thing to do
is to use an existing tech
summarization data set.
You can find several online.
But this is why you can
think of interesting ways
to create your own data.
So something that you might have
noticed if you look at Twitter
is that journalists often
promote their own stories by,
or their newspaper or TV station
does by putting out a tweet.
And so that's sort of
like found data, which
is sort of self summaries.
Could you collect
some of those and try
and learn to generate
tweets for a news story?
So I'll say a bit
about data set hygiene.
You want to be careful
about working things out
so you have train
sets and test sets.
I'll say that in a minute.
You want some way to
evaluate whether you're
doing well as you build models.
And you pretty much need to have
an automatic evaluation metric,
even though human
evaluation's great,
since you want to
train a bunch of models
and see whether they're
better or worse.
You normally want an automatic
metric that's semi-decent.
You should make sure you
have some kind of baseline
that you want to have some sense
of whether you're doing well.
And so commonly,
you, first off, want
to implement some simple model
like a logistic regression,
or just averaging word
vectors or something,
and see how well that works.
Because then if you're not
doing better than that, that
you're actually making
no progress whatsoever.
Then you should implement
some neural net model
that you think might
be good, and see
if you can get that to work,
and have that work well.
Make sure you keep
looking at your data
to see what kind of
errors you're making,
and think about how you could
change the model to avoid them.
And then, hopefully,
you've got time
to try out some model
variants and see
if they're better or worse.
And then that will help
in having a good project.
Yeah, so quickly, for what
I call here pots of data.
So many public data sets
come with a structure
where they have
train, dev, and test.
And the idea is that you keep
your test data until the end,
and you only sort
of do test runs
when development is complete,
or at least almost complete.
[INAUDIBLE]
Train on the train data, and
you evaluate on the dev data.
Sometimes you need
even more data sets.
Sometimes you want to do
tuning of hyperparameters,
and you might need a train
set, a tune set, a dev set,
and a test set.
If the data set, if it
doesn't come pre-split
or it doesn't have
enough pieces,
it's sort of your job to work
out how to cut it into pieces
and to get things working.
And the reason why
you need to do this
is that it's necessary to have
these different sets to get
realistic measures
of performance.
In fact, ideally, you're
only actually testing
on the test set once and,
at any rate, very few times.
So if you're doing the
default final project,
we limit you to three
runs on the test set.
So remember that, and
save your three runs.
And the reason
that we do that is
that if you mix up and
overuse these data sets,
the results just become invalid.
So when you train on
data, well, you'll
always build a model that does
well on the training data.
So that's not exciting.
And, well, if you want
to tune hyperparameters,
if you tune them on
the training data set,
you won't get good
valid values for them,
because they're not tuned to
good values for something that
would work on
different test data.
But the surplus part
of it is I think
a lot of people starting
off think, oh, there's
no harm in just keeping on
testing on the test set.
Every time I try
out some variant,
I'll just see how it's
going on the test set.
It's a really compelling thing
that you want to do, right?
You changed your
model, and you'd
like to know whether it made
the score on the test set
go up or down.
But the truth is that if you
do that, you're cheating.
Because what you do is
you're sort of slowly
training on the test set.
Because you keep every
change that helps on the test
set, and you throw
away every change
that doesn't help on the
test set, or makes it worse.
And so you're learning
about the test set,
and what things happen by chance
to work on that particular test
set.
So you effectively slowly
training on the test
set, and you get biased,
unrealistically high levels
of performance
OK, let's see.
I think there are
then sort of a bunch
more slides on
neural nets that I
think I'm going to
just skip for a moment.
But I think in general
they're useful to have seen.
Maybe I'll just sort
of mention this one.
So for the final projects,
you're much more on your own.
And you have to work
out for yourself
how to get your neural
network to work.
So the first thing
is you want to start
with a positive attitude.
These neural nets are amazing.
They really want to learn.
They want to find any pattern
they can anywhere in data.
They really just do that.
It's in their DNA.
So if your neural
network isn't learning,
it means you're doing something
wrong that's preventing it
from learning successfully.
But at that point,
there's a grim reality.
There are all sorts of things
that cause neural nets to not
learn at all, or a more
common case, actually,
is they sort of learn
a bit, that they
don't learn very well.
There are bugs in the code.
You're dividing through
by the wrong thing.
You're missing some
connections in your network,
so no information is
flowing from one place
to another place.
You're calculating the
gradients wrong in some layer,
there are all sorts of
things that can go wrong.
So you need to then work out
how to find and fix them.
And the truth is that this
debugging and tuning can often
take way more time than I'm
going to implement the model.
So in terms of thinking about
how much you could get through,
you should be thinking,
OK, I've coded up my model.
That doesn't mean
that you're 75% done.
It's pretty frequent, it means
that you're only 20% done,
and there's still a lot of work
to go to get things working.
OK, so for the last
minutes I just want
to say a few minutes about
[INAUDIBLE] final projects,
and I've got some
idea about what this
is about as an NLP problem.
OK, so the problem
is most commonly
called question
answering of a document.
But really the part
that we're doing
is perhaps better called
reading comprehension.
And so the idea of
this is that you
want to actually be
able to answer questions
based on documents.
So here's an example
of a question,
who was Australia's
third prime minister?
And once upon a time, if you
type the question into Google,
all you got was web search.
And it returned to you a list of
pages with the implied promise
that some of the ones
right near the top
probably had the
answer to the question.
But if you do this now, it
gives you back an answer.
And so here is the answer,
John Christian Watson.
And the important
thing to realize
is that this kind of
featured snippet, Google
has 101, or maybe 1,001
different pieces inside it.
But this featured
snippet isn't coming
from the Google knowledge
graph structured data.
It's coming straight
from a webpage where
some part of the
Google search system
has actually read this web page
and decided what the answer is.
So for this kind of system,
the most straightforward way
to do it is you have two parts.
First you have a
web search system
that finds the page that
probably has the answer.
And then you have a reading
comprehension system
that actually looks
inside the text
and works to extract the answer.
And so if you look through
this piece of text,
and this sentence says, was
an Australian politician
who served as the third prime
minister of Australia, that's
what I'm asking for in slightly
different wording, Australia's
third prime minister.
This answers the question.
And so it correctly says that
the answer is John Christian
Watson.
And so what we want to build
in the default final project is
systems that do that
second part, that
given a piece of
text and a question,
they can give the answer.
And so the general
motivation for why
this is important
is once we have
massive, full-text document
collections that simply we're
saying, here's a list of
maybe relevant documents,
is of limited use.
But we'd really much prefer to
get answers to our questions.
And you know, that's
true in general.
But it's especially true
if you're using your phone
to try and look for
information, rather than sitting
in front of a 27-inch monitor.
It's especially
true if you're using
a virtual assistant device
like Alexa or Google Assistant.
So that's the problem
that's being worked on,
reading comprehension
or question answering.
And so the SQuAD
data set, which was
built by Pranav
Rajpurkar and Percy Liang
consists of passages
taken from Wikipedia,
and questions, which
team won Super Bowl 50.
And what you're meant
to be able to do
is read through this passage,
blah, blah, blah, blah, blah,
and say, aha, the answer
is the Denver Broncos.
And so there are
100,000 such examples.
And so the answer
is always just taken
to be a span of the passage.
And that's referred to as
extractive question answering.
So to collect this
data, what was done
was that people
were shown passages,
asked several questions, just
like reading comprehension
in school, or perhaps
slightly simpler questions.
And they were asked to
choose a standard answer.
And as in these
examples show, they
showed it to three human beings.
And they didn't always
choose exactly the same span.
Because there's some
uncertainty as to how many words
to include.
But roughly they're answering
the question in that way.
And so then we have
evaluation measures.
And so there are two
One is exact match, whether
you return exactly what
one of the humans returned.
And the other one
is the F1 measure,
which is the overlapping
words of your span to one
of the humans, roughly.
So for SQuAD, the
[INAUDIBLE] We're
going to do SQuAD 2.0, which
is just a little bit more
complex, because they make it
a little bit trickier that some
of the questions have
no answers in the text.
So here's a piece of
text about Genghis Khan.
And the question is, when did
Genghis Khan kill Great Khan?
And, well, if we read
through this text,
there's Genghis Khan
at the beginning.
And there's talk
about different Khans.
And there's the person down here
who became Great Khan in 1251.
Genghis Khan didn't
kill Great Khan.
It doesn't say that at all.
But actually, here's
Microsoft nlnet,
which is another strong
question answering system.
And if you ask it this
question, it says 1234.
So the reality is that
a lot of these models
have effectively, heuristically
behaved like, OK, well this
is asking for a year.
Let me look for a
year in this passage.
So this is near discussion
of Genghis Khan.
And maybe weakening is
somehow similar to killing.
I'm going to guess 1234.
And that's sort of the wrong
thing to have done here.
So this is a good
reliability test
for question answering models.
So that's an interesting
add-on problem to look at.
OK, I'm going to
stop there for today.
Good luck with your projects.