Hi, everyone.
Welcome to CS224N, lecture
nine, Self Attention
and Transformers.
If I am not able to
be heard right now,
please someone send
a message in the chat
because I can't see anyone.
But I'm excited to get
into the content for today,
we'll be talking about self
attention and transformers.
Let us dive into
the lecture plan
and we'll talk about some
sort of to do's for the course
as well.
So we'll start with
where we were back
last week with recurrence,
recurrent neural networks
and we'll talk about a
movement from recurrence
to attention based
on NLP models,
we talked about
attention and we're going
to just go all in on attention.
We'll introduce the
transformer model,
which is a particular type of
attention based model that's
very popular, you need to know
it, you're going to learn it.
We'll talk about
some great results
with transformers and then
some drawbacks and variants
and sort of very recent
work on improving them.
So some reminders before we
jump in, assignment 4 is due,
the mid-quarter feedback survey
is due Tuesday, February 16th.
You get some small number
of points for doing that
and we really
appreciate your feedback
on what we've done well,
what we can improve on.
And then final project
proposal is also due,
one note on the proposals, part
of the goal of the proposal
is to, I'd say the main part
is to give you feedback on the
idea that you have presented
and make sure that
it is a viable option
for a final project and make
sure we kind of recenter
if not.
And so we want to get feedback
to you very quickly on that,
OK.
All right.
So with that, let's
start in on the content
of this week's lecture.
So we were in this place
in NLP as of last week,
where we had recurrent
neural networks,
sort of for a lot of things
that you wanted to do.
So it's around 2016
and the strategy
if you want to build a strong
and healthy model, is you have
sentences that
you need to encode
and you have a
bidirectional LSTM say,
and maybe it looks a little
bit like this pictographically
and maybe it's a source
sentence in a translation,
for example, we saw
machine translation.
And then you define your
output, which is maybe
a sequence of words which is the
target translation that we're
trying to predict or
maybe it's a parse tree,
or it's a summary, and you
use an LSTM with one direction
to generate it.
And this works really well.
We use these architectures
to do all kinds
of interesting things, but
one thing that we said,
we talked about is information
sort of bottleneck that you're
trying to encode, maybe a
very long sequence in sort
of the very last vector in your,
or one vector in your encoder,
and so we use the
tension as this mechanism
to take a representation from
our decoder and sort of look
back and treat the encoded
representations as a memory,
that we can reference
and sort of pick out
what's important to any given
time, and that was attention.
And this week, we're going to
do something slightly different.
So we learned about sequence to
sequence models, the encoder,
decoder way of thinking
about problems, more or less
in order to deal with this
idea of building a machine
translation system that's end
to end differentiable, right?
And so this is sort of
a really interesting way
of thinking about problems.
What we'll do this
week is different.
We're not trying
to motivate sort
of an entirely new way of
thinking about problems
like machine translation,
instead we're
going to take the building
blocks that we were using,
recurrent neural
networks and we're
going to spend a lot
of trial and error
in the field trying to figure
out if there are building
blocks that just work
better across a broad range
of problems, sort of
slot the new thing
in for recurrent neural
networks and say,
voila, maybe it works better.
And so I want to take us
on this sort of journey
to self attention
networks, and we'll
start with some problems with
recurrent neural networks.
So we spent a bit of time
trying to convince you
that recurrent neural
networks were very useful.
Now I'm going to
talk about reasons
why they can be improved.
So we know that recurrent
networks are enrolled
left to right in air quotes, it
could be right to left as well.
So what does this mean?
A recurrent neural network
encodes linear locality, right?
So once I'm looking at
tasty in this phrase,
I'm about to look
at Pizza or if I'm
going in the other direction
once I look at Pizza,
I'm about to look at tasty.
And so it's very easy
for their meanings,
for their presence
in the sentence
to affect the meaning, to
affect the representation
of the other word.
And this is actually
quite useful
because nearby words frequently
do influence each other, that's
practically one of
the things we talked
about with the distributional
hypothesis as encoded
by something like Word2vec.
But if words are
distant linearly,
they can still interact
with each other.
This is something that we
saw in dependency parsing.
So if I have say the phrase the
chef, notice chef bolded here,
I'm running a recurrent neural
network over this, and then
the chef who, and we're going
to have this long sequence
that I'm going to encode.
And then the word
was, right, maybe it
is the chef who was,
but in between I
have O of sequence length many
steps of the computation that I
need to get to before chef
and was can interact, right?
And so in the middle,
things might go wrong.
Maybe it's hard to
learn things with where
they should interact.
So in particular, it might be
hard to learn long distance
dependencies because we
have gradient problems.
We saw that LSTMs
propagate gradients
better than simple
RNNs but not perfectly.
And so if chef and
was are very far,
it becomes hard to learn
that they should interact.
And the linear order
of words is sort
of baked into the model, right?
You have to unroll the RNN
throughout the sequence,
and it's not really the right
way to think about sentences
necessarily, obviously
linear order isn't really
how sentences are
kind of structured.
And so here you have
Chef, and then you've
got all this sort of
computation in the middle, all
of those applications of
the recurrent weight matrix
before you allow it
to interact with was.
And again, sort of dependence
is O of sequence length,
and then you got
the word "was" okay?
A second problem
is very related,
this is the lack of
parallelizability.
So this is going to be a
huge refrain, now that we've
gotten to the transformers
lectures, is parallelizability,
it's what you get
from your GPU and it's
what you want to exploit.
So when you run
an RNN, you have O
of sequence length many
unparallellelizable operations.
And so while you have a
GPU that can kind of chunk
through a bunch of independent
operations at once,
you're unable to sort
of do them all at once
because you have this
explicit time dependence
in their current equations.
In particular, a future
RNN state down the line
can't be computed until you've
computed one that's earlier on,
and this inhibits training
on very large data sets.
So let's take a look at
this, unrolling an RNN.
If this is say the first
layer of an RNN or an LSTM,
maybe it doesn't depend
on effectively anything,
you can just compute
it immediately.
And then the second
layer, so this
is a stacked set of two LSTMS.
The second layer depends
on the first layer here.
In the time dimension though,
this cell here depends on this,
so you've got a 1, and then
this depends on this so you've
got a 1, so you have at most,
I'm sorry, at least two things
that you need to
compute here before you
can compute the value of this
cell, likewise three here.
And with the sequence
length, it grows
with O of the sequence length.
So here I have been unable to
even try to compute this value
when I get here because I had
to sort of do all of this first,
so I can't parallelize
over the time dimension
and this inhibits training
on very large data sets.
OK, so and then I guess,
Christopher, or TAs,
feel free to stop
me with a question
if it feels like that's
the right thing to do.
OK, and so you can see how
it's a related problem, right?
It's really directly related
to the recurrence of the model.
The thing that we
thought was really useful
now is being problematic.
OK, so what I'm trying
to say with that is,
we seemingly want to
replace recurrence
as the building block itself.
So let's go through
some alternatives,
and we've seen each of these
alternatives in the class
so far.
We'll start with word
window, sort of building
blocks for our NLP models.
If we wanted to
replace our encoders
and our decoders with something
that sort of fit the same goal
but had different properties.
So a word window model will
aggregate local context, right?
We saw this with our sort
of word window classifiers
that we've built already.
You take a local
context of words,
you use it to represent
information about the center
word, this is also known as
one dimensional convolution,
we'll go over this in
depth later in the course,
right now we'll consider
it as word window contexts.
So the number of
unparallellelizable operations
with these word
window building blocks
does not grow with
the sequence length.
And here's sort of
a picture of that.
You have the embedding
layer say, so
you can embed every
word independently,
right, So you don't need to know
the other words surrounding it
in order to pick the right
embedding dimension out.
And so these all have
sort of zero dependence
in this sort of
hand waving notion
of how much
parallelizability there is.
Now you can walk a
word window classifier
on top of each one to build a
representation of the word that
takes into account
its local context.
But in order to apply
it to this word h1
I don't need to know
anything, sorry,
I don't need to have
applied it to h1
in order to apply it to h2.
Likewise, in order to apply
a word window contextualizer
to ht, I can just look at its
local window independently.
And so again, none of these
have a dependence in time.
I can keep stacking
layers like this, right?
So this can look
like an encoder,
right, an encoder like
our LSTM encoders.
If I didn't allow you
to look at the future
by just cutting
off the window, it
could look like a decoder
for language models.
And this is nice.
And we get this beautiful,
O(1) dependence in time, right?
No dependence at all
in the time dimension,
that's an improvement.
But there are some problems.
So what about long distance
dependencies, right?
This is why we said we wanted to
use recurrent neural networks,
it's because they
would do better
at encoding long
distance dependencies.
It's a problem, just like
it was a problem before
but by stacking
word window layers,
we can get to wider,
longer contexts.
So if you have some
sort of window size
and then you stack two
layers, so red states
here interact, a state,
kind of how you can look,
how far away you can look in
order to encode hk, right?
So in the embedding layer, you
have these sort of words here.
So this is the last layer, this
top layer of the word window
classifier.
Here is the embedding of hk
at the output of your encoder,
and so it looks at
the local five words
because that's the window size.
And then as well, the
farthest word over here
has also looked a couple
of words away, right?
So if you stack these and
stack these and stack these
without growing the window
size at all at any given layer,
you can look pretty far.
And actually there
are tricks you
can use to look even farther.
But you still have this sort
of, at least in principle,
problem where you've got
a word like this, h1.
And you can see how it's in
blue and with these two layers
of the network, I don't
know anything about h1
at all when I'm building up the
representation of hk over here.
I could solve that by adding
another layer in depth,
but in principle you always
have some finite field.
So this is actually
pretty useful.
These word window kind
of contextualizers,
and we will learn
more about them later.
And there was sort of
a lot of this effort
that I talked about at the
beginning of the class,
was actually sort
of partly deciding
which of the word window
stuff, convolutional it's
called stuff, or
attention, and attention
has won out for the time being.
And so yeah, what
about attention?
So why could it be useful
as a fundamental building
block instead of sort of
sugar on top of our LSTMs?
So just to recall some of
the intuitions of attention,
it treats a word's
representation as a query
and it looks somewhere and tries
to sort of access information
from a set of values, right?
So we had a word
representation in our decoder
in our machine translation
systems, the set of values
were all of the encoder states
for the source sentence.
And today we'll think
about instead of attention
from the decoder to the encoder,
we'll think about attention
within a single sentence.
So just a very
quick picture of it,
you've got your
embedding layer again,
I'm putting the
computational dependence
counts here so all
of these sort of
can be done in parallel for
the embedding layer again.
And now you're doing
attention, right?
So you're kind of looking
at every single word
in the embedding layer
to attend to this word,
and I'm omitting a
bunch of arrows here,
so these are all arrows.
All words interact
with all words
and we'll get deep into
this today, I promise.
But I just wanted to make this
a little bit less dense looking
of a graph.
And then so in the second
layer, again all pairs of words
interact and this is
all parallelizable.
So you can't parallelize
in depth, right,
because you need to encode
this layer before you
can do that layer but in
time, it is parallelizable,
so it checks that box.
So again, we have O(1) sort
of computational dependence,
a number of
unparallelizable operations
as a function of sequence length
and as an added benefit, right,
the interaction distance
between words is O(1) as well.
So whereas before we
had recurrent networks
where if you are far, so t is
the last word in the sentence,
you could have O(t)
operations between you
and a far away word.
With attention, you
interact immediately,
that's the very first layer, you
get to see your far away word.
And so that's O(1).
And this ends up being seemingly
fascinatingly powerful,
and we'll get into a
lot of details today.
OK, so this is sort of why
attention solves the two
problems that we brought up
with recurrent neural networks
but with our
empiricist hats on, it
shouldn't be proof yet that it
should be a good building block
and in fact, it takes a
little bit of thinking
to think about how to turn
attention into a building block
like RNNs were.
So let's start by digging
right into just the equations
for self attention,
which again is attention
to whether everything is
looking within itself,
we'll formalize this for you.
So we're going to be talking
all lecture today about queries,
keys and values.
Our queries are going to
be a set of t queries,
each query is a
vector in dimension d.
You can just think of them as
just those vectors right now,
not worrying necessarily
about where they came from.
We have a set of keys, k1 to kt.
Again, each vector k
is in dimensionality d,
and we have some
values, each value
is going to be also
in dimensionality d.
And for now, we're
going to assume
that we have the same number
of all of them, that's
not necessarily the case later.
So in self attention, the
keys, queries and values
come from the same
source of information,
the same sentence for example.
And so yeah, in
practice when they all
come from the same
sentence, right,
this is going to be the
same number of all of them,
it's all going to
be t, in practice,
you can have the numbers differ.
So where do these come from?
We'll get into the specifics
of this later but for now,
think about the output
of the previous layer.
So imagine the
output is you have
like the embedding
layer, right, and that's
the input to something that's
going to do self attention.
Think of all of these
outputs or the embeddings
as some vectors xi.
And now we can just say that
the value is equal to the key,
is equal to the query,
is equal to that xi.
So we're going to use the
same vectors for all of them,
but labeling them as
keys, queries and values,
I promise will be very useful
in how we sort of think
about what's going on and how
we look at the equations that
implement this.
So self attention
pretty generally
but with this dot product,
so dot product self attention
here is just the math.
Math is, you compute key, query
affinities and the dot product
bit is the fact that
you're using the product
function here.
So you take a dot product
for all pairs i and j of qi
dotted with kg.
So that is a T by
T matrix, capital
T, right, by T
matrix of affinities.
These are scalar values,
not bounded in size.
Next you compute the
attention weights.
We saw this as well using
the softmax function.
I've just written out the
softmax function here.
So you exponentiate the
affinity and then you
sum over, in this
case, right, you're
summing over all of the keys.
So you've got a given query
and you're summing overall all
the keys for the normalization.
So where should this
query be looking?
Remember you've got T
different queries that
were doing this for here.
And so for a given query,
you sum over all the keys
to get your
normalization constant,
normalizing by that gives you a
distribution over the sequence
length T. So now you
have sort of a weight
on all of the indices.
And again, we do our
weighted average, right?
So we've got our
weights for our average
and then the output,
right, there's
going to be one
output per query.
And the output is the
weights for that multiplied
by the value vectors, right?
So again if you set the
keys, the queries, the values
to all be x, this
makes sense, but it's
nice to have the qs and the
ks to know sort of, which
thing is doing what?
You can think of
the query as being
sort of looking for
information somewhere
the key as interacting
with the query,
and then the value is the
thing that you're actually
going to weight in your
average and output.
John, a question you
might like to answer
is, so if now we're connecting
everything to everything,
how is this different to
using a fully connected layer?
That's a great question.
A couple of reasons.
One is that unlike a
fully connected layer,
you get to learn the
interaction weights.
Well, the interaction
weights are
dynamic as a function of what
the actual values here are,
right?
So in a fully
connected layer, you
have these weights that
you're learning slowly
over the course of the
training your network, that
allow you to say sort
of which hidden units
you should be looking at.
In attention, it's the
actual interactions
between the key and
the query vectors
which are dependent on
the actual content, that
are allowed to vary by time.
And so the actual strengths
of all the interactions,
of all the sort of
attention weights, which
you could think of as connected
to the weights in the fully
connected layer, are
allowed to change
as a function of the input.
A separate thing, is
that the parametization
is much different.
So you're not learning an
independent connection weight
for all pairs of
things, instead you're
allowed to parameterize the
attention as these sort of dot
product functions
between vectors that
are representations,
and you end up
having the parameters work
out more nicely, which
we'll see later.
We haven't gone into
how we're paramitizing
these functions yet.
So those are the two
answers I'd say, is one, is
you have this sort of
dynamic connectivity and two,
it has this
inductive bias that's
not just connect everything
to everything feed forward.
Great.
OK, I think that's a very
interesting question.
Yeah, so I'm glad you asked it.
OK, so we've talked
about self attention now,
the equations are going
to self attention.
But can we just use this
as a building block?
I mean, you take
all of your LSTMs,
throw them out, use the self
attention that we've just
defined instead, why not?
Well, here's a couple
of reasons why.
So look at self attention
as a building block.
So we have some words in
a sentence, The chef who,
some stuff, long sentence,
food is the last word
of the sentence, OK.
And they have an embedding
and from that, you
get your key, query, and value.
We've said so far,
right, there's
the same vector actually, but
key, query, value, key, query,
value, key, query, value.
And we might stack
them like LSTM layers.
So you have key, query
value perform self attention
on the key's queries and values.
As we said, self
attention is a function
on keys, queries and values.
So perform self attention
now that you have these, get
new keys, queries,
values, and then
perform self attention again.
Look, this a lot
like stacking LSTMs.
But it actually has a
few issues as it stands.
So we're going to need
to go on a journey
to determine what's missing
from our self attention.
And the first thing
is that self attention
is an operation on sets.
OK, so for the equations
that we had before,
the self attention
equation never
referred to the
indices of k, q or v,
except to sort of
say which pairs were
interacting with each other.
It doesn't know what the
order of your sentences.
When it's computing though,
the weights it has no idea.
And so if I were to input this
sentence, The chef who food,
it would be the same as if I
just swapped though with chef
and then swapped who with the,
and it just would have no idea.
So already this is
not going to work
because the order in which words
appear in sentences matters.
So here's the first problem
that we need to work with.
So I'm going to have
a list of barriers,
this is just the first, we have
a whole journey ahead of us.
And then we're going to
have a list of solutions.
So we need to represent
the sequence order somehow.
We can't just lose that
information entirely
because we wouldn't know what
order the words showed up in.
So somehow if we're not going
to change the self attention
equations themselves, we need
to encode the order in the keys,
queries and values, and let the
network sort of figure it out
on its own.
So think about this, we
have T sequence indices
and we're going to bound
t to some finite constant,
so T is never going to be
bigger than something for us,
and we call it T. And now we're
going to represent the sequence
index as a vector.
So pi is going to be the
vector representing index i,
and it's going to be n
dimensionality d just
like our keys,
queries and values.
And so we're going to have
one of these for 1 to T.
So don't worry yet
about what the pi
or like how they're constructed,
we'll get right into that.
But think about this, it's easy
to incorporate this information
into our attention
building blocks.
At the first layer if
you let tilde v, tilde k,
tilde q be our old values, keys
and queries, we can just add.
We could do other stuff too,
but in practice we just add.
So vi is equal to v tilde i,
our orderless value vector,
plus pi.
So this might be
your embedding vector
and then you add the index
that it's at to its vector.
And you might only do
this at the first layer
of the network for example.
So you do the same thing
for the query and the key.
So this is something you
could do, in practice which
is only slightly different.
But this is
something that now it
knows the order of the
sequence because if these
pis you set properly
somehow, then
now the network is able to
figure out what to do with it.
So what's one way of
actually making this happen?
One way of making this happen
is through the concatenation
of sinusoids.
And this was an interesting
take when the first transformers
paper came out, they used
they use this method.
So let's dig into it.
So you have varying wavelengths,
so sinusoidal functions
in each of your dimensions.
So in the first
dimension you have
this sine function
with a given period,
and then this cosine
function with a given period,
and then sort dot,
dot, dot, you sort of
change the periods until you
get to much different periods.
And what does it look like?
It looks like that.
So imagine here in
the vertical axis,
we've got the dimensionality
of the network, right?
So this is d and then
this is sequence length.
And by just
specifying in each row
is sort of one of these signs
with different frequencies.
And you can see how this
is encoding position,
these things have different
values at different indices.
And that's pretty
cool, I don't really
know how they thought
of it immediately.
But one cool thing about it is
this periodicity notion, right?
The fact that the sinusoids
have periods that might be less
than the sequence
length, indicates
that maybe the absolute
position of a word
isn't so important, right,
because if the period is less
than the sequence length,
you lose information maybe
about where you are.
Of course, you have the
concatenation of many of them.
So that's a pro.
Maybe you can extrapolate
to longer sequences
because again you sort of have
this repetition of values,
right, because the periods
will when they complete,
you'll see that value again.
The cons are that
it's not learnable.
I mean, this is cool
but you can't, there's
no learnable parameters
in any of this.
And also the extrapolation
doesn't really work.
So this is an interesting
and definitely still done,
but what's done more frequently
now is, what do we do?
We learn to position
representations from scratch.
So we're going to learn
them from scratch.
So let all the pi just
be learnable parameters.
So what we're going to do is
we can have a matrix p, that's
going to be in dimensionality
d, dimensionality over network
again by the sequence length.
So this is just a big matrix,
right, of the size here,
of this size effectively,
d by sequence length.
But every single
value in that matrix
is just a learnable parameter.
Pros, flexibility,
now you get to learn
what positions is sort of
supposed to mean according
to your data end to end.
So that's cool.
Cons, you definitely can't
extrapolate the indices
outside 1 to T,
great, because you
set the size of this parameter
matrix at the beginning
and you learned them all.
Now if you want to
go beyond position T,
you have no way to
represent it effectively.
But most systems use
this, this is super useful
and sometimes people try
more flexible representations
of position because again,
the absolute index of a word
is not sort of its natural
representation of its position
in the sentence, and
so people have looked
at kind of the relative
position between words
as well as position
representations that
depend on syntax,
but we're not going
to be able to go too
far into those today.
OK, so that was
problem one, right?
No matter what we did, if we
didn't have representation
of position, there was no way
we could use self attention
as our new building block.
And we've solved it with
position representations
that we just sort of
add to the inputs.
Next, we're going to see
this problem that you
don't have nonlinearities.
We've been saying
nonlinearities,
abstract features, they're
great deep learning,
end to end learning of
representations is awesome.
But right now, we're just
doing weighted averages.
And so what is our
solution going to be?
I mean, it's not going
to be all that complex.
So all we're doing right
now, is re-averaging vectors.
So you've got sort of
the self attention here
and if you just
stacked another one,
you just keep sort of averaging
projections of vectors.
But what if we just add
a feed forward network
for every individual word?
So within this layer,
each of these feed
forward neural networks
shares parameters,
but it gets in just the output
of self attention for this word
as we defined it, processes
it, and admits something else.
And so you have output
i from self attention,
which we saw slides ago.
Apply a feed forward layer,
where you take the output,
multiply it by a matrix,
non-linearity of the matrix.
And the intuition here you can
think of at least, is well,
you know, something like
the feed forward network
processes the result of the
attention for each thing.
But more fundamentally,
you needed some kind
of non-linearity there
and a feed forward network
will do a good job, OK?
So that that's another
problem solved, easy fix.
Add a feed forward network,
get your non-linearity, now
your self attention output,
you can sort of process it,
have that sort of
depth increasing
as the layers of the network
increase, which we know
is useful.
Another problem.
OK, so bear with me on this one.
We don't want to look
at the future when we're
doing language modeling, right?
So language modeling,
you're trying
to predict words in the future.
And with a recurrent model,
it's very natural, right,
like you just don't
unroll it farther.
Once you unrolled your
LSTM to a given word,
there's sort of no way to
have given it to the next word
as well.
But in self attention,
we'll see that this
is a little bit trickier.
So you can't cheat
and look at the stuff
we're trying to be
predicting because then we
would train networks that
were totally useless.
So what are we going to do?
We're going to mask,
masking is a word
that's going to keep coming up.
We're going to mask the
future in self attention.
So in particular,
this is important
when we have decoders, right?
One of the reasons why we
could use bidirectional LSTMs
in our encoders was that, we
could see the whole source
sentence in neural
machine translation.
But when we're predicting
the output sentence,
right, we can't see
the future if we're
going to train the model to
do the actual prediction.
So to use self
attention in a decoder,
you would mask the future.
One thing that you could do, is
you could just every time you
compute attention, you change
the set of keys and values
that should be.
Keys and values, to
only include past words.
So you're sort of dynamically
changing the stuff
that you're attending over.
But that doesn't let us
do stuff with tensors
as well as parallelizability
as we will see.
So we don't want to do that.
Instead, we're going to
mask out the future words
through the attention
weights themselves.
So in math, don't worry we'll
get to the sort of diagram.
But in math, we have
these attention scores,
and they were equal to
just this dot product
before, for all pairs, right?
But now only if
the key is strictly
less than the key
index, is strictly less
than, this should be i.
If only if the key
index is strictly
less than the query index, so
this would be j less than i,
should we let the
network look at the word
and it should be negative
infinity otherwise,
so we don't let you
look at the output.
So let's go to the picture.
For encoding the words
that we'll see here,
so maybe we'll
have a start token.
You want to decide this is
your whole sentence now.
You want to decide which
words in the sentence
you're allowed to look at
when making your predictions.
So I want to predict
the first word.
And in order to
protect The, I'm not
allowed to look at the word The.
I'm also not allowed to look
at any of the future words.
I am allowed to look
at the word Start.
So this kind of block
is not shaded here.
In order to predict
the word Chef,
I can look at Start and The.
Start, The but not chef
naturally, or the word
that comes after it.
And likewise for
the other words.
So you can see this sort
of matrix here, right?
So we just want to make sure
that our attention weights are
0 everywhere here.
And so in the
affinity's calculation,
we add negative infinity to all
of these, in this big matrix.
And that guarantees that we
can't look to the future.
OK, so now we can do big
matrix multiplications
to compute our attention
as we will see,
and we sort of don't worry
about looking at the future
because we've added these
negative infinities.
And that's the last problem
with self attention,
sort of that comes
up fundamentally
as like, what do we need
for this building block?
You didn't have an
inherent notion of order,
now you have a good
notion of order
or at least something
of a notion of order.
You didn't have nonlinearities,
add feed forward networks,
and then you didn't want
to look at the future,
you add the masks
for the decoders.
So self attention is the basis
of any self attention based
building block, hello, position
representations are useful,
nonlinearities are good.
You don't have to use a
feed forward network, right,
like you could have just
done other stuff I guess,
but in practice actually
it's really easy
to parallelize these feed
forward networks as well.
So we end up doing that.
And then the masking, Yeah,
you don't want information
to leak from the future to
the past in your decoder.
So let me be clear, we haven't
talked about the transformer
yet.
But this is all you would need
if you were thinking like gosh,
what do I need in order to
build my self attention building
block?
We'll see that there are a lot
more details in the transformer
that we're going to spend
the rest of the lecture going
through.
But I want you to
sort of at least
as you're thinking about
what's going to come next
after the transformer and how
you're going to invent it,
think about the
fact that these are
the things that were necessary.
And then the other things end
up being very, very important
it turns out.
But there's a lot
of design space here
that hasn't been explored yet.
OK, so let's talk about
the transformer model.
And I'm going to pause there
and this is a good question,
I can take it now.
OK, so transformers,
let's get to it.
Let's look at the
transformer, encoder,
decoder blocks at
a high level first.
This should look a lot
like the encoder, decoders
that we saw with the recurrent
neural network, machine
translation systems that we saw.
OK, so we have our
word embeddings,
we're going to add in our
position representations,
we saw that, and that's
from our input sequence.
We'll have a sequence of
encoder blocks, each of them
is called a transformer encoder.
And then we have our output
sequence, word embeddings,
position representation again,
we have a transformer decoder.
The last layer of
encoders is going
to be used in each layer
of the transformer decoder,
and then we get some
outputs, some predictions.
OK, so this looks
pretty much the same
at a very high level,
maybe minus the fact
that now we need to do the
position representation
edition at the very beginning.
So now let's look at
these blocks themselves.
So the encoder and
decoder blocks.
What's left that we
haven't covered, right?
Because we could
just put the building
blocks that we just came up
with in the first part of class
in these things, right?
Encoders, we need
our self attention,
our feed forward networks,
we have our position
representations, we get the
masking for the decoders,
right, we can just
slot these in.
But it turns out they wouldn't
work all that well compared
to transformers.
So what's left?
So the first thing is key,
query, value attention.
This is a specific way
of getting the k, q and v
vectors from the single
word embedding, right?
So instead of having k, q and
v equal to x like the output
from the last layer, we're
going to do something
a little bit more.
Next is multi-headed attention.
We're going to attend
to multiple places
in a single layer, and
we'll see that gets us
sort kind of interesting
properties in the homework
later on, but we'll talk a
little bit about it today.
And then there's
a bunch of things
that just help with training.
These seemed like they were
very hard to train at first,
a lot of these tricks
are very useful.
So we'll talk about
residual connections,
layer normalization and
scaling the dot product.
Everything in bullet
point three here,
tricks to help
with training don't
improve what the
model is able to do,
but they're crucial in that they
improve the training process.
So modeling improvements
of both kinds
are really, really important.
So it's good that we're
using self attention which
is this cool thing that
had these properties.
But if we couldn't train
it, it wouldn't be useful.
OK, so here's how the
transformer builds the key,
query, and value vectors.
We have x1 to xt,
the input vectors
to our transformer layer.
OK, and we're gonna go ahead
and put the transformer
encoder here.
So we have one of these
vectors per word, you can say.
And again, each
xi is going to be
a vector in dimensionality d.
And here's how we compute
the keys, queries and values.
We're going to let each key
ki, which we saw before,
be equal to some matrix k times
xi where k is d by d, right?
So this is a transformation
from dimensionality d
to dimensionality d.
We're going to call
this the key matrix k,
and we're going to do the
same thing for the queries.
OK, so we're going to take the
xi, multiply it by a matrix,
get the query vector, and we'll
do the same thing for v. OK,
so you can just
plug this in, right?
Now instead of saying that
all the k, q and the v
are all the same
as x, they all are
slightly different because you
apply a linear transformation.
What does this do?
Well, you can think about it
as like well, the matrices k, q
and v can be very different
from each other, right?
And so they sort of
emphasize or allow
different aspects
of the x vectors
is to be used in each of
the three roles, right?
So we wrote out the
self attention equations
with the three roles to indicate
the different things are
being done with each of them.
So maybe k and q are helping
you figure out where to look,
and so they should
be a certain way,
they should look at
different parts of x.
And then v the
value, maybe you want
to pass along a
different information
than the thing
that actually helps
you access that information.
So this is important.
How do we do this?
In practice, we compute it
with really big tensors.
So we had our X
vectors, which is
what we've been talking
about sort of word by word,
is where you had the
sequence xi, x1 to xt.
Now we're going
to represent them
all in a matrix X, which
is in our sequence length
bidimensionality.
So sequence length
by d, capital T by d.
And now if we have the
matrix for each of our key,
query, and value, right,
we're going to apply,
like we're going to
look at these things
XK, XQ and XV, which are all
of the same dimensionality as x
because of the d by
d transformations.
So how do we compute
self attention?
We have our output tensor,
which is the same dimensionality
as the input x.
This is going to be
equal to soft max,
there's a soft-max of this
matrix multiplication,
which we'll get into,
times the value vector.
So the matrix multiplication
here is computing affinities
between keys and
queries we'll see,
and then here's our averaging.
What does that look
like pictorially?
So you take the key,
query dot products.
So this term here,
XQ, XK transpose,
is giving you all
dot products, all
T by T pairs of
attention scores.
So our e, i, j are in this
matrix right here, it's T by T
and this is just a big
matrix multiplication.
So you do the matrix
multiplication XQ and then XK
and then you get all of the
dot products by through this.
OK, so now you have this
big T by T set of scores,
that's what we wanted.
And now, you can soft-max
that directly as a matrix
and then do a matrix
multiplication here with XV
in order to give
your output vector.
So this is actually doing
the weighted average
that we saw at the
beginning of the class.
And this, there's
no for loops here,
it's really beautifully
I would say vectorized
and it gives us our output
which again, remember,
same dimensionality, T by d.
OK, so all periods
of attention scores
then compute the averages
by applying the softmax
of the scores to the XV matrix.
So that's it for key,
query, value attention,
that's how we implement
it with tensors.
Next we'll look at the
next thing that ends up
being quite important
for training transformers
in practice, which is
multi-headed attention.
So transformer encoder,
So the question
is, what if we want
to look at multiple places
in the sentence at once?
It's possible to do that
with normal self attention.
But think about this,
where do you end up
looking in self attention?
You end up looking where the dot
products of Xi, your Q matrix
transpose your K
matrix, XJ is high.
So those are the Xij
pairs, I'm sorry,
those are the ij pairs that end
up interacting with each other.
But maybe for some
query, for some word
that you want to focus
on different other words
in the sentence for
different reasons.
The way that you
can encode this,
is by having multiple query,
key and value matrices,
which all encode different
things about the Xi,
they all learn different
transformations.
So instead of a single Q,
a single K and a single V,
what we get are a Q sub
L, K sub L, V sub L,
all of a different n
dimensionality now.
So by their dimensionality
d by d over h,
where h is the number of heads.
So they're going to still
apply to the X matrix,
but they're going to
transform it to a smaller
dimensionality, d by h.
And then each attention head
is going to perform attention
independently, it's
like you just did it
a whole bunch of times, right?
And so output l is equal to
softmax of, here's your QK
but now it's in
l form, times XVl
and now you have sort of
these indexed outputs.
And in order to sort of have
the output dimensionality
be equal to the input
dimensionality and sort of mix
things around, combine
all the information
from the different heads,
you concatenate the heads.
So that's output 1 through
output h, stack them together.
Now, the dimensionality
of this, is
equal to the
dimensionality of X again.
And then we use a
learned matrix Y in order
to sort of do the mixing
Y is d by d, and that's
the output of multi-headed
attention, multi-headed self
attention.
And so each head gets to
look at different things,
right, because they
can all sort of,
the linear
transformations you can
stay focused on different
parts of the X vectors,
and the value vectors also
get to be different as well.
So pictorially, this
is what we had before,
single headed attention.
You had X multiplied by
Q in order to get XQ.
And what's interesting
and you can see this,
you can see this from
this diagram I think,
is that multi-headed
attention doesn't necessarily
have to be more work, right?
We saw that the Q,
K and V matrices
in multi-head attention, have
a lower output dimensionality.
So here's two of
them right here,
here's Q1 and Q2,
the same size as Q,
and then you hit
outputs XQ1 and XQ2.
And so you're effectively doing
the same amount of computation
as before, but now
you're sort of doing,
you have different
attention distributions
for each of the different
heads, so this is pretty cool.
OK, so those are the main
modeling differences, right?
We did key, query
value attention,
that's how we got the key,
queries and values from the X
vectors, and we saw how to
implement that in the matrices
that we're looking at.
And then we looked at the
multi-headed attention,
which allows us to look
in different places
in the sequence in order to have
more flexibility within a given
layer.
Now we're going to talk
about our training tricks.
These are really important,
it turns out and so,
Yeah, thinking
about them I think
is something that we don't
do enough in the field
and so let's really
walk through them.
So residual connections,
residual connections
have been around,
residual connections,
you can think of them as
helping the model train better
for a number of reasons.
Let's look at what
they're doing first.
Our residual connection
looks like this.
So you have a normal
layer X in some layer i,
i is representing sort of the
layer in depth in the network.
So Xi is equal to some
layer of Xi minus 1.
So you had, I don't know
what this layer is doing
necessarily, but this layer is a
function of the previous layer,
OK.
And so you've got this.
So again, I want
to abstract over
what the layer is doing but
you just pass it through.
A residual connection is
doing something very simple.
It's saying, OK,
I'm going to take
the function I was computing
at my previous layer before
and then I'm going to add
it to the previous layer.
So now, Xi is not equal
to a layer of Xi minus 1,
it's equal to Xi minus 1
plus layer of x minus 1.
This is it, these are
residual connections.
And the intuition,
right, is that like,
before you started
learning anything sort of,
you have this notion that
you should be learning only
how layer i should be
different from layer i minus 1,
instead of learning from scratch
what it should look like.
So this value here
layer of Xi minus 1,
should be something
in some sense
and you have to learn
how it's different
from the previous layer.
This is a sort of a
nice inductive bias.
So here you can
kind of represent it
as you have this layer Xi
minus 1 goes through the layer,
it also goes around
and just gets added in.
Now think about the
gradients, right?
We talked about vanishing
gradients, they're a problem.
The gradient of this
connection here is beautiful,
right, even if
everything's saturating,
all of your sigmoids
are saturating
or your ReLUs are all negative,
so the gradients are all 0.
But you get
gradients propagating
back through the rest
of the network anyway
through this connection here.
That's pretty cool.
Turns out to be
massively useful.
And just to take a
quick visualization,
this plot just never ceases
to look really interesting.
Here is sort of a visualization
of a lost landscape.
So each sort of
point in the 2D plane
is like it's a sort of a
setting of a parameters
of your network, and
then sort of the z-axis
is the loss of the
network that it's
being optimized for, right?
And here's a network
with no residuals,
and you are stochastic
gradient descent
and you sort of have
to find a local minimum
and it's really hard to
find the nice local minimum.
And then with the residual
network, it's much smoother.
So you can imagine how
stochastic gradient descent
is sort of walking down
here to this nice, very
low local minimum.
This is a paper that
was trying to explain
why residual connections
are so useful.
So this might be an intuition
that might be useful for you.
So this is the so-called
loss landscape.
So those are
residual connections.
And they seem simple but
a lot of simple ideas
end up being super
useful in deep learning.
So in layer
normalization, we're doing
something sort of
similar, we're trying
to help the network
train better but we're
doing it via a pretty
different intuition.
So layer normalization
is thought
to say at different
times in my network
when I'm training it
doing the forward pass,
there's a lot of
variation in what
the forward pass looks like.
And a lot of it is uninformative
and that can harm training.
But if we normalize
within a layer
to unit, mean and
standard deviation,
then it sort of cuts
down on all this sort
of uninformative variation.
And the informative
variation, sort
of how the units were different
from each other is maintained.
So it's also thought
that the successive layer
norm, and there's been a lot
of successive layer norm,
has been to actually
to helping normalize
the gradients of each
layer, this is recent work.
So let's talk about
how it's implemented.
So we're going to go back to X
and I'm not going to index it
here, so it's just X is some
vector, some word vector
in our transformer.
We're going to compute
an estimate of the mean,
OK, just by summing
the hidden units.
We're going to
compute an estimate
of the standard
deviation similarly.
So like you've taken a single
Rd vector, you've just sum them,
you compute the mean,
you estimate the mean,
you estimate the
standard deviation, OK.
Now you also potentially and
this is optional, learn element
wise gain and bias parameters to
try to sort of re-scale things,
if certain hidden
units sort of should
have larger value in general or
should be multiplicative larger
in general.
So these are vectors in Rd,
just like X was a vector in Rd.
And then here's what layer
normalization computes,
you have your output,
which is going to be an Rd,
just like your input, OK.
And you take your vector
X, you subtract the mean
from all of them, you divide
by standard deviation,
should have.
Yeah, sorry, this
shouldn't be square root.
And then you add
an epsilon that's
small, in order if the standard
deviation becomes very small,
you don't want the denominator
to become too, too, too small
because then you
get huge numbers
and then your network goes
to NaN and doesn't train.
OK, so you have some
sort of tolerance there.
And then so you normalize there,
and then our element-wise gain
in bias.
Now remember this
fraction X is a vector,
everything is being done sort
of element-wise here, right?
So this is Rd, and then
you have this element-wise
multiplication, this Hadamard
product with your gain,
then you add the bias.
Whether the gain and bias
are necessary is unclear.
This paper here suggests
that they're not helpful,
but they're frequently used.
So it's sort of an engineering
question at this point
and a science question
whether we can figure out why
in general.
But yes, that's
layer normalization
and it ends up being very
important in transformers,
you remove it and they
really don't train very well.
OK, so that's our second trick.
The third trick is
probably the simplest one
but it's useful to know.
And it's just, you can call it
scaled dot product attention
because we're going to scale
the dot products like so.
OK, so what we're
going to do, is
we're going to
have this intuition
that our dimensionality d in
really big neural networks,
is going to become very large.
So maybe our hidden
layer in our transformer
is 1,000 or 2000 or 3,000
anyway, it gets big.
And when the dimensionality
becomes large,
the dot products between
vectors tend to become large.
So for example, if you take
the dot product between two
random vectors in Rd,
it grows quite quickly,
their dot products
grow quite quickly.
Now are the vectors
random in transformers,
well, they're not
uniform random but you
can imagine there's
sort a lot of variation
and in general as the
dimensionality is growing,
all these dot products
are getting pretty big.
And this can become a problem
for the following reason,
right?
We're taking all these dot
products directly and putting
them into the softmax.
So there's this variation in the
dot products and some of them
are very large, then the
softmax can become very peaky,
putting most of most
of its probability mass
on a small number
of things, which
makes the gradient small
for everything else
effectively, right?
Because the softmax
is trying to be well,
it's a soft argmax, right,
so it's sort of saying,
which one of these is
like the max or these sort
of relative to how close they
are to the max of the function.
And so if some of them are very,
very large, you sort of just
zero out the connections
to everything
that's not being
attended to, that
has low probability
distribution and then
they don't get gradients.
And so here's the self attention
operation we've seen, OK.
I've taken, this is the
multi-headed variant here,
right, because we've got
the other indices on output,
I've got the indices on Q, K
and V. And all I'm going to do
is I'm going to say,
well, the things that I'm
about to dot
together are vectors
of dimensionality
d over h, because
of the multi-headed
attention again.
And in order to stop them
from growing, the dot
products from growing
too large, I'm
just going to divide
all of my scores.
So just remember up here, XQ,
K top, X top is a T by T matrix
of scores, you're going to
divide them all by d over h.
And as d grows, d
over h grows, right,
and so your dot
products don't grow,
and this ends up
being helpful as well.
OK.
Any questions?
Yeah.
John, could you--
interesting question--
when you're doing the
decoder attention,
do you only do the
masking in the first layer
or do you do the masking
also in the middle layer,
in the decoder?
Yeah, nice, nice.
So if we were to only do
masking in the first layer,
we would get information
leakage in the later layers.
So if we look at this, if we
were to look at this diagram
again, right, so here's the
first layer of the decoder,
and we said that
there's masking, right,
and you're able to look at
any of the encoder states
and you're only able to
look at the previous words
in the decoder.
In the second layer
if I'm suddenly
allowed to look at all
of the future words now,
hey, even though I didn't
in the first layer,
it's just as good that I
can in the second layer.
And so I can just learn
to look right at what
my word is supposed to be.
So every single
layer of the decoder
has to have that masking
or it's sort of moot,
like it says if you didn't
mask it at all effectively.
Thanks.
OK, so scaled dot product
in the bag, we've got it.
So let's look back at
our full transformer
encoder, decoder framework.
We've looked at
the encoder blocks
themselves, so let's sort
of expand one of these,
zoom and enhance.
And we've got our word
embeddings position
representations,
and first we put it
through multi-headed attention.
So we've seen that.
We put it through a residual
layer and layer norm,
right, so you have
the word embedding
and the position
representations going
through the residual
connection here, and also going
through multi-headed attention,
add them, layer norm.
Next, you put the result of that
through a feed forward network.
There should be an arrow
between the feed forward
and the next residual here.
But the output of this
residual and layer norm,
is added into that
residual and layer norm
along with the output
of the feed forward.
And then the output of this
residual and layer norm,
is the output of the
transformer encoder block.
So when we had each of
these encoders here,
internally, each one
of them was just this,
and we've seen all these
building blocks before.
And this is multi-headed
scaled dot product attention,
I omit the scaled word.
Yeah, so this is
the block, and you
notice interestingly how
you're doing residual and layer
norm after the initial
multi-headed attention
as well as after
the feed forward.
OK, so each one of these is
just identical, right, different
parameters for the different
layers but the same things
that we've seen.
Now let's look at the
transformer, decoder block.
So this is actually
more complex.
In particular, you've got
that masked multi-headed self
attention.
And now remember, this is
not just for the first one,
this is for all of the
transformer blocks.
So we've got masked
multi-headed self attention,
where we can't
look at the future
because we've added
negative infinity
to the negative infinity
to the affinity scores.
Residual and layer norm,
like we did for the encoder.
Now we've got multi
head cross attention.
So this connection to
the transformer encoder,
this is actually a lot like
what we saw in attention so far,
right?
We're attending from the
decoder to the encoder.
So we actually in each
transformer decoder block,
we've got two different
attention functions going on.
So we do the cross
attention, we add the result
of the residual and layer
norm to the next residual
in layer norm along with that of
the multi head cross attention,
okay?
And only after both of those
applications of attention,
next we do the feed forward
and residual and layer norm,
where the residual is
coming, so the Xi minus 1
is the residual layer norm
here, goes into this one
along with the feed forward.
And so you can think of
the residual layer norm
as coming after each of the
interesting things we're
doing, right?
We're doing one
interesting thing here,
multi-headed masked self
attention, cross attention
after each one, do
residual and layer normal,
help the gradients pass,
et cetera, et cetera.
And then the output of this
residual and layer norm
is the output of the
transformer decoder.
OK, and so the only thing
so far that we really
haven't seen in this lecture, is
the multi-head cross attention.
And I want to go over it,
it is the same equations
as the multi-headed
self attention,
but the inputs are coming
from different places.
And so I want to be
precise about it.
Let's take a look.
Cross attention details.
So, right, self attention
recall is that when
we're taking the keys,
the queries and the values
of attention from
the same information
source like the same
sentence for example,
and we saw last week, right,
attention from the decoder
to the encoder.
So this is going
to look similar.
We'll see some
different notation.
So we're going to have
h1 to ht, the output
vectors from the transformer
encoder which are all Xi in rd.
Remember, this is the last
transformer encoder here,
right, you never attend to
the middle encoder blocks,
it's the output of the
last encoder block.
So this is the output vectors
from the last transformer
encoder block and
now we have Z1 to Zt,
the input vectors from
the transformer decoder.
So here maybe that is
the input is the word
embeddings plus their
position representations
or, right, it's
actually the output
of the previous
transformer decoder,
are going to be the
inputs for the next one.
So yeah, we've got
a Z1 to Zt and we're
letting them be the same
sequence length again
T and T, just for simplicity.
These are also vectors Zi
and Rd and then the keys
and the, sorry, the
keys and the values
are all drawn from
the encoder, right?
So when we're talking about
attention and allowing us
to sort of access
a memory, right?
The memory is sort of what the
value vectors are encoding,
and the way that the values are
sort of indexed or able to be
accessed is through
the keys, and then
the value and then
the queries are
what you're using to try to
look for something, right?
So we're looking into
the encoder as a memory
and we're using keys from
the decoder to figure out
where to look for each one.
So pictorially
again, we can look
at how cross attention is
computed and matrices like we
did for self attention.
So we've got the same thing
here before, we had X,
now we have h, these
are the encoder vectors,
these is going to be RT by d.
Likewise, we have Z, notice
we had two of these before.
Before we just had
X, right, we had
X because X was going to be
for the keys, the queries
and the values.
Now we have h and Z,
both are in RT by d.
And the output is
going to be, well, you
take your Z for the
queries, right, Z
is being multiplied
by the queries.
You take your h for the
keys and your h for the V's.
So you are trying to take the
query, key dot products, all T
squared of them in one
matrix multiplication.
So the purple is saying, this
is coming from the decoder,
the brown is saying it's
coming from the encoder.
Now you've got
your dot products,
soft-max them as you did before
and now your values are also
coming from the encoder.
So again, same operation,
different sources
for the inputs.
And now you've got your
output, which again is just
an average of the value
vectors from the encoder hv,
the average is determined
by your weights.
OK, so results
with transformers,
results with transformers.
First off was
machine translation.
So we built our entire encoder,
decoder transformer block
and you know, how does it work?
It works really well.
So these are a bunch of
machine translation systems
that were out when the original
Attention Is All You Need
transformers paper came out.
And first, you saw that
transformers were getting
really good BLEU scores.
So this is on the Workshop
on Machine Translation
2014, English, German, and
English French test sets,
you get higher BLEU
scores, which means
better translations, right?
Notice how our
BLEU scores on this
are higher than
for assignment 4,
lots more training
data here for example.
But then also, not only do
you get better BLEU scores,
you also had more
efficient training, right?
And we had a lot of tricks
that went into getting training
to work better, right?
So you have more
efficient training here.
OK.
So, that's a nice result. That
was in the original paper.
Past that, there are a number
of interesting results,
summarization is one of them.
So, here's the result
on summarization.
These are part of a larger
summarization system,
but you have--
I liked this table because
you have sort of seq2seq
with attention,
which we saw before.
And it got perplexity.
Lower is better with perplexity.
Higher is better with ROUGE
on this WikiSum dataset.
And then sort of a bunch of
transformer models they tried.
And at a certain point,
it becomes transformers
all the way down, and
the old standard of RNN
sort of falls out of practice.
And actually, before too
long, right, transformers
became dominant for an
entirely different reason,
which was related more to
their parallelizablity.
Because they'll allow you to
pretrain on just a ton of data,
very quickly.
And this has made them
the de facto standard.
So there's-- A lot of results,
recently with Transformers,
include pretraining.
And I'm sort of
intentionally excluding them
from this lecture so that
you come to the next lecture
and learn about pretraining.
But there's a popular
aggregate benchmark.
This took a bunch of
very difficult tasks
and said, do well on
all of them if you
want to score highly
on our leaderboard.
And the names of
these models you
can look up if
you're interested.
But all of them are transformer
based after a certain point.
So the benchmark is called GLUE.
It has a successor
called SuperGLUE.
Everything is just transformers
after a certain time
period, partly because of
their pretraining ability.
OK.
Great.
So, we'll discuss
pretraining more on Thursday.
And so our transformer is it.
The way that we
described the Attention
Is All You Need paper.
So, the transformer
encoder decoder we saw
was from that paper.
And at some point, we want
to build new systems, what
are some drawbacks?
And we've already started--
People have already started to
build variants of transformers,
which we'll go into today.
And it definitely has issues
that we can try to work on.
So I can also take a question
if anyone wants to ask one.
I mean, is that the bit
that something there
were several questions on
was the scale dot product.
And the questions
included y square root
of d divided by h, as opposed
to just d divided by h,
or any other function
of d divided by h.
And another one was that,
why do you need that
at all, given that later on
you're going to use layer norm?
The second question
is really interesting
and not one that I
had thought of before.
Well, right, so even if
the individual components
are small--
So let's start with
the second question.
Why does this matter even if
you're going to use layer norm?
If layer norm is
averaging everything out,
say, making the unit
standard deviation and mean,
then actually, right,
nothing is going
to get too small in
those vectors either.
So when you have a
very, very large vector,
all with things that
aren't too small, yeah,
you're still going to have
the norm of the dot products
increase.
I think.
And I think it's
a good question.
I hadn't thought
about it too much.
That's my off the cuff answer.
But it's worth
thinking about more.
I think the answer is
that the effect you
get of kind of losing
dynamic range as things
get longer, that that's
going to happen anyway.
And the layer norm
can't fix that.
It's sort of coming
along too late.
And, therefore, you gain
by doing this scaling.
I think so.
But I think it's worth--
I think it's worth
thinking about more.
why square root?
Well, let's see.
The norms of the
dot product grows
with O of D. And so
when you square root 1--
No.
I guess it scales with O of
root D. I can't remember.
There's a little
note in the Attention
Is All You Need paper
about why it's root D.
But I actually can't take it
off the top of my head here.
But it is in that paper.
OK.
Anything else before we go on?
Great.
All right.
So, what would we like to fix?
The thing that shows
up most frequently
as a pain point in
Transformers is actually
the quadratic compute in
the self-attention itself.
So we're having all
pairs of interactions.
We had that t by t
matrix that was computed
by taking these dot products
between all pairs of word
vectors.
And so, even though we argued
at the beginning of the class
that we don't have this
sort of temporal dependence
in the computation graph that
stops us from parallelizing
things, we still need to
do all that computation,
and that grows quadratically.
For recurrent models, right,
it only grew linearly.
Every time you
applied the RNN cell,
you did sort of more work, but
you're not adding quadratically
to the amount of
work you have to do
as you get to longer sequences.
Separately, position
representations.
I mean, the absolute
position of a word,
it's just maybe not the
best way to represent
the structure of a sentence.
And so there have been these
two, among other advancements
that I won't be able
to get into today,
but you can take a look at
these papers and the papers that
cite them.
There are other ways
to represent position.
People are working on it.
But I want to focus more
today on the problem
of the quadratic compute.
So, how do we reason about this,
why is this a problem, right?
So it's highly
parallelizable, but we still
have to do these operations.
We have T squared,
that's a sequence length,
and then d is the
dimensionality.
And so in computing
this matrix, we
have O of T squared d
computations that our GPU needs
to chunk through.
If we think of d as around
1,000, or 2,000, or 3,000.
If we had sort of single,
shortish sentences,
then maybe T is like 30-ish,
and then T squared is 900.
So it's like, yeah, it's
actually not that big a deal.
And in practice,
for a lot of models
we'll set an actual
bound like 512.
So it's like, if your document
is longer than 512 words,
you're out of luck, you're
truncated or something.
But what if we want to
work on documents that
are 10,000 words or greater?
10,000 squared is not feasible.
So we have to somehow
remove the dependence
on T squared if we're
going to work with these.
There have been a
couple of ways that have
been taught how to do this.
This is all very,
very recent work
and it's only a smattering of
the efforts that have come up.
So the question is,
can we build models
like transformers that get
away without the O of T squared
all-pairs interactions cost?
One example is the Linformer.
And the idea here is that
you're going to actually map
the sequence length dimension
to a lower dimensional
space for values and keys.
So you had values,
keys, and queries,
and you had your
normal linear layers,
now you're going to project
to a much lower dimension
then the sequence length.
And in doing so, right, you're
sort of getting rid of that T
by mapping it to
something smaller.
You're saying just combine
all the information
from all these time steps
into something that's
lower dimensional.
And so, in this
plot from the paper,
as the sequence length goes from
512 with a batch size of 128
to the sequence length being
65,000 with a batch size of 1,
you get the transformer
inference time
growing very large.
And then the Linformer
with various bottleneck
dimensionalities, k
is 128, 256, they're
doing much, much better.
A separate option has
been to kind of take
a totally different
take on can we
get away without these
all-pairs interactions,
which is the following.
Do we need to even
try to compute
all pairs of
interactions if we can
do sort of a bunch
of other stuff
that's going to be more
efficient to compute?
So, like looking
at local windows.
We know that's useful, but
not sufficient in some sense.
Looking at everything.
So, if you were to just take
an average of vectors, just all
the averaging of
vectors, you don't
need to compute
interactions for that.
And if you look sort
of at random pairs,
you don't need to take
all that much time
to compute that as well.
And so, what this paper did
is they did all of them.
So you have random attention,
you have a word window
attention where you're looking
at your local neighbors,
and you have sort
of global attention
where you're sort of attending
without interacting with stuff,
attending broadly over
the whole sequence.
You do a whole
bunch of it, right,
and you end up being
able to approximate a lot
of good things.
These are not
necessarily the answer.
The normal transformer variant
is by far the most popular,
currently.
But it's a fascinating
question to look into.
So now, as the time
more or less expires,
I'll say we're working on
pretraining on Thursday.
Good luck on assignment 4.
And remember to work on
your project proposal.
And I think we have time
for a final question
if anyone wants to.
I guess, are you
aware of any use case
where an RNN might
outperform a transformer?
That's a good question.
I mean, I believe still places
in reinforcement learning.
I mean, places where
the recurrent inductive
bias is clearly well
specified or useful.
There was a conversation--
I don't know of places in
NLP where people are still
broadly using RNNs.
It was thought for a while that
Transformers took a lot more
data to train than RNNs.
And so you sort of should use
RNNs on smaller data problems.
But with pretraining, I'm not
sure that that's the case.
I think the answer is, yes,
there are still use cases.
But they should be where the
recurrence seems to really
be the thing that is winning
you something, as opposed
to maybe needing more
data for Transformers.
Because it seems like
that might not actually
be the case, even though we
thought so back in like 2017.