hi good morning welcome back to cs372
today we start the last segment of the
course
and we plan to cover consciousness for
the next six lectures
then why do we get into consciousness
because several scholars agree the
current ai is again some limitations
and the major reason is because the
current eye only models human
unconsciousness so we have to be able to
understand consciousness thoroughly
and then we perhaps can model
consciousness
and try to study consciousness involving
multiple disciplines
including psychiatry biology
neuroscience physics and so on so forth
and today we start our first lecture and
doctor vladistud rajdu duvari
will present the topic of ai in
psychiatry
and dr duvari enjoys distinguished
academia records including his bs degree
in biology and chemistry from caltech
and phd in psychiatry from stanford
university and finally md from uc san
diego
without further ado let's welcome dr
duvari
so
in the initial seg in a
title you've seen this phrase brainless
and mindless and i just wanted to give a
little bit of an introduction to that
um
this is a quote from a new york times
magazine article
where one psychiatrist is quoting
another psychiatrist
and the psychiatrist being quoted as
leon eisenberg so that's what the
support refers to
so the quote is that in the first half
of the 20th century american psychiatry
is virtually quote unquote brainless
and the second heart half of the 20th
century psychiatry became virtually
mindless
so
hence
my
hope is that
with advances and maybe particularly
technology
uh we're able to go past both
mindless
and brainless specifically the reason
these terms were used here is because
historically
uh psychiatry had a lot of
reliance on psychoanalysis some of the
earlier ways of treating patients and so
that's what is being referred to by
leon eisenberg as brainless and then
mindless refers to this
shift to using medication to treat to
the exclusion of everything else
and the point he's really making is that
it really should be a combination i mean
at the end of the day it should be a
holistic approach
um so
taking a step back before we kind of get
into what we want to do i like this
quote because ultimately um we should
know what we're solving for so this is a
quote from steve jobs
so if you define the problem correctly
you almost always have the solution
so what is the problem so hopefully the
next few slides will start to define
that so um
to begin with um if you look at the
overall burden
in terms of
diseases and their impact
you'll find that about fifth down is
mental health and substance use
disorders
so pretty large impact
so
really making the point that
not is it only suffering although that
should be plenty of a reason
there's also
an equivalent of a
[Music]
lifetime impact and impact in terms of
disability and other measures will show
you money as well
when it comes to money this is a
an older quote this is from about you
know seven ish years ago um seven eight
years ago so 186 billion was spent on
healthcare services to treat mental
health disorders um and we're talking
about the us so
44.7 million or 18 almost 20 percent of
u.s adults 18 or older reported any kind
of mental illness and that's in 2016.
and then again close to about 10 of
adults um
visited a provider in in the prior year
in 2015 again speaking to impact
why is all of that important well one
important reason is
suicides
one of the unfortunate consequences of
problems with mental health and
particularly that there's a worrisome
trend in suicides
now if you look at
the graph here
the solid line uh
hopefully you see my pointer
is the average so that's the average
across the us and it's average over time
going up so
there up to about 2015 in this graph
and
the interesting thing that this shows is
that if you look at the top half of the
graph
and you would ask okay let's divide it
between rural and not rural and there
are details about what that is uh which
one do you think would have a higher
rate um you know in the past there have
been all these um
um ideas about how
more urban aspects have a negative
impact on um well-being of people
and so
what this in fact shows you is that the
top half of the graph is all
less than urban so
small metro micropolitan so-called
and then presumably rural non-metro
all of those are higher and one
source as to why
could be this graph
this this depiction so on the left side
you have the suicide rates that we were
talking about except in this case the
color codes for
the number per 100 000
um over a similar period that we talked
about
and across the country so deeper blue is
a problem
and then now if you overlay that
you'll see
at least one thing but maybe two one is
that it also starts to correlate with
a deeper color on the right graph and
the deeper color on the right graph
speaks to
basically a negative
sort of availability as in a deficit of
psychiatrist relative to what we'd like
so the the white colored boxes are
presumably kind of the middle of the
road
and um
things going down deeper in this color
scheme towards the reddish pinkish
um our deficit so the deficit starts to
overlap with where the problems are and
so maybe that's telling us something
the other thing is that we're also
looking at rural areas
much like what we saw in the graph
before
so
if you're not enough providers maybe
that's part of the problem
now and and where they are in terms of
networks
of resources
this graph tells you a little more as
you try to understand the problem and
say okay well who's at high risk who's
not this is males and females
and so male patients as you can tell the
numbers are higher on the right side
just to give you
a trend here
and also across age groups so higher
across the board
so potentially something
biological potentially something also
social in terms of roles involved
now if we look at continue to look at
the impact
of mental health
in in our social context and how that's
evolved
very recent
trend has been that the pandemic really
changed how virtual care is viewed
and so one might think okay well um
virtual care means you can reach people
you don't have to be bound by physically
geographically where you are that should
be a good thing
um and well
that's potential has certainly been seen
there's lots of money that's been raised
um starting in 2019 um and that
continued through 2020 2021
and
you know we'll see how that continues
into the future but with all this
money being poured in and opportunity
for seeing therapists
what's also been noticed is that there's
been a big uptick 30 percent increase in
the um
sorry 60 increase in users
uh
in this one particular instance of an
app called talkspace which again makes
access very easy
and
the 60 of his users are in therapy for
the first time so again speaking to this
idea that maybe maybe with virtual care
becoming
more widespread
and more
easily
accessible
across the u.s despite all those graphs
and
pictures i showed you maybe that will
have an
impact um
so as we're defining the problem um and
we kind of this is much more current
as of this month
one of the companies that was part of
this group of many companies that
were heavily invested in to provide
mental health services
had a bit of a setback
where
there was a lot of concern about how
prescribing was happening and in this
instance
the headline is referring to how
adderall which was being prescribed
was now being halted
and there's a lot more news about this
so again kind of maybe following the
pendulum maybe it got too easy whatever
that means
one
thing to note in this context especially
with
adderall which is a control substance
is that
it was not something you could do
earlier you you you you couldn't
um prescribe adderall
uh essentially over the internet um
before we were in this emergency
authorization period which we're in now
so one of the questions is
by making virtual care easier to get to
by removing barriers
are we only doing good or are we also
doing some harm
um
and and why is that harm happening if
it's happening what is a better way to
do it so again starting to define the
problem um what
is access the issue and uh with access
uh starting to be addressed is that
gonna be enough
so
we've talked about kind of the the needs
side of the equation um
you know it's i think important to start
to understand a little bit about what we
talk about when we talk about depression
or anxiety or some of these other
disorders
and so we'll go through a few snapshots
of these disorders so depression of
course
specifically major depression which is a
clinical diagnosis one of the most
common mental disorders in the u.s
and it can really impair your ability to
function in life
and obviously have very serious outcomes
um bad ones like we just
looked at in the graph
there's a manual that um
basically provides the diagnostic
criteria in psychiatry and that's called
a dsm-5 so that's what you're seeing
abbreviated here and so this is one
example of a summary of what
clinical depression or major depressive
disorder looks like so period of at
least two weeks
where a person experiences
loss of interest
low mood
and a few other symptoms that go along
for the ride
and if you look at the next slide
and we're only talking about depression
here
in a recent survey this is from 2017
from one of the federal
agencies what you see is that
if you were to use this whole
donut here to represent
folks coming in or needing depression
care
you find that about one third 35 percent
have no care when it comes to adults
this is adults on the left side
and then on the right side
60 double that so almost two-thirds of
adolescence no treatment at all
and then you have pieces of the other
aspects so on the left side the adults
have a combination of seeing
mental health professional and
having access to medication
some do medication only on the left side
and then similarly
there are smaller proportions of
medication only
on the right side
and male health proportion mental health
professional visits
along with medication now the
significance
of the dark blue is that um
for really most of the conditions that
are studied in mental health treatment
um it's important that
the treatment involve both a way to
think about your endless how to cope
with your illness learn skills
to manage your symptoms to escalate when
needed in addition to taking medication
so it's really that combination that is
seen to be the best option and yet the
the data here tells you that um there
are a lot of people who are outside the
quote-unquote best option
among both adults and adolescents so
again further defining the problem
now
that little quote up there uh with the
dsm-5 might have given you the idea that
you know
depression is one thing
well turns out depression is not one
thing
depression is uh many things and what i
mean by that is there are many versions
so uh this is just to give you an
example not to go really into uh depth
on any of these topics
but
an example of one variety of depression
here if you see my pointer is psychotic
depression so this is where depressions
get so bad
that um it starts to create a break from
reality so where the person cannot
separate reality from the um
delusional
aspects of their thinking that are
starting to emerge
and that influences their behavior
influences their thoughts of course
um
and then we talked about major
depressive disorder uh postpartum is
another case you often hear about it
when there are bad outcomes here um you
know it could be somebody who's given
birth and something bad happens to the
to the baby because um
basically uh the the mother who's
delivered has severe depression
and if untreated unrecognized unmanaged
that can have pretty bad effects um
for the mom as well as for the baby
uh and in some cases it can result in
the death of the child so um
in in that case uh death of the neonates
a newborn
baby
and then there's other patterns um one
sort of different direction is that so
far when we talk about depression most
people refer to one direction of
dysfunction meaning that your mood goes
down
if there's a baseline it drops
and it drops persistently bipolar is an
example where
it can go both ways so you can have an
unreasonable
amount of
excitement joy
and essentially what ends up becoming a
really big problem in terms of risk
assessment
because
your extreme sort of
so-called mania can impair your
cognitive decision making so as you can
tell just like having a low mood and
seeing everything to a dark lens can
obviously have a negative impact on your
life
so can an unreasonably positive uh
switch of that and there are some other
characteristics as well so again
starting to give you a sense of there
are different kinds of things out there
when we talk about depression different
flavors
each with their own course
and so when we start to think about what
is the problem we're treating what are
the consequences of this problem we also
need to recognize that uh we're gonna
have to somehow
uh deal with this issue that there are
um
uh other variables than basically saying
it's is it depression or is it not
depression
well dr duvaris can i uh ask a question
so this month is is called uh mental
health awareness month right in may
and i i saw some statistics seems to
show uh
about 2020 end of 2020 or in the 22 2019
the percentage of
u.s adults suffering from depression is
about
19.8
so that's much higher than your
yeah or 10
and because of pandemic and
the ratio further increases
so so this is really a major crisis and
for
teenagers
folks in high school and maybe college
because of academia
pressure
job pressure and many other pressures
and it seems like the ratio is even
higher
yes yes no i think the pandemics really
had a pretty bad impact um when it comes
to
mental health in general
uh and then various you know problems
within depression being one of them
um yeah so i think as
to your point as bad as some of these
problems are that we're looking at here
and as bad as the numbers look like
they're actually underestimating uh
the current situation and that's
unfortunate uh because uh it's not like
uh you you needed more emphasis it was
already pretty bad so yeah i agree
um and i think i touched on it a little
bit at some point um but um
the the impact of kovid
has definitely been
multifaceted
to some degree it's just the impact of
having a pandemic take over your life
on the other side it's also limitation
of resources
which now are starting to open up and
and maybe even pretty good in some areas
but um that was a big issue during the
pandemic certainly in the middle of it
so now you've got this problem of
there's more problems and there's fewer
ways to address them so of course you
know the outcomes are going to be bad
um
does that does that address the question
oh yes yes yeah the motivation of me
asking this question is i think the
severity of the problem is even worse
than you just presented yes that's true
and also the severity of the the
depression itself means the condition of
depression because of my my family
routinely
we have this kind of weekend gathering
with our friends
and two three years ago
virtually all the kids are very healthy
and uh
i mean very sadly in recent days and
they are one-third of kids suffer from
major
psychological disorders
and they cannot go to school they are
one person
even in a coma state
so so it's not really just getting
depression but the severity
right of the symptom
it's just horrible and it's one
one out of three means even your family
is okay but your surroundings your
neighbors i mean you can encounter
people having
these kind of problems and most of the
adults or parents they don't really
understand depression very well right so
in the beginning may be mistreated uh
consider depression symptoms as
something like
uh
moral problems right like
eating disorder often uh parents will
say well this is a bad choice you're a
bad joke
but in fact it's not a matter of choice
it's a matter of uh
psychiatric disorder yeah yeah no you're
right you're right and actually i've
those are some great points i was
actually going to say that actually um
eating disorders is one of these aspects
that really has shot through the roof
during this period
um and and exactly to your point um
it's all
it's it's such a common thing in terms
of having a cultural and social context
for eating that people feel like well
you know i think i can feel like an
expert on this
as a parent or as a family member and
um i'm not going to think twice about
what i'm saying or doing about it
because you know it's eating
what what's what's there to think about
so deeply
but unfortunately
that can lead to trouble and and i yeah
i see this all the time i mean literally
last week
um a parent basically said exactly that
uh where you know oh we thought this kid
and this was a very young kid
um you know was being picky kind of
picking and choosing and otherwise doing
you know her thing
we didn't think it was a big deal and
then the next thing we know the heart
rate drops and uh the kid's in trouble
has to be in the hospital so it's a
complete shock for the parents um
even though as you say you know there's
all these articles there's all this
information out there but i think um you
know what you're also highlighting this
is separate really from at least
uh some of the
technology initiatives there's a big
challenge in terms of translating what's
out there in terms of information to
something you can use personally
because what you can use personally uh
seems to somehow fall under the radar uh
and and it's hard to kind of separate
your own experience from sort of
quote-unquote knowledge that um you know
people have access to so i think i think
it's a great point uh and maybe in the
conversation ahead uh we'll be able to
um
pick up on that and see maybe maybe
there is a role for technology there
um
okay thank you
yeah of course um
uh great points so
um we were talking about depression
until now this is anxiety again giving
you snapshots of some common disorders
um
so when we talk about an anxiety
disorder as opposed to hey i'm anxious
about this or that uh
this is anxiety that doesn't go away it
gets worse over time
and it interferes with your ability to
do your job go to school
function in society really
and so similar to depression i want to
give you a taste that again there are
different types
um
many people have heard about having a
panic attack so panic disorder uh which
is where people have these frequent
panic attacks
um is
anxiety that's kind of concentrated in a
short amount of time which looks quite
different compared to generalized
anxiety disorder which is what people
call quote unquote worry words right you
worry all the time about everything you
wake up in the morning you just worry i
mean everything is just a worry um and
then again that's different compared to
phobias which are hey i'm afraid of
spiders it's not just afraid of spiders
it's very good fighters to the point
where it's actually you know influencing
how you manage your day-to-day um and
causes some pretty extreme reactions um
and in many cases it may be things that
other people
don't find an issue at all
so again giving you a sense that um yes
you know we start to get a sense of
some of these problems like depression
anxiety but also start to understand
that
um there's gonna be types of those that
need to be factored in when you design
solutions
substance use disorders is another
category
and
it can either
come by itself or together with one of
the others
so this
little
graphic shows you that
it's a big problem
over 7 million as of this count
this is again from one of the federal
agencies
[Music]
as we were talking about it can come by
itself or separately so on the left side
you see about 40 percent
um
also have other mental health diagnoses
so that's two out of five
and then
you look at it the other way now you
look at somebody with
things that are not a substance use
disorder so some other mental health
diagnosis about one out of five of those
has a substance use disorder so again
pretty pretty significant overlap given
the size of these numbers
and then
back to what we were talking about with
depression we had that big problem in
terms of people not being in treatment
and so here among adults this gives you
a flavor because if you're trying to
solve this problem you want to get a
sense of okay well why aren't people
accessing the solutions
um
about 40
the top one here
not ready not ready to stop using
whatever the substance is
have no health insurance and could not
afford the cost
so maybe this is pointing to this fact
that in this subpopulation versus maybe
others
there's a concentration of people who
are not able to afford treatment
so again when you have solutions you
want to be able to address the
demographic you're trying to solve it in
and maybe your solution is great if
you've got all kinds of resources but is
basically useless if you were in this
bucket of 35
um
of the people surveyed here
um and then there's other things you
know like it says might cause neighbors
to have negative opinions so
typically that's under the bucket of
quote-unquote stigma
um and people worry is this gonna affect
my job or you know if i use my insurance
is it gonna
you know are people gonna find out
um who has access to that um what do i
do you know that i see the
underparamount where you know it's not
clear where where do you actually get
people uh what's the first step um
so uh start again starting to get you a
sense of what are the problem points
um
and then um this is an example where um
just like we talked about earlier
there's that percentage of people who
either have the substitutes alone or
have it together with a mental health
disorder that is not substance use
and so in that so-called co-occurring
subset um off the people who did not get
access to care what were their reasons
so this is the combo this is not just
substance uses combo of substance use
and another mental health disorder
top reason can't afford the cost uh it's
a big problem like we were talking about
so when you start designing solutions
that's that's a big consideration
because
now you got to think about okay is my
solution actually going to be useful you
know i think it's great and i think it
works great but maybe it only works
great if you have the resources
um
and then there are other aspects that
have to do with perception fear of being
committed oh what are they going to do
once they find out that i need help
uh am i going to be locked up i might
you know what's going to happen next i i
won't have any control over what happens
to my life and this maybe even if
they already don't have much control
over their lives because of the uh
illness that they're dealing with
um and then futility of treatment uh you
know which again raises questions about
why that is
um
and then we talked about some of the
others
so
as we're trying to summarize the problem
you know again you you saw the trends as
i as i mentioned them earlier
um
it's it's it's quite a familiar list
probably for many of you
um because
more and more has been written about
this now during the pandemic especially
but um one thing i would recommend um
and this is um
somebody um
that's really taken a a deep look at
this
it's tom insult who used to be the
director of the national institute of
mental health
and more recently has worked with
california
at the state level and and in other
capacities
he decided um
in this book that just came out to go
around and interview people across the
mental health system in different forms
of the mental health system
pretending basically to be a journalist
not that he said he was then most people
know who he is in the field
uh but to take that role and to say okay
let's ask questions about from a patient
journey perspective
uh what's working what's not working
and when something's not working uh why
is it not working
um and so this is one review there have
been plenty of other reviews for this
book that just came out
um so
what it does is it gives the reason i
mention it here um
is that um it gives a bit of flavor to
some of these uh bullet points so we
know there's a problem with access we
saw that even in this talk from the
beginning with the with the graphs and
the maps of the us
but
what is the problem with access so one
of the points that the book makes is
well actually if you look at the ratio
of how many therapists are available
it's a pretty decent number there are a
lot of therapists in the us
okay well then how is there an access
problem and what he points to is that
there's a problem in terms of how
therapy is delivered are the
evidence-based
tools being implemented are the
resources that
we know
work
being implemented in a in a regular
uniform effective way and so that's one
problem right is that the
access may be there to a person who can
help you see you but it's not done in an
evidence-based way
they're system hurdles which
you'll see all over the book basically
whether it's you want to get into a
program get into a hospital
get a certain kind of medication that is
recommended for you
there's hurdle after hurdle after hurdle
that
requires you to be quite dogged
persistent and in many ways
even super functional
and all this from somebody where you
know it's a brain disorder that's
actually impairing them so how does that
work how are you supposed to be able to
overcome those hurdles to actually get
access
and a related issue is treatment
decisions so meaning that again if a
disorder is impacting you and say it's a
psychotic disorder like schizophrenia
it changes how you perceive reality you
had a real problem because
now that person has to decide for
themselves that oh you know never mind
what my voices are telling me i have to
go get them
and the laws and you know a lot of the
states
fit that they fit this idea that you
know people should be making their own
decisions they should be doing what's
good for them
some places um the mental health and
clinical systems can can uh
take take control of the treatment
process
for various periods of time uh in other
places not so much so there's not a
uniformity there
california is a good example there's not
a uniformity across the 50 plus counties
in california so the mental health
treatment you get especially for a
severe mental illness like schizophrenia
can really be 50 plus versions within
one state
so
that's obviously not conducive to
anything positive in terms of good
outcomes
and then the other point he makes
is
we talk about stigma a lot that's
definitely
gets a lot of air time in in the public
sphere
but what he actually starts to make the
point of is that it you know stigma may
be underselling it it's really
discrimination it's just you have to
come out and say it it's discrimination
if somebody's got a mental health
diagnosis it's flat out a problem
uh and unless you're in some very secure
position
status or something else
people are just not willing to risk that
and so that can lead to all the problems
you saw earlier as to why people don't
seek treatment or sometimes when they do
see treatment like when you go to an
emergency room
the way you're treated is quite
different
to if you came in with a heart attack uh
in many ways some of these psychiatric
emergencies are like a quote-unquote
brain attack well why is that different
why should that be treated differently
uh
the fact is
uh these conditions are treated
differently
um and then as you're sort of starting
to get the picture here a lot of the
hurdles here require social support so
whatever form that takes it could be
your family it could be a broader group
like you heard um
from
from professor chang here and so
it's
it
it could be
um it could be mitigated by social
support but what should that social
support look like
um and uh do people know that they need
to implement that put that into action
one of the issues is
confidentiality
at least in the context of mental health
extends to family
so what that means is
um
there are lots of situations where you
could have
a young adult in a hospital or an adult
uh older
older person
and if that person for whatever reason
decides i don't want anybody else to
know maybe it's because of how
the mental disorder is impacting them
and they can't think through that
where they feel bad because they're
super depressed and they don't really
want to talk to anyone whatever the case
all of those
factors
end up having this negative impact that
if they say no i don't i don't want
anybody else to know um
even if they're worrying out there not
knowing what happened to you know their
family their loved one
that's okay that's that's how the
current law is written
um so
so yes we talk about social support but
in fact this the way the system is set
up
uh is terrible to actually facilitate or
even allow it
and then um this is something that's
touched on here but is probably
addressed
even better or elsewhere which is
diagnoses we refer to in dsm 5 that i
alluded to
the diagnosis in psychiatry they're
really syndromes they're a collection of
symptoms that we put together that hang
together and as they come together
and present as one thing or so one
combination of things
it's easy to forget that they're
actually a collection of things
uh it's not it's not one thing as in oh
you know
um there's this deficiency of this
protein or
a signaling molecule like insulin and
then therefore you get the downstream
effect it's it's it's many things coming
together to create the scenario that we
see
so
um a lot more needs to be done obviously
to understand that aspect and and
there have been a lot of advances one
book i think
you'll probably get some
exposure to here
is a book called projections which was
written by a
neuroscientist psychiatrist
friend of mine from back in training
who's who's on the faculty at stanford
uh and he he really wrote this amazing
book um
and i say amazing not just because of
the science it's a very beautifully
written book uh
in terms of the writing style um and so
[Music]
so in that particular book
written by carl diceratzo carl really
talks about
how you can start to conceptualize
to some extent
the presentation of the mental health
disorders but also the science behind it
you know how do you tease it apart how
do you start to understand
uh the neurons the neuronal circuits
that may be driving um some of those
aspects and and what does the future
look like
so again lots of
interesting stuff there but that that's
probably
the last part uh with diagnosis and
syndromes is probably best served um
through a through a different source
yes yes dr dr duvari i i actually just
finished reading the book projections
oh great it's a remarkable remarkably
written book
uh
for the the troubles or the problems or
challenges you just mentioned right i i
think uh i i talk to many
young kids the first one is uh
often people do not want to reveal they
have problems or they don't seem to have
problems right especially like eating
disorder if you send a kid to the
hospital they are going to be evasive
they are not going to say yes i have
eating disorder right so it's really
hard to detect and number two is that
you mention
reputation you don't want people to know
and
the law actually saying if you are above
your parents cannot make a choice for
you so we do see parents they want to
really want to they are totally stressed
out they want to see when they are kids
so in institutions
but their kids refused to go to
institutions though so they kind of
stuck in the middle right but finally
come back to carl's
book
i think the amazing thing is this uh
optogenetic right optogenitic technique
and because so far for mental disorders
we can only see kind of symptoms we
cannot use instruments to detect
different from other diseases like you
can do blood work you can do x-ray but
for mental disorders there's no
scientific tools you can say oh your
serotonin is too low or your dopamine
dopamine whatever level is too low so
therefore you have this and that or it's
really subjective sometimes yeah so so
i'm really excited about this
technology of
opto genetics hopefully eventually will
be
uh in this treatment process
yeah training process and even at this
point you know as we understand more
about how some of the symptoms come
about uh to your point um because the
symptoms seem so commonplace
um you know yeah i have days where i'm
depressed or i'm anxious or something
else
um
or tired um well
what what's to say
i'm not trying hard enough i mean you
alluded to some of this before you know
it becomes sort of the social construct
so
um
once we start to understand that
at the level of what's happening in the
brain
as optogenetics is certainly one
powerful way to do
my hope is that that can help drive
people starting to feel like you know
what i'm not making this up when
somebody says i should just deal with it
uh that's not okay
uh you know i know that's not okay but
now this gives me something to hang on
to to say okay i i can i can grab this
this fact here
uh that has been established somehow and
that gives me the confidence and
validates my experience
uh which is i think a major problem in a
lot of what we see in mental health um
and and maybe that'll also drive some of
the solutions you're talking about such
as maybe
um
allow better communication between
parents and kids and you know provide
kind of that context as opposed to sort
of everything getting more
hidden because of stigma and shame
at least in that context so
kind of
you know in sync with that um the whole
the hope is that apps maybe can help
technology can help you know ai can help
and um some people simplistically say
well you know when we do some
comparisons people are more willing to
share on uh technology platforms than
they are in person to person um
again these are you know
small assessments small studies maybe
even anecdotes
but time will tell
the other big thing is of course
accessibility so
as opposed to having to make
appointments etc there is a way to
collect information that is time and
location agnostic potentially can be
highly personalized we're certainly able
to do that in the commercial world where
things are getting super personalized to
be able to sell you things well maybe we
can use some of that technology to
actually do some good
in this sort of way
and then improve engagement you know
people are not coming to treatment
they're not doing the things that are
good for them well how can we drive that
how can we use again the same kind of
tools that are being used to get people
to keep using apps or selling them
things to actually apply it in the
mental health sphere
and then there's a few other things
which i think time will tell whether we
are able to do you know better diagnosis
are there ways to use
big data and different ways of
using sensors different ways of
combining sensors and data
that is patient provided to drive
analytics to do decision support that's
better
um you know time will help
and then we'll touch on some of these
and what what the problems are uh along
the way
um and then we talked about treatment
you know maybe there ought to be some
standardization that can be driven by
technology
uh maybe part of that is delivered by
the technology maybe part of that is uh
directed by it so maybe not delivered
but at least you start to push the idea
that hey you know this this really
should make you consider treatment x it
shouldn't
be
what the person you happen to contact is
good at it should be the thing you
actually need for the condition that
you're presenting with
um and then as you talked about
optogenetics and other things uh maybe
that can be factored in as time goes on
um
i just want to do a quick time check so
how much time do we have um through the
rest of the lecture here about 30
minutes okay great so that will give me
plenty of time
um
so
[Music]
the next few slides are just to give you
a sense that um people have been looking
at trying to apply technology this was
one review and basically their idea is
you know anytime and everywhere
ubiquitous tech right that's what
they're looking at
to add to traditional care
and that's this laundry list here
non-clinical focus on the bottom
clinical focus on the top
tailored to specific diagnoses so in
this survey there's a fair number um
30 plus up here and about 10 plus down
here
and the pattern that emerges is that
a lot of them focus on sensing right
that's that's where the technology is
it's both passive and active sensing and
i just want to spend a few minutes on um
passive versus active so the main
takeaway is that because in a lot of
these situations where somebody going
through especially a mental health
crisis
may not be the perfect person to
actually use an active
sensing strategy
it would be great if technology can
create ways of doing
effective passive sensing so something
that technology is tracking over time an
app kind of tracks xyz
maybe 10 variables 100 variables
more
and sets off an alarm and that says okay
this this is something's going wrong
here and let's try to use predictive
analytics so that um as you see up here
30 good predictive modeling uh use
predictive analytics so that you can use
that sensor data that's grabbed
passively to then hopefully prevent
a bad outcome that would be
really one of the great ways that
technology can help with the treatment
of mental health conditions and so
but in order to get there obviously
there's a lot of obstacles and we'll
kind of talk about where things are in
the meantime but as you can see we're
really at the first step here where we
are most of our effort in the field at
least as of this point pre-2020 is uh in
sensing um
this is another review that kind of
looked at it over a couple of years to
see okay you know now we're getting this
proliferation of apps in the last few
years this particular one was published
let me see i think 2019 2020
uh 2019
um
you know what do we look at and so they
looked at you know what kind of platform
they looked at are there any claims
being made about hey this is going to
treat xyz condition does it cost you
anything what kind of intervention is
being used
um
and then
you know what are the mechanisms you
know is it is it tracking where you are
is it asking you questions
is it looking at what you're doing with
your phones and asking you to write
notes or is there gamification
as some examples
and so
basically in this particular comparison
where they looked at
a group of apps they looked at 10
android and 10 ios by these six
categories so 120 total
so some as you can tell like
hypertension are not mental health uh uh
the others are
um
and they basically say okay um so in
brackets it's what happened in 2018
outside brackets what happened in 2019
so the hope is well apps are increasing
in number
uh
you know as of now there's thousands um
so are they getting better if we use
these metrics you know do users like it
is their privacy policy now whether it's
good or not
just is there one do they tell you
what's happening uh is there a way for
you to get rid of your data
uh if you don't want it to be there uh
is it gonna cost you something
um
and uh how often is it being updated is
it telling you something about is it
gonna treat condition xyz
um
and is there evidence so say they tell
you okay we're gonna do this that and
the other thing but is there actually
evidence in some kind of a way or
they've studied or somebody has studied
to actually provide some support to that
and that that's probably the worst of
this table where you can see it's in you
know it used to be zero in many
instances
went up to tens and 20s but it's still
very low in terms of the percentage of
apps that are providing any sort of
support to say we're gonna do x and this
is the reason why you should believe
that
so that's a big problem so it's sort of
like you know
being provided medication and saying
well you know i think this will be good
for you well what's the evidence for
that well never mind about that
um or you know one out of five or one
out of ten
times that happens you actually have
some basis to say that so that's where
we are in this space
so it's it's unfortunate the numbers in
terms of what's available definitely
increasing
uh but it seems like the quality is not
so how do you navigate this um one of
the ways um to navigate this is um there
thankfully there are a few sort of
categorizing websites
uh that do a bit of reviewing and also a
bit of basically feature categorization
and so this gives you um an index of
done on the left side here and then
these are just some examples various
apps and this column
you know is it well written
there's a patient facing etc so this is
done by mind hosted on one of the
harvard hospital sites
um led by a team up there that does
digital psychiatry and so they have a
group of raters that goes through and
systematically does
basically what they describe on their
website you know this is how we're
rating them so when you go in and you
want to look for something
we can tell you what we think of it in
this somewhat detailed way so then you
can go filter and the hope is that
ultimately it will help you with app
selection
um these are some examples of what that
looks like right so accessibility how
much does it cost um
does it need to be online
uh privacy policy as you saw um you know
what features does it have um how do you
get people to engage with the app and
then as we talked about clinical which
is an important category
there's also another site that's called
one mind which tries to do a similar
thing it's reviewing
aspect seems to be less extensive
um and so i think in time hopefully um
it'll be a good complementary resource
to the um
first mind site that i uh pointed to
so
now that we see okay there are apps and
you've seen some characteristics of what
those apps are what are they trying to
accomplish
um
you know technology in the service of
mental health um
what is it that they can help with you
know you've kind of seen that okay there
are these problems with the apps but if
you look at the the course of an illness
in a person
where can we intervene so this gives you
maybe a a bit of a flavor of that where
should you intervene so prevention
um is there a way to give you a risk
score
that could be one way and especially as
genomics comes into the picture and we
maybe learn more from neuroscience so
maybe there's ways of behaviorally
testing some of that
um
and so really focusing on wellness uh
and and measures that are preventive
because in medicine we tend to do
prevention the best when we can succeed
at that
early detection we talked about sensors
using
analytics to serve alerts
maybe also create stress tests so maybe
it's not obvious if you just do passive
collection maybe there's passive is
tailored to active where there's a you
know you play a game and that kind of
tests maybe how you react to things
um
and then again personalizing that
in an evidence-based way we talked about
access in terms of being at the right
time and the right place maybe even
being agnostic to
the current limitations
we talked about some of these other
things like decision support
and then also gathering data is is the
thing you're doing to treat the
condition is it working
um
most people are not out there
putting out data that says hey when i do
xyz
this is how well it works and i think
that should be something that should be
easy to do so
and i think technology could be a great
way to get us there
because then from a consumer end you can
be a much more informed consumer when
you say hey i want to do this and i want
to do it there because look their data
really speaks um volumes of what they
can do
and then we talked about downsides like
alerts for
adverse events
so
the other side so those are in the life
cycle of anxiety depression on the other
side when we talk about
um
what should ai be mindful of as we
collect all this data as the number of
apps goes through the roof
we need proven interventions we've
talked about that um otherwise what
you're doing um it's kind of like
selling snake oil i mean that's that's
not okay
um the consenting process needs to be
simple especially for this population
especially if they're in crisis
um and for equity you know because you
don't know if uh everyone in there is
going to have the resources to kind of
work through what needs to be worked
through to understand
what's the right answer what is what are
the problems they might run into by
signing on to something like this
um
which then speaks to transparency and
trust supercritical so extra effort has
to be made especially in this mental
health space
um the other aspects have to do with
more practical things um you know
passive monitoring tends to be more
practical for the reasons we talked
about
reduce friction so that people
incorporate whatever you're doing into
their workflow
um and then trying to tailor devices to
mel health you know right now
phone is a general purpose thing uh
maybe it lasts um
for for longer
uh but potentially maybe there's even a
version that um
that's that's built better uh to cater
to mental health um and then as we
talked about social support is super
critical so now i want to switch a
little bit to start to say okay you know
we talked about apps individual
sort of in some detail talked about the
individual course of illness now let's
take a step back and sort of say what
are some
more um
aiml type strategies that are being used
this is one
survey um that i found quite useful and
let's look at the landscape so big
picture
and that will also include systems not
just individual patient journeys
um so
in the application of mlm houses
specifically looking at ml as opposed to
just technology in general or apps in
general
um as you've seen the
nice little spike here this is 2019 and
hopefully that continued
the main
work was in model development um with as
opposed to you know empirical study
um
applying algorithms or design and
based on what we're talking about and
what we've seen so far i would argue
it's probably a good time to spend a lot
more time on design and concept because
there seem to be some fundamental issues
with how
the apps are being designed and fun
those issues with identifying what is
the problem they're trying to solve you
know what is it that they're solving
first because if that's not clear then
you know the solution you have is really
uh not going to be effective
this is another way to slice the data in
terms of what people have been up to um
this is either collecting data
or it's access to
existing data and uh where it's coming
from so
a big chunk of it is existing data sets
that's what a lot of the ml work is
being done on health records some part
and some combination
and then as you can tell here sensors as
we talked about had a good head start
that remains and then the rest of it is
coming from
either
patient
provided information
or a large part from social media
and then
the other question is okay well these
are the sources and the system setups
who are the people who's actually
providing the data
and as you can see both categories
whether it's existing data set
or data collection a significant chunk
is folks without a mental health
diagnosis so here it's a large one which
is troubling because
really if our goal is we want to collect
data make good models test the models
and then we'll implement them we should
be
doing that based on folks with diagnoses
that we're going to try and treat
that's not the case at least in the data
collection survey here um it was the
case more so
when we're looking at existing data
that's good but that also has some
pitfalls as we'll see
so this is a bit of a busy slide
what it's trying to do is give you more
granular information so what is the kind
of data that's been out there so the
data collection so people with mental
health conditions small numbers 10
patients with bipolar 24 with ptsd 25
with mdd
and then you know you start to look at
500 users on twitter
uh 600 participants um
students are working professional
almost 2 000 twitter users who
self-report
various diagnosis 4 000 twitter users
who have some other
clinical characteristic
so this is in the bucket of folks where
there is
some connection to mental health but
it's not a diagnosis that you know and
here um it's a verified diagnosis so the
folks in the left column as part of the
survey of what's going out there going
on out there in terms of ml studies
tells you that
the small studies
have some level of verification in terms
of
mental health diagnoses outcomes even
the larger groups are for social media
not been verified
and a lot of self-report in terms of
what folks have
and so
and and then on the right side here you
can also see um
participants without a clinical
diagnosis
massive data sets so 16 you know almost
17 000 right participants
um
and
no use of clinical screening tools so
these
massive sets in terms of
um
the studies being done to build ml
models and to test ml models are being
done on folks where there is not
a lot of
clinically informed
data gathering
and so if we're going to use this to
actually design our apps it's going to
be a problem
this gives you a sense of what we call
stepped care basically in order to put
some of that
information that we've been talking
about
in context so it helps to understand
when somebody has some level of
an illness
who sees them
what do they do
and how does that
escalation happen so mild is sort of at
the bottom this is of course general
scheme
there are outliers there are maybe even
non-outliers but different ways of
navigating the system but this is one
model
where
you can have this sort of stepwise
escalation and stepwise increase in the
resource allocated and more specialized
treatments so inpatient care is at the
top outpatient care primary care
basically is at the bottom
ongoing care assessment prevention this
is a great place for prevention and then
at the top is
severe life-threatening scenarios
um
severity of illness that is hard to
treat so you have medications etc and
everything in between so when you start
to design apps i think one of the
important things that one has to look at
is where is it going to fit in this
continuum what are you targeting and so
far you know there really hasn't been
much that we can look at and say oh this
is where this app was designed to help
it's it hasn't gone to that point at
least any of the surveys that we've
touched on haven't really addressed any
of that so that's obviously an important
thing to look at
so this is just summarizing what we
talked about
now another survey um that digs a little
deeper and says okay well we talked
about how social media is really being
mined
uh to try to use um
ml for um for mental health so where is
it coming from and so these are two ways
of slicing that data one is that you can
see twitter's on top we saw lots of
studies out there thousands tens of
thousands of folks who are providing the
data
that's being scraped from trader um
and then what is it being studied what
is being used for uh it's been used for
depression probably predominantly and
then
suicide next and then you see the others
so again
the reminder here is that
where would you even apply data that
comes from twitter right maybe primary
care i don't know
but maybe that person's in a crisis and
on twitter so
unless you ask unless you have some
context for that um and unless you're
able to understand okay what what is the
utility of the data i'm collecting
uh whether it's about depression
schizophrenia something else suicide as
you saw in there
um
it's it's hard to know what to do with
it and potentially it's harder to do
anything useful with it in the context
of an app
so again think about this this sort of
framework
um when you're trying to say hey i have
an app that's gonna help with depression
well okay what kind of depression where
in the spectrum
can it maybe cross the spectrum does
your app have the agility that it can
take somebody who's
kind of mild right now
uh or maybe only has a family history
and then maybe it operates at a the
lower end of this or maybe it operates
at the higher end where it's really for
folks who have
identified problems
and in in other parts of medicine there
are concepts of um you know primary
prevention secondary prevention etc and
so you know one can maybe apply that
kind of framework but so far the apps
don't seem to do that
um
so again summarizing the problems with
the efforts out there that are heavily
driven from data in social media that's
easy to access it appears
but seems to have quite a bit of
problems in terms of uh being either
valid
in terms of what the objective is
lacks a ground truth because
how do you reference it to something you
know where a data set has folks with
depression
um
and then um
how about healthy controls how do you
compare that how do you how do you know
that what you're doing is going to react
differently when somebody doesn't have a
mental health diagnosis
so
one way potentially to address that is
okay let's look at medical records so
electronic medical records emrs
maybe they're a good source right
they're
collecting data as we speak because
whenever you install one of them in a
hospital all your future patients their
information is in there
past information's in there for
different lengths of time
um
so so maybe that's going to help well
okay so
in in some of the natural language
processing efforts out there that seems
to be the case people have focused on
medical records
um to say hey can we get really good at
using nlp to confirm a diagnosis so i
can look at the words in what i'm seeing
in a note in a chart
and then i can say oh yeah that's the
right diagnosis or that's the wrong
diagnosis hey maybe we should look at
that again
um look at the prognosis and say you
know how well does this person do
because you have that whole history so
can you take some of that initial data
or even decisions
and then start to do some predictive uh
modeling
that actually helps clinicians do a
better job the next time
and prompts them saying hey you know
this algorithm says
you know you're probably going to be
wrong
70 of the time if you pick this kind of
a choice for somebody with this profile
so that would be amazing
um
and then there are other aspects of
course when you're using emrs how do you
do consent because it's somebody else's
data
um especially outside of academic
settings um
um how do you create the appropriate
training set so that there's the right
way to look at uh populations and and
use them
um are your conclusions valid
uh how do you test that they're valid um
and then how do you deal with false
alarms so maybe you have an alert that
oh this person's you know going through
some terrible things
but if you're wrong
how do you deal with that
um
so
one example of what might be a problem
with electronic medical records because
maybe it seems like a panacea it's like
oh great this is awesome
uh we're gonna have all this structured
data it's gonna be written by clinicians
so none of that twitter stuff
well
this is an example where
you're able to generate an entire note
with basically
all this text that was generated by the
computer by the system
and
the two parts in yellow are the only
ones that apparently
came from a provider
a physician or other clinical person
so that's a bit of a problem
as people are crunched for time
more and more things get into templates
more things
maybe are formatted automated clicked
into place
in electronic medical records so now if
you're going to use
all those fancy algorithms with nlp etc
on notes
clinician notes like this with the idea
that hey i'm going to extract something
unique
well the problem is that uniqueness is
not coming from what that physician or
other
clinical person is seeing
when they
treat the patient
it's coming from the computer
and it's not entirely clear what that's
going to do i mean for one thing it
doesn't seem right it doesn't seem like
that ought to be the source
of what individualizes our knowledge of
somebody with depression or some other
condition
so
this is another thing to deal with as we
start to look at alternatives to using
what has been popular such as social
media
as we talked about lots of uses
but there's a few problems
then there is another use case where
again um
has been implemented in lots of ways
and that is to have chat bots that
help you cope better so this is going to
supplement or maybe even completely
replace
you
speaking with your therapist so these
are some examples of conversations
between a patient and a chatbot and this
particular one
will talk to you on the basis of
what the emotional threat of your
conversation is
and it will give you what they
say is evidence-based
so they have in their algorithm
something that uses a certain kind of
therapy
that's tied to how you use emotional
words and it's supposed to respond
according to those rules
um
sounds kind of cool that doesn't work
well so
again
the the proof is proof of the pudding is
in the eating so
one of the
one example is the randomized control
trial um
so that's a good way to study a problem
like this in this instance a
non-clinical population basically
college students from a bunch of
universities
was recruited
each group is about 25-ish people
and they basically measured
a depression scale
uh which starts off somewhere in the
region of seven to eight and then
watched it over time the blue
um according to their statistics gets
worse that's the control group
where they give them a website or some
resource to get information and then the
other two
they have access to what they call
integrative ai it's
it's this ai that can kind of work
through
text or messenger or some format and and
basically uh be
be kind of this
supportive
conversational
chatbot
and the idea is hey you know it does it
help when you have this
in this case they claim it helps
the ph 9 which is a measure of
depression goes down
depressive symptoms goes down over time
when the chatbot was used interestingly
not as much when you go to four weeks
than when you go to two
the problem with this scenario is that
um
this is not somebody who has depression
so it was not
meant to be that way they didn't ask for
people with depression
they asked for volunteers and they said
hey we're gonna measure your score and
we'll see what happens
so
really
this may be a model for what needs to be
done but as it stands this type of study
is of limited use because we don't
really know what it's going to do in
somebody
with a clinical diagnosis
but but this is we need a lot more of
this we need large studies
and we need ways of tracking that well
sounds cool to have a chatbot it doesn't
actually work does it help
and then again the question would be
where does that
apply and potentially it applies in step
one and two right so this starts to give
you you know where can you intervene
some automated things maybe prevention
okay so you're not trying to actually
treat so you don't need a study like
that
but maybe larger longitudinal studies um
and um
so maybe there's relief for some
feedback that the patient can report to
say oh yeah you know i don't feel
stressed as often during the week for
instance
so primary prevention
and then as you go up the spectrum
you're going to have to provide more and
more proof for an app that does
something with somebody who already has
depression who's in between episodes
depression that's hard to treat etc
having problems with access
this is just summarizing what we talked
about
so
hopefully what you've seen so far um as
we've kind of navigated
the problem which starts off with
certain kinds of access issues
um we didn't talk about really equity in
that context that's definitely a big
thing in mental health
uh availability of resources as part of
the access problem
and then
in addition to providing
the
effective
solution to the mental health problem at
the right time and place
um it's engaging with the patient
um
and giving that person
the the kind of the hook the motivation
to get through what they're dealing with
which often comes in a therapeutic
relationship
so
those are the aspects you're trying to
solve for
because the current outcomes are bad
and have gotten worse during the
pandemic
the number of technological solutions
have really skyrocketed
in
many of the assessments we've looked at
those solutions don't seem to
improve over time in the metrics we're
able to look at or
other folks have looked at
um
and
so at this point i think it's important
to go back to concept and design which
wasn't getting a lot of traction in one
of the surveys that we talked about
and start to say what is it we're
solving for
where should this be
in that process of providing mental
health services
and
um
what are the specific problems where
what are the pain points we're trying to
solve for
otherwise
maybe against all odds you even have a
great app that does some really useful
thing
but
if it's not
easy for it to fit into the system then
it's not going to be used
and that's that's no good
so it'll it'll be added to the list of
things out there thousands
that don't make a dent
um
and so and then finally whatever we do
hopefully
improves user engagement like we said
and i think
we've certainly seen that in the
commercial sector
technology companies have been
maybe too good
at
engaging users to various ends
commercial ends and perhaps it's time to
start to use that
brain power
to try to help in mental health
and help folks engage in
treatments and
services that can improve their
well-being so thank you for uh your
attention
thank you so much dr duvari
are there any questions for the cause
so if you have questions maybe you can
enter into the chat room i have one or
two questions so first of all i think
the diagnosis process is really
challenging right a lot of things may be
subjective
we talk about the patients may want to
hide their symptoms right and the second
thing is even like depression depression
unlike uh suppose my glucose level is
high
and you test in the morning in the
afternoon i think level will tend to be
high but depression
the mood can swing right you can say in
the morning i'm okay and often i'm i'm
not so okay
and also i sometimes i can be confused
with the unhappiness unhappiness is uh i
see something i don't like it uh
yeah it's nature to be unhappy
but
unhappiness doesn't mean the person is
in in a depression situation that's not
correct yeah so when the maya when you
say mild depression uh it's kind of
challenging so let me let me wrap up
with the second question because the
purpose of our study mental disorders is
because we want to understand the
interactions between consciousness and
unconsciousness so once we study
some mental disorders
then it's much easier for us to
understand what is normal and
maybe we can
work toward
modeling consciousness
and so for this purpose uh i found uh
deserts work
essentially optogenetics can be really
helpful because we want to see oh when
the person has depression what happened
to the neurons
right
and what are the stimulus and how this
person responds to the neurons and one
of his chapter talking about eating
disorder it's kind of scary to me at the
same time
i think promising there because
it seems like he was saying okay when a
person has mental dis
eating disorder a normal person because
evolution teaches us we have to eat
otherwise we will die right evolution
means uh the purpose of evolution is
survival first
and then we want to want to just
reproduction so that you can continue so
survival is our nature to say i don't
want to eat right so when you have urge
to eat and this is starting from
unconsciousness we we don't
try to sense whether i'm hungry or not
right because physical condition
triggers my awareness of
being hungry
and now there's a second set of neurons
in his book he say well
it happens
a set of neurons get recruited to come
in to say no you don't want to eat
because
you are going to get fed and you are
going to be right right and this second
set of neurons
because we often say well this person
has two identities in the body you know
in the past i couldn't understand what's
going on he said oh this person is evil
processed
but when when deserts were saying
actually not really because yourself is
somewhere in the brain
but when this and another cluster of
neuron got recruited uh this set of
neurons tend to be in your neocortex
only human being has neocortex right
animals
only advanced beams have neural cortex
so there's these castle neurons
ask you not to eat
and this is in the separate cluster of
neurons so oh then i kind of agree i say
okay one cell neuron is your set
yourself the other set of neurons is
another personality
and sometimes the second person comes
out sometimes
yourself is dominating yeah it's not a
picture this kind of what do you mean
about evil story
from this video
yeah i mean i think they're just like
other mysteries in science or society
that
you know people
uh used either nature or superstition to
explain i think this this fits right so
for instance you could imagine somebody
who has an epileptic seizure
as being one version of possessed you
know it's somebody who
shakes violently has foaming in their
mouth and you know i mean that's sort of
like oh you know how do you make sense
of this
um and and you can make a story as to
why that person is doing it and maybe
there's cause and effect as opposed to a
brain
uh disorder similarly uh somebody who
suddenly
you know is presenting a psychotic
southern suddenly to you maybe it's
quietly been building
similarly with eating disorders
um you know in treatment we'll often
refer to refer to that aspect as the
eating disorder voice right and and and
one of the critical aspects of treatment
is separation from the eating disorder
voice so is that person able to observe
this eating disorder voice not be
one with it and then influence how they
cope and then ultimately overcome it
so
absolutely if we're if we dial the clock
back probably not that long ago
you're you're basically exercising
demons i mean
there is
not a long
gap
between those concepts yeah these are
this one's promises
if you know where
your your class of neurons your demon
are or is
they and using
uh optogenetics you can turn them off
you can turn them turn the turn the
neurons off that's interesting anyway so
so uh because of starting consciousness
uh one relevant topic would be dementia
or alzheimer's diseases or maybe uh
artisan right
so for dementia this is getting worse
and worse because we are living longer
and longer
and how to keep your neuron uh healthy
and why people lose their memory and
this is one another phenomena is uh a
lot of a lot of kids will say well my
parents get into dementia but my parents
can can recognize the chao givers but
they cannot recognize me right that's
kind of very very sad
but but if you really know how the
neurons work for memory that could be
explained and that's actually quite
interesting so we are trying to study
all these
interesting topics yes yeah yeah no i
think i think there's a
there is basically this
potential uh to tease apart the layers
of memory because you could think that
you know maybe
you know at least in clinical experience
the so-called autobiographical memories
and tends to persist for a long time
uh even when you're losing short-term
memory so building new memories and so
yeah maybe it's possible that we can
learn
the structure of that to the point where
you can sort of see oh look there's this
layering of how
uh you know maybe not physically but
conceptually there's this layering of
how memories are put into place
uh over autobiographical time
uh as one concept or maybe you know
other people have other
structured ways of looking at this as in
uh you know there's short-term memories
that need to go through this process to
become consolidated and once they're
consolidated they're a little less
perturbable whereas if it's in the short
term period then there's a lot you can
do to it so there are different
constructs of how they've been modeled
uh so to your point i think as that can
be tweaked more whether it's with
optogenetics or other tools
we might be able to tell
and then similarly
i think for any range of things in
psychiatry where
essentially you're looking at a break
from reality right so psychosis is
obviously a clear example eating
disorder is another version of that
which is in some ways
very curious because
that person is not psychotic in the
general sense
they're perfectly fine in terms of being
able to tell reality from not in all
these different ways except for this one
aspect
so
how do you do that in the architecture
of the brain right
where you would think if you're breaking
from reality that really needs to be
this general phenomenon
that but in fact that doesn't seem to be
the case so yeah i i agree with you i
think as as you can tease apart um some
of those contract constructs it may
start to give you maybe a fundamental
uh
set
of circuits that are kind of our
baseline
uh way of keeping the brain functional
and aware and all the characteristics
that people talk about when they talk
about consciousness uh
and then maybe
uh
a lot of the day-to-day behaviors and
functions we think about are actually
overlays
uh they're they're not kind of the
essential aspects of consciousness
they're are sort of these
not quite extra but additional
uh layers and so maybe psychiatry by
kind of
pulling off some of those functions in
these different
disorders is able to
inform because then that common
set of inter the intersection set will
basically tell you okay all of these
things have consciousness
so which means that as you delete these
various things
whatever you then delete and still
retain consciousness is actually
informing you about what is that
that intersection
um
that maybe helps you to find at least
some circuits um and then go from there
yeah no fascinating yes so thank you so
much dr davari and dr daryl will come
back in nine days
to wrap up uh the part of psychiatry
and if you have any questions just maybe
send me your questions i can aggregate
them and look forward to dr duvari thank
you so much and
i will see you on thursday next week
all right
okay bye