welcome again to cs 372
this is the final
lecture of this quarter
and
before the lecture i did a survey asking
what topics now will be of your interest
and use suggested i should cover privacy
preserving machine learning
and i think i agree because privacy
preservation
is an important topic and you must heard
about gdpr this is the european
privacy act
and in the medical domain we have had
gpa for some years
and the california last year passed and
also put into practice ccpa
and one important element is
and not only
you want to allow user to do
explicit up in
and up out certain items right
and you have to be able to prove
you have done so
and a lot of time a company can just say
yes this is the policy we have we have
informed
the users and yes they can press the
button to open up about
but you have no idea what's really
behind
the screen so the key is
must be verifiable and then you need to
the company to prove to in the court
they really have done what they have
promised
so the details will be covered in
today's lecture
and let me make two announcements
and our final project presentation we
have uh scheduled beyond the stack
select channel and make sure you are
present on this wednesday and
i'm looking forward to
a wonderful presentation of yours
and
regarding
a project suggestion
put
all our electric material together to
develop a caring agent for example we do
health care caring for elderly
in the nursing home and building a robot
using the technologies we cover like
virtual assistant
by making the dialogue between a patient
and a caregiver
a really
caring as we said
lobbying means you make
another person a better version of him
or herself
and i would put materials together
and we can work on this interesting
project
as an optional
project in the summer
and now let me project
the slides of today and let's get
started
okay today's outline we are going to
start cover the major concerns about
privacy from users perspective and also
from
companies perspectives
and the privacy regulations the key
regulations are ccpa and gdpr and we
plan to explain them in details
and also in the medical domain right we
have we have
another set of regulations
but they are pretty similar
then from these compliance requirements
if we cannot comply as a company the
company may be fined heavily so we have
to understand the complex requirement
and convert the requirement into
execution requirements
and we must have heard about
like federated learning or differential
learning
will those
implementation fulfill the regulation
requirements or not
i personally consider they are not
adequate
but it's really hard to say until
the company and
was a company will be brought to the
lawsuit situation the court eventually
will clarify
the boundary of the regulations
so we enumerate three major technical
approaches
to be able to preserve privacy
and finally uh i mentioned is the
standard system called saltaria it's
called developed by
by stanford and also my previous
colleagues
and use this blockchain
to safeguarding privacy
so privacy for sure we know that they
said using cell phone using laptop
whatever information we enter
we will be tracked right so there's a
trade-off between free usage
applications and you have to give us
something
and in certain situations
if you don't give up your information
the application cannot be run like
google maps right google maps you say i
want to about
location tracking then good luck
it just cannot be functioning so but
other applications like news so i i'm
consulting a japanese company right now
and they are worried about if they track
your reading patterns uh what will be
the regulation ramifications right so in
certain applications the
yes or no between yes or no the
boundaries is kind of tricky
and the sale giant vehicle for sure
he has been collecting tons of data and
take tesla as an example if you see the
fine print behind the vehicle you can
see uh it collects your
battery status temperature inside
outside your location
also in this level two
cell driving they have to track the
user's status right if a user is dozing
off
they quickly they will just turn off
self-driving mode
and all those information potentially
where you are and what is your
conversation even in the car uh they
will track and for instance if you are
in they say in some countries you get
into a taxi and everything uh you you
kind of conduct in that tennessee
in that space
uh
it's not personal information it's
actually private and so when we talk
about health care we introduce this
tricorder device with the number of
medical iots
and all those information such as
the
walking pattern and the the ecg
information on apple watch right those
data
is being collected and utilized
and uh frankly i have no idea who is
using my
ecg data and will
apple
resell my data to
other companies
at this point i'm just totally clueless
right so it would be nice to be informed
what kind of data is being collected
from me
and
to to which party the data will be sold
although as part of stanford over we're
doing this virtual system and virtual
system will become more and more popular
even you don't have a speaker just talk
to
your computer through siri
information is being collected and all
these speakers
suppose we turn them off they are still
sort of listening right because they
need to be be waken up to perform their
duties
so conversations at home uh will be
recorded so one situation i got into
this was about a week ago i went up to
the dish and i came home and i i feel i
feel my knees were hurting
so i i on the one hand i'm searching for
remedies for uh
hitting my knees
at the same time i also talked to my
wife about the situation
and suddenly facebook uh prompt this
video to me so that was very spooky
right uh so this could be one of two
situations one was
facebook sue uh
macbook
was listening to me
and the second thing is maybe i was
typing something in real time the
information was transmitted to facebook
and facebook do this kind of real-time
matching
so this is uh to me it's a kind of
horrible experience means well in real
time people can target me uh
or you can say this is a blessing i have
this health health concern and someone
is really caring for me
so
top consumer privacy concerns so yes i
do have a lot of concerns this is a
survey uh conducted by uh some agencies
and you can search all these kind of
different surveys on the internet so i
summarized some key concerns one is
definitely identity
theft
it's not really changing these days even
you say i want to anonymize myself
but still
do cross-court correlation
uh the if people really want to target
you individually
they could get your
pi information personal identifying the
information
and the private data then will be made
public and this is
really bad for especially politicians
even for us right it's not a glamorous
government glimmer situation
and data can be sold and distributed
without our knowledge and certain data
especially medical data could be
valuable so when data been sold uh
people will be willing to sell the data
for revenue or for charity but they'd
like to know
the fact the data has been used
and the safety if my location can always
be tracked
then if people want to uh impose harm
to myself and that that's kind of
not a converting situation so let's
enumerate some details of ccpa and the
gdpr regulations so gdpr
was established by
european union and ccpa was passed by
california congress
uh about two years ago then the was
become active
january
and they gave all the companies some
great spirit to implement it
and currently as i
if if my information is not obsolete
means if a consumer asks for certain
privacy related actions
uh to be conducted by a company let's
say erase my ss history the company has
to respond in about three months
so
because the regulation was just uh was
just out there last year so therefore
they gave this long grace period for all
the companies to get their ad together
and recently
when you access certain sites you
started to get a pop-up like can i use
your cookie can i track your cookie and
so on so forth those are pretty much
because of a ccpa
and
lawyers agree ccpa although was
initiated in california but will be
widely adopted by other states very very
soon
so like i mentioned
ccpa started last year
and some terms let's
define them so when we discuss all the
implementations we will be on the same
page so here we say person person we
talk about uh
juris prudence uh nature person just
like
the person with with the body
with temperature right it's not like a
business business kind of unit
so
personal information
defined by information that can identify
or relates to describes
is reasonable capable of being
associated with
a real person okay so this
kind of personal information could
include my address
ids
and
several other things and we talk about
more in later slides
and then
to
store the data imagine data
we divide the people into uh kind of
three two or three categories one is the
people need to match data right data we
call data subject
and the data controller
is a person who determines the process
of managing the data and set up the sop
standard operation process for
processing data and data processors
are the people who are instructed by
data controllers to process the data so
basically you have controller and
processor they play different roles
okay
and the
pi personal information is divided by
a few categories one is personal
information strictly prohibited to
disclose including a person's religion
genetics biometric
health healthcare data and ids
and there there are more
and some data
they are anonymized
right so suppose you have a database
storing a person's name
and then all the personal information
plus their access history ss means i say
i access a news
website the access history will be all
the news i have read in the last let's
say several weeks
so you like to be able to anonymize
not really the assets patterns but my pi
personal information need to be
anonymized
and another category is pseudo
anonymized so even let's say you
anonymize
my record but still
using some mechanisms i can still
re-engineering or re-identify identify
that person right i will give an example
shortly so basically suppose i have your
address
and
that's very very simple i have your
gender and maybe your working location
maybe it's not too hard to pin down
your identity even not yourself per se
but can profile you into a specific
group
so
this is a example
suppose you have
data stored
by let's say facebook or google
and they need to worry about two things
one is how to store data
and
the second thing is how the data will be
accessed right and the storage because
when you store data data will be used so
how the data gets stored can affect
privacy
so let's say you have your
database table
which consists of
personal
information and like i mentioned some ss
history you have to separate the two
into two tables and do it to a join
and the only data controller can see
both tables and the data processor
can only touch on
the table with only data data history
but without bi information okay so you
kind of reduce the
number of people who can touch the pi
information
and oh
even let's say data controller can
access pi information and all the
accesses must be logged
and logged on indebtable record for
future audit
so here one important point uh sticks
out is indelible record
for audit
and the auditing process must be
transparent
and must be
trusted and all the actions done by this
dc
and also
need to be provable right so you say
yeah i did it i did this and that but
that's your verbal cleanse
but when fcc audits a company they want
to see
provable evidence
so privacy
governance and the
policy
clearly returned to cover the following
so i will talk about
gdpr and ccpa separately but they are
very similar
only about one or two items
they are they have slight differences
so the policy clearly written
just sent to the user user need to
consent the policy has to cover
what data the site
collects from the user
and the collection method mechanism how
data will be used
and what the user will receive as an
exchange right so for example your you
would give
more accurate ads as an exchange whether
you like it or not you can make a
decision
and
where the data has been stored
and where the data be shared and share
with them so this required information
must be stated in in the privacy policy
and
some consent must be
is pleasingly given by the data subject
and you cannot say i give you this
policy with 10 items
and then you say well you have to agree
with either or or nothing
so the key thing here is that by default
all the items will be opt out
and we have to itemize each collected
data item separately
and then there's no bundle agreement and
the user has to to click each one of
them to say yeah either i accept your
collection of my data collecting my data
or not right so
no box
can be pre-checked and the option is up
out
and the user can come in to select the
items they feel comfortable about and
they can always come back to
about okay
so everything has to be done explicitly
that's the key so unlike currently
many many consumer activities you will
be given a huge or
a huge huge deck of documents and you
you are required to sign to finish
signing within 10 or 20 minutes right
especially let's say you
buy a house or you can even buy a car
and the contract agreement
a few pages and you just cannot see all
the details of or fine prints
within
the the pressure timing
okay the second uh
information pieces specifically cover
gdpr it's european regulations and the
consumer has right to
kind of inform right any data
being assets must be
be told and the right of assets must be
granted by the user and right the user
has right to erase to be forgotten and
right of data probability if i want to
move my data from hospital a to hospital
b b you you cannot say no you have to
let me do it right to restrict data
processing and write to object and data
processing can you you can you can even
be very specific saying okay my gender
information or my age information
should not be revealed
right to
rectification it means i can make
changes to my personal information and
right to reject automated individual
decision making or profiling or even as
targeting
and ccpa
as i said
the
b of rights are very similar to gdpr
except for two items so i highlight in
in red
the first here is know whether their
personal data is sold or disclosed and
if so to whom okay and gdpr didn't say
not specifically but ccpa is saying well
if your data has been sold you have to
tell the the owner it's basically and
this is probably because of the the a
few problems happen
in in the past years and i have
some examples to show you uh shortly
and the final one is it's a little bit
dicey it's got
not to be
discriminated
and i couldn't understand it until uh
the the company's smart news and try to
implement the privacy
rules so
so smart news in the usually say well
our privacy data stored in the backend
is very convoluted
so if we really need to be in compliance
then we have to
redesign the database schemas we have to
do this data
downloading reloading this will take
some time so why don't we do a shortcut
we just tell the users who
up out this kind of access
data agreement we just say okay sorry
you cannot use our application anymore
and they basically install them they
install their applications from their
phone or from your desktop
and from ccps percent perspective you
cannot do that because this means you
are discriminating certain
users they are not waiting
to let you collect their data
but why this is very kind of dicey
because suppose uh
in the situation of
google maps right so you say okay i'm
not going to allow you to track my
location so you say oh then i cannot
give you a driving direction
that's not really discriminating against
you that's i cannot serve you because i
don't have certain information about
your
your situation there's no way i can give
you a reasonable prediction of your of
your next driving uh direction so
another scenario you can say the
opposite let's say i have this
application i want to charge you for
let's say subscription fee 10
a month
but if you allow me to access your data
then it's free
so then then this if you if you have
this kind of kind of over
it's hard to say whether you are
discriminating against a user or not
right so all these kind of boundary
conditions uh we can interpret right now
but eventually will be interpreted by
the law of
the core of the law
so finally a very subtle point but it's
extremely critical is i'm not going to
read redesign all details the critical
thing is you have to be able to
write all your privacy safeguarding
actions
somewhere
and eventually
your actions have to be provable
so give you example this a person x
requested company y to erase is or
probably consent via email
and companywide did not fulfill the
request and but claim they claim that
they have done the request right so you
say okay you raise my data i say oh i
did it but i actually did not so how can
you prove it and you can get into this
uh he says she say situation that would
be very convoluted
so the law requires
the company has to be able to prove
they have done all the processes to
safeguarding the user's privacy so let's
come back and talk about probability
in the end
and these are some landmark cases of
privacy positive violation
and the consequences
on the top row
you see in the beginning or
maybe a couple of years ago
uber was fined for 148 million by eu so
the top line was a violation of
gdpr
and then there was a
230 million dollars fine
uh
from british airway
and the most recent one was ftc
versus facebook and facebook was fined
by five billion
dollars
and the
the bottom is of course is the case
happened just last year
uh ftc
brought a lawsuit against
google youtube and google youtube did
not send consent
to children's parent for accessing
children's data right so this is also
kind of complicated because for minors
uh they don't have even they say well i
agree you collect my data but they don't
really have they do they don't have a
sufficient uh ability to make such a
judgment so the consent should be sent
to parents
then this was google was flying by 170
million dollars
so a very
uh tricky situation here was
some company they would say okay i get
fined by
ftc or some agencies for millions of
dollars
but on the other hand
because of the information i can earn
billions of dollars
so
for some companies they will say
well
this is cost of sales
i don't know whether you have heard
about this term or not um like one
example i can provide is
like
google use page rank in the beginning
and then they do this
adwords right if you you can buy words
on search terms on google
and the patents of adwords was owned by
the european company
so if you
implement it without licensing then
you'll be fined heavily
but if you
want to license it and there's a cost so
how can you deal with the situation
right so that's
when that happens that's a consideration
i'll say yeah let me let me just violate
it
if uh
it's not working then i just uh during
this kind of disagreement or dispute i
can just drop it but if i make huge
profit about it then i i can just pay
the fine because at the end i'm earning
more than then
my my loss
so that was very uh that kind of act was
very
not ethical but
it's it's actually in practice
okay
now we want to say you talk about all
these compliance requirements how can we
implement it and be very careful
there are many methods presented out
there
but os on mine is one
even the policy has been implemented
can private private information still
be
re-identified or
people can do reverse engineer to find
out who you are or which group you
belong to right so that's one thing to
consider the second thing to consider is
again the probability
and trust right so you say you had done
that but
prove me
how did you do it and when did you do it
so
the execution to comply consists of uh
five steps
one is you have to delegate an oversight
committee in a company
so this is just not saying say i have
done that so when ftc orders a company
my previous company was audited by
ftc so when they came in they say hey
give me all the documents to show you do
have oversight committee who they are
and these people do exist okay
and
they they map the data you have
collected to
your usage and storage so where do you
store data can you show us the document
and how the data has been used so it's
definitely hard for fftc to really get
into your database to look around but
they want to see documentations
and then do you have this sop
for your employees
right so all the regulation we talked
about
do you have this compliance process for
your data controller and also data
processors if frankly you don't even
have a process in place then everything
is just talking
and do you have your personnel divided
into
dc and the dp and also specifying their
roles very clearly right
and
sop for serving consumers when consumers
is served did you really give them
this kind of contract to sign so allow
them to operate and about and comply
with all these required items and
finally probability
uh let's look at the technique technical
approaches
so the first one is very
uh understandable you say i just
anonymize the data right then we have
this differential privacy was popular
before cc ccpa
was activated and the federated learning
is still very popular and google was was
pushing that uh pushing this back this
is effort and quite a few papers have
been published uh on this particular
subject then finally talk about
distributed ledgers
so
anonymize versus pseudo
anonymization
there are some subtle differences so
anonymization means if i even i look at
the the data or a sql table i have no
idea who is that particular person so
basically just hide all the personal
identifiable information right so
including a cell already your gender
your profession and so on so forth
so but
even let's say data has been anonymized
uh still
could be re-engineered to find out who
is a person for instance
let's say cell phone will track
my locations so he knows in the day time
i will be in certain locations around
stanford so
for sure i think
the google maps or say oh edward
is affiliated with stanford university
and he lives in palato right and
from the duration i
stay in a particular location they say i
stay in the gates building but
i'm not moving around very frequently i
mean at one spot for more than one hours
so easily to
infer
well maybe you are not a student your
student will be moving around to
different classrooms but maybe you are a
staff or a faculty member right so
if you say oh every
every other days you will show up at a
particular building and for about one
hour and a half now i say okay it's more
likely you are
a professor rather than the staff so see
you have not really disclosed any
information explicitly you only have
this person's moving patterns but
already you got lots of information from
this person right and the another
example is on facebook you say i'm not
going to give you any of my personal
information
including my birthday and where i live
but
unfortunately if you have your social
networks and you are interacting with
people uh
about 20 some years old and they
are college students and most of them
are from ucla
it's not really hard to infer you should
be in in high probability you are ucla
student right then with other
information probably not stored in that
particular app
then people can identify you
so
because i'm in this
news business now you know when you do
ads targeting if you just use the user's
news data itself
so i was joking with our engineers i say
well i
i read uh
election news let's say i'm either pro
republican or pro democrats
just based on either i go to cnn or fox
news can you target me with ads
right this is just ridiculous if i
i'm a democrat do you sell me tesla or
do you want to sell me for
it's not very clear so i said well news
data news reading history
using those to target ads it's kind of
ridiculous but then all companies
would buy information data information
from browsers from other sources
and the facebook information i just gave
you
i was doing a search on google i was not
doing a search on facebook i would never
do a search on facebook saying oh my
knee hurts what should i do i did a
search on google but how come facebook
will pop up this particular ad right so
somewhere someone was collecting
information then they aggregate
all information from all different apps
maybe through the browser or somewhere
then they aggregate and they target
myself so if you just look at one
application you may say oh i'm very safe
no problem
virtually about everything but when i
collaborate with
some other applications then maybe our
pi will be identified
so there are many horrible switch
scenarios you probably can
find on the internet
if a person really want to target you
find who you are
it's not impossible so
so a basic practice is as following uh
like i say if you have a consumer's data
right you want to say i want to separate
the data into two relational relational
database tables and
in one table i can store his or her name
and the personal uh
information or personal identifiable
information and then have a hash id
then using this hash id i can join
another table the key will be hash id
unique hid or you want to say maybe the
hid may not mean to be unique so that's
another way to make sure the data uh you
cannot target one person maybe just a
google person then hash id
has
then indexed to
non-pii information so
the table this second table can be
accessed by a data processor if they
look at the table they look at hash id
they look at all these num pi
information they are fine they are not
able to be able to identify who is doing
what right only data controller oh
he or she can join two tables to know oh
this person with this hash id is edward
so edward has accessed
facebook and google in the last few days
so this is a
very primitive way of
trying to be compliant but for sure
it's not really in fully compliance
so the second
method is differential differential of
privacy this was proposed by
professors in hong kong
ust uh the idea was
i don't really need to separate your api
from your
his access history but i just need to
introduce noise to the data right in
this example here
on the top you see
you have a very specific information
about person including office in london
department i t
date joint
2015 and sell information and so on so
forth right if you get a hold of this
this piece of information
uh in the company if you work in a
company you see this it's probably not
not very challenging to infer who is
this person
so you say okay i'm going to
try to
introduce noise so rather than london i
say well uk
and
they joint i wouldn't want to specify
the the month just a year
then the day of birth i specify and then
maybe just a decade or an hour time but
still this is not booty proof so but
in theory uh differential privacy is
attractive because they can come up with
a
quantifiable method to safeguarding
privacy
and you can see the formula is in the
middle of the screen the idea here there
are two uh parameters one is this uh uh
sigma parameter so they have this sigma
algebra the sigma edgewise i'm going to
introduce introduce to your data certain
noise right so
for particular field we already seen you
say well i'm going to apply this uh
age expansion or
birthday kind of anonymize your year but
we put your day and month over there
this kind of algebra and
then they have these privacy parameters
right they say well it's just like a
newest neighbor search and so last time
we covered newspaper but we didn't
finish we continued next time was when
you do a news neighbor search you don't
get just yourself you get a group of
people so then you say i cannot really
pin you down as
a particular person in a group so this
is this appstore means you can introduce
this epson and
then there's a trade-off here for the
company to decide you see the left-hand
side the trade-off is oh private
private privacy magic so you want to
save guardian privacy then the epsilon
value need to be very small but if you
say well i don't quite care about your
policy i care about uh utility sorry
it's the other way if you want to
safeguarding privacy epsilon value need
to be large so
when you want to
when the information is given you you
identify actually a lot of people not
just a small number of people so it's
hard to pin down one individual and by
the same nice utility metric so if i get
a whole bunch of people here then
these applications suppose i want to do
uh
do a search i want to do information
dissemination recommendation then my
accuracy right the applications target
performance metrics will suffer
and for
any company which needs to
generate revenue the revenue for sure
will go down
so the question here is very very simple
uh
privacy is possible to be implemented
right so you say my privacy regulation
is very loose and comply with privacy
eventually
can be
kind of enhanced but i'm going to lose a
lot of revenue will the company do that
or would they try to do any kind of
circumvention to prevent compounds so
this is a real problem and that's the
reason again probability becomes
important so let's come back to look at
this differential privacy and depends on
how large the epsilon you want it to be
the privacy can be a local privacy or a
global privacy local privacy means okay
i have a small group of people i just
want to
implement this
sigma algebra so magically
alter
their private data then i have an
aggregator and eventually i can store
the data
but
i can make my privacy
slightly more global means i have an
aggregator i already aggregate
information from a large number of users
let's say female or male then i use a
magic formula to alter them right so
then i have this anonymous output and
because the input is a group of people
so it's much harder to track back to
individuals so when you combine both
right suppose i say well your private
data
individual data i'm going to do a
shuffling and then i do another layer i
analyze the shuffling results and
applying even more magic
then i really anonymize every everyone
so the question is let's say the the
final master is probably the most secure
one but
it probably provides uh
the the business usage information
to make their profit right so again this
is a big trade-off situation
so people are trying to
do this differential privacy
uh then
i think it's kind of uh dying out now
it's really hard to prove to an auditor
saying
this is my epsilon this is my sigma
so
this is this is the way i conduct the
business and i prove in theory this will
work but no you cannot prove everything
is done empirically and the even you
show the empirical data and who can
trust you in pure data so harvard
published this uh interesting article
it's interesting but it was not very
sung basically this paper saying well
you you do your differentiate uh
differential
or pseudo
anonymization on the data but we can
re-engineering we identify the users
right so
the experience they did was they get
about 300 users data from the the
medical databases then they say well
everyone was anonymized so let's start
to add additional information let's say
a zip code and date of birth and so on
and so forth at the end they say well we
can identify accurately about 90 of
people
so
i
really i mean i understand this is a
kind of uh uh
interesting result showing the more
personal data you know about a person
you can more accurately infer who the
person is but this is no brander right
so the the change to me was if you only
have 300 pieces with information then
you clam you can identify person 95
accurately i think it's an easy problem
but if you enlarge your pool from 300 to
3 million and i bet even with the zip
code
you cannot do that and if you have day
of birth here frankly
uh even even with 1 million people the
accuracy can still be quite high right
so i respect the paper but
the paper itself didn't really tell me
any promising or exciting methods
so federated learning it started from
google uh
wrote a paper and also a blog introduced
the method the method is very logical so
we all have our
devices our
laptop or cell phone and whatever
personal devices and
we don't
send our private data
to the app to the concluder cloud
so all data mining all this kind of
machine learning will be conducted on
the phone right so after
the machine learning has been conducted
the model has been learned on the phone
then the model will be sent
to the cloud
and the cloud or is the centralized
system then will aggregate all the
information and
develop the global model and the global
model will come back in return compared
to this target
individual cell phones
so on the one hand this is
kind of attractive
on the other hand it also introduces
arrows to the classification
and not only introduce these arrows but
there could be other
problems let's say
what kind of information you aggregate
suppose
i own the android system and or
ios so the amount of data i collect is
not just from one application i actually
call it data from all different
applications
so as i as an example i gave you a few
minutes ago this is even more dangerous
than getting all information from one
applications right one particular
application but you get all information
get information from all applications
then you do
uh
kind of color collaborating among them
and the kind of information you can call
it is just totally horrible
and okay let's look at healthcare as one
example suppose i have a
deep neural net
and
this feature shows there are multiple
layers attention layers and so on so
forth
and the idea of this federative learning
is i'm going to cut off this
multi-layer neural networks into
two parts
right so my animation doesn't work but
actually the key thing is in the middle
here let's say i draw a line in the
middle here
okay okay actually this picture will
show
so i have four hospitals each has been
training the model based on their let's
say x-ray data they want to do this cd
scan or
maybe lung disease
classification
so each hospital have collected certain
data then run their own
training algorithms and then i say okay
i'm going to cut your
neural net into a half
so the top half
so you learn in the middle then i say
stop don't continue learning just ship
me all the model parameters
then you say okay i'm going to continue
learning here in my center database so
you guys stop learning i'm going to
aggregate right so at the bottom here
you show this is a send central
centralized continuous learning and
getting parameters from all different
sites
and
this method seems to be
reasonable
but there are clearly
two shortcomings from medical
perspective
the first shortcoming is
as angeline said
every hospital
may collect data using different process
different devices or even same device
same device with different process or
calibrations
so when you aggregate the parameters in
this subsequent model uh those
parameters may not agree with each other
and that could problematic because
each other will become
your
noisy disturbance rather than trying to
help you so for the test data
that could be this method could be
productive because text it attached is
the text but for imagery this pipeline
may not be able to improve your accuracy
and in practice i see these kind of
methods
it's really hard to be realized because
no hospital here
would trust other hospitals
every hospital consider their own data
to be
to be a piece of gold they don't want to
share with others
so only perhaps
in on android phone or on ios this
federated learning can be conducted but
for health care i have
really strong doubt okay
so problem solved
and i
don't think so and the two key problems
one already
enumerate which is the trade-off between
privacy safeguarding
and the utility to the company or
revenue of the company right this is
always an ethical problem
and
a company
ipo post ipo company they have
obligation to their shareholders and the
ceo is under tremendous pressure to
perform
so i don't know where the
ceo would draw the boundary then the
second challenge is
probability right you can claim anything
but
ccpa now requires a company to prove
so this again this is the picture to
summarize regulations but at the end on
the right hand side is you should be
able to
trust the company and
the company has to be able to prove
their results and the policies
so let me spend the remaining time to
introduce saltaria sautare is the
goddess of greece it's kind of providing
uh individuals safety
and
the
basic idea is we want to lock
everything
including user consent user
revocation
and so all the consumers actions on
their data and all these actions
conducted by the company basically need
to be
hardened
a ledger and this ledger
if you want to be able to be people to
trust the ledger this ad ledger need to
be open transparent to the public
so anyone can audit the ledger if i say
no no this is a centralized system this
is the bank's ledger so you can i i'm
going to log everything but sorry i
cannot allow you to come in to see
the details because i don't want you to
see other people's account balance then
this is a ledger
which is not transparent and cannot
bring people's trust okay so
transparency is the key so that leads to
the centralized and versus decentralized
system the centralized system
by the names basically saying all the
data all the synchronization is
conducted by one unit right let's say a
central bank
or
all the banks in the u.s uh they have
this uh bank
the headquarter bank and all information
need to be synchronized with the
headquarters so when a bank want to
close their books every day they have to
synchronize
from the center to all the distributed
bank bank branches to try to reconcile
their their books and decentralized
means
all individuals
can communicate with each other
and you can
do local decisions but eventually
we need to be able to reach global
agreement okay
so
we come back to see an example is this
centralized banking system uh deposit
withdrawal and so on so forth let's say
i have two atms i'm using two atms from
one atm i
deposit money the other atm i will show
money right so the important thing is
you need to be consistent you cannot say
well before my deposit goes in i already
withdraw my money so i have this kind of
i kind of double deposit whatever this
kind of secret scenario and you know in
the bitcoin situation they want to
safeguarding double spending right you
say i want to use my bitcoin to buy ten
dollars of uh goods in
in one company or one store use the same
bitcoin to buy another thing so there's
a window about
30 minutes for a bitcoin transaction to
be committed within the 30 seconds
a person can double spend and that
problem has to be closed right so
but bitcoin is a decentralized problem
it's much more challenging a centralized
problem but central apartment bank is
one example and another example can be
hospital so you say okay i'm going to
perform certain process on a patient the
information will be stored in the
hospital but eventually the information
had to be sent to who sent to a payer
right sent to an insurance company so
insurance company
pays the bills and
they
pretty much aggregate all the data
together they have all heart skills data
and this is
pretty much universal in canada they
have a universal health care run by the
government the government has to pay the
bills so the government has all the
health care records of the canadian
citizens
now again the question is trust if you
have a centralized system
how can i trust you because you are not
going to reveal me all the actions you
have conducted so
we like to be able to have a
decentralized system so decentralized
system the question then will be you
have certain inconsistency that will
happen you have
local agreement but
globally may not be agreeable so
therefore
consensus protocols need to be executed
so consensus protocol can be separated
into two camps
one is
distributed consensus you could have
local consensus eventually you
convert to global consensus or you just
have a centralized consensus protocol
and centralized consensus protocol has
been out there for many many years
because bank banks or airline
reservation systems have been out there
for more than two decades right
uh for allies airline reservation
systems and uh
when they started about even 20 30 years
ago
even today they haven't
be able to really changing the system
because it's just too many agents try to
access the database and any modification
to the system around into the risk of
data corruption
so we don't get into all these protocols
in in details because we want to stay in
a
on a high level and the server has
courses to cover uh the detailed message
and when i was back in the cs department
20 years ago there was a database course
then there was a transaction processing
course and the transaction partnering
costs will cover
all these
protocols to safeguarding agreement
so let me just give you an example this
is a rudimental consensus protocol talk
or two-phase commit protocol
so i have my
participants right and eventually i need
to make a decision so let's say
i want to
have a consensus with in the class to
say when are we going to do our this
hypothetically when are we going to do
our final exam and then i send send now
two dates one is next tuesday another
one next thursday then
students start to vote right so
once i get all the votes i say okay
majority people vote for
thursday so i always say i will return
back to you to say okay now i'm prepared
to come commit because our rule is
majority wings
and then the decision in the decision
phase the student will say
yeah i was i was saying tuesday i prefer
but now
the
kind of
a majority decision thursday so i'm
going to okay
commit i'm going to decide to commit so
you have second phase of communication
so in the two-phase commit protocol here
you see the overhead
is the number of messages going back and
forth to reach consensus
and if the number of participants is
small and you have this kind of
centralized system
and the cost is linear to the number of
participants right say i have 10
students and maybe the message will be
sending back and forth 40 times because
the two-way messages for each face
but then when you say i want to do
a global but decentralized kind of
company protocol
then the cost will be much much higher
will be n square right so everyone has
to be able to talk to everyone in in the
most general situation and this is not
affordable now you say well on the one
hand i want to be transparent i want
each person to be able to make their
kind of own decision they can look at
other people's data but on the other
hand i have this kind of enormous cost
how can i mitigate or i do the
reasonable trade-off and the trade-off
easy to understand here is i'm not going
to talk to it to everyone although i
want to do decentralized system but i'm
going to talk talk to just a group of
people right a group of people who i can
trust they say
i when i want to make a commit decision
or when i say i want to sell my medical
data record to sahil and
this agreement
only need to be approved or been seen by
let's say a
bank of america and maybe tesla only
three because why i don't think they
together have any interest to con
conspire together to kind of hear me
right so i say okay that's good enough
three participants to vote for years now
i can move on and
so this is a kind of compromise
but also reasonable right but if you say
i'm going to randomly select uh a few
then the situation will be much more
dicey
so just sorry talk about the bitcoin
situation bitcoin is entirely
decentralized
and they say oh
if two-thirds of people
are voting saying your transaction is
hard it's just just an example or
when they start to build new blocks
right so when the new boss has been
granted has been committed they have
this kind of longest block uh will win
now this condition so you have a block
which is six blocks
longer
you have a chat which is six longer than
the other chain then all the previous
blocks will be hardened or
will be granted or be committed but this
will take some time right and
they don't actually identify who are the
people who can make a block
committed so it's like racing you have
to solve a puzzle and when a large
number of people solve a puzzle then the
block is kind of hardened and
so who can solve the possible is random
and they say even you say two-thirds or
one-half the people in this two-third
and one-half one-half one-half pool they
are random you don't know whether they
can be trusted or not trusted so
eventually you know uh
some powerful uh
kind of resource company they actually
can hack down a bitcoin because they can
own the majority of gpu in the world and
they can be
the majority of this kind of voting
scenario right so
instead of doing that kind of so
uh expensive computation why not just
saying oh i'm not going to send to 1
billion people i'm going to get these 10
people right uh these 10 people have
confirmed interest with each other if
they saw it or say yes then that's fine
with me so that's pretty much ideal be
between a centralized decentralized and
decentralized you have this n square
messaging cost and extra messaging cost
is huge because you know i o is much
more expensive than cpu or gpu time
computational time
so
that would just grind your system to a
halt
again the trade-off will be okay i'm not
going to talk to n
i'm going to talk uh just a small subset
of n
so this decentralized
uh
picture shows the trade-off between cost
and the trust between transparency again
and the trust and there are so many
different protocols recently got
proposed
to be able to achieve a very good
compromise between the two so what do i
say good compromise really depends on
the applications objective okay i can
again give you a couple examples shortly
so
consensus versus
transparency
in the privacy situation uh all the
actions like what can the data allow the
consumer to be uh processed by the by
the by the business and the the contract
often about information and
rectification all the information need
to be transparent to the public so can
be audited
and using blockchain to solve the
problem first of all let's quickly
identify
the structure of blockchain so a chain
of blocks let's say
h is the height means i have edge
individual blocks
and every block
may consist of a number of transactions
right in the transaction is in the sense
of bank is straight forward deposit and
uh maybe withdraw or i look at my
account history in the case of privacy
every transaction is like oh user
account a user is consent user b's
revocation and uh
business a access user b's data right
those are the transactions upon your
data subject will all be locked on the
blockchain
so this is one example or in one single
block of the chain
and the transactions are organized
into a merkle tree
so the characteristic of merkel trees if
you change one of
the leaf
and then the hash value in the merkle
tree will be modified so why we call
this indelible because no one can come
here to hack your data if someone did
then the hashing value will be
mismatched
and we can identify
and then this is like a binary tree
eventually going up to the top and we
have this root hash which is usually
easily to authenticate this block is not
contaminated then this block has a
hash index to the previous hash block so
when we in in the index all together you
can see the blockchain has a number of
blocks they are linked together with
this kind of previous uh
previous head address and every block
has a the number of transactions
organized in this merkle tree and it's
very evident why you only have a pointer
to the previous plot because you have no
idea when you establish a plot you have
no idea when the next flow will be will
be established
so
key requirements here i'm not going to
repeat transparency and the privacy and
probability so now let's let's step back
to see how the blockchain can be
utilized efficiently because i talk
about bitcoin and you know bitcoin very
well
it's the problem is it's latency right
latency of bitcoin means i
need to trust a transaction but i need
to wait for about uh
half an hour because unless the
transaction
uh the the block which the transaction
resides get committed
and in addition
that particular block resides in a
blockchain which has a length six more
blocks than the second longest one then
i would say okay my transaction has been
hardened and this will take half an hour
and this is a pretty long time if you
want to do this half an hour transaction
then payment is impossible you do
payment you go to stock box you say i'm
going to use use blockchain to pay my
bill the commit time is a six hours so i
think starbucks wouldn't accept your
payment so
like privacy or like uh
currency if you want to use this kind of
bitcoin methodologies something has to
change
and this is the way we did it so before
we get into detail let's look at this
eric poor's cap theorem cap ca p c
stands for consistency
so
data viewed by different parties need to
be consistent in the same order right
you say i withdraw then i i deposit
other people look at the record they
want to see we saw deposit they want to
see the other way then you have this
inconsistent problem availability is
another one you want the system to be up
all the time so this is like the cell
phone networks so if if my if i shut
down my cell phone now it shouldn't
affect your your cell phone right it's
very easy to understand because you want
your cell phone to be available not
depending on other people's cell phones
and the partition tolerance
and in the banking system partition
tolerance is not allowed but
in our cell phone scenario general
network scenario internet partition
tolerance should be
allowed otherwise
if my laptop is done your letter needs
to be in a standby mode that's not
acceptable so
if we look at this picture then we say
well in the internet era if we want to
do a distribute system
this is one property we cannot sacrifice
right which is partition tolerant okay
we have to safeguarding this uh
partition torrent property which is p
but now since every poor theory is
saying you can only
ensure two out of three properties can
be guaranteed at a simultaneous at one
one time so either you choose uh
cp or you choose
a ca
a pa pa
or only two other three or ca
the the banks choose ca right they don't
care about partition tolerance if
there's a partition they shut down the
system right away they guarantee
consistency and when the system is
consistent they open up they
they make sure it's a scalable available
so
decentralized system as i just
summarized we need to provide people
just either cp or ap for the sake of
bitcoin they provide this
a
and amp because bitcoin want to be
available all the time and they want to
also allow a network to be partitioned
but they sacrifice
consistency as i again just mentioned we
think about six hours or half an hour
depending on the situation your
transaction was in an inconsistent state
so double spending could
happen
and uh summarize bitcoin's problem
one is it's very expensive to maintain
such a blockchain and one billion
dollars a year and the lack of privacy
why because you put data on the chair
so now you say edward are you kidding
you want to put medical data on the
chain
so you want to put medical data in the
public
so i will come back to address the issue
shortly and
use a pos proof of work protocol means
you want to solve a parcel and nuance
it's very expensive and uh finally low
throughput right transaction per second
for bitcoin is only seven transactions
per second the ethereum is 15
not much better
so we if we utilize that to be a payment
that's impossible and if we want to
utilize for
security privacy preservation
that's kind of also not very convenient
but we can solve the problem so banking
i talked about the centralized system
using ca
and we also already discussed the
trade-off between
centralized and decentralized
consensus protocols
and then let's look at soteria how can
you implement a system which is
at the same time can ensure this uh ap
ap kind of property also can ensure uh
pc my pc and pa at the same time so pc
and pa if you union a tube
you become pca
the trick here is we want to be able to
achieve short latency like one to two
minutes and the super need to be
extremely high and we are arguing
this is actually argued by professor uh
measures
professor measures by the way
he was one of founders of
stellar a standard or the ipo
is maybe number eight
the
public published company probably ibo
company on blockchains
and
he he and us had many many interesting
debates so basically i say okay let's
have this two-layer ball chain so you
have men chen insures ap properties in
the worst case manchester ethereum it's
in the public domain but the side chain
will be on the ca using ca property
right we are using uh cp property is
also okay so the side chain will be
very very quick but the mention will be
very slow
so
this is the picture or sidechain let's
say even using cs system the mention is
using this is a ap system we organize
them into three layers
the first layer is a public chain with
very slow
response time and high latency
and the second layer with very fast
execution time low latency and high
throughput the method to improve super
is like david measure said you just
replicate your cpu right you just
improve just duplicate your local system
and i only care about latency you want
to guarantee latency then when you want
to guarantee super if you have
sufficient business you just replicate
your system so that's a claim by
professor david measures and we have to
agree with him and finally you have this
smart contract which is the way to not
to put data on the blockchain but you
put contract on the blockchain even more
beautifully
the contrast is in
nature language so if you say i put uh
something on the blockchain which is my
private data is is really bad if i put a
digital contract which is a piece of
code on the blockchain in fact
we will be eventually put a piece of
code
on the blockchain let's say i want to
access your data and this is a agreement
in nature language but we need to be
able to convert this nature language
statement to a piece of restful api or
sql statement let's say fetch
something from
relational database k
with attribute equal to what right so
with this particular piece of code but
already approved then certain people can
just
execute the code to get your data so
smart contract is a very important piece
of information sitting here for two
reasons one through nature language user
can understand what they are up to then
we convert the piece of
information into a piece of code and
this conversion i pretty much covered
when i talked about oval right we had a
lecture about this uh
human
voice speech interface and in that i
talked about in alvo and we need to do
semantic grounding so many grounding in
principle is very challenging but if you
want to just go on into programs it's
much easier because programs only have a
small number of instructions and also
they are not ambiguous right in nature
language a word can mean multiple
meanings you have polygamy or other
situations but in code when you say
write is right when you say move it's
move so
smart contract is the good solution
so smart contract summarizes it it's a
piece of nature language construct to
convert to a code and the data is
offline retrieved by
approved code and the contract
validation relocation execution will
generate transactions and these
transactions will be written onto the
blockchain so when you look at a
blockchain you you do see oh i have a
piece of code executed but the code
number is 722 you have this id and then
you have
transactions to form a tree and
the root of the merkle tree on the sub
chain right we say sub chain will be
very efficient but you say okay i make
the subject very efficient
but the root of the
merkle tree i lock it to the main chain
so when i
lock the secondary route to the main
chain the process will suffer from low
tendency but it's okay right because i
can
locally guarantee
the transaction has been hardened
but probability can be done
can be guaranteed maybe half an hour
later
so
this is a sabato acceptable to the
private situation because even i want to
steal a company i cannot file a lawsuit
within
within half an hour right so i do have
half an hour probably if you want to
contact a lawyer to find a lawsuit that
would probably take a few days so this
hierarchical architecture is just
beautiful you can accomplish the
objectives to summarize
we have this
on a side chain we have
hash blocks
and they got they got linked together
and they enjoy the performance of high
throughput because you can replicate the
systems and more importantly low latency
and the privacy is safeguarded because
we don't store data on the blockchain we
only store uh the id of the code on the
blockchain data is in the database
access to
the code and then we hash
the root of the local merkle tree to the
global uh blockchain so
when the public auditing
when the public audit is is conducted
they can go back to the global uh
global blockchain to verify the local
mercury hash value is not altered right
this
ensure
often authenticality
so this picture just to complete when we
implement system we still need to have a
reasonable user interface if you'd like
to know the details you can look into
our publication available
on the internet let me get into slightly
more details
see on the left-hand side right you have
interface here
both data consumer data provider
can access through the web and the data
provider let's say i'm a patient i can
say okay i have a data my x-ray i'm
willing to sell my data at the price and
data consumer comes in to say this maybe
a pharmaceutical company say i like to
be able to beat uh 20 pieces of data in
a particular situation or i say i want
to do irb i want to do
some job discovery or or vaccine tests i
need to recoup 10 10 million people or
10 000 people i can go through the
system and say who willing to give me
your vaccine
drug interaction or side effect data so
then this agreement can be conducted
through the web application so once the
consensus have been performed then the
data will be stored right into the
database at the same time the blockchain
will be also locked on the blockchain
and then when the audit comes in is the
bottom is audit audit comes in you can
look into the local database which
caches the blockchain's information and
right away i can say well
the company already fulfilled your
requirement and this is the information
i can give you right away the response
time for this ats cache tell me just
within seconds then they say no i don't
trust you i want to go to the core to
verify then the core will not access the
company's private data here storing the
cache the core will go to zotero which
is a transparent public ledger and the
court or auditor can go there to access
the all the transaction transactional
information
and this is a picture
thanks to professor david measures
monica and the shivaya in ntu and we try
many different local protocols and
eventually we identify stellar and
tender mean those are two
good protocols we can employ
and uh
there's a very strong argument from
professor david measures he's a
no-nonsense guy he said
why do you guys want to use blockchain
because i can see this entire system can
be implemented by a log only
method it's just log right you just
logging why do you need to
ensure
consistency in this whole thing this is
not payment
and we do have a very good counter
argument the counter argument
ceased
uh is concerned so if you have time to
think about it
why
we need to have
consensus on consistency on the order of
transaction in the privacy preservation
scenario
you know it's an interesting question to
think about
uh so we
did some experiment we conducted but the
details uh again refer to our
publications so summarize today's
lecture lecture
privacy is very critical if you started
the company you want to be able to
consider privacy before ipos right or
the lawsuit wouldn't come in when you
are a curry company but when you go
public the next day you see a number of
uh
a number of letters from lawyers
and compass requirement
and
also some solutions they are
complementary right you can use them in
a combined method but the ndm
probability transparency
they must be safeguarded
and
with this concludes today's lecture uh
you have questions please ask on the
slack
and this concludes the lecture today
and
tomorrow i am going to host an office
hour as scheduled and announced and then
next week we look forward to
seeing your project presentations
and thank you and
go back