so welcome to
cs 372 and today we
are very glad to be able to invite uh
professor melissa gao to come back to
give us a lecture on cancer
biology again uh i met melissa about two
years ago
i took her course it stands for
continuous
study session and then last year we
invited melissa to give us
two lectures and i learned a lot from
from her
and she graduated from mit in major in
biology
then finish her cancer biology phd
program
at stanford and she's right now a fellow
of
science and engineering education so
melissa please
just take over thank you so much yeah
thank you for having me again
uh welcome everyone good morning hope
you're doing well
uh yeah so this is the first of a
two-part little series that i'll be
doing um
this thursday and then also next
thursday just really thinking about
cancer i will give an introduction to a
lot of aspects of cancer that are
important so if you don't have a lot of
biology
background i'll try to provide the
context that you need
but we will look at sort of the front
end of cancer which is how it's caused
how it's diagnosed and then next
thursday we'll focus a lot more on
how do we then treat it based on all
this stuff that we've learned from it
so the agenda for today is i do want to
give you sort of the background that
you'll need so thinking about how cancer
is caused we'll talk about things like
carcinogens and mutagens um we'll talk
about the genetics of
cancer so thinking about how
mutations in genes contribute to cancer
which is
how it contributes to cells acting
really abnormally
and becoming what we think of as
cancerous and all those sort of
traits associated with cancer cells so
we'll connect
the genes themselves to what cancer
actually
does and how it acts um and then we'll
start getting into like with all of that
sort of foundation we'll start getting
into the more data-driven side so we'll
talk about the different ways that we
characterize cancer
through data and thinking about how we
diagnose cancer and how those two relate
so how do we use
lots of different big data and big data
methods
to maybe diagnose cancer better either
more accurately
um earlier or as we'll get to
next week like diagnose it with an eye
towards treating it better so that's
really the goal for today and then as i
said next week we'll focus much more on
the treatment piece
and also next week there's a lot of sort
of open-endedness for people who have
questions or they just want to ask about
connecting you know if you're
more from a cs engineering side like how
do you connect to
careers that relate to this kind of work
um so just a little bit about me um
thanks for the introduction so
i'm sharing a little bit more about
myself so i'm a local
i grew up in the california bay area i
did go away for college but i came back
for grad school and i've been here since
as mentioned i'm a science and
engineering education fellow in the
bioengineering department
and what that really just means is that
i work on
education for that specific department
so i focus a lot on
um what is the goal of a bioengineering
education what do we want our undergrads
to actually get out of doing a four-year
degree program but my background was
very traditional sort of cancer biology
um i did major in biology like i work in
education a lot now but my background
was all
first wet lab biology and then
computational biology
and so what my own research was about
was trying to
use methods like visualizations to
understand
why some cancer cells would die with
treatment but others would resist
and so these bottom pictures here are
sort of hinting at that i did
a lot of graph visualizations to try to
figure out what was so special about
these resistant cells
and i just want to say um i am very
happy as
always to talk to students at stanford
um that's why my
the joys of my work is getting to
interact with students so if you want to
chat at any time or connect
just feel free to email me i've put my
email here and i'm sure that it's
probably
listed somewhere or because your stamper
you could look me up and
shoot me an email so i'm very welcome to
that
all right let's get started so let's
talk a bit about cancer
so if you're not familiar with sort of
the the
the story around cancer which i think is
a very
dominant thing in the us and it tends to
be the dominant thing
or it used to be the dominant thing in
countries where um
for example infectious diseases or
diseases
of childhood are less of a thing like in
what we would consider
the developed world that's where cancer
tends to emerge as then
the thing that preoccupies society
and that's largely because cancer is
associated with people getting older
so in general in countries where they
don't worry as much about diseases that
affect
youth and where people have longer life
expectancies
that's in turn where you tend to see
more and more cancer
and at some point you start to feel like
you know lots of people who have
at some point fought cancer at some
point died from cancer
and so currently i think the statistics
are something like
one in two or one in three americans
in their life span will get cancer so
it's very it's a very large number
and as you can see it's age associated
so something is happening as we get
older
um it's true that there are some young
people who get
cancer like children even um but by and
large we're looking towards like
middle age and sort of into 50s 60s
70s is where you get cancer and then it
kind of falls off i would say probably
in large part because those folks
are less likely to get diagnosed with
cancer and even if they're diagnosed
it's they're sort of all these other uh
i
believe comorbidities like other
conditions that they're dealing with so
it kind of falls off because they're
less likely to catch the cancer and
actually be trying to fight the cancer
as opposed to dealing with other health
issues so let's talk a bit about
what's happening as we age and so
first off as we age you're sort of
accumulating
your life experiences so you can think
of it as you're accumulating exposure to
stuff so as we live and navigate the
world we're going to be exposed to
carcinogens um i know the joke in
california is that we have the little
proposition signs that say warning
something in this building will cause
cancer
um that's that then some sense may
seem overblown but it's kind of just
like a byproduct
of living in the world where there's a
lot of pollutants or there's a lot of
chemicals that maybe we haven't even
identified yet
that might have some role in promoting
cancer
um and you just kind of run into them
over the course of your lifetime and
it's sort of just
incidental that here and there you might
run into a chemical
that then causes a mutation um
so i just want to give an example
actually this isn't even a chemical this
is
uv radiation so if you just get a lot of
sun exposure
to the extent that maybe you're getting
sunburned
um that is evidence of you know
being exposed to something that has the
potential
to cause a mutation and so what i'm
showing you in this picture
is just this idea that some of these
chemicals
and the way they interact with your body
might be then interacting with
dna in some of your cells right so if
you're getting uva radiation from a
sunburn
chances are um the radiation is acting
with this
cells on your skin and so it could be
causing mutation in your skin
cells and so what's happening generally
speaking
in a lot of adults as they get older and
they
navigate through life they take a plane
trip maybe they smoke depending on their
lifestyle choices
they go to the beach is that they're
accumulating mutations over time
and it's the case that we'll talk about
that it's not just one or two mutations
it's kind of a kaleidoscope
of mutations kind of all coming together
and that's really what leads to cancer
so
as we age it's kind of like accumulating
these little genetic
tweaks and hits and if we get enough of
them
in the right constellation then cancer
arises and that becomes just more likely
as you get older
so let's talk a bit about mutation so
we're exposed to these things exposed to
the sun exposed to these chemicals
our dna changes so what so we're going
to connect that dna change to
what we actually get out with cancer
so if you're not super familiar with
why dna matters um you can think of it
as
dna basically is the recipe book it is
the instructions to make
almost anything that matters in the cell
in terms of you know the recipe to make
things like
proteins or things like rna and the
protein
rna is the material that does something
right so when the cells are sort of
sitting there and it just has
all of its dna if the cell needs to send
signals if the cell needs to grow
in certain shapes or directions or if it
needs to divide
all of those things would happen like
that that
action would manifest as a result of the
dna
providing the instructions to make
proteins um
so we call this the central dogma which
is the idea that you have your dna
but that is used to make rna which is
then made used to make protein and the
protein
does something right so pretty much
anything you can think of
chances are a protein has been made to
help facilitate
that ability right so it could be
something structural or could be
something like
behavioral all of those come about
through
gene expression which is what we call
this pathway
and so the reason why mutations matter
is because they change the recipe
right so i'll just give you an example
here there's just a way that we know to
read the code of what the mrna says
in terms of these letters and that sort
of has
a an output like an expected output in
terms of the recipe for the protein
and when we have a mutation it changes
the recipe
and so it could be the case that it's
just a very small change like basically
switching out an ingredient
a ingredient you could think of it as
you're baking cookies instead of using
brown sugar use white sugar but it could
be something really catastrophic so the
way i told people is that maybe there's
just a slight
mutation but it's kind of the same as if
you were reading a recipe for cookies
and then the pages got stuck together so
you flip to the next page and then you
start making croissants instead
so there's this real potential to sort
of have these genes that are just
completely
disrupted like the recipe is almost um
nonsensical after a certain point
and as a result that protein is just
different the way it functions could be
very different
it's possible to have mutations that
don't change the function of your
proteins but there's lots of mutations
that could make the protein
not work or work better which sounds a
little strange but we'll talk about what
that means when it like is
overactive all of those depending on
what the gene
actually normally does could be a
problem
um are there any questions up until this
point i have my chat open and i have all
of people's
pictures up so if at any point you have
a question you can hit the raise hand
button or you could put the
question in chat because i'll see it
either way
um and i did just want to highlight
there are bigger mutations so the one i
showed you on the previous slide was
kind of like a
you know in that sequence that we're
familiar with in terms of um
like the dna we represented as like a
series of letters like atcg
i was showing you small changes before
where it was just like oh just change a
letter
or add in a letter or delete a letter
but what we do see
it you know occurring by accident um
in our dna is bigger changes where
there's sort of like a
swath of dna that gets changed in some
way
so what could happen is you could have
sort of an entire piece of your dna get
copy pasted
it can get flipped around it can get
deleted
um it can move from one chromosome to
another
all of these are possible um changes
i just want to show you here what that
kind of looks like this is a karyotype
which is when we
take the dna in a cell we stain each of
the chromosomes so that they
they can be kind of easily identified
and then we
lay them out in size order and normally
people are supposed to have two of each
one
and the two they have should look fairly
identical at this level
um and what you can see is that there's
examples here where there's chromosomes
missing
there's chromosomes that kind of look
like they're a mishmash of two
chromosomes because they have two
different colors
these are the types of things we might
see in cancer where we just lose
chromosomes gain pieces of chromosomes
or chromosomes kind of get
pieced together we see this in cancer
and in fact there are some
famous examples of basically two
chromosomes sort of
swapping dna and that results
at that interface where the swap happens
in this sort of franken gene
that's like parts of two genes so that
example i gave a part cookie park
croissant
there's an example in cancer especially
childhood cancer where there's a franken
gene that's part
one protein and part another protein and
actually drives a majority of a specific
type of childhood cancer
just from that weird happenstance
occurrence where these two genes come
together which is not typical
so these are all the kinds of mutations
we might expect to see but why do they
matter
so if you're not familiar with how we
talk about
genes in the context of cancer when
we're usually looking at a mutation
and we're like okay you know say that a
gene was deleted
when we're looking at that gene and how
it relates to cancer we're
thinking about things like oh is it kind
of neutral like it didn't have any role
in the development of the cancer or does
it have a role and is the role that
when that gene was lost that enabled
cancer to happen because the cancer that
was previously
held back lost the thing that was kind
of constraining it
or is it a mutation where maybe
something became overactive
and that overactivity actually allowed
cancer to be
to be able to do the thing that it wants
to do so we kind of think of it as
is it a gain of function or is it a loss
of function
in a gene that's relevant to cancer and
so if it's a
loss of function in a gene if that's
relevant to the cancer
that gene might be what we call a tumor
suppressor gene
so it's a gene whose normal function
generally keeps
things like cancer at bay it usually
holds things back
and so when you lose it it's kind of
akin to losing the brakes
in your car so the car just kind of
doesn't know how to stop anymore
versus gain a function happens in what
we call an oncogene
and so these oncogenes are genes that
normally do something that cancer likes
and so cancer instead you know it likes
that activity and then it takes it to
11.
so it gains function it becomes let's
say uncontrollable
and we think that that as analogous to
when you're hitting the gas
but it's just jammed like it just
continuously is encouraging the car to
accelerate
so those are kind of our um paradigm for
thinking about
genes and their relevance to cancer is
the gene more like a tumor suppressor
gene or is it more like
an oncogene when we see it being mutated
in cancer
so i just want to give an example of how
we get these breaks
versus how we get these gas pedals
so an oncogene i want to be very clear
is
not a new piece of dna a new piece of
gene that came from nowhere there's
actually a really interesting story
in the history of cancer where we used
to think that maybe
cancers happen to us because of
something external
um so the way you could think of it is
that we used to kind of think like oh
there's like a virus or a bacteria or
something
that gets into us and makes us ourselves
start acting abnormally
but one of the really cool stories with
what we realized was that
there are examples of cancers being
caused by viruses
but what's actually happening is when
that virus infects us
it actually is either giving us dna that
is that came from us originally
just it's a mutant version of our own
dna
or it's being it's it does change our
dna but just to make our own dna
more active for example and so we do
have these genes that do
promote things that cancer likes right
like we have our own cells that need to
grow
our own cells that need to divide right
like that's how we
develop from a fertilized egg into a
person is that our cells grow and they
divide
so we already have that blueprint within
us to do those types of things
it's more a matter of um in the case of
cancer
you take that gene and then you turn it
on when it's not supposed to be on or it
becomes
way more overactive right so just
showing you here
it could be a slight tweak in the recipe
so then it's just
super active right like it's just way
more potent than it was supposed to be
or maybe you have just a lot more of it
right and so in the case of
um uh cancers caused by viruses
it was actually something that looked
like this where it was basically we
had that dna already it was just that
the virus sort of came in
and either gave us an extra copy or gave
us a mutant copy or gave us
sort of this hyperactivity it gave us
this way that our own genes got dialed
up to 11
so that our cells would start acting
cancerous so it's just this kind of neat
story in the history of cancer where we
thought these viruses were giving us
something completely
foreign to our cells and we actually
discovered
that what they were giving us was our
own dna or activating our
own dna and that it came from us
originally
all right so that's oncogenes again this
is something that
gains functionality it's something that
cancer cells
like and they just dial it up and the
reverse is the tumor suppressor gene
so as you can imagine um the way
that our genes sort of operate in
totality
is like a circuit right so we have
certain things that we will do
especially switching on in response to
something about our environment
but it usually has these like uh
feedback loops or self-regulation
mechanisms right so often something will
switch on
and then that as a result of sort of the
cascade of
genes and how they interact with each
other it then switches itself
off again right so there's a way in
which a lot of how our genes have
evolved is
this circuit where things will switch on
and then switch themselves off just to
prevent sort of
um you know a runaway process
um and so we have these things called
tumor suppressor genes that are just
inherent in our dna um we like to
have cells divide but we want to do it
in a controlled manner right we want our
cells to divide but we want them to just
then
stop and wait for the q to then divide
again
and so these tumor suppressor genes just
normally exist in
our body and the idea is that when
you have a mutation in the case of
cancer that protein gets deleted
or it just doesn't function there's
something about it the recipe that
changed and it just doesn't do its job
properly anymore and so it's just not
holding that process back and so one of
the main
uh uh examples of this that you may have
heard of
is a protein called p53 and so
p53 has gotten this nickname as the
guardian angel
of the cell and one of the reasons for
that is it's just such a
all-encompassing sorry tumor suppressor
gene
it's very sensitive to all of these
different
things that the cell is facing so if the
cell doesn't have enough nutrients if
the cell
is in a low oxygen environment if the
cell experience
dna damage or let's say that it's in the
middle of replicating if something went
wrong
p53 responds to that it senses that
and what it does is it mediates all
these things that cancer doesn't like
all of these things do not serve a
cancer cell well so it either would
cause the cell to die
it caused the cell to stop dividing it
caused the cell to enter a state where
it never divides again
all of these things are sort of the
antithesis of
what cancer cells do and so that's why
p53 has sort of this central
role in cancer and in fact mutations
where we lose p53 and it doesn't work
anymore
are found in like 50 of cancers like
cancers are very diverse in terms of
what ends up getting mutated
it's not like there's one gene
responsible for a hundred percent of
cancers
but the closest we come to that is
something like p53 p53 is lost in
most cancers all right are there any
questions up until this point
questions
so we talked about these different types
of mutations and i just want to be very
clear
that cancer is actually as i said before
the accumulation of
lots of these mutations so it's not the
case that you just get
one mutation oncogene and then suddenly
you would see the
full-blown pathology of like stage three
lung cancer you usually need several
mutations in a collection of oncogenes
and tumor suppressor genes
all together in the same cell for it to
then start
acting like a cancer cell and start
developing into a tumor
um and so the way you can think of it is
this is sort of a timeline from
left to right where it's like oh
starting from when we are a single cell
and then we start developing and at that
point we become a multi-cellular
individual we just accumulate mutations
and some of that actually is not even
related to carcinogens
it's just a feature of every time our
cells divide they need to copy literally
billions of letters and they just make
mistakes right
it's kind of like if overnight you had
to stay up and copy a three billion
letter or character novel and just type
it up by hand
you'll make a mistake here and there and
that's what happens in our own cells is
that they just make
random mistakes as they're dividing and
so we're accumulating those mutations
and then we start accumulating mutations
associated with our environment and our
lifestyles that could be radiation
pollution certain chemicals and those
start to accumulate and at some point
you might start to see then
the onset of cancer so if enough of
those
random mutations occur together in a
single cell
that cell then might start you know
let's say dividing
more than it's supposed to and every
time it divides
it's kind of like it's rolling the dice
to see oh will i mutate again
and it's just by chance if it mutates
again that could kind of keep it uh
snowballing towards being a cancer cell
and so that's what we see here
closer to the right is that you start
having like this like early tumor and
early
growth that's just more than it's
supposed to but at some point
as it keeps growing and growing it could
take on
new abilities to be closer to cancer
which is not just about growth it's
about being
invasive and really disrupting not only
that part of the body but also
migrating to other parts of the body as
well so that's what you see here more on
the far
right um so yeah i want to just be very
clear it's a multi-step process
it's again just by chance are you
getting all of these mutations
um all together in a single cell that
lead to this cancerous ability
there's some lifestyle sources that do
accelerate this
but again it also is completely random
as well
so when we're looking at what these
mutations are perturbing
so we're mutating some genes those genes
normally had a
job within the cell and that job is
being changed either that protein
doesn't function anymore or that protein
functions way too well
all of that contributes all those
different mutations
to the traits that we associate with
cancer
um and so if you see haven't seen this
diagram before it's it's
sort of like a seminal diagram in the
field of cancer biology
we call this the cancer hallmarks these
are like the defining
feature of cancer and so some of these
are a little more
obvious of things like the fact that
these cells just
keep on growing keep on dividing i think
that's just
what most people associate with cancer
but there's other things that um
are associated with cancer as well so
the fact that for example
um as the tumor starts growing um
it becomes this big mass of cells and
it's a very hungry mass of cells and at
some point
normally cells are being fed by the
blood vessels nearby those blood vessels
bring
oxygen and food but when you have this
giant growing mess
of cells like a developing tumor
they get super hungry and there's not
enough food and so they actually
develop a way to recruit additional
blood vessels to sort of bring them
all the food that they need and so
that's an example of a trait that you
might not associate with cancer but it
is actually very critical for cancer to
advance sort of further and further
along so it's sort of
all of these traits together are really
what we see for cancer to get to a stage
where it's like
clinically observable and you know it's
something that needs to be treated we
have all of these things happening
together
all right um
sorry i just wanted to check something
all right
so i did mention this but i do want to
uh emphasize it again because it comes
up a lot with how we think about the
data that we get from characterizing
cancer um and so we're going to talk
later about or we're going to talk in a
second about how
we characterize cancer you know cancer
is sort of
the result of all these genetic
mutations right so it's the evidence is
in the dna right if you extract
a cancer cell and look at its dna you
can see all of these things
happening right you can see genes being
changed or lost or
new copies of being pasted in
but i wanted to be clear that not every
mutation you've seen a cancer cell
is directly contributing to the cancer
being the way it is
right we we get lots of random mutations
and some of them don't really do
anything
or maybe they do something but it's so
slight and it's not contributing
to the cell being cancerous um and so
the way we think of that
about them is what we call the ex the
difference between a driver mutation
versus a passenger mutation and so as
we're growing as our cells are dividing
and you know
we're accumulating these mutations some
of those mutations
don't really have any purpose or any
role like maybe they slightly alter a
process
in that single cell but it's not enough
to contribute to the cancer in a
meaningful way
and so again when i say you need the
constellation of the right mutations all
happening in the same cell
all those mutations need to be driver
mutations they need to actually be
actively
something that uh is part of the cancer
process they can't just be random
mutations
anywhere a lot of those mutations either
don't do anything or they just don't do
anything that's
relevant to cancer and so you can
imagine when we're sifting through this
data where we have all of
these you know cancer genomes and we're
trying to figure out
okay well what went wrong here there's
actually going to be tons of mutations
we see in the data
that have nothing to do with the cancer
they're just mutations
they either do nothing or they just
don't do something that's cancer
relevant
and so that's something as sort of data
detectives that we need to keep in mind
is figuring out what is
we don't just want what is the most
common mutation we want a communication
that is actually
relevant to the cancer being the way it
is
and i just bring that up to say that
there's been a lot of efforts
to characterize the genetics of cancer
so if you're not already familiar with
tcga
it's called the cancer genome atlas and
as the name would imply
it's sort of this massively funded and
coordinated effort to just collect
many samples of a certain type of cancer
so for example they might be like okay
we're going to study kidney cancer
so they collect tons of kidney cancer
samples from lots of different patients
and they sequence them all to sort of
have this bank of data
um you know this you know here is a
genome example from
you know kidney cancer patient one
through
a thousand um and the goal of this has
just been to then try to figure out okay
when we're looking at kidney cancer
what is being mutated does that give us
more insight into how the cancer is
happening
or how we could possibly treat it and
you are welcome like
the data is in many cases open for study
if you want a more guided way to study
it i highly recommend
cbioportal.org which will let you
search through this data set but it
actually guides you and does a lot of
the visualizations for you
chances are you could probably access
the data on your own if you want more
closer to the raw data but you can start
to see
that um cancers are actually quite
different from each other i'm not going
to even fully touch on
that in this talk but you know if we're
comparing a kidney cancer
to skin cancer to brain cancer there's
actually quite a few
differences in what we observe
in from the data from those different
types of cancers they all fall under the
umbrella of cancer
but technically depending on where the
cancer is happening the
the way it comes about can be very
different
all right um i'm going to now transition
into thinking about diagnosis so that's
sort of the background
all about cancer how it's caused what is
going on
and i hope some of that molecular
context then helps make uh
the data makes the data that we collect
makes sense because again when we're
trying to
understand cancer we're actually
collecting a lot of data that's looking
into what's happening
at the protein level or at the dna level
or the mrna level
so that's the data we're actually
collecting and needing to sift through
so it just helps to see
what does what does that mrna mean what
does the protein
mean in the context of cancer
are any questions before i move on to
the next thing
all right so let's start off we're
thinking about
diagnosing cancer um so i'm just going
to give you an example so we have a
neighbor our neighbor is
sasha um they are a local bartender they
like to hike they like to play guitar
they haven't really had any serious
medical issues
um they do have a family history of
melanoma but otherwise you know
nothing that they've been diagnosed with
in their own lifetime
but they start to experience symptoms
they start to get abdominal pain
they start to lose weight without the
intention to lose weight
they feel nauseous um they oddly notice
that there's
pain in their leg so the leg is kind of
swollen
looks inflamed there's a change in the
color of their urine and all of these
worrying symptoms prompt them to go to
the doctor
i'm just curious if you have any guesses
what do you think this could be
anyone want to share in zoom chat what
this could be
just had a random guess
yeah it's some type of cancer so
someone's pointing out maybe kidney
cancer
given that there's a change in the color
of their urine
any other guesses
all right
so obviously we're gonna go to the
doctor with all of these symptoms and so
the doctor is gonna go through some sort
of process to try to figure out
what is going on um so i will say
when you're looking at cancer at the
stage at which
it's causing symptoms
um at the stage at which a person is
experiencing something like yeah like
like these different symptoms
at that stage the cancer is usually
large enough that you start to have what
we call like
gross features like things you could
just observe
and i just want to give you an example
of that when you're looking at
a tumor so let's say that you imagine
you could kind of just like
take a slice of the tissue if you know
where to look
if you're looking at that tissue you can
already tell that something's wrong if
it's at the stage where the
person's experiencing symptoms um
chances are you'll
notice the large abnormal growths
like the architecture of the tissue will
be off
right like our you know through very
interesting miracles that you can learn
about in developmental biology
somehow our cells know to grow into
certain 3d
shapes right like it develops into
tissues and the tissues come together
somehow in the correct way for us to be
functional
and so when you're looking at cancer in
a specific tissue that architecture is
way off it's not just really necessarily
that they'll just be this giant
growth where there isn't supposed to be
but it often will sort of remodel
a lot of the tissue around it and you'll
see things that are abnormal i already
gave the example
of blood vessels will start to spring up
where they don't normally show up
because they're trying to feed this
growing mass
all of that is sort of the influence of
the cancer changing
the layout around it and so even if you
just took a slice you can kind of tell
hey something's wrong here
and the joke was when i was in my cancer
biology research program
a lot of us was very molecular oriented
not many of us had clinical experience
but even we could kind of look at these
side-by-side
histologies these cut out tissues and
see hey
this just looks chaotic like there's
something wrong here
this is probably the cancer sample as
opposed to the normal sample just
because of how
messy it looks and a lot of that
messiness also is
observable at the cellular level so
shown here on the right is a comparison
of sort of
normal cells versus cancer cells and you
can already tell that there's something
way more chaotic about these cancer
cells
they don't usually sort of sit nicely
with other cells normally other cells
will
sit nicely in like a sheet and sort of
all hold hands together
if it's a cancer cell it doesn't hold
hands it's kind of more
mobile mobile it's not connected to
things it's kind of going
rogue and it also just is very um
uh diverse in terms of like the size and
the shape like normally they're fairly
uniform if they're all cells in the same
tissue serving the same purpose
but cancer cells don't obey those rules
anymore so they start to
change in their size and their shape and
they lose a lot of the features we'd
expect
and the one thing i want to point out is
that they have these larger nuclei
and some of that is actually because of
the fact that they might be
duplicating chromosomes and their dna is
like
quite abnormal compared to the normal
cell so the dna will look at
or the nucleus will actually look larger
than we would expect
so we can see all these features if we
know where to look i'll just say that
you know obviously we don't
necessarily know where to look and so
when we're trying to diagnose a cancer
we often rely on some sort of
imaging um so we can use things like
ultrasound
um pet scans mr mris to look again for
something
about the expected architecture of the
area that looks different
depending on the type of cancer
something that we think might be in the
blood we can look at a blood smear and
just
look at the cells that are floating
around in our blood
if it's a skin cancer because i know
some people brought up melanoma
you could look across the skin it's just
like a physical examination
look for moles and try to diagnose based
on the mole there's actually certain
characteristics of a mole that tell them
if it's a more dangerous
mole versus a benign hole all of these
are sort of the ways that we would
hunt around to figure out if we see
something that's suspicious
chances are if we find something that
looks suspicious
the best way to then really truly know
that it's cancer
is to do a biopsy and so very often what
might happen i'm just gonna give the
example of lung cancer that doesn't
happen to be the case
in this uh today's case study um
but if you were if they suspect uh were
suspicious that you had lung cancer
they might have found that out by doing
this imaging
um so mr mri or ultrasound they might
see like a mass that's like abnormal
like the density of the tissue where
that tissue is located it just might be
weird the pet scan actually shows them
where there's an area of
high metabolic activity which is more
likely with cancers you can imagine
something that's growing and dividing so
much
is churning through lots of energy
and so that that growing tumor is
actually hungry
like it wants lots of food and sugar to
feed itself to power
dividing so much and so if you're
looking at a pet scan you don't expect
this random mass of metabolic activity
but that might be a sign that points to
a tumor in that area
and so let's say they have all of that
evidence so far
the best thing they could do then if
they suspect maybe you have a lung
cancer
is to take a tissue sample and they
don't want to do that willy-nilly
right like taking a sample of your lungs
is not ideal especially if you're let's
say an older patient
but that might be the best thing to do
if they really truly
have enough evidence to suspect that you
have lung cancer
because that's the most definitive right
to look at the
the tissue up close to look at the cells
in the tissue
that is the best way to diagnose a
cancer currently
are there any questions about that
all right so one question what is that
so when you talk about this biopsy
taking the cells out of this potential
tumor
location so what doctor will look into
is the sequence sequence of dna or
anything else
yeah so the first thing they will check
is
the histology so they will really truly
just want to look
at an up-close sample of the cells right
so in all of the other things they just
see like this blurry mass
and a well-trained doctor knows that
that blurry mass might be off
but really the best way to discern
cancer is by looking at like a
cut out of the tissue where the cancer
lies
so they can see the abnormality of those
cells and what they're doing
a well-trained doctor can tell like like
they're dividing they're dividing
rapidly look how much they are
like abnormal relative to what uh lung
tissue should look like and how much
they've disrupted the
area um so that would be like the first
pass
just to really be able to diagnose this
is actually cancer
you are right that they will often do
some sort of genetic characterization if
that will guide the treatment
or if it might tell them um there are
some cancers where we do sort of
stratify like oh it's not just you have
cancer you have cancer that is
blank positive or negative where blank
is the genetic marker so they might do
some early genetic characterizations if
it makes sense for the kind of cancer
they're looking at um
so for lung cancer there is a genetic
marker that's commonly looked at so they
might do that early characterization
um they probably don't do something like
sequencing the whole thing
um that is kind of something they just
don't do
okay yeah so and another another thing
is that recently
uh d-mine uh accomplished this a
huge breakthrough in protein folding
all right so can protein folding help
anything in this diet in this domain do
diagnosis or treatment
i'm like sorry about my lacking
knowledge environment i don't know
that's uh that's an interesting question
because um i think one thing that i
didn't emphasize is that cancer is by
and large a genetic thing
and so for example by and large
what is making the cells abnormal is
that their recipe for certain genes has
changed
but technically there can be ways that
cancer is
i don't know if it could account for 100
of the cause but the
things that can contribute cancer can be
technically non-genetic
um so what we've noticed is there can be
things that are not at the genetic level
that actually encourage
cancer behavior and so what you're
talking about where it's like oh well
maybe the the recipe for the protein
doesn't change but the way the protein
folds changes that could technically
encourage
cancer if the weight folds for example
makes it less functional or more
functional right because basically
the the whole of what a protein does is
based on its shape
and if the shape changes what it does
changes
um so yeah that's an interesting point i
don't know of any
really solid examples off the top of my
head but
theoretically it's very sound to say if
there was some way in which
a particular gene and the protein it
makes
the recipe didn't change but the way it
folded kept
changing that could contribute to cancer
um
i don't know an example of the top of my
head but theoretically that does make
sense because ultimately
the end product if it somehow still ends
up being different
like it stops working for example that
could be contributing to cancer
thank you yeah awesome
um so let's talk about this first
example which is our friend sasha um
they get an ultrasound a ct case again
a pet scan i'm just showing you the
images um they don't mean a ton to me
because i am not a clinician i'm very
much molecular
computational biologist but if you are a
well-trained doctor you will notice that
there are
shadows or masses or bright signals
not where they're not supposed to be or
in a shape that they're not supposed to
be and so ultimately the doctor actually
diagnoses sasha with pancreatic cancer
and so my question for you all is um
this is your friend sasha their your
neighbor you've known them for a while
you hear that they have pancreatic
cancer what is your first
question when you hear this news
and you can just type in zoom chat what
would be the first thing that comes to
mind
so i'm saying how far has spread is it
recoverable like can you be treated what
stage is it
can you get surgery for it all of these
are very great questions
um yeah you might have tons of different
reactions or questions i will say
probably the most common one does get at
this which is sort of what are your
options
how bad is it uh that tends to be our
first reaction and what that's hinting
at when we think about that is actually
what stage is your cancer and so if
you're not familiar with cancer staging
that just reflects
really how far it's progressed so
an early stage so you know stage one
is something that tends to be smaller it
tends to be
very localized so for example if it's a
cancer of the lung
it just shows up on one lung in one
place that would be an early stage
cancer
as we move towards stage two stage three
stage four
that means that we suspect that the
cancer has maybe moved from one lung
to the other lung maybe it's moved from
that lung to somewhere else in the body
um basically the farther it's spread
that's where we have
later stages um stage
one through four is usually what we talk
about sort of
in more common interactions technically
at the doctor's level we have like a
more
sophisticated uh system of
of looking at things like we wonder like
what is the relative size
of the tumor and how much has it invaded
locally
and then we will examine lymph nodes
because that's a very common sort of um
transit transit opportunity for a cell
if a cell is
leaving one organ to go to another organ
the lymph nodes are
one of the major sort of highways that
they take so one thing they might do is
they might
look into the lymph nodes nearby and see
if they see a crazy
abnormal lung cancer cell in the lymph
node which really stands out because
normally in the lymph nodes you maybe
have like types of immune cells
you don't expect to see a lung cell in
the lymph nodes they might
check to see if they observe that and
again depending on the patient if they
notice oh this patient
has um you know we diagnose them with
lung cancer but we also notice the
suspicious mass
appearing on their kidneys that is
evidence of a metastasis which is that
the cancer is spread
really from one organ to another organ
and so these do kind of map stage one
through four kind of map to this
tnm system but this is a little bit of a
more detailed system showing
you how they kind of arrive at saying
you're stage three they're kind of
looking at all these different features
and i will just say um it's not just
size and invasion
sometimes they are looking at the cells
themselves
so for example um this is more common in
something like prostate cancer which is
that
it's not just a matter of like how big
is the tumor how far is it spread
um they actually are looking at like the
cells themselves to see like how
different do they look from what we
expect like do they look like what we
expect prostate tissue to look like
or how different are they because
usually
less normal is is evidence that it's
actually
worse so um normally the the prostate
tissue is supposed to form these sort of
like small little
gland structures and as you can see on
this spectrum
as it starts to not really even form
that structure anymore that's a sign
that the cells are just
more and more abnormal and so when
you're staging the cancer and you look
and you see oh like
maybe one patient's pancreatic cancer
sorry
prostate cancer looks closer to the top
and one prostate cancer
sample looks closer to the bottom the
person whose sample looks close to the
bottom you'd actually expect that their
cancer maybe is
more aggressive or is harder to treat
and so that might be additional
information that impacts your staging
decision
so when we're looking at sasha's case uh
sasha's tumor
measures two inches across there's a
presence of cancer cells in the nearby
liver
there's high metabolic activity in three
nearby lymph nodes
and then if you recall sasha's symptoms
they have leg pain
they have a abnormal color in their
urine
how would you stage sasha's cancer
based on this information
yeah it sounds fairly late stage
um and so i just wanted to point out
something like leg pain
could be evidence that cells maybe are
in
lymph nodes nearby and causing them to
swell
um as we mentioned like someone thought
oh maybe it's kidney cancer
because it sounds like it's affecting
the kidneys well maybe it wasn't
originally from the kidneys it's those
cells have moved to kidneys and are
affecting their ability to function
normally
so yeah this would be fairly late stage
cancer
and so i just wanted to walk you through
this example to show you really like
this is the process by which we are
understanding
someone's cancer currently i mean i'm
not a clinician but this is by and large
sort of the most
common way it's probably the most
accessible way when we don't have the
means to do
tons of fancy genotyping um and and
surveillance of someone's body
um but this is just how someone would
find out they have cancers
usually they show some sort of symptom
in some cases they might be screened
screenings a whole nother conversation
but they might
show symptoms they go in they get some
imaging done they might then get a
biopsy if they see something suspicious
and then that's where they start to sort
of put the pieces together and figure
out what stage are you
and that guides treatment generally
speaking
so this is a great uh i don't know if
you guys usually do like five minute
breaks this would be a great
stopping point if people want a bathroom
break
hi marisa just two minutes before we get
started i'm just very curious about the
car in the
strategy for kovi 19 because they have
you have these new mutations keep on
coming out
and similar to the cancer mutations
so kind of worry about it yeah i mean
i think so
ultimately
when it comes to these mutations um
like i'm to be honest like immunology
isn't super my strong point
um but i will say that in general when
we're thinking about
immunity the
the covid virus right like will have a
particular shape and architecture and
ultimately
what you're just hoping is that your
immune cells will realize this is
something really problematic and have
like a
strong enough rejection response fast
enough right
you don't like for a lot of people the
issue is that
they do have something somewhere that
will respond to
a covet virus but at that point the copa
virus is starting to infect the
infection is spreading
and so it's kind of like they've been
stealthily invaded before they mount
a large enough response fast enough um
and so with the vaccine trying to get
people to like really have that
quick immediate reaction right away to
just reject it
um i think there can be mutations in
viruses that aren't necessarily
changing like you know it's like a a
tiger changes its spots like it's
some of those mutations aren't
necessarily changing the outside
arrangement that we recognize i mean
some of them do
i think that's something that's really
tough with you know things like
uh the seasonal flu it's like they are
changing their spots often and so we
just don't have the same
immune reaction quick enough as it
starts to change
the features that we recognize right
like the things we're looking for are
literally changing
some of the mutations might change
things that aren't that particular
protein
on the surface they could be other
things right
um but yeah i think as long as
the tiger is changing its spots and
those features are changing
then yeah it could be that our immune
response to them is weaker and at some
point maybe we don't
have the same immune response at all and
then we need a new vaccine to like
prompt us to respond to that one instead
so i think some people who've said like
depending on the degree of the mutation
um and whether it's always kind of in
these recognizable
outer proteins that might prompt us to
just keep having like
updated vaccines the same way we do the
seasonal flu
um but it could be the case that also is
mutating in ways that don't affect that
surface protein
okay thank you so much yeah yeah i
noticed we're at time so i'm going to
resume and now we're going to sort of
really segue into thinking about where
does
machine learning and ai come in and so
honestly this is kind of
when i'm thinking about machine learning
this is kind of again how i break it
down right thinking about the difference
between
a supervised task versus an unsupervised
task and all of the methods associated
with those
and i just want to give you examples of
the types of things we think about
in cancer that relate to each of these
areas
so for example a lot of work we do is
unsupervised
and i'll just say that that's because
with something like biology there's so
much open-endedness where we're just
trying to discover
what is happening what is this how does
it work
and so there's a lot of unsupervised
tasks so there might be something like
figuring out what are the different
types of
tumors in patients right so we might
have some
big disease like all of lung cancer
but maybe if we're sort of doing an
unsupervised analysis we might realize
oh there seems to be these different
types of lung cancer all under this
umbrella
um and so that's just at the level of
looking across
patients but you could go a little
further and say oh well we're taking
samples of lung cancer cells and you
might realize oh there's different
types of lung cancer cells right it's
actually kind of a
heterogeneous space not every lung
cancer
cell in a in one person's tumor is
actually the same
and so as we're doing sort of this
unguided analysis where we're just
looking for what is there what is the
diversity there are there certain
clusters or archetypes
we might discover oh in lung cancer we
tend to notice that there's
this common cell type alpha beta you
know just i'm making something up but
like we do a lot of this type analysis
just because
previously we haven't had this level of
detail
available to us about lung cancer you
know either at the single cell level
or just not enough samples to be able to
appreciate what is there
and so we do a lot of unsupervised work
a lot of visualizations a lot of
clustering to just figure out what is
the diversity of things within a given
cancer
we do do a lot of supervised tasks so we
do a lot of trying to be able to better
discern
normal patients versus tumor patients or
trying to relate
tumor types to like their prognosis and
their survival
so we do a lot of these more guided
tasks they tend to be the much more
clinical ones i'd say the unsupervised
ones tend to be the more
figuring out how cancer works we're
still many or many decades later
figuring out how cancer works and a lot
of the supervised ones tend to be
very clinically relevant like how can we
automate sort of this ability to
diagnose patients just based on a
certain type of data that we collect
and so there's lots of things that
relate i think
going from machine learning into cancer
biology
um and we have lots of data i think the
tough thing with biology is our data is
very messy
as soon as you work with real world real
life things
things get very messy but i will share
that we just
we measure many things in biology we
measure many different types of things
at different levels of scale at
different levels
in the biological process um we have
things like sequencing we have things
like imaging we have things where we're
looking at the three the the spatial
arrangement of
cells um we might be looking at the
proteins in a given cell so we have
all this kinds of different data that we
look at and i'm going to go through and
explain a couple of these different data
types
and how they relate to cancer
so we talked about this already this
idea that we have the dna which is our
sort of recipe book it tells us you know
what how do you make any given protein
and so the dna
and what's going on in our cells the dna
is being copied into
rna which is sort of this temporary
intermediate it's kind of like a
photocopy of the recipe book
that photocopy floats out and goes to
a ribosome which is where the protein is
constructed so it references
your your photocopied recipe and uses
that to then put the right pieces
together to make a particular type of
protein
and so if we're looking at these steps
we basically can collect data at each
step
of this process so we can collect data
about the dna we can collect data about
the rna that's floating around in our
cells we can collect it about what
proteins we have floating around in our
cells
um i will just say one underappreciated
part of this process
is actually that our dna isn't just sort
of this like
it's it's it's you know it could be like
a text
corpus right like it's a it's a lot of
letters in a certain order
but it's also a 3d physical thing right
our dna is these molecules and these
molecules actually have a lot of
folding and sort of coiling that's
happening
so there's this really cool world where
they look at like the 3d structure of
dna and how dna
basically turns into like knots and
coils
um but i i just bring up this up to say
that actually that 3d shape
matters in the sense that when we're
expressing
genes if a gene is sort of super coiled
it actually becomes sort of hidden away
like it's it's so folded up that we
can't
reference it anymore and that gene isn't
expressed
versus if there's a part of the dna that
unfurls and uncoils and is very
accessible
that gene is easier for the cell to
express
and that um that shape that it takes on
is actually very purposeful
in certain cells they will fold up parts
of their dna that they're like i don't
need to use this anymore
and they'll unfurl the parts they do
need to use and that's usually relevant
to the type of cell it is
right your dna has the instructions to
be
any type of cell in the world but if
you're a lung cell
you don't need the instructions for how
to be a kidney cell or how to be a skin
cell so you fold up that dna and you
reference the parts that are relevant to
being a lung cell
and so that 3d architecture actually
really matters and i will talk about an
example of data where we look at
what genes are more open and more
accessible versus which genes are
closed and that is relevant to looking
at cancer
and then one other thing i'll mention is
that our
notion of cells is that um this is
actually kind of relevant when we're
talking about viruses
is that the surface features of a cell
usually tell us a lot about the cell
like what it's doing and what kind of
cell it is
and so even if we weren't diving in and
looking at hey what is the cell sort of
thinking and doing
by studying its dna or studying its
proteins
if we just look at the outside of the
cell there's usually
like flags that tell us what the cell is
like what kind of cell it is and so a
common example is that if we just look
at your blood
if we take a sample of your blood and
measure certain flags
that are present on the outside cell we
can say oh this is a white blood cell
specifically it's a t
cell or this is an immune like an innate
immunity cell it's a
monocyte versus a red blood cell like
those are things we can um
detect looking at the flags on the
outside of the cell so these are all
things you can measure we can measure
what is the dna what mrna is it
producing
what proteins is it producing what
proteins are on the outside of cell that
make it a certain type of cell versus a
different type of cell
and we can also tell the not only like
the dna in terms of what mutations it
might have we can also tell what kind of
shape the dna is taking on so these are
all different types of data that we
collect
are there any questions before i kind of
get into those
all right so probably the most obvious
one i just talked about
tcga we do a lot of dna sequencing
this has been aided by the next
generation sequencing
we used to do sequencing in a very
labor-intensive and
cost intensive way and now we have new
technologies where we can do dna
sequencing a lot
faster and a lot cheaper and so this is
a commonly cited plot where before it
used to cost you know back when
back in the 2000 era um it would cost
millions of dollars to sequence a single
genome right it was a
huge effort took many labs millions of
dollars to get
one genome and nowadays maybe in a week
or two you could get a genome for closer
to like a thousand dollars and it can
get cheaper and cheaper all the time as
the technology gets better
so that has allowed us in many ways
whereas before we couldn't
study the genome of a cancer now we are
able to collect those samples and
actually
look at their entire genome as opposed
to just looking at one mutation at a
time
for example
um i mentioned the example of looking at
the shape of the dna so like is the dna
very open or is it very
closed um there's two ways we detect
this
so there's this thing called dna
methylation
um the long and short of it is that with
dna methylation
the dna gets like a chemical flag like a
little modification
and that modification basically tells
that dna to shut down
the dna doesn't disappear right like the
cells don't usually want to
ever get rid of parts of their dna but
they do like to sort of tag something
and say okay we're done with this gene
we're not going to express it anymore
and so methylation in this case is just
this little flag that says okay we're
done with this gene close up shop
we're going to use something else and
we're able to detect that
using a particular type of sequencing so
it's not just sequencing the dna you're
sequencing the dna to look for
where that modification shows up and so
i could tell you hey
it's not just what the recipe reads
it's that oh this part of the the book
has been sort of post-it note like this
is the actively referred to part of the
book
versus parts of the book that are almost
like uh taped shut
like they're just done with the the cell
is not using that dna anymore
and so this gives us a better picture of
like what the cell is
in the midst of expressing at any given
time
so there's that methylation flag another
thing that maybe is a little more
um physically clear is that we can
actually look
at the folding of our dna so normally
our dna gets kind of
coiled in a way where it's kind of like
beads on a string
or like if you're winding up a hose
there's kind of like a spool
and the dna goes around it um
but some parts of your dna will have
sort of like dna wound around spools and
then round around
each other and other parts will have the
dna kind of loosely associated with
the beads but otherwise it's very open
and accessible
and so that's shown here on the left
where there's the closed chromatin
the closed dna very tightly wound you
can't really
see what's happening in there and
there's the open parts of the dna
and so recently and this was actually at
stanford they developed a way to
specifically figure out where are these
open regions
so they developed this clever technique
where something comes in and
tags the open regions because well the
closed reasons aren't accessible to that
particular enzyme
so enzyme goes in it tags all of the
open regions of dna
it can't get into the closed regions and
then there's a way at the sequencing
level to see oh
this is the open region where there were
lots of tags
and when there's no tags oh that was the
region in that dna that was closed off
in that particular cell
just based on how it coiled so this
isn't even a chemical flag anymore it's
just based on like oh this part of the
dna kind of folded
in on itself and so it's not being used
so this is another piece of data that is
also
available and becoming more available
all the time
so let's look at mrna so we've moved
from dna how it folds what mutations are
present
now we're moving to the next level which
is we were photocopying the dna to get
rna and that tells us really
what this is getting closer to what the
cell is actually doing right so the dna
with all those mutations they only
matter if they affect what this
cell creates right the cell might have
certain mutations but if it's not
producing the mrna and protein then the
mutation kind of doesn't
make a difference it's just sort of what
the cell is but not what the cell is
doing
and so when we look at things like mrna
and protein we get a better idea of what
the cell is
actually doing because the mrna and the
protein are what
what um the parts of the cell that do
things as opposed to dna which just sort
of sits there
so how do we characterize mrna um
there's a way in the past that's very
quick to just characterize the relative
amounts
of different mrna and that's what's
being shown here with these microarrays
which is where they basically
take uh your they take up they chop up
the mrna
they adhere it to probes on a
on a on a chip and basically if there's
less of the probe or more of a probe
it's like a relative
measure then it turns different colors
so if you compare two samples let's say
a
normal lung tissue versus a lung cancer
tissue
the relative proportions of each type of
gene will stain different colors so if
there's
more in the lung cancer sample it might
turn red versus if there's more in the
normal sample
it might turn green and so you get this
relative measure of how much mrna there
is in let's say
tumor versus normal and this was the
original way we did it it was cheap it
was fast
and just gave us this readout on genes
that are maybe
expressed more in cancer or expressed
less in cancer
what we actually use now which we were
talking about a bit is
rna sequencing so it's kind of the same
as dna sequencing but it's at the rna
level so rather than collecting
all of the dna and all of the genes we
collect all of the rna that the cell has
happened to create at that given time
and we figure out okay well what genes
are represented
in these mrna what is it in the process
of
making and so it works very much the
same way in terms of like
the reading out the sequence but the
nice thing about it is it's both
quantitative and descriptive so rna
sequencing can tell you the relative
amounts like if there's a lot of a
certain gene you know like oh there's
like
uh this is a rough like there's like on
the order of a lot
like 20 30 hundreds of this one
mrna transcript it's expressing a lot of
this gene versus very little
of a different gene so you do get these
quantitative readouts
but you also get descriptive readouts so
even if you hadn't sequenced
the dna you can tell at this level if
hey
we know what um gene x is supposed to
look like
we can tell that this mrna is off it's
been mutated in some way because the dna
it's referencing has also been mutated
and so at this level you can both
characterize mutant
instructions for making proteins but you
can also quantify how much
mrna is being produced like is it
telling the cell to make a lot of a
certain oncogene for example
um and then sort of the last in this
progression so we talked about dna
rna and now we're talking about protein
there are ways to quantify protein
it is harder i would say than dna and
rna
dna and rna are nice in the sense that
they are these like
little linear molecules and they only
have like four distinct options they
either read
you know atcg if your dna or
a ucg if you're an rna and just knowing
that they
take on a certain shape and that they
only have so many letters at a time
makes it very easy to read and reference
them
and measure them protein is actually a
lot harder
right protein is like this physical 3d
glob that takes on different shapes and
so when we're trying to measure
protein it's harder we can use things
like mass spec where we try to look at
the
chemical composition basically of a
protein
or we can do things that are antibody
based or
probe based so we can for example
engineer to like
look at a particular protein that has a
little light on it
basically so it's like oh it lights up
green versus it lights up blue
or we could add antibodies which
recognize the protein and they are
basically the flag that says oh you know
i added this antibody the antibody has a
little red
dot on it and it looks for protein x and
so
by proxy of how many antibodies i see
binding that tells me how many of
protein x i have
so these are all very indirect measures
um so measuring proteins tends to be a
lot more difficult unfortunately
but in some ways it's very impactful as
i said
this will tell us it could tell us what
kinds of cells we have and it really
does tell us directly what a cell is
doing because proteins are what
the action comes from in a cell so it's
like one of the most important
end stages of the process but it's also
the hardest to quantify
are there any questions about that
all right um i just want to touch on two
things which is that
when we're looking at cancer there's
lots of levels
i think that's one of the hardest thing
for a lot of students in cantor biology
to unders to sort of wrap their mind
around is that we move through these
different levels of scale
really interchangeably right there's
like populations of people who get
cancer there are you know cohorts who
get certain types of cancers and have
certain lifestyles
and you zoom in on a patient and what
the patient does
then you zoom in on their tumor but
their tumor is actually a collection of
very different cells
so then you zoom in on a particular type
of cell you zoom in on the dna
and we're like moving through all of
these levels to talk about cancer as a
whole
which i think is the hard thing to
navigate so everything i've talked about
up until this point was sort of looking
on a molecular level either at one
particular cell or like all of the cells
like mushed together
into like an average but technically all
of the cells
are special right like if we're looking
at a tumor
the cells actually can be quite
different from each other in terms of
what their mutations have ended up being
relative to each other
and also what they're doing at a given
time right
so this picture here is just showing you
like a tissue is like all of these cells
collected together
and actually when we look at a tumor it
is incredibly heterogeneous right
there's lots of different types of
cancer cells there's actually
normal cells kind of interwoven in
they've either been
recruited in or they're just sort of
like bystanders in this process
and so you can think of it as like when
we're trying to take a sample and do dna
sequencing we're actually just
grabbing a whole bunch of these and just
mashing them together to do the dna
sequencing
and so that adds to the noise it also
just adds to the importance of trying to
discern
spatially what's happening right because
these are actually all
different like there's an architecture
to all these things interacting
and we just sort of fuzz that over by
like taking a giant scoop of them
and mashing them up and measuring them
and so i just want to mention there is a
lot of effort to try to
look at them in their original site like
what where do they sit relative to each
other
and this has been done for a long time
so i talked a bit about histology where
you just take a slice of a tissue and
you look at it
but in the past it's been very hard for
them to look at more than one or two
things at a time like they
see the physical layout and they maybe
could
look at one or two proteins at a time
but there's been a lot of effort to try
to look at
multiple things like proteins
or rnas or types of dna
in their current layout like so where do
cells that are doing certain things
sit relative to each other within a
tumor and so that's an active area of
interest is trying to be able to do
those measurements but without
extracting the cells and like pushing
them all together because that just sort
of fuzzes away
a lot of the complexities of the system
all right any questions
all right so let's see let's go a little
ahead i wanted to give an example
of um a couple of these
applications so i just want to say
lots of different types of data that
we're collecting some of these i haven't
even talked about
trying to integrate them is really
challenging like there's such different
types of data measuring you know things
that are related but different
and there's a lot of people interested
in putting that information together
right to have a more complete picture
but that is a very
challenging thing to do um i will
say that this obviously fuels diagnoses
like better understanding
what kinds of cancer are out there and
which kind of cancer you have
but obviously it also guides how we
treat the cancer which we'll talk about
next week
all right so let's talk about examples
in the world of diagnosis that have to
do with machine learning so let's talk
about discovering
different types of cancer cells
so i just want to mention that we do a
lot of clustering
based on markers in the sample so maybe
we collect a lot of different
dna profiles and we've done a lot of
different work clustering to say oh
like it's not just lung cancer it's lung
cancer type
abc based on their genetic profiles
so we've done a lot of work in that area
to sort of discern like
it's not just one homogenous group
there's lots of different types of lung
cancer can we
sort of de novo discover what those
types are on the basis of their genetic
differences or
protein level differences
but i just want to remind you that
clustering could be performed on many
levels you could cluster
patients you could cluster tumors within
patients some patients have
multiple tumor samples if a patient has
a metastasized cancer you could
literally
collect like three or four different
tumor samples just from one patient like
one from the left lung
one from the right wrong one from the
kidney one from a lymph node
and so are you clustering the patient or
are you clustering the tumors within a
patient which is different
or you could cluster the cells
themselves which is an even smaller
level of resolution
so we've done a ton of that and you can
actually find in the literature that
we've discerned different
subtypes of breast cancer lung cancer
this has been done in many different
cancer big cancer
types where we've realized there's
actually a lot of diversity of subtypes
within that type
i just want to give an example of
discerning normal versus
tumor um and so i just want to say that
in general doctors are very well trained
to be able
to see when something is off right they
can look at an image and say hey this
mass
is not what i've seen all the 50 000
other lung images i've looked at like
this is abnormal
and so doctors are experts they're
usually very good at that but there are
definitely
cases where experts differ right get a
second opinion
two experts who've seen different
samples over their lifetime and are
maybe sensitive to different features in
the image might say different things
and so this is where maybe machine
learning could come in and either sort
of
standardize the process maybe see
something that humans
miss but this is an opportunity i think
certainly where we could
bring in machine learning and just help
this process like can we sort of
learn from many many experts and sort of
pile like pile all of their knowledge
together to have a more
accurate uh way of just looking at
images and saying hey this is probably
cancerous you should follow
the biopsy versus it's probably nothing
don't worry about it
just because again humans are biased
humans make mistakes
could machine learning do it better
and then here's a slightly longer
example that i just want to give
this actually came this kind of work
comes out of my previous phd lab it
wasn't my work but it was work done by a
colleague of mine
which is trying to again look at sort of
the difference between
normal versus tumor in patients and
helping with the diagnosis
but also relating those different types
of tumors
to how well they're likely to do
so a lot of profiling these different
patients again
is trying to figure out like what
subtype of cancer you have you have lung
cancer
we discover it you have the symptoms we
diagnose you with lung cancer just based
on
the imaging and maybe a biopsy but if we
measure
flags like genetic flags or protein
flags abc
can we group you into type a versus type
b
and do those types do better or worse um
maybe you have a more aggressive cancer
and that guides us to then
be more aggressive in how we treat
versus something that we can maybe be a
little more
like wait and watch and see what happens
so there's a lot of interest in doing
that um i want to say
i gave the example of uh is this lung
cancer no this is not lung cancer i
apologize
um this is just showing you that
we're developing our understanding of
these different genetic markers and
which ones are relevant
in a given cancer and so this is just
showing you that you know
back in 1987 we realized that there was
this protein
that is commonly mutated called k-ras
and so we would just sort of stratify
patients into
do you have a k-ras mutation or do you
not but then
over time as we've discovered more
genetic markers then we can sort of
create more buckets and have a little
bit more guided therapy right
so then we discovered egfr and so the
way we treat egfr patient
versus a k-rest patient within lung
cancer might be different
and now we have way more buckets as
we've gotten way more data
you can see on the right we have so many
different markers we can look for that
guide how we diagnose and then how we
treat
so here's the example from my lab which
was
looking at pediatric patients who have a
type of cancer
that occurs in the blood and so this
type of cancer you can take a bone
marrow sample because bone marrow is
where
blood originates so a lot of the
different blood types come out of
precursor cells in the bone marrow and
so you could take a sample of that bone
marrow and basically see
what are the kinds of cells that are in
a patient's
bone marrow especially if they have
cancer and what
this researcher did is they basically
were looking at
samples they had ability to like kind of
look at the different types of cells
in different patients bone marrow so you
can imagine they took
maybe my bone marrow and ed's bone
marrow and they can basically discern
like oh how much of each type of cell
do you have and do these cells look
normal or do these cells look
abnormal and so they basically created a
spectrum of like
how much of each type of cell do you
have
does it look more abnormal does it look
more normal
and what they did is they related that
like the amount of each type of cell and
how normal it looks or have normal
how abnormal it looks they related that
to whether that patient would ultimately
relapse or not so they basically know
of their sample how many patients had a
more aggressive cancer had a cancer that
was ultimately resistant to therapy
versus patients who responded well
and they wanted to figure out what is
special about those patients who tended
to relapse
so if we know that ahead of time we can
be more aggressive in how we treat their
cancer we know that they
we need to be careful with that patient
because they're very likely
to not do as well and so they basically
went in
and tried to learn the features that
distinguished
patients who relapse from patients who
do not read lips and they were basically
able to figure out
hey there's sort of this signature of
like things happening
in certain cells that is unique to the
patients who tend to relapse
and that can actually guide them to
think about okay those
that profile those things that are
different about the
patients who relapse can we target those
ahead of time so that they're less
likely to relapse
and basically preempt what we've
observed will tend to happen
so i'm happy i just realized that the
reference to this paper is not in my
slides
i'm happy to add that in for next time
just that you're able to look up this
paper if that interests you
all right in the few minutes i have left
i just want to call attention to
the challenges in this area so i've
highlighted some more success stories
but what is so
hard about machine learning in biology
and in cancer specifically
so i want to say a couple of the
problems are very technical and a couple
of problems are not very technical so
the number one problem i actually bring
up is not technical at all
it actually has to do with crossing
disciplines
it's been very challenging when there's
people who've been uh
traditionally trained in like computer
science and algorithms
and then people who've been trained in
the wet lab biology and they know
how these measurements work having them
talk together and
design a study that is rigorous and
sound has been challenging because they
don't understand the limitations on both
sides
i've dealt with people who don't
understand how rna sequencing works and
so when i tell them hey it's this
average of all this mush they're
surprised they're like oh can't you
get out who contributed what and there
are some ways that you can kind of do
that
but fundamentally you're just mushing
the cells all together like method
wise it's an average and that's been
something they weren't aware of and
other people who don't understand the
algorithms
might assume that you can back solve
things that you can't
so that's one inherent problem in this
field is just the the
siloed off disciplines and the lack of
communication
but there are a lot of other issues i
mentioned noisy data
huge variability within the data like
you can have two lung cancer patients
who actually
despite both having lung cancer seem
incredibly different from each other and
their pathology
and what their tumors say i did mention
the idea of
integrating multiple types of data it's
very hard to bring together the
mutational profile and what the dna says
and what the protein says and make them
sort of work together to have one
picture
um i will also say that it's very tough
these days i think you might have heard
of this idea of personalized medicine
but if you think about it in terms of
how you would go about
setting up a machine learning problem
the more sample the better and so when
we're emphasizing hey personalized
medicine
have an n of one that starts to fly in
the face of the statistical rigor we
need to back
up what we're finding um so i think i
will
leave it at that i have these slides i
think
uh ed you might have these slides
already uploaded if not i'll send you
this is a slightly updated set um i
mostly actually took away things rather
than adding things
i'll send the updated set but i think i
will leave it off there and i'll just
say that next week we're going to really
focus on
okay we can figure out these different
cancer subtypes but how do we discern
how to treat these different patients
and use
ai to do so better okay thank you so
much melissa
any questions questions from students
we'll have plenty of time also next time
for questions i think so you can leave
your question on slack so next time when
melissa comes back
and she can answer your questions
awesome
thank you so much everyone yeah so much
thank you so much
looking forward to seeing you again and
remind the students
your proposal is due the project
proposal is due
tonight if you need more time just let
us know
and the next tuesday i look forward to
your presentation on your proposals and
sahil please try to organize
uh the discussion next tuesday and i
will come back to see malissa again on
thursday
okay thank you and bye everyone thank
you everyone
thank you thank you see you next week
okay thank you yeah yeah thank you so
much i will see you
next thursday um i think the slides i
have sent you in the past