good morning welcome back to cs
372 artificial intelligence for
disease diagnosis and the information
recommendations
and the last time dr melissa ko gave us
a lecture on
cancer causes and the diagnosis
and today we welcome melissa to come
back to give us
the second lecture on cancer focusing on
cancer treatment including radiology
surgery chemotherapy
and targeted therapy and immunotherapy
let's welcome melissa
awesome welcome back everyone so yeah we
will be continuing with sort of
the second half of what we spoke about
last week
so last week we really thought about
how is cancer caused how do we diagnose
it
and so really looking at what's going on
in our cells and in our dna that
leads to cancer and
thinking about those different features
of a cancer cell and maybe how that
might
contribute to what we're looking for in
cancer like diagnosing it as an earlier
stage versus a later stage as a more
aggressive cancer or a less aggressive
cancer
and ultimately i think it was clear from
that conversation that our goal when we
were diagnosing is ultimately that might
guide
better treatment so we're going to
continue that conversation today
so what i'm planning on talking about
today is
giving you a sense of a lot of the
existing treatments for cancer
so we have what i guess i'd call
traditional cancer treatments which are
probably the ones you've heard about
or seen in like popular media whenever
cancer comes up whether it be in a tv
show or a book
there's typical types of cancer
treatment that we've been using for many
many years
i'll talk about some more recent cancer
therapies
and then we'll talk a bit about what the
issue is with those therapies so what is
the issue with the therapies that we
usually use to treat cancer
how is it that cancers become resistant
to treatment
and what are some possible workarounds
for that and then i'll again
talk about um machine learning
applications so we'll think about how
could machine learning help with
discovering new drugs or discovering
better drugs or discovering more
effective combinations of drugs
and then i will talk a bit about
immunotherapy i know immunotherapy
is a big area of interest for
for a lot of us um i think compared to a
lot of
recent innovations with uh cancer
treatment and immunotherapy is sort of
just like a different approach
and i think before it was kind of like
you can imagine we drop
we developed drug a and we were kind of
incrementally
improving on drug a or just slightly
um you know pairing drug a with drug b
to slightly improve the efficacy
but immunotherapy is like let's just
take a new approach
and in some ways that maybe will be more
effective especially for certain
patients
so i'll talk a bit about immunotherapy
and then i'll just touch on um
areas of work and maybe areas that
connect to careers you might be
interested in and i did
try to consciously leave more time
so i think i have fewer slides and fewer
things to touch on than
last week so hopefully that'll give
space if we want to have a more open
conversation
and you can ask either about research or
about sort of transferable
skills or ideas if you're interested in
like the healthcare context or cancer
biology context
so that's the plan for today um let me
get started first off
before we kind of jump right into
talking about cancer treatments i did
want to talk a little bit about
again i think last time i gave an
example of like different
types of machine learning approaches so
like supervised versus unsupervised
learning how they relate to cancer like
what are the types of problems we think
about in the context of cancer when
we're thinking about
using clustering or using different
types of modeling like classification
regression um so those are kind of like
paradigms for like types of problems
you'd solve and how they relate to
cancer
but i also want to talk a little bit
methodology wise
one thing that comes up a lot in cancer
is this
you know well it comes up in machine
learning is this trade-off between
very complex and accurate models but
they become
models that you can't really scrutinize
like you don't know what's happening
under the hood it's just sort of a black
box
you feed in your inputs and you might
get really accurate
outputs whether that be a regression or
a classification
but you don't know what's happening per
se in the model
and so this actually comes up a lot when
we are working as researchers
in terms of how do we choose which model
to use
and it really kind of where we fall on
the spectrum of preferring accuracy and
giving up the interpretability versus
preferring interpretability and giving
up accuracy
kind of depends ultimately on our goal
as researchers
so for example as a cancer researcher if
your goal
is really to try to
reveal how cancer works
so this comes up a lot in sort of basic
research thinking about
how how is the cancer functioning does
um does the cancer function
um so in that sense when we're trying to
model a process
we're really interested in what are the
important
features what is leading to one outcome
over another
and so it's not just enough if your goal
is to understand the cancer
to say oh yeah you as a patient have the
aggressive cancer and you as a patient
have the less aggressive cancer we want
to know what's leading to that
distinguishing that distinction between
the two
is there a really important feature in
our cells is it a really important
mutation like we want to
be able to pull the model apart and
reveal what that feature
is and so a lot of like how does cancer
work kind of problems we
we tend towards these more simple models
but then of course i think there is the
clinical application which kind of falls
up here
which is where there are definitely
people whose ultimate goal is you know i
have
real-life patients humans dealing with
cancer i just want to be able to
have high certainty high accuracy and
telling them
oh you have this type of cancer this is
the best treatment regimen for you
and so when you're thinking about how to
approach
cancer research really knowing is your
goal to
understand cancer better or is your goal
just to
you know optimize something so that you
maximize the good for your patients
and that's something that we struggle
with we know that all like cancer is so
complicated that a lot of the more
simple models
are definitely over simplifications of
how cancer works but ultimately our goal
might be just trying to
pull apart like what are the mutations
that that contribute to cancer
and those kinds of things would be lost
if we used really complicated models
that make it really hard to figure out
what's going on
so this is a trade-off that we struggle
a lot with and it just kind of depends
as a researcher like what are you
ultimately trying to contribute to
by giving doctors the best tool and
giving the best tool for patients
or just like furthering our
understanding of the cancer
all right so let's return to our
case study from last week so you might
remember that last week what we talked
about was our neighbor sasha has been
diagnosed with stage
four pancreatic cancer so
you both know the stage of the cancer
and you also know the type of the cancer
it originated in the pancreas
if you remember last time one thing we
noticed was that
and what contributed to the diagnosis of
stage four was that it was affecting
the kidneys as well so it is a cancer
that has metastasized or it has spread
to another organ and so what i want you
to just spend a quiet moment
reflecting on and you can share your
ideas in the chat is
what treatment options do you know for
cancer and which ones do you think would
work or not work in the scenario so you
can just sort of recall what you've
heard about for cancer
and then think about which ones do you
think would be used here
and and may help versus ones that might
not help
so just take a quiet moment to think
about that and again share your answers
in chat
yeah so i see people mentioning
chemotherapy
and surgery um
so i'm seeing comments about
chemotherapy and how effective
it might be um again there's a lot of
trade-offs or chemotherapy itself
um chemotherapy is a very harsh
treatment which we'll talk about in a
second
um and then surgery think about surgery
um
surgery you would need to know where the
tumor is and you might clearly know
where the tumor is
with regards to the pancreas and maybe
even the kidney
but one thing that's never really clear
with a cancer that is late stage
and that has spread is is it somewhere
else and we just don't know it yet and
so that makes surgery really difficult
um and you can imagine with a very sick
patient you don't want to keep
putting them under the stress of
surgery awesome thank you for your ideas
so yes i think really thinking carefully
about what will work
at this stage in the game knowing that
the patient is probably
sick and will only get sicker knowing
that the cancer
isn't localized it has spread all of
those are kind of
information that will inform our
decision and generally speaking
when you're asking up if well if you're
faced with a patient who has
cancer and you you know the first
question we often ask is staging because
that tells us a little bit about
how bad it is you know how how far along
it is what is what are their chances
but really from the treatment
perspective it really guides what we're
going to do about it
and so this example here i believe this
is taken from
this is taken from colon cancer this
mapping is really showing you like what
would you do
if cancer was early versus what would
you do if cancer
is late stage and so what you can
actually kind of see from here is that
certain things become more of an option
at different stages and versus other
things sort of
fade out and so an example given give
here is that when uh
colon cancer is developing it's just
usually a small growth which we'll call
a polyp
and if you find that polyp early you
just cut the polyp out
like usually it's kind of a benign
growth i guess the way you could
visualize it is kind of like
the way you'd picture like a wart on the
surface of your skin just imagine that
on the surface
of the lining of your gut like that's
how we think of a polyp it's like it's a
abnormal growth but maybe it hasn't had
the chance to like really
it be invasive like in its own context
or beyond
its own context to other organs and so
you just cut it out
and so that's definitely the main option
that you would pursue early on there's
really no
reason at that point to use chemotherapy
or any of these additional lines of
treatment you
just cut it out versus as what you can
see in this diagram sort of as you go
further along this is the surgery option
you can see it kind of just
fades out here because when you're
dealing with
metastasized cancer again maybe you
could cut out
the main tumor or the tumors that you've
identified
but again it's a trade-off where if the
cancer is metastasized generally
speaking
surgery at that stage is not going to
cure the patient
it's more like is it worth it to maybe
alleviate their
symptoms like to relieve pain so if
there's a
giant tumor and you know that tumor is
metastasized
somewhere else the only reason why you
might consider surgery is if it's sort
of
you know if that in combination with
other things might
eliminate the entire cancer and
everywhere it's spread or if the patient
is suffering a lot you might consider
cutting out the tumor
just because it that tumor is probably
still a huge burden and leading to lots
of
uh effects on their health but you can
see in terms of really thinking about it
as
curative at that point surgery is no
longer curative so it kind of fades out
as an option
um radiation is similar um we'll talk
about radiation in a second but
radiation generally tends to be
something that kind of like
surgery you kind of want to point to a
specific space and say treat here
and so again radiation you don't want to
radiate the whole body you're trying to
target the radiation and we'll talk
about why we use radiation in a second
and then in terms of options that become
more
relevant as we get into later stages
chemotherapy is one of them so you can
see chemotherapy sort of fades in
as we go further along in staging and
then there are some more
targeted therapies that we use
especially for aggressive
and late stage cancer
and we'll talk about these different
targeted therapies here
compared to the general chemotherapy
which is probably the most common
treatment that you've heard about so
this anti-anagen
sorry anti-angiogenic therapy and this
anti-egfr therapy
those are targeted therapies and those
are ones that
might be used for more more than one
type of cancer but you might not have
heard about it in
any cancer context like these these
specific ones listed here aren't ones
that you see used in
every type of cancer you might have
heard about them in the context of
you know lung cancer or maybe brain
cancer
but you don't hear them with literally
every type of cancer
and that's because there is some
specificity involved
all right so let's talk a little bit
about how these treatments work
so what i can just say is that in
general most
classic cancer treatments the way they
work
this might seem obvious but we're going
to kind of dig into this a little more
is that
they the way they work is they're either
physically removing the tumor in the
tumor cells
which you know is the case for surgery
or they're inducing what we call
cytotoxic effects on the cancer cell
so surgery over here you just cut it out
you cut out
the tissue there's definitely a
challenge where you're trying to think
of the margins of like
how big is this tumor how much will this
affect the patient negatively if
i've cut out such a big part of their
body
um and you don't want to like miss some
by accident so that's definitely the
struggle with surgery
versus the cytotoxic effect really is
taking advantage of you know we talked a
bit about
cells and dna and the goal of cytotoxic
effects is that you're killing cancer
cells specifically
and trying not to harm normal healthy
cells
which is challenging as we'll talk about
in a second
but basically we're either cutting out
and removing the tumor tissue from the
body
or we're trying to induce cell death in
the tumor cells specifically
so how do we induce cell death so
radiation is one way as i said radiation
is something that generally has to be
you want it to be targeted you don't
want to sort of be
introducing radiation to healthy parts
of the body
um radiation has been talked about in
terms of oh we use it for
diagnostics like we take an x-ray and we
might see
something that looks abnormal right so
we both use it on the end of
you know when we first have a patient
coming into the clinic we might use this
to diagnose that there's something wrong
and
lead to the diagnosis of cancer but
we're also using it on the treatment end
where we're taking this radiation and in
really high concentrated strong
doses we aim it at where we think the
tumor is
and when radiation hits the tumor
um it basically is inducing
damage to the dna so i think i showed
last time the example of
um a mutagen like a cancer-causing agent
was radiation so when your skin for
example is exposed to a lot of
sun it gets a lot of uv radiation and
especially if you
are prone to getting a lot of sunburns
that's sort of
representing that this this your cells
and your skin are getting
a lot of radiation dosages and it's
probably actually hurting
those cells because like basically the
radiation hits your dna and can cause
that dna to mutate
when that happens in our body our cells
will usually
spot that there's something wrong and
try to repair
the damage but if you have an incredibly
high dosage
of radiation all at once generally
speaking there'll be so much damage to
the dna
that it's kind of hard for the cells to
repair and they actually will tend to
make the decision
to basically kill a compromised cell
like if there's a cell that's highly
mutated it is beyond repair
that cell will generally speaking die it
won't be able to recover from that much
damage
so here you can just imagine we're
taking high doses of radiation we aim it
at where we think the tumor is and we
sort of
shoot the radiation there induce mass
amounts of dna damage in those cancer
cells and those cancer cells
generally speaking might not be able to
recover from it
um so of course again that becomes
less of an option if the tumor isn't
localized because we don't want to just
radiate the whole patient right if the
cancer cells have sort of spread
everywhere
and we don't know where we are we don't
want to introduce that radiation
anywhere right because that's going to
be harming and mutating
normal cells too if we don't focus it so
again that becomes less of an option in
late stage
um if there are any questions i have the
chat open but you can also
click the raise hand button and i'm
happy to answer questions as i go you
don't have to
just wait to the end i'll keep an eye if
i see any
all right and let's talk about
chemotherapy chemotherapy is actually
pretty similar it's just the delivery
mechanisms very different
um i'll say generally speaking a lot of
chemotherapies actually
mess with our dna mess with dna's
ability to
replicate itself so if a cell is
dividing
it needs to make a second copy of its
dna so that the two
resulting daughter cells both have their
own copy of dna
and so if that process is messed with
then those cells just
don't divide or they divide and they run
into issues and that might either
stall them in the middle of dividing or
they might die because they can't
recover they're kind of like stuck and
they kind of can't fix it so at some
point they will
those cells will just die because they
can't resolve the issue
and then some of these chemotherapies
will mess with cell cycle which again is
that process of cells dividing
so there's a particular drug for example
that messes with the ability
of the cells to sort of partition
themselves like they're trying to move
things around so that they can split
into two cells
and basically the the physical things
that help with the
manipulations and pulling things apart
actually just stops working and so
they're just kind of frozen
in place so there's lots of different
chemotherapies that basically
mess with these processes they mess with
our dna they mess with
making more dna they mess with cells
dividing
and as then as that kind of implies
that's kind of a problem because
healthy cells have dna too healthy cells
replicate themselves too
um and so this really hints at why
chemotherapy has so many side effects
because when you're introducing a drug
and i'm just showing a drug here this
is um cisplatin specifically
it's a very commonly used chemotherapy
it's used with
breast cancer probably also lung cancer
lots of different cancers use cis
platins or or
related drugs like carboplatin which is
just a different chemical formulation
but all of these drugs basically go in
and stick to your dna
and that causes dna damage so you can
see here with this uh little
this little chemical here it's going in
and it's basically
sticking itself physically like it's
chemically reacting with our dna
and this in the mind of the cell is
damage it's basically messing with
your dna structure and so if we were
trying to
read this dna or trying to copy this dna
we would run into issues because the
chemical structure of the dna is
different
um and so this is particularly potent
for cancer cells um cancer cells are
kind of
how do i describe them they're kind of
like
cancer cells may come across as very
powerful in terms of all these
additional abilities and the fact that
they sort of um
conquer the environment they're in like
they basically
can kind of uh you know hijack certain
processes
you know steal blood vessels steal
resources but they kind of also just
like
rule over the normal cells around them
because the normal cells around them
obey all these rules and the cancer
cells obey no rules
so they seem very powerful but cancer
cells also kind of are skirting the line
where they are so
that they themselves are so warped and
mutated
in some ways they actually can be very
fragile and so when you're
giving them dna damage sometimes they're
like yes more mutations like this makes
me more powerful but then too many and
they actually
don't have the normal means of resolving
them
and so they can actually be more
sensitive to things that mess with cell
cycle or mess with their dna
because they just they've lost the means
to repair those so they were kind of
super powerful and then they got too
much of it and then they just sort of
give up eat more easily because they
just can't fix it
um but yeah this is also a problem for
healthy cells too
having this sort of compound go around
and bind
to dna and especially mess with dna in
cells that divide
that's what leads to a lot of the side
effects that we see with chemotherapy
when we're thinking about treating
patients with chemotherapy it's
basically
this really careful balance that's
sensitive to the patient
it senses the patient's age and like
coexisting
health conditions like if a patient has
cancer but they also have
um they're also older or maybe they also
have diabetes they have other
conditions um when we're trying to
figure out how much chemotherapy to give
them they're sort of this instinct to
give
tons of chemotherapy right like they're
fighting this battle with cancer and
we're trying to
kill as much of the cancer cells as
possible but basically
as we ramp up the the dosage of the
chemo we just get more and more
negative side effects and there are some
patients where literally if we just kept
giving them chemo the chemo would end up
killing them because the chemo
does things like it harms the lining of
their gut it harms
their ability to produce blood cells so
they become very anemic
um all of these things are like symptoms
that you may have heard cancer or sorry
cancer patients
experience and that's being caused by
the chemo
like of course the cancer is hurting
them and is causing issues but a lot of
the sort of hair loss
nausea and vomiting anemia
skin issues like a lot of those are
coming from actually the chemo
and so we're trying to give them high
dosages to be an effective treatment
against the cancer but then we often
have to hold back because of what the
patient can tolerate right
both in terms of like quality of life
tolerate but also in terms of literally
too much could actually end up killing
them if it's just you know
constantly eroding at their gut and
constantly eroding at their ability to
produce blood cells um
if there are any questions just let me
know let's talk a little bit
about newer treatments so we talked
about surgery
radiation chemotherapy let's talk about
targeted therapy right because i think
one thing we can
realize with chemo is that it's just
sort of this um
it's sort of this like shotgun spray
like it's a very aggressive
treatment and it kind of just hits
there's all of this collateral damage
that's going on because of the nature of
chemo it's like
to kill cancer we're going to target dna
it's like well that's a feature shared
with all cells
so that's kind of a problematic approach
so targeted therapy is trying to be
a little more um like you know narrow
the scope look for a specific feature
that maybe is
more unique to cancer cells or again is
something that just
doesn't hit literally every cell in the
body
and so targeted therapy the real goal
there is that um
by being more specific you just limit
the amount of
um you know side effects that the
patient has to deal with and maybe you
can then
up the dosage because the side effects
are more tolerable it's less harmful to
the body
and again you can then be more
aggressive towards the cancer itself
yeah in terms of thinking how to
personalize
um i would say that there are cases
where you can imagine that
um when making
i mean it's such a tough question when
you're like how much chemo do i give
this patient right
and you're taking into account all of
these features about their current
health
but you're trying to make a prediction
right because you don't want to be in
the case where you
went real easy on the chemo and it
actually wasn't super effective and the
patient's cancer just kept growing
kept spreading right like that that is
such a uh
a terrible position to be in to realize
oh i should have been more aggressive
because the cancer was continuing to get
worse in the meantime um so in that
sense
having more data to influence that just
that choice to be like
okay because of everything we know about
you whether that be
the sequencing the genetics of your
cancer or some other data just like
knowing your circumstances and other
patients who are like you if that could
tell us
yes it's really difficult but we just
have to be more aggressive
up front like we know that if we don't
chances are very likely that it just
we might as well not treat it all i
think that kind of information could be
very useful because
currently yeah it's a regretful position
to be in if you
kind of ease up on the chemo but it just
ultimately isn't
helping the patient at all right like
you don't want to have them go through
the
the stress of chemo and not have it add
additional
you know quality time in their life um
i will speak a bit in general about how
chemo doesn't tend to be curative
for most patients usually the
conversation that's being had is how
much can we add to their life like
chances are
if it's a very late stage cancer they
will probably die to that cancer
but you're hoping that you can add
several months or maybe even
a couple of years to their remaining
life by treating with chemo
so that's kind of the trade-off it's
like you don't want to give them chemo
and have them
suffer and not actually add any time to
their life
so if we had the data to know based on
this patient based on the features of
their tumor based on their
their patient level features we know we
should be more aggressive or
less aggressive like don't make them
suffer chemo if it's not going to help
them in the end that's the kind of
decisions you might want to make
all right so let's talk a little bit
about targeted therapy
um so targeted therapy is something
that's thrown around a lot
it actually isn't super new in the sense
of
we discovered some really early targeted
therapies just based on our
understanding
of um normal human biology
and that helped us discover some
particularly useful
targets but since those early
discoveries a lot of the target
therapies we've discovered have to be
more involved like we've had to turn to
big data to
discover new targets so the classical
targets for targeted therapy were
actually things that are related
to um hormones
and and sexual development so if you
think about what hormones do
in in like the typical human body
whether um biologically male or
biologically female the way a lot of sex
hormones work
is that when they sort of kick into gear
during puberty
they enact a ton of changes in the body
right
when these hormones sort of ramp up and
are being expressed more and they're
moving through the body
in people's teenage years it leads to
the development
of you know the sex organs but it's
basically
switching on all these pathways for a
lot of
tissue and cells to develop right it's
basically saying okay
time to create these new organs or
develop these organs and it basically
ramps up growth and it ramps up cell
division
in those tissues and so our bodies have
this sort of
natural programmed way by which you know
obviously as we
grow older we just like grow bigger and
taller but also that's like a very
key moment in our in our species
development where
we just suddenly will develop new
tissues and grow new tissues
and so there are lots of cancers that
arise
in sex organs that sort of hijack that
normal
process so for example in the uh in
breast cancer i mean in
normal woman development it's like when
the hormones start that actually
kick-starts the development of the
breast so like breast tissue starts to
divide and proliferate
and so when you have a breast cancer
it's actually using that pathway to sort
of
tell itself to keep growing and dividing
so it's like what happened in puberty to
lead to growth of that tissue
cancer is using that pathway to just
tell itself continuously to grow and
divide and so that's a very
precise pathway that's specific to
cells that relate to the sex organs it's
not
true of all cells right like not all
cells in your body
are using for example estrogen in that
way
and so when someone realized hey these
breast cancer tumors seem to be
expressing a lot of
estrogen receptor like they're they're
they're really responsive to this
hormone
um that made them realize oh if we block
this the signaling the messaging through
this hormone receptor
um so that it stops basically picking up
on any amount of estrogen and telling
itself divide divide forever keep
dividing
um if we block that it is something that
the tumor is very
reliant on like it really uses that uh
hormone receptor to power its ability to
keep dividing
but that's not true of all of the
healthy cells i mean it's true of some
of the healthy cells like there are some
normal cells especially in a woman's
body that do
respond to estrogen but it's not true of
literally every cell in her body right
literally every cell in her body has dna
so if we target dna that's a huge
problem but if we target this estrogen
receptor it's just
more specific the the the eligible
population is a lot
smaller of who would be affected and so
that's what they basically did was they
created what we call these estrogen
blockers
an example of that is tamoxifen so
tamoxifen is something that
kind of looks like estrogen
and when it's flowing through someone's
body if someone's undergoing
treatment for breast cancer and they
know they have a cancer
that is reliant on estrogen which is not
true of every breast
cancer but if they test and they know
hey you have breast cancer and you
specifically have estrogen
dependent breast cancer it has a large
amount of this
estrogen receptor because it mutated in
a way to have tons of it
if they identify that about the tumor
then they know that they're a good
candidate for this specific
treatment this targeted therapy and so
you add the estrogen
mimic this tamoxifen it'll bind to the
estrogen receptor but it doesn't
actually send
the signal it basically blocks the
ability of that receptor to
respond to normal estrogen because it's
kind of sitting in its spot
and blocking their ability to talk to
each other
and so generally speaking if there's a
cancer again that's really reliant on
this estrogen signaling
it can no longer send those signals and
chances are its ability to
divide and grow will be stalled and in
some cases without that
kind of uh continuous
encouragement the cells might also die
this is maybe one thing that isn't super
apparent about cells but
if you ever go on to study and research
cell biology um we grow lots of cells
in cultures and dishes but that's not
actually very typical of
normal cells generally speaking if you
extract cells from a person and put them
in a dish
they won't grow because they don't have
the environment they expect
and the environment they expect is both
the interactions with their neighboring
cells
who like tell them reassuring things but
there's also
like um signals that our bodies produce
that sort of flow everywhere
that help reassure ourselves basically
i i don't know how to describe this
other than saying like our cells get
really lonely
like if you just extract the cell and
put in a dish without
all of the messaging that it expects and
all of the communication with its
neighbors those cells will actually die
because they don't
have that constant messaging around them
so cancer cells can be similar where you
sort of starve
the messaging that they're expecting and
they'll actually die without that
messaging
and so we have used this very
effectively again specifically in
patients
who use estrogen receptor um
so if they we test their tumor and we're
like oh your tumor is
dependent on estrogen it has a lot of
this receptor being expressed
those patients will do very well with
tamoxifen with these this particular
therapy
if they don't express a lot of this
estrogen receptor their tumor
isn't using the estrogen pathway and so
the the treatment doesn't make any
difference to them
and so at the diagnosis stage you would
diagnose someone for example a woman
with
breast cancer but you would also then
genotype you
test the genetics of her tumor to figure
out is she
er positive is she dependent on estrogen
or is she not in terms of her tumor
and i just want to say this has been
really powerful because for some women
who we anticipate might be very
sensitive to developing breast cancer
you can actually give these women
tamoxifen preemptively as a preventative
measure so before they even get breast
cancer if a woman
because of her family history or her
lifestyle or other factors if a woman is
very
likely to develop a severe breast cancer
you can tell her to take tamoxifen
early and she just will be less likely
to to develop it in her lifetime
so this is a very effective and again
targeted therapy it's not like there's
no side effects
but the side effects are less severe
compared to
a treatment that literally targets all
dna
are there any other questions up until
this point
okay
all right so let's talk a bit about
discovering new targeted therapies
um and so i'm gonna walk you through
this diagram and explain what it's
showing
but i'm gonna just give you a couple of
ways that we've sort of tried to
discover
new targeted therapies because again you
can imagine in the prior case with the
woman who has breast cancer if we
test her her cancer and we realize oh
it's estrogen dependent
we've created this new option for her
right she might be very responsive to
tamoxifen
but imagine the patients who test
negative like what do we tell them they
basically
don't have that option it's harder to
treat their cancer so we're trying to
think about what is
what is true about their tumor that
gives us a new way to treat
them specifically that maybe isn't true
of the women who
use tamoxifen instead so we're trying to
discover these new targeted therapies um
the ones involving hormones were a
little easier because it was
it it leveraged what we already knew
about how
certain tissues work especially those
related to sex organs
but now everything else is sort of more
of like this open
search for anything that might be the
achilles heel of a given cancer
and so there's a couple ways we think
about identifying
um new targeted therapies so one thing i
will mention
is when we're thinking about targeted
therapies you can imagine and i think i
showed the inner
ring last time in terms of a diagram is
that there's all of these
facets of cancer part of cancer is that
it you know is able to divide forever
part of cancer is that it's able to
invade and metastasize
another part of cancer is that things
that would normally trigger a healthy
cell to die such as you know breaking
the rules
um or not enough food to go around
cancer cells have evolved to overcome
that
messaging and so they're able to resist
cell death
and so all of those that inner ring is
showing these traits that are
true of cancer cells and so what's being
shown along the outer ring
is showing examples of treatments that
are basically trying to
target that feature so for example if
cancer cells are able to invade and
metastasize
there might be an inhibitor of a
specific protein or
enzyme that has a role in
cells ability to move around or a cell's
ability to go from one place
and like land and survive that journey
and land in another tissue
so what's being shown around the outer
ring are examples of targeted
drugs that are aimed at that trait
like if cells if cancer cells can change
their metabolism let's target their
ability
to change their metabolism and so that's
sort of
one very targeted approach
yeah sahil that's a great question do we
layer targeted drugs on top of each
other
um we do we absolutely do um
so one thing that might not have been
obvious from
um from that first slide i showed
you actually let me go back to it very
briefly
um from this sort of staging diagram and
thinking about the treatments
something that might be not so obvious
is that
there are times where we kind of will
try one treatment and then when that
doesn't work we just go to the next one
so that's a lot of this sort of first
line second line is deciding oh you know
we'll try this first if that doesn't
work we'll go to the next
option but there are cases where
um we've done research and we realized
certain things are really effective
in conjunction with each other and
assuming that
two drugs which generally speaking then
brings two different sets of side
effects
if those still are tolerable there are
cases where we know that the combination
is more effective
um and we will actually talk about why
we tend towards combinations
um there's sort of like a a theoretical
reason why combinations do really work
well um that we'll talk about but yeah
we there are cases where we just sort of
go from one to the next and i think that
tends to be where
the two together are intolerable or um
there's still this hope oh if this one
really works we don't even like we can
save that other option
till later so that we just have more
options so like
let's exhaust this one first um yeah but
there is a lot of research where
clinical
trials are just basically like let's try
a plus b
or let's try a plus b plus c um that's
definitely something that's always
being researched
all right um i think i will actually
skip this next one and go to here
because i think this is very relevant to
how
when you're when you are someone who's
very data oriented i think
this mean this strategy of identifying
targeted therapies might resonate a lot
which is to say there's been a lot of
work
where people as they are
collecting all of these different tumor
samples
and sequencing all of them they're
really interested in okay well what
mutations are really
common either across all cancers or in
certain types of cancer so if you
collected a lot of different
lung tumors what is like the
general profile of a lung tumor what
tends to be mutated
um and the idea is that if you identify
certain things that
tend to be mutated you would think okay
well then
is that a target if there's something
that's mutated and often is like
acting abnormally in cancer if i target
it
um specifically like the mutant or the
overactive version
that might be an option for treatment
for can for patients who test positive
for that mutation as well
and i want to be clear that's not true
of all patients so for example here you
can see
this was true of like 13
of patients but the idea is that you can
imagine oh if a patient comes into the
clinic we might test for this one
this one and this one and you know
together
that might account for 30 to 40 to 50
percent of patients
have at least one of them and so we
might test them for all of these
mutations to then point to like
should you take drug a or drug b or drug
c that target each of these mutations
and so there's been a lot of work where
we've sequenced so many tumors to try to
basically be able to develop
like hey a subset of lung cancer
patients are eligible
for this we've developed a drug that now
targets this so we'll
we'll genotype them when they get
diagnosed to point them to this therapy
so this is something that has happened a
lot as long as we've
had sequencing available and been
sequencing tumors we've been working on
trying to figure out
what mutations are targets
but i wanted to be very clear though
that all of these different options
don't tend to work so well in practice
um generally speaking once a patient is
at
a later stage so the cancer has
metastasized
i think i forgot to emphasize this but
when you're at a later stage
in in cancer and the cancer has spread
we often use a lot of these therapies
like these targeted therapies or
chemotherapies because the idea is that
they go throughout the entire body
right when you're a patient who's being
given cisplatin
um you'll get it usually for like an iv
drip or maybe you take a pill
that sort of just goes throughout your
whole body like it's flowing
in your blood going throughout your
whole body
and the idea is you take those types of
treatments those
systemic treatments because your cancer
spreads such that
yeah we know that there's a tumor and we
can you know target that tumor
but the cancer cells could kind of be
anywhere and so you're taking the
systemic treatment to hopefully kill
the cells wherever they might be
hopefully you'll hit the tumor cells
wherever they have ended up
and so later stage patients usually what
we
point them to is chemotherapy or a
targeted therapy they might be eligible
for
because it will go throughout their
whole body but again these are patients
who
are at those later stages surgery was
not a curative option for them so we
point them to chemo or we point them to
targeted therapy
but i will just say again i mentioned
this this doesn't tend to be curative
it's more like it buys them more time
um generally speaking we tend to see
curves like this one
what this curve is showing you is sort
of out of a total number of patients how
many were still alive after a certain
point of time when they've been
um when they've been diagnosed
they've tried the localized treatments
and then they get on a targeted therapy
um or a chemotherapy what you can see is
that all of the curves collapsed to zero
right
ultimately all of the patients in both
cohorts
died but what happened to the patients
who got the targeted therapy
versus the ones who didn't is that it
was shifted
so we've shifted the curve to the right
which just means that they get more time
they get some number of months and lucky
cases they get some number of years
where they continue to survive but
ultimately
it doesn't cure them of their cancer
and i'll just say that the closest we've
come to that so far
has been things like immunotherapy which
is where a lot of the excitement has
come from
and so i'm just going to compare these
two curves which is
on this side it's as you've seen here
where it's like there's a shift
there's a shift but ultimately both of
them collapse
to zero and so in both cases all
patients
die it's just a matter of some of them
get more time
what's being shown here on the right and
this is in the case of immunotherapy
is um you don't necessarily see this
shift
but there are a subset of patients again
what this is showing here is of the
hundred percent of patients who were in
the cohort originally
if all of them die the curve collapses
down to zero
but what you'll see here is that this
curve actually doesn't collapse all the
way to zero so this is
shown here in the purple this doesn't
collapse to zero and so there's a subset
of patients who just keep
living and so for them essentially
they've been cured or they're like they
they are sort of the exception
versus everyone else who they had more
time but they never they still ended up
dying
these patients just keep living and it's
not all of them
it doesn't work for all of them but this
in and of itself is just a
change in what we've tended to expect
right with every additional treatment
it's kind of been like oh i can shift it
even more but it still collapses to zero
that's been the dichotomy that we've
been used to is
the original curve versus a shifted
curve and how far we shift it
versus thinking about are there patients
that just keep living
so that's been a lot of the excitement
around chemotherapy but i did want to
touch on
why some patients or why is it so hard
to cure patients
why is it that with all of these
targeted therapies ultimately all
patients still die
um sorry i should be clear that's not
the case in literally every cancer there
are some cancers where we
can cure them with target therapy it's
just that tends to be the exception
rather than the other way around so
rather than saying oh target therapy is
cure most patients but there's some
patients who
can't help it tends to be that target
therapies
don't cure most patients but there are a
couple of exceptions where it does
um and so some of you may have heard of
there's this drug
called uh glebec and it is specifically
used in a type of blood cancer i believe
the cancer is used in this cml
and so in that very particular type of
cancer for patients who are eligible for
that targeted therapy
it actually works really really well
like a lot of those patients tend to be
cured or survive many years um some of
them might relapse
after a long period of time but there
are some patients who just seem to keep
living with this drug
um so i don't want to say like it
literally never works i would just say
by and large and especially for a lot of
the most common types of cancer like
lung cancer or breast cancer or cancer
of the brain
we tend to see this type of pattern more
where
you know it helps for a while but it
ultimately can't cure them
um and i just want to talk about why
that is and really
the theoretical point of view for why
this is the case
is actually evolution so you may have
learned about evolution in the context
of like species of things like
animals or plants or people or bacteria
and the idea is that
with evolution these
different populations of living things
like i think the common example is like
oh the gazelle and the gazelle needs to
outrun the lion
um and the idea is oh the gazelle would
evolve
ways to be able to better elude the lion
right so they can survive and they can
reproduce and so if there's
a way they can evolve better camouflage
if they can evolve to run
faster all of those things would
contribute to them being more likely to
survive
attacks by lion and so their genetics
sort of slowly evolve over time to
select
for if a mutation arises that like leads
to a coat that's harder for the lion to
see
that gets selected for and that becomes
more common in the population of gazelle
because that
gazelle basically lives when whereas
others might die
and they pass on that mutation um cancer
works very similarly in the sense of you
have to think of it as
a tumor is a collection of cells
each cell has its own dna granted they
all
originated from your body so they share
a lot of dna
but as cancers start to become cancerous
they're basically accumulating mutations
and each cell is its own
agent like each cell may have come from
another cell
but during the lifetime of that cell
they can continue
to mutate because of you know the cancer
cells just make a lot of mistakes
the cancer cells are being exposed to
all of these dna mutating
substances um and so each cell is kind
of like its
own agent that is unlike that is
undergoing changes
and if an uh mutation arises in one of
those cells
that is advantageous it becomes selected
for
so when we're thinking of a cancer
cancers arise from a single cell
that accumulates some mutations and
generally leads to that cell
growing and dividing more than it's
supposed to
and when it grows and divides more than
it's supposed to it ends up creating a
population right because that growth
all of the cells that descended from
that growth there's a collection of them
right and each of those has a chance to
mutate
so in this collection there might be a
certain cell that
randomly gets a mutation that allows it
to then do something that it was
unable to do before so for example this
could allow it to
invade physically into a new space that
it couldn't survive in before
and as it invades it you know makes a
home in that new space
it continues to grow and divide and so
it again it creates this
population of cells and each cell
has a chance to divide and each cell has
a chance to
mutate and so if it mutates it can gain
a new ability
it can become selected for and again
create its own new population so it
basically just continues to evolve from
there
and that's what we actually see when we
try to treat so this tx basically stands
for treatment
um when we're treating basically at that
point in time
let me clear this so when we're treating
at that point in time
we see this sort of collection of cells
that makes up the tumor and it's a very
diverse collection which is
what's being shown with all these
different colors and when we're trying
to treat them we're trying to kill all
of them and maybe we're very
successful at killing most of these but
maybe there is
one cell that has mutation that means it
doesn't respond to the treatment
we've killed all of its competition that
cell is selected for it is the one
gazelle that outran the lion and so left
to its own devices it basically keeps
dividing and all of its
uh cells that it creates all carry that
resistance mutation
and so that's what we tend to see in
cancer is that we'll treat
um with a targeted therapy the tumor
looks like it's responding because it'll
generally stop growing it might even
regress
so the tumor looks like it's getting
smaller and smaller
but then at some point we sort of killed
all of the cells that were sensitive to
the drug
but there might be some number of cells
that have a resistance mutation
and so at that point they don't shrink
any further
and actually they start to grow back
because the drug makes no difference
them they basically don't see
or don't respond to the drug so we see
that with patients where the tumor
regresses
stops responding and it starts regrowing
and that is
very typical because basically their
cancer has evolved at that point
are there any questions about that
so my question is again refer back to
the kovi situation we know the
rna keeps on mutate mutating
yes so are we eventually going to face
this kind of dilemma
because of this mutation the current
vaccine may not work
so you mentioned about the shape of uh
the the virus may be the same but
who knows i i i don't have any
information to do any prediction yeah i
mean that's a really interesting
question
i will say one thing to keep in mind is
generally speaking
the repertoire that a virus has to work
with
tends to be a bit smaller than a cancer
cell
right like a cancer cell basically has
all of the genes that you do and then
starts to like
use them in very creative ways right
like it takes your existing genes and
maybe expresses them in new
configurations
or mutates them so it's expressing like
a different version um
viruses have a much smaller genomes
so they generally speaking have a little
less to work with like the amount they
can mutate
and kind of change what we're working
with is smaller
um i think what more people tend to be
worried about and what leads to really
big issues is when
viruses sort of combine um
so i'm trying to think of the picture
there's this really great picture of it
actually let me just
try to show it
um so there's this really great picture
so when you're thinking about a virus
right
um and i'm just gonna draw like spikes
on the outside because this is basically
the spikes are important because the
spikes are basically how
if it runs into a human cell it's
basically
looking for something on the human cell
that it can
grab onto and is the means by which it
invades
so if this is a virus if this protein
is specific to this feature and this
tends to be the case for kovid that it's
something that's common in your lungs
it basically can bind to that and that's
its entry route is that it it binds to
those types of cells and it enters right
so someone who's getting infected by a
virus it's like oh just having the virus
interact with your skin
for example isn't enough because the
thing it binds to isn't on your skin
it's a specific feature on your cells
that are common in your lungs or in your
like
the track to leading to your lungs um so
what i'll say
is that the amount of genetics that's in
here
tends to be pretty limited for viruses
compared to cells
so first off that just means like
probability wise if you're dealing with
something i don't actually know how long
the covid
genome is like just compared to human
where it's like oh we have you know
three
billion bases to work with it's much
shorter
for actually let me look it up copied
genome length
um it is thirty
thousand three thousand thirty k
so compared to three billion it's a lot
smaller
um and so the amount that it can mutate
tends to be
quite limited like it doesn't sort of
have as many of the endless
possibilities for what it can do
i think the thing to also consider is
that
i think there's a lot of concern around
it mutating
these outer proteins so that what
our immune cells right our immune cells
are supposed to develop these receptors
that can find these viruses
and the idea is if they change their
spots then our immune cells can't do
that anymore
um but i think a thing to keep in mind
is these outer proteins are
serving a purpose for the virus like it
literally can't change its spots to be
any color any shape because at some
point if it changes too much it actually
can't bind to the lung
cells anymore sorry i apologize if i can
hear that
um so i think that's a problem for the
virus where it's like there are some
mutations that might make it
really good at evading our are prompted
our vaccine immune response but that
also might make it worse at infecting
right or it might change who it infects
um i mean i think that might be
something to be concerned about is that
if it
somehow very effectively changes who it
infects it just means that the like
yes our vaccine won't work as well but i
think also then the
the disease it leads to will be
different right like the disease we know
is because it infects on lung cells so
if that changes its target it's gonna be
a different disease in some sense
um so that's what i would keep in mind
is just it's smaller it doesn't have
like the potential to mutate literally
in any way because it's kind of facing
this trade-off
it's like oh if it evades the immune
destruction it just might also not be as
good at being a virus
uh those are the things i would consider
i think one of the concerns people have
had is
what it's it's um it's something that
happened
with the i believe that's what happened
with the 1918
flu which is the concern of a
co-infection that leads to exchange
between two viruses
so generally speaking when a cell a
human cell
or an animal cell is infected by
two different virus particles at the
same time
um what can happen is the way these
viruses often work is that they kind of
just basically
inject their genetic material into the
cell and make the cell do what it wants
and often what it wants is it wants the
cell to become a factory to make more
virus
but if you have a co-infection so two
different viruses at the same time
their dna both gets plopped in here and
in generally speaking
it's not like it knows which dna came
from
who and so what can happen is you can
end up with a virus that's kind of like
a hybrid between these two viruses
and i think that's something that people
are concerned about with
viruses in general not specific to cova
just in general
usually this hybrid virus can sometimes
be the worst of both worlds
so i think that's something that people
might be concerned about
but generally speaking like we deal with
this with the flu
every year is that it changes its spots
enough
that it avoids our vaccine response but
i think there's only so much it can
change
that like i just don't know if
covid variant in future years
i don't know if we'll have endless
variants or even then i don't know if
the variance will just keep getting
worse they just might be different um
yeah i'm sorry i think it's very hard to
say but those are just some of my early
thoughts
thank you so much yeah no problem um
so let me see sorry i'm just looking
ahead at stuff
um i think this is a good place for just
one well
actually we go to 10 right
is that accurate edward oh you're muted
we we end at about 9 50 but we can't go
to
oh no no i don't i don't believe in
keeping people beyond
um so i'm trying to think about what
would be more interesting for people
to hear about are people more interested
in hearing about
immunotherapy or do they just want sort
of an example
of algorithms being used to guide
treatments
people can sort of either weigh in
verbally or they can weigh in in the
chat but they'd be more interested in
immunotherapy or
applications of ml in treatments
all right i'm hearing applications of ml
okay so let me give
one example um
that was actually research i worked on
so let's go to
here all right so let's talk a little
bit about examples of this kind of
research so again we face this really
difficult issue where we have
patience we're trying to figure out what
therapies would work
better in them often better just means
longer survival times it doesn't often
mean cures
but even then we still think that's a
worthwhile area to pursue
and so i have several examples that are
shown in my slides but i'm actually
going to focus on the one
that i worked on um so the one that i
worked on
um one thing i have to establish about
the thing that i worked on
is that we are dealing with sort of
two levels of data in this data set what
we have
is um like first off what we have is
basically a collection of cancer cells
but what i'll tell you is that what can
be the case for this type of data
is that we're collecting single cell
data where we basically measure and
profile
each individual cell but what you can
imagine is when you're doing
research on patients you can have
this data collected from every single
patient that you work with
and so you have kind of two levels of
data you have the level of data that's
like each individual patient
but then if you're collecting a sample
from them and and uh
characterizing their sample with
single cell data you actually get
two levels of individual there's the
individual cell
that came from an individual patient so
there's a population of patients
and for each patient they have their own
population of cells that we're working
with
and so that's something that leads to a
lot of interesting like
multi-level problem solving where you're
like oh i'm trying to
predict something for the patient on the
basis of the diversity of cancer cells
they have
so if you're used to working with data
where it's like oh for every single
patient i have these rows
and on the columns i have different
features about them
it actually becomes that this is a
tabular data set you have
for every single person each person has
their own tabular data set for every
cell that you collected from them
and so again this is like a multi-level
problem-solving step
but i just want to give you a glimpse
into how we deal with the single cell
data so just like
ignoring the individual we can't that it
came from let's just focus on these
single cells
so i was working in a lab where we had a
means by which we could take these cells
and sample them and basically measure
multiple features in each individual
cell
we were measuring it on the protein
level so again we talked
last time about like measuring their
genetics measuring what their rna
they're producing and then measuring the
protein they've produced
we were measuring protein they've
produced so we took these cells
and what we did is that we exposed them
to a couple different
treatments that are very commonly used
to treat
this particular type of cancer so the
cancer i was dealing with is called
multiple myeloma it is a cancer of the
blood
um so you would can't you would collect
cells from their blood or from their
bone marrow
and so we take these cells and we expose
them to the most
common treatments that are used for this
particular type of cancer because
our interest was looking at different
time points like
before treatment during treatment
sorry i'm gonna get rid of my little
doodle um and after treatment
we wanted to see okay what's happening
like
starting cells cells in progress of
being exposed to drug and you know
responding to that drug and then cells
at the very end where it's kind of very
clear that some cells have died and some
cells have lived and so those
living cells are resistant for some
reason or another
and so we had a means by which we could
collect cells at these different time
points
and measure up to 40 proteins
in each individual cell so again the
data format was like
each row was a different cell collected
at a different time points you have to
remember
each cell which time point it came from
and then on the columns was like amount
of protein a
amount of protein b amount of protein c
and so forth
so that's the data set we collected you
can imagine it's like a tabular data set
of cells
maybe for each separate time point in
each separate treatment as well
and what i was interested in doing um
again methods wise it wasn't the most
like sophisticated method but again
we're always dealing with this trade-off
where it's like the more complex the
method is the more we don't actually
understand
what is happening under the hood so the
way we
worked with this was actually we wanted
to do a classification
which was to sort of determine what
cells
are ultimately the ones that die with
drug which is the sensitive cell
versus the cells that don't die of drug
those are the resistant
cells so if you have this data where
you've treated them with drug and some
of the cells are alive and some of the
cells are dead after drug treatment
so again um resistant versus sensitive
we wanted to use a classification model
to figure out well what are these
features that lead to cells that tend to
be alive or tend to be dead
at the last time point and so we were
interested in basically identifying
the most strong features that lead to
cells being classified as sensitive
versus resistant
so if you're not familiar with how
random force models work um
you don't get one single tree so i've
drawn a single tree here for the
classification where it's like oh
depending on the levels of this protein
you would go into this bucket versus
this bucket when you're dealing with a
random forest it's a forest so there's
too many of those trees you don't have
one single tree or one consensus tree
but you do get a sense of what tends
to be an effective split um
i wrote gate here because that's the
word we use a lot in biology is the
gating based on expression like high
expression versus low expression of a
protein
but you can think of it as like the
split in each level of the tree
so something that tends to pop up a lot
like let's say
marker x does a really good job of
splitting between cells that are
resistant versus cells that are
sensitive
um in a random force model you can see
what tends to be a good
splitter and those become like
more important variables so they're
weighted more highly
and so even though you don't get a
single tree you do get that information
and so we got that information and what
we saw was that there were clearly
a most important marker for
distinguishing cells that live in cells
that die
and it actually tended to be pretty
similar between these two drugs that
work
in wildly different ways like the
biology of what these two drugs are
doing is incredibly different
and yet the same two features were the
most powerful for making the cells
more likely to be resistant or more
likely to be sensitive to both of these
drugs
and so again if you're thinking about
the goal of this project is to identify
what makes a cell more likely to be
resistant and ultimately the practical
application of that is if you know what
makes that cell
special from the get-go like if you know
oh ultimately this patient will probably
relapse because there are these cells
that have a lot of these proteins and
that for some reason makes them more
hardy like more resistant
if you know that ahead of time your goal
would be oh can we like preempt that
somehow right
if we can kind of cut them off at the
pass we know that those cells will
ultimately probably
not respond to the drug can we add
something additional so they
they they'll kind of like we hit most of
them with the first drug
but the second drug kind of hits the
ones who would have responded
or would have failed to respond the
first time we still eliminate them with
the second
like line of attack um and so that's
what we've decided to pursue which was
that we had a specific therapy against
mcl1 which is one of these two top
features
and so what we did is we showed that if
you co-treat
with a therapy against mcl1 so that's
what's actually shown here on the far
right if you co-treat with them they're
very
synergistic and i want to be clear to
define what synergistic means for
cancer biology what synergistic means
for cancer biology is that
the effects of the drugs are not
additive
so if one drug kills 10 and another drug
kills 30
it's not like you just add those
percentages together it's actually that
you kill more than you would have
expected than if you just added the two
together that's when it's synergistic
and what we found was that using this
inhibitor against mcl1 which was that
highly predictive feature
using that in concert with the original
drug was
very synergistic it was like we killed
the original cells with
dexamethasone and we killed some cells
that would have been left over with the
mcl1 inhibitor but we also just
generally
killed more than just the two of them
added together
i just wanted to say that these other
two were just other examples of
treatments that are kind of similar to
mcl one and they kind of help but they
don't help to the same extent
as mcl one because that was what we
identified as the
key feature of our resistance cells
and i just want to share we did find
that that ultimately was true of
patients as well is that patients just
did better
with the two treatments as opposed to
with any treatment alone like we had
more killing of cancer cells
but i do want to really highlight again
and this is a continuous problem
this middle bar here these middle
samples these dots are showing for each
patient how many cancer cells did we
kill with the combined treatment
and you can see that each point tends to
be lower
than either treatment alone so these are
just one treatment at a time
and you can see for example this purple
dot we
it actually this this treatment actually
led to more cells being alive which was
interesting
uh versus this treatment killed some
some of the cells
with the two together we tended to kill
more cells
but it also tended to be more than just
the addition
it would kill like multiplicatively
um but i do want to point out that most
of these don't actually go to zero
and i think that's a very important
thing to highlight is that we again kill
more cancer cells but we don't usually
kill
all of the cancer cells and that's where
we draw the line between being curative
versus just helping prolong life
[Music]
all right i think realistically that's
all i had time
to talk about i thought i had less to
talk about but i didn't
um so i think i wanted to just put this
slide up and just like open it up for
questions broader questions um i just
wanted to put this here that if you're
interested in careers that relate to
cancer biology and ai applications
there are a lot of options um so i just
put a couple of different
companies or non-profit institutes that
i know have actively recruited a lot of
computational biologists recently
or computational folks who work on
biology problems
there's a lot of issues around again
trying to
you know create the best algorithm to
know how to stratify
patients or just be able to dive into
the data and
better understand how cancer functions
or a specific type of cancer functions
all of those are really active areas of
research and of course
in current usa i know that kovid is
dominating
health interests right now but i will
say that's kind of anomalous like for so
long america has been sort of this first
world country where we don't
think a lot about infectious disease
with like a couple of exceptions
cancer has by and large been like the
thing that dominates
the american consciousness in terms of
health and that's
we've just kind of been in a weird time
where that's actually not true
but that's been true for like decades
like i think the war on cancer started
in like 1950
and we've been fighting it ever since to
try to understand
how to cure cancer so i think this is a
very active area if you're interested in
it um
it really draws on a lot of different
understandings of modeling and
the different types of data you'll work
with
yeah definitely this is a very critical
area so so one quick question i have is
one of my colleagues jeff huber started
a company called grail
g-r-a-i-l the the mission was to detect
cancer
early so do you know anything about the
work
at grey grail um i'm not familiar with
it
i'm just like looking it up so yeah to
be able to detect early
uh seems to be very useful right
like in my age i will be very happy to
be able to do some kind of early
detection yeah yeah that's a great point
um i didn't even bring it up
but there's an entire world of cancer
screening
which we consider different like cancer
diagnosis versus cancer screening cancer
diagnosis is where you have a reason to
suspect there's cancer right like you're
like oh
you have symptoms like you're coming
into the office the doctor's office for
a reason
and so the issue of diagnosis is like
yeah you don't want to
misdiagnose you don't want to you want
to understand what's happening as best
as you can that involves staging or like
how aggressive their cancer is or if
it's a certain subtype
so that's diagnosis screening is where
you find cancer where you have no reason
to suspect
the person has cancer and so that
actually usually tends to be
imaging related things so like for for
for women it's like
mammograms for general population like
colonoscopies like
there's lots of ways we try to screen
for cancer ahead of time but a lot of
them
are intense like resource intensive
and a lot of them are imaging based so i
do know i'm just looking at
grail it's like there is a lot of
interest to see if you could
detect the hints of cancer from a blood
sample like
taking blood and testing blood is like
one of the most like common workflows in
healthcare
so if you could just like take blood and
you're like yeah i'm going to test your
cholesterol but i'm also going to like
see if you have cancer like that would
be very easy to integrate into
healthcare
pipeline like it wouldn't be as onerous
as
currently we just have to bring people
in and do a colonoscopy which takes a
lot
of resources um yeah so i know there is
a lot of interest there i think a lot of
times though what i
imagine for those types of um problems
in trying to solve those problems is
it's partially a hardware issue like
it's harshly like
do we have technology that's sensitive
enough to be able to pick up on the
signal
and then on the software side it's like
okay if we have this really dim
signal and it's a mishmash of like it's
very noisy can we still
tell that it's something significant so
i think that's still just an active area
both on the
engineering side and also on the data
side okay thank you
are there any other questions i can
answer
do blood tests currently screen for
blood cancer um
i don't know how routine it is it is
something that
tends to be very obvious um
if someone has a blood-based cancer if
you take a blood test
um it both can affect
the way your blood behaves so for
example the way that you
you form like clots like if you bleed
like
the ability of the blood to clot the way
that we'd expect it to
is changed so a nurse might be like wow
this blood is not
like this blood is behaving kind of
abnormally um but also if they do any
kind of test that involves a smear where
they just like
splay out the blood and they look under
a microscope if you have a blood cancer
they would be able to see that right
away i just don't know that every single
type of test
involves looking under the microscope
but those tend to be really
um obvious yeah
blood cancers though tend to be very
like they tend to
manifest quickly and have symptoms
quickly um
yeah i think health and physical
examinations i think that's really
interesting because again
things like colonoscopies or prostate
exams can
help with early detection but like it's
a very
private experience and so a lot of
people just don't want to get
screened like they're like oh i don't
want cancer but i also
either like it's a lot of resources you
need good health care access but a lot
of people also just
don't want to go get the screenings done
because they're very invasive
or if they feel personally invasive so
that's also an
issue as well so like something like a
blood test i think is very normal to
people and i think they would be more
willing to
to be part of that procedure
um yeah i don't know if there's ways to
detect
other types of cancer from blood imaging
um technically if you have a
late stage um one way that cancer
might be spreading from one place to
another is through the blood
but it's very rare um i mean it's very
rare to see
right like so if you have a cancer
that's started in one organ and it's
metastasizing to another organ and the
way it's doing so is by
transit through the blood so technically
in your blood somewhere there might be
transiting cancer cells
i just think that the chances that
you'll like extract some blood look
under a microscope and see that cancer
cell is still
fairly rare like there's so many blood
cells
like they're you've kind of drowned out
any of these rare
spreading cancer cells but yes
technically there are these things
called
circulating tumor cells so the common
name is ctcs
and there's been interest in either
finding them but again they're very rare
so it's hard for researchers to
specifically get them even if they're
trying to pick them up um and so that's
not even to diagnose like you you
already know the person has cancer
you're just trying to catch them
that's very challenging but i think
there is interest again it kind of hints
at this company grail
is that um when you have ctcs like these
circulating tumor cells in the blood
they very often break like they very
often will just die in transit because
they're undergoing so much like
pressure like the blood that flows
through fast at such high pressure
that cells often will break apart um if
they're not
blood cells blood cells are designed to
do it but you know a cell in your from
your lungs isn't designed to
to withstand that type of pressure and
so those cells will break open
and their dna and their contents will
then be flying around in your blood
and so a company like grail is trying to
find the fragments
of a cancer cell in your blood
um that's a little more likely that you
might like pick up on hey there's some
rogue dna
in this blood sample like that that is
something you might be looking for
instead
rather than imaging and seeing a cancer
cell
uh what am i most excited about um
i do think immunotherapy is very
exciting as i said i mean my
my my thesis work was on targeted
therapies but it was kind of
disheartening because like
the evolution paradigm is so powerful
right like the diversity of life we see
on this planet is because of evolution
and the fact that
you can see such clever evolution like
it's supposed to be a completely random
process and yet you see
living things adapting to the most
ridiculous circumstances on this earth
like evolves to eat this one thing and
live in this one place and adapt this
one
crazy weather pattern and so
knowing that that's the power of
evolution and that cancer cells are
really
in tune with that power um is a little
disheartening when you work on targeted
therapy because you're kind of
very outpaced in terms of what you do
versus immunotherapy
is using your cells to fight these
cancer cells like your cells
unfortunately have kind of been
suppressed
during cancer like for some reason the
cancer has
evaded your immune system but if you
could empower your immune system immune
systems are a little more
flexible or adaptable than like a
chemical compound
and so i think that's exciting if we can
somehow empower our own immune system
because our own immune system
is flexible it's not just sort of do we
see compound or not does compound bind
to target or not
there's like more to it yeah so i think
that's what i'm most excited about
yeah any other questions
okay so if you have more questions to
ask melisa just
enter to select or just send or send
email to
melissa directly i really like to
appreciate
the insightful and edifying lectures
given by
melissa and it's always my pleasure to
listen to your lectures
even this is the third time every time i
can learn something from you
it's really wonderful so thank you thank
you very much
yes awesome thank you yeah feel free to
be in touch i put my email in the chat