good morning
everyone
last time we started presenting the
history of nature language processing
and we started
presenting the first epoch
and engineering features
so
today i'm going to continue to go
through the history until
last year and hopefully we can get into
some future discussions if not we can
wrap up nlp in the next lecture
and meanwhile i'd like to encourage you
to
finalize your
project proposal
and we can have the proposal decided
by this week or latest the next tuesday
okay so
after
about 20 minutes into a lecture i will
pause
for a few minutes so you can raise
questions
and at any time please enter your
questions into the chat room
so
we divide the nlp history into
three major parts
and then we have this frontier research
and the last time we started with the
hand engineering models based on
heuristics
and we motivated
nature language is unique to human being
and from the dna structures
the only difference from us
from our predecessor chimpanzees just
the second pair of dna
but however with that difference
we are able to
accumulate knowledges and also based on
the existing knowledge
and we do exploration to create novel
ideas
and this is only unique to human other
species
after they were born they have to start
learning from scratch
of course i our dna may already give us
some priors
and if you listen to
uh professor chomsky's lectures
and he he will probably say but this is
an interesting hypothesis he made
he considered language
is something like a liver
so when we are born
we have this
language organ this guy prior so we
could pick up language very very quickly
not because we are working extremely
hard to pick up languages but because we
already have this intrinsic capability
already been
pre-programmed
so
you can probably tell
virtually everyone even just a
primary school graduate they can speak
language without any problems
but to further
to do writing and to prepare your
writing of course we need additional
training
but just spoken language it doesn't seem
to take a lot of effort for us to be
able to start to
make conversations
so we had this example last time we say
okay suppose i went to kyoto
and i have seen a lot of different
sceneries and i want to convey what i
have seen to my friends or family
and
the only way i could do it if this is
about a thousand years ago even 200
years ago there was no photography right
i mean unless i can just say i
do a painting i show my my wife saying
well this is the beautiful scenery in
tokyo otherwise i have to use speech
today is much easier because we have
images we have videos but
500 years ago no right so language is
only the mechanism for us to communicate
what we have seen
so so when we convey in language
the perception obtained by the audience
may be different from our intent
so
gradually the language need be further
refined and refined
and if we look at this picture
we will talk about consciousness uh in
in week nine
but this is a preview
so
by psychologist we can divide our
conscious state into three
unconsciousness
like our heartbeat is ongoing in
unconsciousness state pre-consciousness
and in the consciousness so today i'm
not going to get into details but you
can think about how we position vision
and language
when we position
vision
on this two-dimensional space on the
left-hand side i say micro if we want to
plot
various applications on the on the graph
we can do that but today we just look at
the right-hand side macro
we compare vision and the languages
where do you think vision should be
placed
should region be in subconsciousness
pre-consciousness
or consciousness
right let's just say it's an interesting
question and i'm not going to
give you the reasonings but
this is what most of people believe
vision is
unconsciously unconscious state
but
it's also
in pre-consciousness thing
and one example is you
suppose you are looking in a garden
right and you are thinking about other
things
but when
a chimpanzee would
that definitely wouldn't be chimpanzee
but animal comes comes over and you can
you can see the animals but then you
realize suddenly you realize okay
something's going on so our perception
is ongoing even we are not really
interpreting the situations so it's
probably in the unconscious or
subconscious state and when we are
alerted and then we get into a conscious
state so conscious state of course
language plays a big role right so
this is the intuition behind where where
we place them
uh
definitely we can do even much more
let's say ethics where should we place
ethics
and uh
when we talk about the robots today uh
they don't have
ethics a robot cannot come with sins
right so but if we want to put ethics
into a robot
how can we approach the problem from
this kind of two-dimensional diagram and
those will be discussed in lecture 15.
so come back to the past so we started
to say okay uh
before
year 2003 the
word representation is done by using
this one hot vector and one half vector
the major shortcoming is you can you
just cannot compute similarity okay
that's given
so
the remedy was people using this kind of
handcraft
graphs or structures to try to encode
similarity
and in this particular
work done by princeton warned that
a lot of researchers encode this
hierarchy of is a relationship so you
look a picture at the bottom dog man cat
they are
animal an animal
is an organism and so on so forth right
and
later they consider well how can we
depict has a relationship
a hospital has nurses and adulterers
right so
again that will require a lot of
hand engineering work
and
you must know about this kind of uh uh
tagging right entity relationship
tagging
a word is a verb a noun that's fine but
this word is a it's a location or a name
that's just a heavily involving human
involvement and it's definitely not
scalable and proven encounters not only
similarity cannot be precisely
quantified we could say
men
and the cat they both belongs to mammal
but
what is a similar score 0.3 or 0.7 so
it's not really precise and it's not
context but context based
and
another problem is it's a polysomy
problem right four in tokyo can be
interpreted in different ways so all
these problems need to be addressed so
in summary there are two major problems
over the last fifty years and all the
researchers try to uh try to overcome
one is a synonym synonymy a word can
have
multiple words can have the same can
share the same meaning car and the moto
automobile for example
so even more challenging will be like
say i say mercedes-benz
and the toyota
so do you think they are
synonymous cinnamons or not right the
answer is tricky you say well in the
context of car
in the context of luxury cars they are
not similar but in the context of cars
they are similar
so
cinnamon can also be context dependent
the strength of similarity
and polysamy is even even a worse
problem right potato chips or computer
chips
and
even in one sentence
the word chip or the word for
can
appear twice and each one means
different things let's say i go to a
bank which is located located in the
bank of charles river right the bank
itself has two meaning the first one is
this commercial bank the second one is
the bank of a river and chip could be
the same thing right you say uh can you
chip in some money so we can go go to
buy some potato chips right
so how to solve the problem initially
researchers using this kind of
word called curious matrix and we
describe a very simple one last time we
need to decide this is a two dimensional
matrix
we need to decide what are our own rows
and what should be in the columns and
then what should be put in the cells
and the simple one is we just say okay
we put all the documents uh
on this column level
and all words maybe three hundred
thousand words
as this is a low right then we say okay
this particular document one which words
appeared
and then when a word appear you can
count on how many times a word appears
so if one's against just put one and
maybe this uh against in document seven
three times we put a three over there so
this is similar from it so so this is a
very simple uh concurrence matrix but we
can utilize the vector documents seven
is depicted by a battery of words we can
simply use a vector to compute
similarity cosine distance function
or any kind of
nuclear distance function or other other
similar functions
but again this is not really fine grain
so definitely we are moving to be more
and more fine grain in the last few
years
and uh
with this uh word counting
so we already moving us
from this
not considering contextual information
at all to consider contextual
information we see a document right so
we are moving up we like to be able to
move to the right upper corner so we
took the first step
so
the memory of merely occurrence
again i mentioned
is a relationship is there but has a
relationship
is not encoded
so we need to solve the problem of
tsunami and the polygamy the bmw example
has been given to you
and
this was another example eddie plays
piano in a play right the play
two plays uh they they mean different
things
and uh
a very famous problem in this particular
dimension two-dimensional matrix is
called
market basket problem
you must have heard about this if you
are majoring in computer science so the
the problem is
we go to market we do shopping what we
put in the shopping carts
we
put in the data structure you say i
went to trader joe i bought carols about
milk i bought potato
so initially this market basket problem
was trying to
help the supermarket
to decide their promotion
so if say
if a lot of people they bought milk at
the same time they will they will buy
beer so you can do some sort of
promotion scheme so one famous promotion
scheme was during weekends and a lot of
men would be urged by their wives to go
to sioux market to pick up diapers for
for the kids
and
the man i think us right some of us
would say well i like to watch sports so
i would buy beer and maybe potato chips
at the same time and the supermarket
do these frequent items say mining they
say well this is association between
diaper and the beer that was really
interesting in the beginning when they
found out so
they say okay let me do a
diaper
sales right 30 off and you can imagine
my wife would say yeah go for it edward
diaper is off
it's own discount they go go go to buy
get it then i look at the beer and beer
they secretly raise the price by 30
right so at the end the supermarket
makes even more money and
i i cannot say i don't go right so
that's the scheme another one is if you
have experienced experience going to
costco
and
so
suppose i
buy merchant one and two and they are at
adjacent
aisles and by next time i go there
i couldn't find the second item but the
second it was move away so this is
another trick they say okay most of
people buy one and two so i like to
shelf them as far away as possible so
therefore you have to walk uh to look
for the things and then along the way
like as bad as i am i will pick
something originally i i actually i
don't need to buy so so many times i go
home my wife would say why why do you
buy this i didn't ask you to buy this i
said well it sounds it looks interesting
so this is another way using this kind
of market basket
kind of mechanism can address the
promotion in the supermarket but in
general this could be looked at as this
kind of association rule prediction
suppose uh
a user has seen three photos
right and we like to recommend the
fourth photo for the user and how should
we do it we say okay
which photo has high associations with
the previous three so you mine the data
of all the usage pattern in the past
then you say okay suppose
a person look at a b and c now i want to
add this d
and which d will give this probability
condition probably the largest value
right so you look into
the user's access patterns other uses ss
pattern in the past then come up with
this very very simple bayesian
interpretation
and
there are some theory behind it i don't
i don't need to cover today but this is
a very popular scheme uh for very simple
ads matching or merchandise
recommendation
and the it's a small trick is this nabc
need to be slightly large if this nabc
abc pattern
it doesn't happen it does happen but
doesn't happen very frankly frequently
this is called the support it is too low
so you cannot trust this prediction but
if you have a abc
happen very frequently so to predict d
and that makes a lot of sense okay
so how can we accomplish uh this kind of
heuristic what's what is the
implementation surprisingly it's very
simple
so it's just a two dimensional matrix
and on these two dimensional matrices
like we mentioned about in this call
called curse matrix we need to decide
what's on the xs essay and what is on
the on the y
and you can do a lot of different things
you can say okay
on this
column we have different images we have
different documents news
ads
on these rows we have every individual
users right and the mission is when
a user click on a particular object we
put on a cell
one
if not
zero
and then the mission is to predict the
missing value in this matrix right so
let me see whether the next slide would
hey yes the missing values so we say for
user number one should we recommend this
first image or the sixth
and we don't know so what can we do we
look at other users
also assets
number three four and five so similar
users right suppose i consider this
person the second user is a similar user
as myself so
the first
object no i'm not going to recommend
because second user did not click on it
but
he or she click on the sixth one so i'm
going to recommend that one to uh to to
to this user and this is aggregation
right because i saw it as accounting if
you have a lot of users
one two three i'm sorry ss two three and
four at the same time they will access
number six yes you go go go forward to
do the recommendation
so the flexibility
you can just put anything virtually
anything on s and anything on the y as
long as they have so light correlations
right
and
we can show even more examples uh later
but this is the cheapest
most rudimental collaborative filtering
algorithm out there has been used by
many many
companies the major reason is
is computationally
not very intensive and in year 2207
we made the algorithm wrong on parallel
machines so we paralyzed the
mechanism
and you see berkeley adopted into its uh
it's open source
so
my question is okay then we have we
solve the problems
the answer is not really entirely right
so the problem number one is we haven't
encoded strength of interest
oftentimes i click
an article i look at an article within a
few seconds i i just go away it's called
a bounce because i i say well i get
trapped so there are a lot of this kind
of uh
click bait right you put some beautiful
pictures on the page and
to kind of seduce people to click and
people click on the page and they say
well it's not what you said and nowadays
a lot of news will put question mark
behind a statement rather than saying
well this is a summary of the news they
don't do that because you do a summary
on the news if you do a perfect job no
one will click so they put some
ambiguous statement
well what happens do you know then you
you get
enticed to click
and the second challenge is the matches
tend to be quite sparse right so you
consider all the merchants in costco so
how many sales would you say one or how
many sales would you say two or three
most of the sales will be just a zero
and number three will be semantics right
just give you an example let's say uh
suppose i have i'm a new company and i
haven't gotten a lot of
advertisements from vendors suppose i
only have bmw's advertisement
and
i probably
maybe i have mercedes-benz or maybe two
or three
but let's say you click on mercedes-benz
and uh suppose i don't have
mercedes-benz advertisement but i have
bmw i can say oh this is the luxury car
so i don't have to match you
by your keyword i can match you by your
semantics right that will broaden my my
ads offerings so that's one example of
having a semantic layer can be very
useful
and so this leads to
the major breakthrough in early year
2000 this is done by michael jordan's
group
at berkeley and angel ning was one of
the
authors
so the idea was okay we want to create a
latent layer between
words and the documents again we don't
have to put words and documents on two
accesses you can put other things but
this example here is we like to be able
to recommend users user may do a search
and we want to match with documents
so
two examples on the top right so suppose
you do a search like iphone crack where
you do a search like apple pie right
iphone crack doesn't have apple in there
and on the other hand apple pipe has
apple in there but this apple is not
the i.t apple this is fruit apple
so you'll be good so at the bottom we
see if it's good if we can build a
latent layer and the characters are very
small but the latent layer you can see
this we have four different categories
here
from it
food
and history
and this is another one i couldn't read
so
you say okay the first one i t iphone
crack belongs to it
and the apple pie actually should be
food then when we do search
then this because of this semantic layer
the accurate responses or the accurate
results can be returned okay
and the second thing is we need to
encode strength into the cells we don't
say just binary zero one we say oh you
often access this particular document or
this kind of document so we bump out the
numbers
and lda
the algorithm basically is extremely
simple we have this two dimensional
space two dimensional code called
current matrix and this example here is
a document and words again you can have
document users right and then we say we
want to factorize these matches into two
sub matrices
and the right hand side matrix is the
semantical matrix so look at these words
and topics right basically you we can
cluster words
into topics
so this is good because suppose we
cluster play play this word under the
topic sports or we closer play
under the topic instrument right so
different cluster if the word play falls
in under different topics then you know
the semantics of this particular word
and a word can appear on multiple topics
so this is not a strict class ring the
membership can be quite flexible
and the bottom layer
is also important this is basically
doing classification right so you have
news
one dimension would be news or documents
the other dimension would be the
categories
of your news sports politics so you look
at this algorithm the output very very
useful
and the the complexity is about n square
so let's look at the
example this is a
example experiment run on 37k documents
and the documents consists of 26k words
and we set
the latent layer number to be
1700 topics okay the 1700 here is the
tricky thing you see how many dollar
documents you get
uh you cannot decide right just call the
document in and uh how many words are
there is it's accounting
these these two numbers are given these
two parameters are given but how many
topics is very tricky and if you can
recall like k-mean k-means is an
unsupervised classroom algorithm you
want to cluster your objects into k
clusters without any uh labels in those
kind of situation how to determine k is
is rather tricky and here uh
we don't have time to get into how to
decide k equal to 700 but most of people
just try and narrow suppose okay 1700
around 700 are article topics coming
from libraries okay so you get this 1700
clusters and this is a list of example
classes we get right so when we we talk
about semantics or latent layer each
latent layer is represented by a set of
words
let's look into what's in there
so
on the left hand side we have this
character here but you look at the other
words in the same cluster characters
okay you say form copy and paper or you
say okay this is probably alphabetics
right and the same character when we go
to the second column or character play
stage oh this is a character in a movie
in a play okay so in different cluster
the worst meaning depending on the
context is different and the play okay
we shift to another cluster play here
you see chord you see score
this could be
uh play in the g in a gym or maybe play
tennis right and the core we move to the
next one chord case jury evidence oh
this is uh
related to law to a trial right and then
evidence moved to
the right-hand side again
correlate with experimental scientists
and tests this is a scientific
experiment and so on and so forth
so
how to use it utilize it so every
cluster has a has a id
so when we go back to parse the the
documents we assign every word with its
id number right so play here the top one
we get 082
cluster from 82 and a player a play in
the middle document zero seven seven and
finally one six six
so this is fantastic we get this through
this very simple
matrix factorization we get
semantics
right
context-based semantics so it seems like
this policymaker problem got resolved
and this is really great
but there's one shortcoming which i
would enumerate again is
the play
in article suppose i the example i gave
you this
i
play piano in a play or whatever so if
you have
two
the one word in a in the same document
but they can mean different things in
different sentences the granularity of
the lda is two cores but this is in oda
the disambiguation is only done in the
in the document level not done
in a sentence level okay so this is uh
something definitely can be improved
and so issue summarize
uh for
polysomy is is cost grant
and therefore
those are two examples i already talked
about and we need better mechanism
and for synonymous synonym
like four could be autumn for could be
dropped right the tokyo fall and could
be star marquee fall or the tree fall
and then in this situation again
we cannot really
quantify these different kind of
synonyms in this lda scheme
so in short we need to have finer
granularity
so now we get into the second epoch
and this is five years this is 2013. uh
last time i motivated the
nlp community did not really get into
deep learning until after they have seen
the vision community was so successful
so in year 2013 a team of berkeley uh
people started saying well well we can
can we encode uh contextual information
you know in the in the final grant so
this is a very
important treaty by harris proposed in
1954.
uh the treaty was very straightforward
the the meaning of a word need to really
uh look at
your context right or the word meaning
depends on your neighbors
or you can say
your character depends on the friends
you make right so that makes a lot of
sense but it takes how many years for us
to be able to finally encode context
into the sentence
over 60 years so we get started with the
the history
so now we're going to go go to this
world to vet so world of ways is
this happened after neural nets started
to be adopted by the nlp community the
the idea was this one harvester was
really bad so suppose we can
classify words into multiple classes in
this toy example we have
dog cat and bird and on the right hand
side we have flower tree and apple when
we plot these words onto a two
dimensional simple two dimensional space
because only on two dimensional we can
visualize we hope similar words can be
in the nearest neighbors so hopefully uh
the
yellow color ones and green color ones
and orange color ones
they are clustered so they can they
should be nearest neighbors in in this
embedding space okay and that's a wish
and then
the the
scientists at google
this is what this was discovered
actually by luck right so they say i
want to put neural net and to just kind
of interpret
documents whatsoever
and in these two papers what they come
up with two different schemes
the first one is called continuous back
of words the second one is a ski gram
the basic idea if if you look at the
example at the bottom is if i have a
sentence i have let's say five words and
i want to just skip i want to just get
rid of the middle world
so
the mission of the training becomes can
you train the machinery which can guess
the missing word right so this is called
continuous continuous spec of back of
word so once you have guessed the
middleware then this uh sentence can
continue to flow the other one is called
skeegram so suppose this is the word i'm
given they say play can you come up come
up with some nearest neighboring words
right so this this mechanism looks
slightly harder so we we just focus on
the left one the right hand side will go
through the similar computational
processes
so the left one the input
will be
one half
and the output here wt will also be
one-half letters
so this example here is our input is the
cat
blank
on the roof or our own floor
and we want the desired output to be set
because that's the ground truth right we
just remove the middle word and later we
will come back when we talk about birth
this is kind of mask
mask language model so we get rid of the
middle one and then we try to guess it
and then this is just we have made so
many different sentences we just
continue to input into this mechanism
and the window size can be adjusted can
be in that particular example the window
size is four we can have 10 or whatever
right it's kind of flexible
and the input again one half battery
looks really ugly and the hidden layer
finally this output layer also won't
have vector
and in the middle they have this hidden
layer
and they only have one hidden layer and
for sure it is
accidental right people like to put
hundreds of hidden layers if not tens of
hidden layers in the middle to perfect
the result but for some reason by acid
then whatever they only put this one
hidden layer and the dimension in the
beginning was 512 and later they
increased to 10 24. so what they
discovered was okay so yeah we get this
new one that right you get
these weighting matrix by having many
many training data events eventually we
trend these weighting matches of this w
v n and wmv
so
these the dimension of one half vector
suppose v is let's say 300 000 and i
just mentioned by 12 or 1024 right and
then on the right hand side you like to
be able to
get this latent layer to produce your
final prediction and that would be
another matrix so this prediction will
go through a soft max
because at the end we wouldn't actually
get zero and one right we will get a
list of probability and then we use
softmax to magnify magnify
the
the word with highest probability then
we would produce now word representation
using one half vector okay
so hopefully the idea was not extremely
complicated
so the advantage at the end we take is
oh thank you for giving us this
v multiply n
matrix
and using this matrix
if this is an end of trending this
matrix will give us
one half vector
map to
embedding vector uh this mapping and
mapping matrix
you you look at this mattress here
and for this cad word category is the
second word so if we multiply the matrix
by our one half vector basically we are
indexing into this uh waiting matches to
get the embedding out of it so the
embedding in this case for cat will be
2.4 2.6 and so on and so forth to 1.8
the dimension is only 512 or 1024 okay
for some reason they eventually they
didn't use these two numbers
uh
this i'm curious if you are interested
you can type in your guess what is the
the the current numbers
uh
we we are using in this world of act uh
just just for fun you type in the the
chat room
uh between
between one and uh the value is between
one and one thousand right
uh
let's continue in about one to two
slides the number will be revealed just
for fun
okay
so
we we look at this this is a way to get
the the v
and this is the way to get
to get cat this is the multiplication to
get this on then eventually we can
predict this this set value
and
this is again this is a mechanism i just
mentioned that you said using this uh
uh
one half vector to index your
embedding or embedding
so the right hand side shows the answer
right so the original space is three
hundred thousand and uh
the dimension
is actually
very funny it's 768.
what is 768
5 12 plus
10 24 divided by 2.
why they came up with this number
i don't know right so they are just
magics somewhere
so let me look at the chair to see
yeah okay that's good numbers three
hundred and five twelve
so 768 but it works really great i bet
those researchers have done some uh
comparisons offline
when they publish the paper so turn out
768 but i just wondering why not 720a or
788 so i don't see signs here right i
see empirical results here
um
okay now the the fun thing starts based
on this embedding
you can put this dimension is let's say
768 still the dimension is very high but
they are able to project
uh this vector onto a two-dimensional
space to visualize and this example here
is once after projection we can do this
kind of interesting uh mathematics king
minus man plus woman equal to queen
this is interesting right the king is
typically i mean
that's true the king is male and
minus
gender plus another gender will become
queen
and this is another example published in
the paper so this is a relationship
between a capital and a nation
and
some folks using this relationship to
perform all these different algebra like
german is equal to berlin minus rome
plus italy and you can do this kind of
uh
hotter minus heart equal to bigger
minus big like this degree kind of
situation can be quantified in this
interesting way
so
um
this is really solving
the similarity problem in a very
attractive manner right
so this is give us a much better
representation rather than just one half
vector as the input and nowadays
virtually everyone
doing this embedding first
then they start the training
and uh
slightly later
we will show the input
from this one half vector they say the
cast sit on the floor so when we convert
cat we convert k into embedding vector
the word to back but also we want to
encode
the position of this word they say oh
cat is the second word or third word we
need to be able to encode
the position later the other side when
they get the information they know where
the words come from so this is in
attention uh lecture i would talk into
details right so this is a
representation
transformation so we again come back to
look at this progress picture now we
have this predictive model not just word
count we are trying to predict the
missing words or we are predicting
either the missing word in the middle or
or the surrounding neighbor neighboring
words the both mechanism will give us a
better representation and
sort of like this is the beginning of
considering context
but if we want to push ourselves so so
this whole sequence is very logical
right so at this point you say oh okay
have we have we done have we hit the
home run so everything is done right
uh not really
still we can do even better
so
we kind of look at this uh uh
accomplishments from this water bag
for cinnamon cinnamon
synonymy
good it's good it's pretty good but for
policemen still
it's still called scram
uh because for every word in this world
to vet
it only has one index right it's really
easy to to see
once you get this vector on the right
upper corner suppose i have this word
called play you come into this matrix
there's only one representation for the
play so it's even worse than lda
so wow this is bad right so how do we
solve the problem then we sort like we
make progress on cinnamons but we we
have this guy kind of digress
degradation on polysomy so we go back to
harris to say hey harris please help us
and harris told us the same thing i told
you for 60 70 years how come you guys
just couldn't figure it out you got a
solution
so the scientists come back to withdraw
the solution on the board they say oh we
have done this word to that and what do
that what's the input one input is this
one half vector and thank you to give me
this uh embedded vector
but
hey
just put a contest as a second argument
okay it's not very complex okay this
harris already told us contest contest
okay finally
in year about 20
2014 exactly 60 years after
our grandparent told us to do the right
thing
finally the community say okay okay
let's put contest
in the computational model
so
there are two major works
one is the sequence to sequence the
second wise attention we heard about
attention right so attention invented
the word is coined by chris manning's
team in stanford but only took off in
year 27
2017 and 2018 and once uh the uh
google folks and implement this uh
transformer model so so let's look at
the design steps so this is a problem we
have seen so far so let's go to this
data driven representation learning so
this far still the community is doing a
lot of traditional model pre-processing
similarity dimensional reduction but
data driven there are driven sequence
sequence sequence model
details are in these two papers so we
look at this example
and this example shows how
this sequence to sequence or we call
recurrent neural net rnn model works
okay so why we call rnn once we see the
picture we probably can figure out so
this is a translation problem on the
left-hand side we have input tokens
three so it works
then our sequence to sequence model
eventually would generate four words
right suppose some of you thought about
france french and generate some english
words and vice versa the lens could be
different and the sequence to sequence
model in the middle take all the input
and generate output
so let's look at
even finer grain the middle the middle
box uh we look at we open it up we see
an encoder and then we see a decoder and
let's focus on the interface between
this encoder and the decoder okay
so this animation we put word one two
three into it we generate context we
shift context to decoder we generate
four words
so if we want to be critical to this
architecture
we will say the following right we say
okay you have this input
one half vector
we convert this wahabiter into
uh word embedding
that's great so not so far so good
then we utilize
this world embedding to start to conduct
training step number one we general
hidden state number one step number two
hidden state two
then we get hidden state three when we
put hidden state in the middle and input
to the decoder then we generate our
output i'm a student
the key here the key shortcoming here is
we only input hidden state three into a
decoder
hidden three one and two
we did not utilize them and this is a
traditional call
long distance dependency we lost the
long distance dependency and this
picture shows the the mathematics and it
can clarify really well
so the bottom encoder we take care of
input on the top we do this output in
the translation situation
so hidden layer generation on the top
uh the hidden layer t
when we generate it it's a function
depending on hidden layer t minus one
that's that's fine that's
straightforward depending on the
previous output
y t minus one that's very logical when
you try to
produce the translation you already
gotten the previous word you get the
previous words content hidden hidden
layer you want to produce the next word
but
the context given is only c
c is the last hidden layer produced by
the encoder okay so this c is that is
the problem and then we look at this
inferencing eventually once we have
gotten this ht
and we use ht
and yt minus one and c to predict the
next word
so again here we only use this last
hidden layer of the input
we have this long distance dependency
problem we lost a lot of information
so
all the researchers are very logical
right they say oh
so i miss some long distance information
how can we solve the problem so i'm
going to encode this information in the
model right so they say okay so we have
this shortcoming only get this
final hidden state and then we have this
vanishing gradient because all these
long decent ones
once they aggregate uh the heuristic
whatever into the final hidden state
most of them are lost right so okay
let's insert something
in the middle
so this something is called
uh short-term memory right this is lstm
stands for long-term short-term memory
so some memory can be long-term and
summary will be short-term
so without getting into much detail so
let's say
for translation for
nature language
what kind of states we would like to
keep right so i say okay maybe we want
to keep three different states the first
day is
the
subject we want to know
the subject type if the subject is
female male that would determine uh how
can i deal with the verb right do i want
to put s behind it and the second is
time is the past future or present that
will impact the tense of my verb right
so those are just two very
simple examples and of course they are
much more complex in situations which i
will give
a couple examples shortly so
so the good thing about having this uh
long-term short-term memory is suppose i
want to generate a translation
and uh you don't depend on just the last
hidden layer you say oh i'm going to go
back to your entire sentence to see
what is your subject if your subject is
i then i know i'm not going to give
the form of the verb will be the
original form if your subject's he or
she i need to
do to put something behind the original
verb
so
then you keep on progressing this uh
long-term short-term memory and
every piece of
data
in the cell so you can have multiple
states i enumerate three different
states but you can have even more so the
state once they say okay yesterday when
you start to say yesterday the state of
the tense is modified so we have we say
we forget about the previous tense state
we change the state to
maybe future or past right yesterday is
the past they say oh yesterday i forgot
to bring my my book to the lecture and
tomorrow i will bring my book so when
you say yesterday the tense was passed
then when you when i look at will
right away in the gate right in the
register whatever i'm going to modify
the state into the future so this is a
very rudimental example but hopefully
you get a sense the reason we're not
going to get your details is
no one is using this
anymore and then the reason is be
the following
so for our rnn model sequence to
sequence we already talked about the two
major shortcomings
for
lstm with rnn
the the major problem is cannot be
parallely trend okay and and also it's
very cumbersome
suppose it could solve the problem well
but it just
cannot be
unrolled to take a take advantage of
gpus
and this is definitely a huge problem so
remember i motivated when i at google
doing this kind of paleo algorithm
research i was ridiculed because the
algorithm algorithm itself if it cannot
be paralyzed nobody will use it right so
here the similar situation yes lstm can
solve the problem to a certain degree
including this uh
nearest neighbors context rather than
far distance context but is really
expensive to to trend
and so
then came out is a transformer using a
tension and this really revolutionized
uh the entire field
so
we remaining of the lecture with our
time another 30 minutes we cover
transformer gpt
and the birth and their uh
kind of fine-tuning kind of mechanisms
so i pause a little bit here uh to kind
to see whether we have questions
so again you can enter questions in a
chat room okay
okay let's get into transformer and i
don't have the transformer picture here
but
you know the movie transformer right
so this is an interesting article
written about
three years ago
and they say what drop your rnn and lstm
because they are not good this is really
straightforward sentence right
in fact and i when i talk to my
colleagues i say if you don't know
anything about nature language
processing before year 2018 you are not
missing anything
so it's not a happy statement or it's a
sad statement
and to me was a happy statement because
i did not know nlp whatsoever before
2018 and and i picked up nlp just in the
last two three years
and i i'm i'm doing okay because all
those heuristic algorithms like lstm
if you want me to do a lecture on my
lstm today i probably couldn't do it
because i didn't dig into the code in in
greater details but if i only need to
learn transformer and the subsequent
materials and that's that's uh okay
that's uh attractable
okay so let's dive in attention model
written by a google group so the
mechanism is very simple this is a very
famous picture
and we see this on the left hand side we
have this encoder on the right hand side
we have this architecture of
decoder
and
this particular picture
is specifically for
the google's purpose they are looking
into translation right so later we will
talk about the language model
traditional language model is given and
characters you want to generate m plus
and google the first
sort like
model they came out with called mask
language model it's a different language
model so
a language model is not really a common
term it's a specific term saying okay
when i say language model it means you
are generating the next sentence based
on previous previous words right so this
is can be more clear shortly so for
translation we have input sentence we
eventually want to generate output
and here
i give you an example mentally input
maybe in french an output in the
beginning
would be just a start character right
nothing start
and then after we process the input
we get this
array of attention which i will depict
shortly and this
array of attention will be inputted to
the middle layer middle attention layer
of the decoder
right so this is the only place
the decoder and encoder talk to each
other okay talk to each other means you
do backward propagation back here
eventually in the training phase you
modify the parameters and then you do
four forward uh training uh in in
between here
so
that was the motivation we came up with
encoder and decoder and the position
encoding was critical because when you
input
a window of words into the encoder
decoder eventually you need to position
which words is where right so encoding
scheme fourier transform
is very straightforward we just consider
you'll be given no research can be
further down over there
and attention
simply speaking
involves in three data structures
one is a value vector
and the second thing is the key or index
into the value vector and the queue is
the query
the query you want to ask information
from the value vector so example very
simple example here is i have three
values 150 175 and 45 and i have no idea
what they are but i have a key
vector key would say oh they are
actually a weight height an h
so now if i do a query on weight and i
will get 150.
so
here you can say
how can we get 150
so you can you can see quite clearly i
have to do a dot product between query
and the key right when i do a dot
product between query and key i know oh
you want to know
weight
so weight indeed i cover that in my
value vector so that will be the first
element so go to the value vector fetch
the first element to return to the
caller to the carrier okay
so this should should be very
straightforward and uh
this is one
simple
attention block right so
we have uh
multiply q and a k
to then we scaled it and why we want to
scale that is again an empirical result
we don't want the value to be too large
and so the formula is without product q
and k
to get the index then we get a mask then
we get into the value a vector
multiplied by this value vector and we
do a soft mesh we get our results right
suppose we have
multiple heads
and
eventually we just aggregate either
concatenate in parallel or we do a
sum and wait is sum at the end at the
top level
so there could be two different ways to
deal with
multiple output
so
we can talk about multiple hats uh in
intense slides
okay so
this mechanism hopefully is quite
straightforward right just just this
formula attention given q k and v
we do us soft max first of all do a dot
product between q and k
and divided by a scaling factor because
we want we don't want the number to be
too large
and then we multiply
with the value of enter
and we get get again get the result and
result again the magnitude can be over
the places we do a soft max so we want
to make sure the value eventually at the
end will be between zero and one okay
and then okay then we just just again we
look at the translation uh suppose we
have french words one two and three and
up will be english word one and two
so input output vo embedding or to react
and the position encoding keeps sequence
positions
and each attention block takes three
input v
k and q
and since v is a vector of all hidden
states of the input token
an output sees the entire input sequence
so we solve the
long distance dependency problem by
having this attention vector
so if the vector let's say the size the
size of vector is
12.
you can see 12 states
right you can see either before or after
not necessarily just before
and
you can see even bigger window like uh
in the burst situation they divide the
buffer of 512 into two buffers
uh 256 and 256. and one question i put
forward if you can think of is
why 512.
if i process a document let's say i want
to do translation
you say 512
and i say okay maybe okay right but you
say well if i do qna i want to do q a on
a particular scientific subject and your
input is a question you say the question
can only have 512 characters i probably
would say good i don't i don't have
i don't i wouldn't have a sentence too
long
a question too long but you say the
right hand side should be
all the information
possibly have the answer
512 you must be kidding my fighter is
just too small
so
why 512
think about it then we come back
so attention mechanism
uh the decision layer basically do a
query dot product to the memory layer
and the values so you do see all the
values in the buffer and through this
attention mechanism the right hand side
is example
and you have this the monkey ate the
banana because it was too
hungry
so this it
is it the banana or the it the monkey
eventually by trending and you can see
the
the weight the attention
it
the thicker the darker color means the
attention probability so we went through
this song max right the attention bob is
higher for
monkey the monkey but much slower for
banana
so
this attention eventually tell us it
here it is the monkey okay
so the next example
is even more interesting we say the
animal didn't cross the street because
it was too tired
so
here you can say oh the attention pace
to the animal so the animal was too
tired
but we're just changing the tire to wide
it was too wide on the right hand side
and attention is so so smart looking at
say oh
the animal cannot be too wide
right the emini mode the street can be
too wide
so it's rather clever
it's really
look at the context in the in the
sentence level
and
the context every words will be looking
to not just the last word
so
pretty much we have this
problem solved i would say
if you can consider that there will be
a missing missing problem need to be
addressed
and you can elevate uh
the nature language processing to the
next level
so so here i'm going to give you a real
real world joke
and when i was at the uc i'm writing my
first uh paper and we are classifying
a wired animal from uh domestic animal
something like that so i had to miss
this misspelling of
wild i i spare in the wide
so my secretary just made a joke with me
saying oh animal is white
or edward must be
kidding so
indeed i i i have this chromatic
writing arrow typo i i did
white so to me then this uh nlp wouldn't
work because i was saying the animal is
very fat like elephant or something
okay this is uh the last slide was an
example sorry i come back here so see
this is how the attention works every
word
pays attention to all other words not
just itself right so and then we have
multiple layers of attention so like the
transformer layer
the encoder state they have so many
layers i think maybe 60 some layers and
decoding state also has
maybe about 20 or
30 30 layers so there's no limitation of
how many layers you want to put there
depending on the task and the accuracy
would you like to accomplish so the
reasoned
monster generated by
open ai do you know how many parameters
are in there so the more layers you have
of course the the more parameters you
get right there are a few things
determining your parameters one is your
window size
so the
vertically how many characters you want
to see
at the same time the second thing is how
many hats you want to have right the
third thing is how many layers you want
to stack your your this attention block
right so attention block uh as
illustrated in the in the
in about four pictures ago encoder has
two of three and decoder has another two
or three okay so
the more complex your model the better
accuracy or the better kind of results
you will be obtained but the cost will
be the number of parameters the number
of parameters decides the computational
complexity
and will demand a lot of
computation powers or gpus
in the case of gpg3 maybe today we may
not have time to gain the gpd3 but gp3
has
500 billion parameters
and it's reaching
1 trillion i i bet there are companies
working on 1 3 and even
5 trillion models
so we have
if you look at the scenario right now
the data we are having
already been fully utilized and people
just trying to
increase
the depth of the the attention layers to
try to increase the number of neurons
a prediction was once we get into
multiple trillion the number of neurons
in the model could be equivalent to the
number of neurons in human brain
in gpd2
the number of neurons in gb2 gb2 is
equivalent to the number of neurons in a
b
okay
so you just keep on increasing but i
don't know whether the effectiveness
will be able to increase
so much i had attention
uh
it's a mechanism
to try to a uh do a divine conquer
suppose i have this uh
input window which is very very long i
like to be able to chop into uh short
segments
and then we i can compute
impale a little and then eventually the
higher level can can give me this kind
of cross attention i wouldn't be able to
lose the information i really need
and another motivation of this multi
multihack is you can really take
advantage of
paleocomputation because uh
the heads operate independently on the
data right they share the same huge
matches and here we look at query key
and values and conceptually they are in
three or logically they are in three
different matrices
but the real implementation they
actually put into one physical
matrix input in the memory and then you
have this
access to different regions of memory to
deal with the situation
so remember i mentioned this 512 right
why vital
so here is a good time to maybe to think
about why because
suppose we i want to map
from input to output
right so input is 5 12. the output
should be 5 12 and so on and so forth
so this 512 to 512 mapping if i want to
do a tension to look at the entire
window either multihat or eventual
aggregate information together
we definitely need to have this 512
multiplied by 512.
memory space
and
if you increase to 10 24 times 10 24
it's doable
so after birth there was a model which
my company is using that is 1024 called
bart bart
indeed
for many tasks 12 24 get much better
results right
another example is i gave you this q a
but another example would be document
summarization
and if we want to do news summarization
a news a piece of news is more than 5 12
characters but typically can be under 10
24. so if we do summarization just on on
512 we have to chop a document into
multiple segments and that's not really
good right so 1024 wonderful but why not
one million
and this is called reformer
was done by
google about two years ago
maybe one year ago i don't remember a
time precisely
but reformer you have this one million
times one media window or one million
times one million mattress it cannot be
put in the physical memory so then
subsequently there are
a few of you work try to do this matrix
reduction
and my team
we using this
uh incomplete scholastic factorization
and that's a very
uh principle method in linear algebra we
reduce the dimension
from n
to square root of n so that makes the
the
matrix it's much smaller can fit into
the memory without losing a lot of
information
so
the 512
window is not really limited by
the logic of the algorithm is limited by
computer resources and because the
memory memory size keep on getting
increased
so nowadays 10 24 is okay but going
beyond 1024 we have to conduct
approximation
so let's recap this everything using
example
example translation right so we have
this encoder decoder architecture on the
encoder architecture on the left-hand
side a decoder on the right-hand side
and
we going through the process let's look
at final grant
the first word comes in sorry this
animation okay i couldn't see the top
bar so the first word comes in
you start to generate the first one on
the right hand side and on the left hand
side you just continue to generate the
third one and then the fourth one
and you can do this animation
at home too
to really get a feel to see the details
and when i post pdf sometimes animation
doesn't come out but i will precisely
cite the sources of all these animations
those are not created by me those are on
the website you can look at those
individual tutorials
and this is a complexity of information
path length
and so self-attention
uh the complexity per layer n squared
multiplied by d
so n squared is really the window size
problem like second sequence length and
this is the bottom neck of the memory
and the at the bottom you see this is
self attention restricted restricted
means
okay you even you have to give me n i'm
not going to look into the entire end
i'm going to do a sub sampling i only
want to look into r right so this can
reduce the memory requirement but how to
reduce from n to r and most of people
just say i'm not going to look into this
entire sentence i would entire 512
buffer i'm going to just look into
substances like maybe seven or ten
characters and that will limit the the
the power of this uh potential mechanism
and uh
in recent papers some people come up
with this something called a
multi-resolution
so you could have n by n at the same
time you could do sub sampling and sub
sampling can be done in a sequential
manner or you can do it in in a random
manner right
so there are a lot of we can say hacks
behind it and i typically i don't care
about those hacks right we care about
principles and hex basically just saying
oh
we have this uh trunk the tree trunk is
there i'm going to make it faster i'm
trying to make it uh
slightly more accurate right so a lot of
people popping in paper say oh i get
this 0.2
higher accuracy but
those are not really interesting because
it could be data dependent improvement
but speed yes speed is liquid is
critical especially the inferencing
speed
so bird and
gpt
so birth lgbt we talk about their
language models are different
for gpt it's a traditional language
model left to right
and for birth is bi-directional
why do they want to do bi-directional
we look at why
because the mass language model depends
on that to be more efficient
so
the key element here but we talk if you
keep on talking about small data
learning in the first two lectures
and the breakthrough for this mask
language model is you no longer
need label training data because the
data itself is your teacher right so you
say computer vision if you do
compression then you do decompression or
encoding decoding
using this minimizing
snr as your objective function you
actually you don't need supervision
because data itself is your ground truth
right you do compression then you
decompress back to
as
original as possible that's your ground
truth likewise in the end of nlp i think
i have to appreciate those google photos
come up with this
mask language model they say okay i'm
going to pretty missing words you give
me an article i'm going to take away
m percent of words so again this n is
the magic and you say why not five
percent why not 20 percent 150.
if we take away many men too many words
of course the guessing cannot be done
well
and if we guess only just two or three
words it's not very powerful so again
this is a magic of 15
so you have this document you take away
15 of words randomly and you try to
build this attention model to guess the
missing words so once you have done this
for a very large corpus
because you don't need label your
document itself is your label right so
this you you are so called self
supervised learning so this big data is
no longer you you need human to labels
but the data itself is its own teacher
this is really fantastic revolution i
think this is more even more
revolutionary
than the attention model itself
okay so
the google did two things one
the mask language model is different
from the traditional alm language model
the second is they have this another
task because they divide
uh character buffers into two sub
buffers
and the first buffer is the first
sentence the second buffer is the next
sentence so every time they provide
input into
the bird training the transformer they
provide two sentences and their
optimization objectives in addition to
predicting the missing words accurately
they do a hack they say oh can you
predict whether the second sentence is
the next sentence of the first
i i found it is mysterious but
but it actually improved accuracy
according to google by two percent right
it's kind of funny because if you look
at poorly written articles
even you you read a paper you say i'm
going to swap some sentences i move the
first sentence or second sentence to be
third or fourth and i move sometimes up
and down
some pretty return papers
i wouldn't say poorly written not so
well written paper not that logical
kind of engaging papers
they still read pretty well if you could
go to news i would i would argue the
same thing right
so
for the language model i'm coming back
here gbt is really doing
generating the next word the man then
next one will be the man went the man
want to
and for the birth mass language model we
take away
random words in the sentences right so
in the top sentence we have two
sentences in the top input we have two
sentences the man went to the
supermarket he bought a can of milk so
this is the example i say
[Music]
why you swapping a sentence
uh
would be a wrong thing i say if i say uh
he wants to buy again of milk and the
man went to the supermarket semantically
it's the same right
even more telling is the next one the
man went to a supermarket mary walks his
he stalks every day so if you switch a
tool it's not impossible people writing
sentences like this especially our
diaries right so i have no idea why this
is next here you say it's nice it's
false but who knows
it works
okay
so to recap
the semi-supervised they call semi
supervised actually it's just
self-supervised
and
using self-supervised learning
we pre-train
this uh we call pre-trend model birth
the bird has all the parameters based on
the optimization of its next and
guessing the missing words and we have
this uh uh the weight matches everything
being trend then on the right hand side
we start to say oh
so what did you want to do actually what
is your target task you want to do q a
and you want to do this uh
annotation name entity annotation or you
want to do classification okay now we
want to collect
uh your domain data your test data like
here i would like to do this spam or not
spam classification so give me your data
data set
here i want to
want you to provide labels right because
of pre-trained model
we have this uh initial prior
so this is a way we don't actually need
to have a lot of label data so the label
data of maybe a few thousand will be
sufficient otherwise in the past we need
tons of tons of data because we need to
trend the
bottom layers right the image in the
image domain we have given this uh
example of edges and contour as a bottom
layer and we can do transfer learning
here the same thing the birth picture
model already trend all the base layers
then here we just won't need to do fine
tuning based on our supervised task on
the top
so let's look at fine tuning uh the
first one
just uh just say we enumerate a few uh
very kind of dominant application uh
recommendation information
recommendation summary document
classification q a mnd recognition
sentiment essence saying so and so forth
and this is one example of fine tuning
want to generate class labels of a
document right so input will be
just the documents itself and then we
input into the birth
and then we provide labels on the top to
do fine tuning so what fine tuning would
do would be
on the top of bird we may create a
shallow neural nets so fine tuning space
on this but the bottom layers we do fine
tuning on the on the top layers of our
so-called adaptive or fine-tuning layers
of weights and eventually we train our
uh model for the target task likewise we
can do qa qa left hand side is a
question right hand side is your
paragraph we ask the question to say
what is the weather tomorrow and then
the output will be the start position of
the answer and position of the answer
and then the span the span will be seven
characters whatever then you look into
at the end actually if you have started
an end you don't need spam but for some
reason they put spent here you extract
the answers out of the paragraph and
this is quite limited because the
paragraph here is only
uh very short about 216 characters
and this is uh
sentence tagging we want to tag place
and person on the sentence again we go
through this
fine tuning process so given the center
eventually john lives in new york we
know john is a person in new york those
two are locations so there are many
successful stories and this uh figure
shows using verbal training model uh the
results on many tasks
and uh performs much superior results
compared with you have this one vertical
uh you do training by using using
traditional cell supervised learning
method right
so definitely you see revolutionary
results so nowadays people start with
preschool model without having any
questions asked
so gpd2 using
this traditional language model they are
also performed very very very remarkably
well i would say both gpt and the birth
the concept is equivalent and just their
language models are different and the
results are very very similar both are
very very powerful and the
congratulations to the whole community
finally we virtually get all the
problems we enumerate in the beginning
addressed
like okay so next time we'll come back
to see uh slightly more fragrant details
but hopefully uh so far this lecture we
provide this uh
history in 1.5 lectures of nlp and we
can
comfortably move forward using the
pre-training model of course the next
question will be well
wow there are so many preacher models
which one i should use right and there i
have this multi-model situation
multilingual situation and i'm in the
medicine so your purpose any model may
not be applicable let's talk about them
in the next lecture
okay thank you so much uh questions
i