hi good morning everyone
today's lecture we are going to cover
privacy preservation
machine learning uh privacy is a very
critical issue
i would talk about the reasons
regulations
approaches and finally one of the
solutions
stanford has implemented uh before we
get started let's talk about this uh
our presentation schedule uh we have two
uh classes uh open for sign up
next tuesday and the next thursday
and each presentation is expected to be
about 30 minutes
so if you your time cannot accommodate
to this
to uh presentation epochs
we can accommodate a scheduling other
time
but it should be before uh the time we
need to turn in the
your grades and also just a reminder
please uh
do cost evaluation and this is
reminding me by the register uh
we would like to really appreciate your
comments suggestions
so for the next addition we can make
improvement
or basically what we have done right and
what
you expect us to improve let us know
and remaining lectures today
again we cover privacy preserving
machine learning
and this thursday and
we had covered already consciousness and
we are going to wrap up consciousness
get into mind and ethics these are two
very critical subjects but at the same
time very abstract
but i plan to root on psychology
and maybe physics right to give you
some of the perspectives from quantum
mechanics
and maybe even from religions
perspective
okay to this outline we are going to
start
cover the major concerns about privacy
from users perspective
and also from companies perspectives
and the privacy regulations the key
regulations are ccpa
and gdpr and we plan to explain
them in details and also in the medical
domain
right we have we have another set of
regulations
but they are pretty similar uh then
from this compliance requirements if we
cannot comply as a company
the company may be fined heavily so we
have to
understand the complex requirement and
convert the
requirement into execution requirements
and we must have heard about
like federated learning or differential
learning will those implementation
fulfill the
regulation requirements or not i
personally consider they are not
adequate but it's really hard to say
until
a company and was a company will be
brought to the lawsuit situation
the court eventually will clarify
the boundary of the regulations so
we enumerate three major technical
approaches
to be able to preserve privacy and
finally
uh i mentioned this is a standard system
called saltaria
it's called developed by by stanford and
also my previous colleagues
and use this blockchain to safeguarding
privacy so privacy
for sure we know that they say using
cell phone using laptop
whatever information we enter we will be
tracked right so there's a trade-off
between
free usage applications and you have to
give us something
and in certain situations if you don't
give up your information
the application cannot be run like
google maps right google maps you say i
want to about
uh location tracking then good luck
uh it just cannot be functioning so but
other applications like news so i i'm
consulting a japanese company right now
and they are worried about if they track
your reading patterns
uh what will be the regulation
ramifications
right so in certain applications the
yes or no between yes and no the
boundaries is kind of tricky
and the sale giant vehicle for sure
uh he has been collecting tons of data
and uh take tesla as an example if you
see the fine print
behind the vehicle you can see uh it
collects your
battery status temperature inside
outside your location
also in this level two uh cell driving
they have to track
the user's status right if a user is
dozing off
they quickly they will just turn off
self-driving mode
and all those information potentially
where you are
and what is your conversation even in
the car
uh they will track and for instance if
you are
in they say in some countries you get
into a taxi
and everything uh you you kind of
conduct
in that tennessee in that space uh
it's not personal information it's
actually private
and so when we talk about healthcare we
introduce this tricorder device
with a number of uh medical iots
and all those information such as the
walking pattern and the the ecg
information
on apple watch right those data
is being collected and utilized
and frankly i have no idea who is using
my
uh ecg data and will
apple resell my data to
other companies at this point i'm just
totally clueless
right so it would be nice to be informed
what kind of data is being collected
from me
and to to which party the data
will be sold and although as part of
stanford over
we're doing this virtual system and
virtual assistant will become
more and more popular even you don't
have a speaker just talk to
your computer through siri the
information is being collected
and all these speakers suppose we turn
them off
they are still sort of listening right
because they need to be
be waken up to perform their duties
so conversations at home uh will be
recorded
so one situation i got into this was
about a week ago
i went up to the dish and i came home
and i i feel i feel my knees
were hurting so i i on the one hand i'm
searching for remedies for
heating my knees at the same time i also
talked to my wife about the situation
and suddenly facebook uh prompt this
video to me so that was very spooky
right
uh so this could be one of two
situations one was
facebook sue macbook
was listening to me and the second thing
is maybe i was typing something
in real time the information was
transmitted to
facebook and facebook do this kind of
real-time
matching so this is uh to me is a kind
of horrible experience means
well in real time people can target me
or you can say this is a blessing i have
this health health concern and someone
is
really caring for me so
top consumer privacy concerns so yes i
do have a lot of concerns
this is a survey conducted by
some agencies and you can search all
these kind of different surveys on the
internet
so i summarize some key concerns one is
definitely identity
theft it's not really changing these
days
even you say i want to anonymize myself
but still do cross-court correlation
the if people really want to target you
individually
they could get your pi information
personal identifying
the information and the private data
then will be made
public and this is really bad for
especially
politicians even for us right it is not
a glamorous glimmer situation
and data can be sold and distributed
without our knowledge
and certain data especially medical data
could be valuable
so when data being sold people will be
willing to sell the data for
revenue or for charity but they'd like
to
know the fact the data has been used
and the safety if my location can always
be tracked
then if people want to impose harm
to myself and that's kind of
not a converting situation so
let's enumerate some details of ccpa
and the gdpr regulations so gdpr
was is established by european union and
ccpa
was passed by california congress
about two years ago then the was become
active
january 2020 and they gave
all the companies some great spirit to
implement it
and currently as i if if my
information is not obsolete means if a
consumer
asks for certain privacy related actions
to be constructed by a company let's
like erase my assets history
the company has to respond in about
three months
so because the regulation was just
was just out there last year so
therefore they gave this
long grace period for all the companies
to get their ad together and recently
when you access certain sites you
started to get
a pop-up like can i use your cookie can
i track your cookie and so on so forth
those are pretty much because of a ccpa
and lawyers agree ccpa although was
initiated in california but will be
widely
adopted by other states very very soon
so like i mentioned ccpa started
last year and some terms let's
define them so when we discuss all the
implementations
we will be on the same page so here we
say person
person we talk about uh juris prudence
uh nature person just like the person
with with the body
with temperature right it's not like a
business
business kind of unit so
personal information defined by
information that can
identify or relates to describes
is reasonable capable of being
associated with
a real person so this
kind of personal information could
include my
address ids and
several other things and we talk about
more
in later slides and then to
start the data imagine data we divide
the people into
uh kind of three two or three categories
why is the people need to manage data
right data we call data subject
and the data controller is a person
who determines the process of managing
the data
and set up the sop standard operation
process
for processing data and data processors
are the people who are instructed by
data controllers
to process the data so
basically you have controller and
processor they play
different roles okay and
pi personal information is divided by
a few categories one is personal
information strictly
prohibited to disclose including a
person's religion
genetics biometric health healthcare
data and ids and there there are more
and some data they are anonymized
right so suppose you have a database
storing a person's name and then all the
personal information plus their access
history
access means i say i access a news
website the asset history will be all
the news i've read
in the last let's say several weeks so
you like to be able to anonymize not
really the assets patterns
but my pi personal information need to
be anonymized
and another category is pseudo
anonymized
so even let's say you anonymize my
record
but still using some mechanisms
i can still re-engineering or
re-identify
that person right i will give an example
shortly so basically suppose i have your
address
and that's very very simple i have your
gender
and maybe your working location
maybe it's not too hard to pin down uh
your identity even not yourself per se
but can profile you into a specific
group
so this is a example
suppose you have data stored
by let's say facebook or google and
they need to worry about two things one
is how to store
data and the second thing is how the
data will be
accessed right and the storage because
when you store data data will be used
so how the data gets stored can affect
privacy
so let's say you have your
database table which consists of
personal information and like i
mentioned some
access history you have to separate the
two into two
tables and do it to a join and the only
data controller can see both tables
and the data processor can only touch on
the table with only data data history
but with rpi information okay so you
kind of reduce
the number of people who can touch the
pi information and oh
even let's say data controller can
access pi information
and all the assets must be locked
and locked on indebted record for future
audit so here one important point
sticks out is indelible record
for audit and the auditing process must
be
transparent and must be trusted
and all the actions done by this
dc and also
need to be provable right so you say
yeah i did it i did this and
that but that's your verbal claims but
when
fcc audits a company they want to see
provable evidence
so privacy governance
and the policy
clearly returned to cover the following
so i will talk about
uh gdpr and ccpa separately but they are
very similar
only about one or two items they are
they have slight differences so the
policy clearly written
uh just sent to the user user need to
consent the policy has to cover
what data the site collects from the
user
and the collection method mechanism how
data will be used
and what the user will receive as an
exchange
right so for example your you would
give more accurate ads as an
exchange whether you like it or not you
can make a decision
and where the data has been stored and
where the data be shared and share with
whom so this
required information must be stated
in in the privacy policy and
some consent must be is pleasingly given
by the data subject and you cannot just
say i give you this
policy with 10 items and
then you say well you have to agree with
either or or nothing
so the key thing here is that by default
all the items
will be opt out and we have to itemize
each collected data item separately and
then
there's no bundle agreement and the user
has to
click each one of them to say either i
accept your collection of my data
collecting my data
or not right so no box
can be pre-checked and the option is
up out and the user can come in to
select
the items they feel comfortable about
and they can always come back to
uh about okay so everything has to be
done explicitly that's the key
so unlike currently many consumer
activities
you will be given a huge or
huge huge deck of documents and you you
are required to sign
to finish signing within 10 or 20
minutes
especially let's say you buy a house or
you
can even buy a car and the contract
agreement
a few pages and you just cannot
see all the details of or fine prints
within the the pressure timing
okay the second uh information
pieces specifically cover uh gdpr
it's european regulations and the
consumer has right
to write of inform right any data
being accessed must be be told
and the right of assets must be granted
by the user
and right the user has right to erase to
be forgotten
and right of data probability if i want
to move my data from
hospital a to hospital b b you cannot
say no
you have to let me do it right to
restrict data processing
and write to object and data processing
can you you can you can even be very
specific saying okay
my gender information or my age
information
should not be revealed right to
rectification means i can make changes
to my personal information
and right to reject automated individual
decision making
or profiling or even as targeting
and ccpa as i said uh the
b of rights are very similar to gdpr
except for two items
so i highlight in in red the first here
is
know whether their personal data is sold
or disclosed
and if so to whom okay and gdpr didn't
say
not specifically but ccpa is saying well
if your data has been sold
you have to tell the the owner
explicitly
and this is probably because of the a
few
problems happen in in the past years and
i have some examples to show you
shortly and the final one is is a little
bit dicey it's got
not to be discriminated and
i could understand it until uh the the
company's smart news
and try to implement the privacy uh
rules
so so smart news in the usually say well
our privacy data store in the back back
end is very convoluted
so if we really need to be in compliance
then we have to
redesign the database schemas we have to
do this data
downloading reloading this will take
some time so why don't we do a shortcut
we just tell the users who up out
this kind of access data agreement
we just say okay sorry you cannot use
our application anymore and basically
you install them
they install their applications from
their phone or from your desktop
and from ccps percent perspective
you cannot do that because this means
you are discriminating
certain users they are not waiting
to let you collect their data but why
this is
very kind of dicey because suppose uh
in the situation of google maps right
so you say okay i'm not going to allow
you to track my
location so you say oh then i cannot
give you
uh driving direction that's not really
discriminating against you that's
i cannot serve you because i don't have
certain information about your
your situation there's no way i can give
you
a reasonable prediction of your of your
next
driving uh direction so
another scenario you can say the
opposite let's say
i have this application i want to charge
you for let's say
subscription fee 10 a month
but if you allow me to access your data
then it's free so then then this
if you if you have this kind of kind of
the over
it's hard to say whether you are
discriminating against a user or not
right so all these kind of boundary
conditions
we can interpret right now but
eventually will be interpreted by
the law of the core of the law
so finally a very subtle point but it's
extremely critical is
i'm not going to read this at all
details
the critical thing is you have to be
able to
write all your privacy safeguarding
actions
somewhere and eventually your actions
have to be provable so give your example
this a person
x requested company y to erase
is or probably consent via email
and companywide did not fulfill the
request
and but claim they claim that they have
done the request
right so you say okay erase my data i
say oh i did it
but i actually did not so how can you
prove it
and you can get into this uh he says
she's a situation
that would be very convoluted so the law
requires
the company has to be able to prove they
have done all the
processes to safeguarding the user's
privacy
so let's come back and talk about
probability in the end
and these are some landmark cases of
privacy positive violation and the
consequences
on the top row you see in the beginning
or
uh maybe a couple of years ago uber was
fined for
148 million by eu so
the top line was a violation of
gdpr and then there was a
230 million dollars fine
from british airway and
the most recent one was ftc
versus facebook and facebook was fine by
five billion dollars and
the bottom is of course is the case
happened just last year
uh ftc brought a lawsuit against
google youtube and google youtube did
not send consent
to children's parent for accessing
children's data right so this is also
kind of complicated because for minors
uh
they don't have even they say well i
agree
you collect my data but they don't
really have they don't they don't have a
sufficient uh
ability to make such a judgment so the
concern should be sent to
parents then this was google was swined
by
170 million dollars
so a very uh tricky situation here was
some company they would say okay i get
fined by
ftc or some agencies for
millions of dollars but on the other
hand
because of the information i can earn
billions of dollars
so for some companies they will say
well this is cost of sales
i don't know whether you have heard
about this term or not um
like one example i can provide is
like google use page rank in the
beginning
and then they do this ad words
right if you you can buy words on search
terms
on google and the patents of adwords
was owned by a european company
so if you implement it without licensing
then you'll be fined heavily but
if you want to license it and there's a
cost
so how can you deal with the situation
right so that's
when that happens that's a consideration
i'll say yeah let me let me just
violate it if uh it's not working then i
just
uh during this kind of disagreement or
dispute
i can just drop it but if i make huge
profit about it
then i can just pay the fine because at
the end i'm
earning more than then my my loss
so that was very uh that kind of act was
very non-ethical but
it's it's actually in practice okay
now we want to say you talk about all
these compliance requirements
how can we implement it and be very
careful
there are many methods presented out
there
but os on mine is one even
the policy has been implemented
can private private information still be
re-identified or people can do reverse
engineer to
find out who you are or which group you
belong to
right so that's one thing to consider
the second
thing to consider is again the
probability
and trust right so you say you had done
that but
prove me how did you do it and when did
you do it
so the execution to comply
consists of uh five steps one is you
have to delegate
an oversight committee in a company
so this is just not saying say i have
done that
so when ftc orders a company my previous
company was audited by
ftc so when they came in they say hey
give me all the documents to show you do
have an oversight committee
who they are and these people do exist
okay and they they map the data you have
collected
to your usage and storage so where do
you store data
can you show us the document and how the
data
has been used so it's definitely hard
for ftc to really get into your database
to look around but they want to see
documentations
and then do you have this sop for your
employees right so all the regulation we
talk about
do you have this compliance process for
your
data controller and also data processors
if frankly you don't even have a process
in place
then everything is just talking and do
you have your personnel divided
into dc and the dpe
and also specifying their roles very
clearly
right and sop for serving consumers when
consumers
is served did you really give them this
kind of contract to sign
so allow them to open an about and
compile with all these
required items and finally probability
let's look at the technique technical
approaches so
the first one is very uh understandable
you say i just anonymize the data right
then we have this
differential privacy was popular before
cc
uh ccpa uh was activated
and the federated learning is still very
popular
and google was was pushing that uh
pushing this back
this is this effort and quite a few
papers have been published
uh on this particular subject then
finally
talk about distributed ledgers so
anonymized versus pseudo anonymization
there are some subtle differences so
anonymization means
if i even i look at the the data or sql
table
i have no idea who is that particular
person so
basically just hide all the personal
identifiable information right so
including
excel already your gender your
profession and so on so forth
so but even let's say data has been
anonymized uh still could be
re-engineered to find out who is a
person for instance
uh let's say cell phone would track my
locations so he knows in the daytime i
will be in certain locations around
stanford
so for sure i think uh
the google maps will say oh edward is
affiliated with stanford university and
he lives in palo alto
right and from the duration i
stay in a particular location they say i
stay in the gates building
but i'm not moving around very
frequently
i mean at one spot for more than one
hours
so easily to infer well
maybe you are not a student yes a
student will be moving around
to different classrooms but maybe you
are a staff
or a faculty member right so
if you say oh every every other days
you will show up at a particular
building
and for about one hour and a half now
say okay it's more likely
you are a professor rather than the
staff
so see you have not really disclosed any
information explicitly you only have
this person's
moving patterns but already you got lots
of information from this person
right and the another example is on
facebook you say i'm not going to give
you any
of my personal information including my
birthday
and where i live but
unfortunately if you have your social
networks and you are interacting with
people
uh about 20 some years old
and they are college students
and most of them are from ucla it's not
really hard to infer
you should be in in high probability you
are ucla student
right then with other information
probably not stored
in that particular app then people can
identify you
so because i'm in this news business
now you know when you do ads targeting
if you just use the user's
news data itself so i was joking with
our
engineers i say well i i read
uh election news let's say i'm either
pro
republican or pro democrats just based
on
either i go to cnn or fox news can you
target me with ads
right this is just ridiculous if i i'm a
democrat
do you sell me tesla or do you want to
sell me for
it's not very clear so i said well news
data news reading history
using those to target ads is kind of
ridiculous
but then all companies would buy
information data information from
browsers
from other sources and the facebook
information i just gave you
i was doing a search on google i was not
doing a search on facebook
i would never do a search on facebook
saying oh my knee hurts
what should i do i did a search on
google but how come
facebook will pop up this particular ad
right so
somewhere someone was collecting
information then they aggregate
all information from all different apps
maybe through the browser or somewhere
then they aggregate and they target
myself
so if you just look at one application
you may say oh i'm very safe
no problem virtually about everything
but when i collaborate with some other
applications
then maybe our pi will be identified
so there are many horrible switch
scenarios you probably can
find on the internet if a person really
want to target you find who you are
uh it's not impossible so
so a basic practice is as following
uh like i say if you have a consumer's
data right
you want to say i want to separate the
data into two relation
relational database tables and in one
table
i can store his or her name and the
personal
information or personal identifiable
information
and then have a hash id then using this
hid
i can join another table the key will be
hash id unique hid
or you want to say maybe the hid may not
mean to be unique so that's another way
to make sure
the data you cannot target one person
maybe just a google person
then hash id has
then indexed to non-pii information
so the table this second table can be
accessed by
a data processor if they look at the
table they look at hash id
they look at all these numpy information
they are fine
they are not able to be able to identify
who is doing what
right only data controller oh
he or she can join two tables to know oh
this person with this hash id
is edward so edward has accessed
facebook and google in the last few days
so this is a very primitive way
of trying to be compliant but
for sure it's not really in fully
compliance
so the second method is differential
differential of privacy this was
proposed by
professors in hong kong ust
the idea was i don't really need to
separate
your pi from your uh his
access history but i just need to
introduce
noise to the data right in this example
here
on the top you see you have a very
specific information about person
including office in london department id
date joint 2015 and cell information
and so on so forth right if you get a
hold of
this this piece of information uh in the
company
if you work in the company you see this
it's probably not
not very challenging to infer who is
this person
so you say okay i'm going to try to
introduce noise so rather than london i
say well uk
and uh they joined i wouldn't want to
specify the the month just a year
then the day of birth i specify
and then maybe just a decade or an half
hour time
but still this is not booty proof so but
in theory differential privacy is
attractive
because they can come up with a
quantifiable method
to save guardian privacy and you can see
the formula
is in the middle of the screen the idea
here there are two
uh parameters one is this uh uh
sigma parameter so they have this sigma
algebra the sigma edgewise
i'm going to introduce you introduce to
your data certain noise
right so for particular field we already
seen
you say well i'm going to apply this
h expansion or
birthday kind of anonymize your year but
we put your day and month over there
this kind of
algebra and then they have these privacy
parameters
right they say well it's just like a
newest neighbor search so last time we
covered news neighbor but we didn't
finish
we continued next time was when you do a
newsletter search
you don't get just yourself you get a
group of people
so then you say i cannot really pin you
down as
a particular person in that group so
this is this appstore means
you can introduce this epson and then
there's a trade-off here
for the company to decide you see the
left-hand side the trade-off is
oh private private privacy magic
so you want to safeguarding privacy then
the epson value need to be very small
but
if you say well i don't quite care about
your policy i care about
uh utility sorry is it the other way you
want to safeguarding privacy
absolute value need to be large so when
you want to
when the information is given you you
identify actually a lot of people not
just
a small number of people so it's hard to
pin down one individual
and by the same nice utility metric so
if i get a whole bunch of people here
then this application suppose i want to
do
uh do a search i want to do information
dissemination recommendation then my
accuracy
right the applications target
performance metrics will suffer and for
any company which needs to generate
revenue
the revenue for sure will go down so the
question here is very very simple
uh privacy it's possible to be
implemented right so you say my privacy
regulation is very loose
and comply with privacy eventually
can be kind of enhanced but i'm going to
lose a lot of revenue
will the company do that or would they
try to do any kind of
circumvention to prevent compliance
so this is a real problem and
that's the reason again probability
becomes important
so let's come back to look at this
differential privacy
and depends on how large the epstein you
won't want it to be the privacy can be a
local privacy
or a global privacy local privacy means
okay i have a small group of people i
just want to
implement this uh sigma algebra
so magically alter their private data
then i have an aggregator and eventually
i can
store the data but i can make my
privacy slightly more global means
i have an aggregator i already aggregate
information from a large number of users
let's say female or male then i use a
magic formula
to alter them right so then i have this
anonymous output and because the
input is a group of people so it's much
harder to track back to
individuals so when you combine both
right suppose i say well your private
data
individual data i'm going to do a
shuffling and then
i do another layer i analyze the
shuffling results
and applying even more magic then i
really anonymize everyone
so the question is let's say the the
final master
is probably the most secure one but
it probably provides uh the the business
usage information to make their profit
right so again this is a big trade-off
situation
so people trying to do this differential
privacy then i think it's kind of
dying out now it's really hard to prove
to
an auditor saying this is my epsilon
this is my sigma
so this is this is the way i conduct the
business
and i prove in theory this will work but
no you cannot prove
everything is done empirically and the
even you show the empirical data
and who can trust you in pure data so
harvard
published this uh interesting article
it's interesting but
it was not very sung basically uh this
paper saying
well you you do your differentiate uh
differential or pseudo
anonymization on the data but we can
re-engineering we identify the users
right so
the experience they did was they get
about 300 users data from the
the medical databases then they say well
everyone was anonymized so let's start
to add
additional information let's say a zip
code
and date of birth and so on and so forth
at the end they say well we can identify
accurately
about 90 of people so
i really i mean i understand this is a
kind of uh interesting result
showing the more personal data you know
about a person
you can more accurately infer who the
person is
but this is no brander right so the the
chance to me was
if you only have 300 pieces of
information then you clam you can
identify person 95 accurately
i think it's an easy problem but if you
enlarge your pool
from 300 to 3 million and i bet
even with a zip code you cannot do that
and if you have day of birth here
frankly
uh even even with one million people the
accuracy can
still be quite high right so i
respect the paper but the paper
itself didn't really tell me
any promising or exciting methods
so federated learning it started from
google uh wrote a paper and also a blog
introduced the method the method is very
logical
so we all have our devices
our laptop or cell phone
and whatever personal devices and we
don't
send our private data to the app so
to the concluded cloud so all data
mining
all this kind of machine learning will
be conducted
on the phone right so after
the machine learning has been conducted
the model has been learned
on the phone then the model will be sent
to the cloud and the cloud
or is the centralized system then we'll
aggregate all the information
and develop a global model and the
global model will come back
in return compared to this target
individual cell phones
so on the one hand this is kind of
attractive
on the other hand it also introduces
arrows
to the classification and not only
introduces arrows
but there could be other problems let's
say what kind of information you
aggregate
suppose i own the android system
and or ios
so the amount of data i collect is not
just from one application i actually
call that data from
all different applications so
as i as an example i gave you a few
minutes ago
this is even more dangerous than getting
all information
from one applications right one
particular application
but you get all information get
information from all
applications then you do uh
kind of color collaborating among them
and
the kind of information you can call is
just totally horrible
and okay let's look at healthcare as one
example suppose i have a
deep neural net and this feature shows
there are multiple layers attention
layers and so on so forth
and the idea of this federated learning
is
i'm going to cut off this multi-layer
neural networks into two parts
right so my animation doesn't work but
actually
the key thing is in the middle here
let's say i draw a line
in the middle here okay okay actually
this picture will show
so i have four hospitals each has
been training the model based on their
let's say
x-ray data they want to do this cd scan
or maybe lung disease classification
so each hospital have collected certain
data then run their own
training algorithms and then i say okay
i'm going to
cut your neural net into a half
so the top half so you learn in the
middle then i say stop
don't continue learning just ship me all
the model parameters
then you say okay i'm going to continue
learning here
in my center database so you guys stop
learning i'm going to aggregate
right so at the bottom here you show
this is a
send central centralized continuous
learning
and getting parameters from all
different sites
and this method seems to be
reasonable but but there are clearly
uh two shortcomings from medical
perspective
the first shortcoming is as angeline
said
every hospital may collect data
using different process different
devices
or even same device same device with
different process or
calibrations so when you
aggregate the parameters in
this subsequent model those parameters
may not agree with each other and that
could problematic because
each other will become your noisy
disturbance rather than trying to help
you
so for the test data that could be
this method could be productive because
text it attached is the text
but for imagery this pipeline may not be
able to improve your accuracy
and and in practice i see these kind of
methods
um it's really hard to be realized
because
no hospital here would trust
other hospitals every hospital consider
their own data to be
to be a piece of gold they don't want to
share with others
so only perhaps in on android phone or
on ios
this federated learning can be conducted
but for health care i have really strong
doubt
okay so problem solved
and i don't think so and the
two key problems one or the
enumerate which is the trade-off between
privacy safeguarding and the utility to
the company or revenue of the company
right this is always an ethical problem
and
a company a ipo post ipo company they
have obligation to their shareholders
and the ceo is under tremendous pressure
to perform
so i don't know where the ceo would
draw the boundary then the second
challenge is
probability right you can claim anything
but
ccpa now requires a company to prove
so this again this is the picture to
summarize
regulations but at the end on the right
hand side
is you should be able to trust
the company and the company has to be
able to prove
their results and the policies so let me
spend the remaining time to introduce
saltaria sotaria is the goddess of
greece
it's kind of providing individuals
safety
and the basic idea is we want to lock
everything including user consent
user revocation and
so all the consumers actions on their
data
and all these actions conducted by the
company basically
need to be hardened on a ledger
and this ledger if you want to be able
to be people to trust the ledger
this ad ledger need to be open
transparent to the public
so anyone can audit the ledger if i say
no no no this is a centralized system
this is
the bank's ledger so you can i'm going
to log everything but
sorry i cannot allow you to come in to
see
the details because i don't want you to
see other people's account balance
then this is a ledger which is not
transparent
and cannot bring people's trust okay so
transparency
is the key so that leads to uh
the centralized and versus decentralized
system
the centralized system by the names
basically saying
all the data all the synchronization is
conducted
by one unit right let's say a central
bank
or all the banks in the u.s uh they have
this
uh bank the headquarter bank
and all information need to be
synchronized with
the headquarters so when a bank want to
close their books
every day they have to synchronize uh
from the center to all the
distributed uh bank bank branches
to try to reconcile their their books
and decentralized means
all individuals can communicate with
each other
and you can do local decisions
but eventually uh we need to be able to
reach global agreement
okay so we come back to see an example
is this centralized banking system uh
deposit withdrawal and so on so forth
let's say i have two atms
i'm using two atms from one atm i
deposit money the other atm i will show
money right
so the important thing is you need to be
consistent you cannot say
well before my deposit goes in i already
withdraw my money
so i have this kind of i kind of double
deposit whatever
this kind of secret scenario and you
know in the bitcoin situation they want
to save money
double spending right you say i want to
use my bitcoin to buy ten dollars of
uh goods in in one company or one
store use the same bitcoin to buy
another thing so there's a
window about 30 minutes
for a bitcoin transaction to be
committed we think that 30 seconds
a person can double spend and that
problem has to be closed right
so but bitcoin is a decentralized
problem it's much
more challenging in a centralized
problem but central apartment bank
is one example and another example can
be hospital
so you say okay i'm going to perform
certain process on a patient
the information will be stored in the
hospital but eventually the information
has to
be sent to who sent to a payer right
sent to insurance company
so insurance company pays the bills and
they pretty much aggregate all the data
together
they have all hospitals data and this is
pretty much universal in canada they
have a
universal health care run by the
government the government has to pay the
bills
so the government has all the health
care records of the canadian citizens
now again the question is trust if you
have a centralized system
how can i trust you because you are not
going to reveal me
all the actions you have conducted so
we like to be able to have a
decentralized system so decentralized
system the question then will be
you have certain inconsistency that will
happen you have
local agreement but globally
may not be agreeable so therefore
consensus protocols need to be executed
so consensus protocol can be separated
into two camps
one is distributed consensus you could
have local consensus eventually you
uh convert to global consensus or you
just have a
centralized consensus protocol and
centralized
consensus protocol has been out there
for many many years
because bank banks or airline
reservation systems
have been out there for more than two
decades right
for allies airline reservation systems
and when they started about even 20-30
years ago
even today they haven't be able to
really changing the system because it's
just too many agents
try to access the database and any
modification to the system
around into the risk of data corruption
so we don't get into all these protocols
in in details because we want to
stay in a on a high level and the server
has courses to cover
uh the detail methods and when i was
back in
the cs department 20 years ago there was
a database course
then there was a transaction processing
course and the transaction partnering
costs will cover
all these protocols to safeguarding
agreement so let me just give you an
example this is a rudimental
consensus protocol talk or two-phase
commit protocol
so i have my participants
right and eventually i need to make a
decision
so let's say i want to have a consensus
we in a class you say when are we going
to do
our is hypothesis hypothetically when
are we going to do
our final exam and then i send send out
two dates one is next tuesday another
one next thursday
then students start to vote right so
once i get all the votes i say okay
majority people vote for
thursday so i would say i will return
back to you to say
okay now i'm prepared to come come meet
because our rule is
majority wings and then the decision in
the decision phase
the student will say yeah i was i was
saying tuesday i prefer but now
the kind of a majority decision is
thursday so i'm going to okay
commit i'm going to decide to commit so
you have second phase of communication
so in the two-phase company protocol
here you see
the overhead is the number of messages
going back and forth
to reach consensus and if the number of
participants
is small and you have this kind of
centralized system
and the cost is linear to the number of
participants
right say i have 10 students and maybe
the message will be
sending back and forth 40 times because
the two-way messages for
each face but then when you say i want
to do a
global but decentralized kind of company
protocol
then the cost will be much much higher
will be n square
right so everyone has to be able to talk
to everyone in the most general
situation and this
is not affordable now you say well on
the one hand i want to be transparent
i want each person to be able to make
their
kind of own decision they can look at
other people's data but on the other
hand i have this kind of enormous cost
how can i mitigate or i do the
reasonable trade-off
and the trade-off easy to understand
here is
i'm not going to talk to it to everyone
although i want to do decentralized
system
but i'm going to talk talk to just a
group of people
right a group of people who i can trust
they say
i when i want to make a commit decision
or when i say i want to sell my medical
data record to sahil and
this agreement only need to be approved
or been seen by let's say triple a
bank of america and maybe tesla only
three
because why i don't think they together
have any interest to con conspire
together
to kind of hear me right so i say okay
that's good enough
three participants to vote for years
then i can move on and
so this is a kind of compromise
but also reasonable right but if you say
i'm going to randomly select
a few then the situation will be much
more dicey
so just slightly talk about the bitcoin
situation
bitcoin is entirely decentralized and
they say
oh if two-thirds of people
are voting saying your transaction is
hard
it's just an example or
when they start to build new blocks
right so
when the new boss has been granted
has been committed they have this that
kind of longest block
will win now this condition so you have
a block which is
six blocks longer you have a check which
is six
longer than the other chain then all the
previous blocks
will be hardened or will be granted or
be committed
but this would take some time right and
they don't actually identify who are the
people
who can make a block committed so
it's like racing you have to solve a
puzzle and
when a large number of people solve a
puzzle then the block
is kind of hardened and so who can solve
the possible is random
and they say even you say two-thirds or
one-half
the people in this two-third and one not
one-half one-half tool
they are random you don't know whether
they can be trusted or not trusted
so eventually you know uh some powerful
uh kind of resource company they
actually can hack down
a bitcoin because they can own the
majority of gpu in the world
and they can be the majority of this
kind of
voting scenario right so instead of
doing that kind of
so expensive computation
why not just saying oh i'm not going to
send to 1 billion people
i'm going to get these 10 people right
uh these 10 people have
config of interest with each other if
they so or say yes
then that's fine with me so that's
pretty much the idea be
between a centralized decentralized and
decentralized you have this n square
messaging cost and x maxing cost is huge
because you know
i o is much more expensive than cpu or
gpu time computational time
so that would just grind your system to
a halt
again the trade-off will be okay i'm not
going to talk to n
i'm going to talk uh just a small subset
of n so this decentralized
uh picture shows the trade-off between
cost
and the trust between transparency again
and the trust and there are so many
different protocols recently got
proposed
to be able to achieve a very good
compromise between the two
so what do i say good compromise really
depends on
the applications objective okay i can
again
give you a couple examples shortly so
consensus versus transparency
in the privacy situation uh all the
actions like
what can the data allow the consumer
to be uh processed by the by the by the
business
and the contract open up our information
rectification all the information need
to be transparent to the public
so can be audited and using blockchain
to solve the problem first of all let's
quickly identify
the structural blockchain so a chain of
blocks
let's say h is the height
means i have h individual blocks
and every block may consist of
a number of transactions right in the
transaction is in the sense of bank is
straightforward deposit
and maybe withdraw or i look at my
account history
in the case of privacy every transaction
is like
oh user account a user is consent user
b's
revocation and business a
access user b's data right those are the
transactions
upon your data subject will all be
locked
on the blockchain so this is one example
or in one single block of the chain
and the transactions are organized into
a
merkle tree so the characteristic of
merkel trees
if you change one of the leaf
and then the hash value in the merkle
tree
will be modified so why we call this
indelible because
no one can come here to hack your data
if someone did
then the hashing value will be
mismatched and
we can identify and then this is like a
binary tree eventually going up to the
top
and we have this root hash
which is usually utilized to
authenticate this
block is not contaminated then
this block has a hash index
to the previous hash block so when we
in in the index altogether you can see
the blockchain has a number of
blocks they are linked together with
this kind of
previous uh previous head address and
every block has a number of transactions
organized in this merkle tree now it's
very evident why you only have a pointer
to the previous block
because you have no idea when you
establish a plot you have no idea when
the next ball will be
will be established
so key requirements here i'm not going
to repeat
transparency and the privacy and
probability
so now let's let's just step back to see
how the blockchain
can be utilized efficiently because i
talk about bitcoin and you know bitcoin
very well
it's the problem is it's latency right
latency of bitcoin means
i need to trust a transaction
but i need to wait for about half an
hour
because unless the transaction
the the block which the transaction
resides
get committed and in addition
that particular block resides in a
blockchain
which has a length six more blocks than
the second longest one then i would say
okay my transaction
has been hardened and this will take
half an hour
and this is a pretty long time if you
want to do this half an hour transaction
then payment is impossible you do
payment you go to
stock box you say i'm going to use use
blockchain to pay my bill
the commit time is uh six hours so i
think starbucks wouldn't accept your
payment
so like privacy or like
uh currency if you want to use this kind
of
bitcoin methodologies something has to
change
and this is the way we did it so before
we get into detail let's look at this
eric brewer's
cap theorem cap cap c stands for
consistency
so data viewed by different parties
need to be consistent in the same order
right you say i withdraw then i
i deposit other people look at the
record they want to see
we saw deposit they want to see the
other way then you have this
inconsistent problem
availability is another one you want the
system to be up
all the time so this is like the cell
phone networks
so if my if i shut down my cell phone
now it shouldn't affect your
your cell phone right it's very easy to
understand because you want your cell
phone to be available
not depending on other people's cell
phones and the partition tolerance
and in the banking system partition
tolerance is not allowed
but in our cell phone scenario general
network scenario
internet partition tolerance should be
allowed
otherwise if my laptop is done your
laptop needs to be
in a standby mode that's not acceptable
so
if we look at this picture then we say
well
in the internet era if we want to do a
distribute system
this is one property we cannot sacrifice
right which is partition
tolerant okay we have to safeguarding
this
uh partition torrent property which is p
but now since every poor theory is
saying you can only
ensure two out of three properties can
be guaranteed
at a simultaneous at one one time so
either you choose
uh cp or you choose
ca a pa pa or
only two other three or ca the the banks
choose ca right they don't care about
partition tolerance
if there's a partition they shut down
the system right away
they guarantee consistency and when the
system is consistent
they open up they they make sure it's a
scalable
available so decentralized system as i
just summarized
we need to provide people just either cp
or ap for the sake of bitcoin
they provide this a and amp
because bitcoin want to be available all
the time
and they want to also allow a network to
be partitioned
but they sacrifice consistency as i
again just mentioned
we think about six hours or half an hour
depending on the situation your
transaction
was in an inconsistent state so double
spending
could happen and uh
summarize bitcoins problem one is very
expensive to maintain
such a blockchain and one billion
dollars
a year and the lack of privacy why
because you put data on the chat so now
you say edward are you kidding
you want to put medical data on the
chain so you want to put medical data in
the public
so i will come back to address the issue
shortly and
use a pos proof of work protocol
means you want to solve a parcel and
nuance
it's very expensive and finally low
throughput
right transaction per second for bitcoin
is only seven transactions per second
and ethereum is 15. not much better
so we if we utilize that to be a payment
that's impossible
and if we want to utilize for security
privacy preservation
that's kind of also not very convenient
but
we can solve the problem so banking i
talked about the centralized system
using ca
and we also already discussed the
trade-off between
centralized and decentralized consensus
protocols
and then let's look at satellite how can
you
implement a system which is at the same
time
can ensure this uh ap ap
kind of property also can insure
uh pc my pc and pa
at the same time so pc and pa if you
union a tube
you can become pca the trick here is
we want to be able to achieve short
latency like
one to two minutes and the super need to
be extremely high
and we are arguing this is actually
argued by
professor uh measures professor measures
by the way
he was one of the founders of uh uh
stellar a standard or the ipo
uh is maybe number eight the
public published company probably ibo
company on blockchains
and uh he he and us had
many many interesting debates so
basically i say okay
let's have this two-layer ball chain so
you have men chen
insures ap properties in the worst case
main change
ethereum it's in the public domain but
the side chain will be on the ca using
ca property
right we are using uh cp property
is also okay so the side chain will be
very very quick but the mention will be
be very slow
so this is the picture or sidechain
let's say even using cs system
the mention is using this this uh ap
system
we organize them into three layers the
first layer is a public chain
with very slow response time
and high latency and the second layer
with very fast execution time low
latency
and high support the method to improve
super is like
david measure said you just replicate
your cpu right you just improve
just duplicate your local system and i
only care about
latency you want to guarantee latency
then when you want to guarantee super
if you have sufficient business you just
replicate your system
so that's a claim by professor david
measures and we have to agree with him
and finally you have this smart contract
which is the way to
not to put data on the blockchain but
you put contract
on the blockchain even more beautifully
the contract is in nature language
so if you say i put uh something
on the blockchain which is my private
data is is really bad
if i put a digital contract which is a
piece of code
on the blockchain in fact we will be
eventually put a piece of code
on the blockchain let's say i want to
access your data
and this is a agreement in nature
language but
we need to be able to convert this
nature language statement
to a piece of restful api or sql
statement let's say
fetch something from
relational database k with attribute
equal to what
right so with this particular piece of
code
but already approved then certain people
can
just execute the code to get your data
so smart contract
is a very important piece of information
sitting here
for two reasons one through nature
language
user can understand what they are up to
then we convert
the piece of information into a piece of
code
and this conversion i pretty much
covered
when i talked about oval right we had a
lecture about this
human voice speech interface
and in that i talked about in oval and
we need to do semantic grounding
simulink grounding in principle is very
challenging
but if you want to just go on into
programs
it's much easier because programs only
have
a small number of instructions and also
they are not ambiguous
right in nature language a word can mean
multiple meanings you have polygamy or
other situations but in code when you
say
right it's right when you say move it's
smooth so
smart contract is the good solution
so smart contract summarizes it it's a
piece of nature language
construct to convert to a code and the
data is offline
retrieved by approved code and the
contract validation
relocation execution will generate
transactions and these transactions
will be written onto the blockchain so
when you look at a blockchain you you do
see oh
i have a piece of code executed but the
code number
is 722 you have this id and
then you have transactions to form a
tree
and the root of the merkle tree
on the subchain right we say sub channel
will be very efficient
but you say okay i make the subject very
efficient
but the root of the markov merkle tree
i lock it to the main chain so when i
lock the secondary route to the main
chain
the process will suffer from low latency
but
it's okay right because i can
locally guarantee the transaction has
been hardened
but probability can be done
can be guaranteed maybe half an hour
later
so this is acceptable acceptable to the
private situation because even i want to
sue
a company i cannot fire a lawsuit within
uh within half an hour right so
i do have half an hour probably if you
want to
contact a lawyer to find a lawsuit that
would probably take a few days
so this hierarchical architecture
is just beautiful you can accomplish the
objectives
to summarize we have this uh
on a sidechain we have cash blocks
and they got they got linked together
and they enjoy the performance of
high throughput because you get
replicated systems and more importantly
low latency and the privacy is
safeguarded because we don't store data
on the blockchain
we only store the id of the code
on the blockchain data is in the
database access through
the code and then we hash the root
of the local merkle tree to the global
blockchain so when the public auditing
when the public audit is conducted they
can go back to the
global uh global blockchain to verify
the local mercury hash value is not
altered
right this ensure often
authenticality so
this picture just to complete when we
implement system
we still need to have a reasonable user
interface
if you like to know the details you can
look into our
publication available on the internet
let me get into slightly more details
on the left-hand side right you have
interface here
both data consumer data provider can
access through the web and the data
provider let's say i'm a
patient i can say okay i have a data my
x-ray
i'm willing to sell my data at the price
and data consumer
comes in to say this may be a
pharmaceutical company saying i like to
be able to beat
uh 20 pieces of data in a particular
situation
or i say i want to do irb i want to do
kind of
draw discovery or or vaccine tests i
need to recall
10 10 million people or 10 000 people i
can go to the system and say
who willing to give me your vaccine
drug interaction or side effect data so
then this agreement can be conducted
through the web application so once the
the consensus have been
performed then the data will be stored
right
into the database at the same time the
blockchain
will be also locked on the blockchain
and then when the audit comes in
is the bottom is audit audit comes in
you can look into the local database
which caches the blockchain's
information and right away i can say
well
uh the company already fulfill your
requirement and this is the information
i can give you right away
the response time for this ats cache can
be just within seconds
then they say no i don't trust you i
want to go to the core to verify
then the core will not access the
company's private data here storing the
cache
the core will go to zotero which is a
transparent public
ledger and the court or auditor can go
there
to access the all the transaction
transactional information
and this is a picture thanks to
professor david measures
monica and the shivaya in ntu and we try
many different
local protocols and eventually we
identify stellar
and tender mean those are two
good protocols we can employ and uh
there's a very strong argument from
professor david measures
he's a no-nonsense guy he said why do
you guys want to use
blockchain because i can see this entire
system can be implemented by a log only
method it's just log right you just
logging
why do you need to ensure consistency
in this whole thing this is not payment
and
we do have a very good counter argument
that counter argument
ceased his concern so if you have time
to think about it
why we need to have consensus
on consistency on the order of
transaction
in the privacy preservation scenario
yeah it's an interesting question to
think about
uh so we uh do some experiment we
conducted but the details
uh again referred to our publications
so summarize today's lecture lecture
privacy is very critical if you started
the company
you want to be able to consider privacy
before
ipos right or the lawsuit wouldn't come
in when you are a current company
but when you go public the next day you
see a number of
uh a number of letters from lawyers
and complex requirements and
also some solutions they are
complementary right
you can use them in in a combined method
by the ndm probability transparency
they must be safeguarded and
uh with this concludes today's lecture
uh you have questions please ask on the
slack
and also remind you to sign up for your
final uh presentation the final page
here is
the publications so gdpr
and uh ccpa and finally this is the
salteria paper
so i see one question oh you know
thank you thank you very much now a
question
any questions
okay next year we are going to fix them
and this year we are going to have
lunches live
so we can have much
more engaged discussion
and uh so thank you so much again send
your message for
questions on the slack do the cost
evaluation
and sign up for the presentation
slots bye bye