hi welcome back to cs372. today is lecture
15. we cover where is consciousness.
if you look at the roadmap of our lectures, and
we are in the final lecture series of the quarter
on consciousness and mind. and this is
the third lecture. in the last lecture
i covered what is consciousness. and
i first motivated why did we study
this particular subject: the reason was because
our current ai hits some limitations including
generalization problem and we cannot explain
causality and so on so forth. therefore like
yoshua bengio was saying we need to start to
study system two. and system two is pretty much
depicting consciousness. therefore we can model
human thinking and we think logically sequentially
and we do planning and reasoning. okay and we have
been arguing whether system two or consciousness
is computation all the way. and some scholars
consider so and some scholars do not consider
the same. when we get into where is consciousness,
hopefully there will be more evidence to support
one or the other. let's quickly review what
is consciousness. there were many definitions
but i consider the ones who (which) can be
supported by science to be more promising.
In particular, the proposal made
by (Michio) kaku, a physicist at
NYU, and he proposed that consciousness
needs to consider time and space, which are
evident and also the number of feedback loops.
feedback loop means sensing and the response.
flowers (plants) may have just limited number
of feedback loops including temperature and
water. for pets at home e.g., cats and dogs,
they may have feedback loops for threats
and for their hunger and interactions
with their masters. and human has numerous
feedback loops: we have five, six sensing
organs--- we have our mouth, eyes, ears, skin---
sensing sensations all the time. and when the
(sensation) energy level reaches a certain
threshold, as Schrodinger said, we
would transition into the consciousness
state. we try to handle these external
events and challenges. and we have emotion
and other people have emotion. we
conduct learning and we receive
feedback on our learning for progress evaluation.
so many many feedbacks that make a human
being the most sophisticated being on earth. so
quickly review this stimulus response diagram.
we started from stimulus.
to human being we started from
the sensory circuits, and we can perceive sights,
and we can hear sounds, smell odor or fragrance,
and taste different food, and so and so forth.
the sensual qualities, as we discussed last time,
will be brought to our nerve system---our
brain. our brain consists of billions of neurons
divided roughly into two parts: our
cerebellum manages unconsciousness,
and our cerebrum manages consciousness. and
eventually consciousness or conscious state
makes a decision on the
corresponding responses to the
stimulus. then we we finish
this stimulus-response pathway
another definition, or sort of discussion made
by a physicist, is made by Erwin Schrodinger.
I found his "what is life" book to be really
intriguing. he talked about evolution,
he considered consciousness has something to
do with learning and adaptation. and physically
the transition between consciousness and the
unconsciousness can be explained by physics laws.
for the human state to transition from
unconsciousness to consciousness and
schrodinger says it's pretty similar to
quantum jumps: when atoms could be in
different states and only when the
energy reaches a certain threshold
then the quantum jump may occur
or occur with a probability.
and likewise our sensing organs, let's say our
skin we sense some itchiness but not severe,
it doesn't really trigger a response. but only
when the itchiness reaches a certain threshold
or consciousness aware about the itchiness and
we start scratching our skin. but on the other
hand we talk about transition from consciousness
to unconsciousness Schrodinger uses the second law
of thermodynamics to depict the phenomenon.
the second law says in the close system and
the entropy in the close system will continue to
increase until the entropy is maximized and when
that happens the system is in the inert state.
the example i gave a few times, like driving or
we learn how to walk. initially we need to really
pay attention to these activities in a learning
mode. but eventually they became routine
and habitual to us and they will fade into
unconscious state, and only until some
unexpected event happens, for instance, an
unexpected pedestrian shows up in front of us,
then we are brought back to the conscious state to
deal with this kind of novel challenge. we have to
plan to react to try not to hurt this pedestrian.
Observations: we talk about the transitions, we
talk about needs and wants, and we will expand
the discussion shortly. we last time talked
about top-down attention is in consciousness
and bottom-up is from unconsciousness into
consciousness and finally unconsciousness
is loaded with inherited skills. when we were
born and we already can do very sophisticated
organ operations. even let's say you ask us to
start to learn how to operate our heartbeats
or changing heart-beat rhythms i think it
probably cannot be learned. so the tough skills we
inherited through dna, and at the same
time all the learned skills on the earth:
like we learned how to bike and swim, they never
got written back to DNA. so we don't pass the
DNA of swimming to our children, they just have
to relearn everything we learned from afresh.
so this is rather interesting and ironic and this
is touching the notion that i talked about wants
and the needs. it seems to be (i just briefly
talked about discussed here), it seems to be what
what are essential to survival, or what are the
needs, respond to needs will pass through DNA
to our offspring. but what are optional, like
our wants to have a new iphone our wants to
be happy living in the better house, and those
are really not passing along through the DNA.
Look at another problem, unconscious to
conscious, last time we didn't talk about it
was unconsciously, different organs
or sensory circuits are collecting
information simultaneously.
Our eyes, our nose, and skin, they collect
respective signals at the same time. But only
one consciousness at one time. in other words,
the consciousness is working single-threaded.
the question here is actually twofold: 1) is
this kind of limitation of human we can only do
one thing at a time? we only have one self,
we cannot have multiple selfs or multiple
consciousness existing at the same time. if
this is a limitation to a human, suppose we
want to build a robot, do you think a robot can
have multiple consciousness at the same time?
so this is your homework number one.
the assignment will be given
to you at the end of today.
We have two questions about cancer and two
questions about consciousness. The first question
here is why one self and one consciousness?
My own hints are the the following.
I remember in the 90s i worked on the
first generation of multiprocessor
at DEC (Digital Equipment Corporation)
even let's say we started with four cpus
and we need to have this called spin lock on
the top to try to synchronize those cpus. you
can consider it's like a scheduler on the top.
and from the notion of writing to the memory or
writing to a file, you know we always want to be
able to ensure consistency. consistency means that
there is an earthly order of events. you write
something you read something... if the order
gets messed up, then inconsistency may happen.
let's say you withdraw certain amount of money
then you pay for certain merchants. if the order
is out of sync then someone will lose money.
So even simultaneously many things can be
going on in the background, there should be
one central scheduler. In the multi-processor
situation we have to do synchronization.
The second notion is that
human may be constrained by our
physical situation because we only have one
body. we only have one pair of eyes, and we have
two hands and two legs. Even we say our sensation
on the left-hand side and on the right-hand side,
both are urgent or need to act on some
responses, but physical body can only
do one thing at a time, (e.g.,
turning right or turning left).
We argue this could be the limitation of
one body of a person. when we implement
on a robot do we have the same constraint?
This is the question i think encouraging you to
discuss and express your thoughts. Next, where is
consciousness? Karl Deisseroth (a Stanford
professor), today pretty much we're presenting his
findings and his research results.
He considers "knowing where" is
very important. Just like everyone,
we agree that we live on this earth,
we have this 3D Cartesian space. And we have
the notion of time. If we don't have memory
then time may not exist. Memory is essential
for us to conduct reasoning, and therefore,
time is a byproduct of the memory. And
then Deisseroth talks about values, and
values are important for human to
evolve and for human to get rewards,
so we do planning to get maximum rewards. I will
come back to talk about value shortly. Values,
there are two sets of different values: one set
of values is for survival and even those could
be brutal. Let's say i'm really hungry or a lion
is very hungry. A lion has to hunt another animal
and that's the intrinsic value or "needs" of
lions. and you may judge lions to be brutal, but
from the evolution perspective, the
value assessment should be neutral.
However, from the moral perspective we
are not judging "needs", we judge "wants".
You say oh you have no problem to survive but you
are stealing things from other people. those are
kind of distinct values once that is intrinsic,
the other side is so like for "wants."
Different! Let's come back to visit those. But
why do we need to know where is consciousness?
And to be able to visualize consciousness,
visualize the stimulus to neurons,
and also responses generated by neurons, we can do
quite a few remarkable things. In the next slide
we get into details and but let's first
talk about a mechanism discovered by
Deisseroth in a very surprised manner. It is the
communication mechanism between neurons.
Neuroscientists always thought neuron
communication should be local. Consider
our skin we feel itchiness. Itchiness, let's say
on my palm. Palm is very small, relatively small,
compared with my entire body, maybe five percent
of my body. So the neurons get into communication
of this itchiness shouldn't be very very vast,
right? We consider to be maybe okay five percent,
ten percent of the neurons. But it turns out
there is a broadcast effect: the broadcast
effect means although sensations may be regional,
but when the sensations is about to raise into
the conscious state, yet it broadcasts to all the
neurons. Other neurons may be managing other
sensory circuits. the reason of doing so is
because we only have one consciousness, and the
consciousness is only single-threaded. We cannot
ask our consciousness to deal with two sensory
circuits at the same time. Let's say walking
to the left and running to the right. Broadcast
seems to be a mechanism to just let everyone
know the current situation so some can back down
a little bit and some can just move forward.
In a sense, it is a kind of prioritization
based on urgency, or based on intrinsic values.
OK. This is the book, this is the foundation of
of today's lecture "where is consciousness".
Karl Deisseroth published this book last year.
This is a distinguished book not only in its
scientific content but also literature excellence.
As we talked about which is
also mentioned by Deisseroth,
we want to visualize our brain, we want to find
out causality. And Deisseroth's team in around
2001 to 2005, they invented a new technology
called optogenetics. I will talk about this
method compared with the traditional electrode
method. Which one is probably more flexible?
Why optogenetics becomes, or is becoming
the mainstream recently. It's also critical
to go back to revisit values. Intrinsic value
is required by evolution survival, and extrinsic
one is optional and then moral assessment will
be involved and that will be covered in the next
lecture: ethics. You may be surprised that we will
be able to quantify certain ethical behaviors,
even that we can quantify sins. OK, let's defer
(discussing ethics) until the next lecture.
For intrinsic values and we have a set of
mental disorders covered by Deisseroth.
A mental disorder, what we call disorder,
means our needs, it goes to one direction but
our mental reaction/mental response goes to
the other direction or the opposite direction.
One example is eating disorder, to which we will
give a tremendous treatment in this lecture.
Our intrinsic value will say oh we have needs to
eat when we are hungry; otherwise, we'll be dead.
We are thirsty we have to drink. But
for eating disorder patients, they defy
these fundamental needs and the challenging
issue for a psychiatrist is to find out why.
If you don't know why then the
diagnosis is really really ambiguous
and the treatment is virtually impossible.
Before we get into more details let's
review how the brain structure works
and so get us get some foundations.
Our brain consists of about 16 billion neurons
(in cerebral cortex) or probably even more
(in total, about 86 billions). The neurons
interact with each other, connect to
each other through uh synapses. Let's go into
details to understand how it works and then we can
understand how these different visualization tools
and why one is more effective than the other.
We see a neuron on the bottom left the input to
the neuron is a number of dendrites and you can
consider dendrites to be the branches of a tree or
the root branches of a tree, which get nutrition
from the soil. Likewise the dendrites here they
are input ports getting signals, electrical
signals or chemical signals, from their upstream
neurons---can be thousands of neurons. And then
the information eventually converts to electricity
in the soma. Soma is the main body of the neuron
and then the electricity flows through the axon
pipe and reaches eventually to axon terminal.
The synonym of axon terminal is synaptic terminal
and you can consider that as an output port.
On the right hand side we see this how the input
and output works in this synapse. The output
ports, axon terminals, emit either electricity
or chemicals. when the emission is in chemical
then there's a gap between the output ports
and the input dendrites. Here we can ignore
the chemical transmission because eventually
when chemical reaches the other side, the next
neuron, or the downstream neurons, the signals
will be converted to be electrical anyway. So
we can in general thinking about only electrical
information getting passed around between neurons.
Today treatments to mental disorders only
mitigate symptoms not really addressing the causes
because we simply don't know the causes. Suppose
we can collect neuron activities of a disorder.
Then, both precision diagnosis and precision
treatment will be possible. But how can we collect
neuron activities? Given a disease and we need
to have visualization instruments. There have
been two visualization technologies developed for
visualizing neurons. The first one is electrode,
which was developed about a century ago, and
the second one is optogenetics. Electrode
injects current into neurons. There are two major
metrics to measure the effectiveness of electrode
technologies. One dimension is temporal dynamics,
or how long the current can be applied to neurons;
the second one is the spatial resolution, or how
many neurons will be covered by this stimulation.
Of course we would like to have fine grained
control or fine grained stimulation. Therefore,
they call this resolution or the spot size should
be as small as possible. And unfortunately,
according to the survey of Hong and Lieber
done in 2019, although the spot size can be
further reduced, and this is really similar
to the Moore's law on the speedup of CPU,
the reduction of spatial resolution can
also be further achieved by about 10%
every year. But the sensitivity of the neuron
to electricity can be an issue. The duration
of electricity exposure cannot be too long. For
monitoring a mental disease, typically we need
to cover the patient for days or even weeks.
Therefore, maybe using light is less invasive.
Indeed using light not only we can
have better resolution and we can have
longer temporal coverage. Also, light can
reach deeper neurons without much trouble.
This optogenetics technology was developed by
Karl Deisseroth in early 2000s, and later MIT
professor Ed Boyden also joins the effort. The
basic technology is the following. First of all,
it was motivated by the fact there are certain
bacterias swimming under water and they would
swim toward light,. Once light can shine on the
bacterias, the light turns into electricity,
and the bacteria gains their energy. The same
idea if we can apply (plant) this kind of
photosynthetic photo-sensory
molecules' DNA into the neurons,
then potentially we can shine light on a neuron
and the the neuron would be (kind of) triggered,
or the neuron would generate electricity
and pass to the downstream neurons.
The light can then be used to turn on and turn
off these neurons. There can be some remarkable
resolutions done. The first one is that we can
target individual neurons, the second one is
we can target different types of neurons by doing
gene therapy. Of course there are limitations,
which we will cover in the end of
the lecture. There have been some
promises: there are several animal trials going
on and the two clinical trials already ongoing:
one for blindness treatment the other one for
retna degeneration treatment. The following is
a short video instructed by Boyden on this
optogenetics technology. Let's take a listen.
Brain is made of maybe thousands
of different kinds of cells called
neurons that are built into very dense
international networks that communicate
each of these neurons compute to use electricity
this cycle implements behavior and thought and
emotion all these different kinds of things we
also think that deficits and these electrical
computations underline many brain disorders that
affect over a billion people around the world
in optogenetics what we're doing is repeating
molecules that convert light and electricity
into neurons to cells of the brain
they're only sharing a bite on those
neurons light gets converted to electricity
and allows us to turn on or off those cells
the goal here is to find a way to control the
electrical activity in some cells and not others
network to do that we had to turn to the natural
world it turns out that dropping all the kingdoms
of life in plants and funguses and bacteria and
so on you can find photosynthetic or photo-sensory
molecules that convert light and electricity so
we borrow these molecules from nature and using
tricks from the field of gene therapy we can
put them into neurons now these molecules can
convert light to electricity and they do it
just in the neurons that we want to control
and not all their neighbors so we can deliver
these molecules to some cells throughout others
and then we shine light on the network we
can turn on or off that subset of the cells
if we can turn on or off the set of cells
that's embedded within this sense matrix
we can figure out how do they contribute to a
behavior for example if we can turn on a set of
cells we can figure out what kinds of behaviors
can it initiate if we can turn off the set of
cells then we can delete it momentarily and
figure what is necessary for so by being able
to dial in information in the cells in the brain
and to delete them we can try to figure out how
they contribute to networks and the behaviors
and diseases that arise from brain computations
we can cut down the exact set of cells that
are contributing to a specific disease state
or which when activated or shut down will remedy
that disease state that's very important because
right now a lot of drugs are developed that target
molecules but molecules are found throughout
the brain and in fact many cells in their brain
might be very molecularly similar to one another
if we can target circuits in the brain though we
might be able to develop much more specific drugs
imagine if we could hunt down the exact set of
cells in the brain that would activate a remedy
of brain disorder and then we can go in and look
at the exact molecules of those cells maybe we can
find drug targets that are much more specific
than existing ones you might also imagine that
we can use option genetics to directly control
brain circuits in patients with brain disorders
electricity is used to stimulate the brain
and deep brain stimulation if instead we can
actually aim light at certain cells and turn
them on or off we might be much more specific
rather than use electricity to turn on and
off the cells of the brain and have many
kinds of cells activated you know the ones we
want to affect as well as all their neighbors
if we can make just one disease-associated
subset associated with light
and we can turn them on or off and be able
to treat them with much more specificity...
Once we have collected massive amount of training
data, which consists of neural activities and
also the target diseases, we can turn
this data into a classification problem.
The training data has X and Y.
An x (in X) instance consists of
neurons, their locations and their
activities, temporal and spatial, and y
is the dependent disorders. Given a lot of
data then we can train a function f and then
remarkable things can be performed. The first part
is diagnosis. Given a set of unseen data X, we can
say well what is the disease of this patient. And
also of a non-disease (normal person), we see a
certain pattern. We then know precisely which
neurons need to be turned off. This could be
a much more precise treatment procedure
developed for mitigating mental disorders.
I have used the term disorder several times.
When we say disorder means something is not
normal. When we claim some behavior is abnormal,
we have to have a standard showing normality.
The disorder can happen biologically or morally.
A moral disorder could imply non-ethical
or illegal behaviors. Here we don't
talk about morality until the next
lecture (lecture #17). We focus on biological
disorders. According to renowned biologists,
when we talk about a biological disorder,
we have to talk in the evolutionary terms.
And accordingly, for example, the quote from Peter
Medawar (upper-left). He said "for a biologist
the alternative to thinking in
evolution terms is not to think at all."
Thus, let's revisit the term evolution. I
think we heard about this term before.
Some of us may have some misunderstanding.
Now, about evolution as related to genomics.
evolution refers to the process by which living
organisms change over time through changes in
the genome. Such evolutionary changes result
from mutations that produce genomic variation
giving rise to individuals whose biological
functions or physical traits are altered.
The part that causes confusion is
mutations. The question is: first
is a mutation a random process or a mutation
has a mission to adapt to the environment.
in other words is mutation a process of
passiveness? or mutation actively tries
to adapt an individual's biological functions and
physical traits to fit the changing environment?
The fact is that the mutation itself is purely
random. It is independent of the environment.
Individuals that are better adapted
tend to survive and produce more
offspring, while the less well adapted
tend to die or produce fewer offspring.
Let's use an example to illustrate the random
process of mutation. Hundreds years ago a brown
hill at the new Mexico state. The mice over
there, their color was in light brown. About
100 years ago a volcano eruption happened over
there, and the dark lava covered the land. Within
about 30 years almost all mice turn their color
into dark, the same color as the color of lava.
Do you consider the mutation is targeted to be
darker color so therefore the new generation can
survive better? The answer is not really. Mutation
is purely random. One of, say, 100 by chance would
turn into dark and the rest will be probably other
colors, or may tend to (remain to) be light brown.
And because the background of the hill becomes
dark, dark mice cannot be seen by the predators,
by the eagles, so they can survive
much better. According to statistics,
if the survival of dark mice is just
ten percent better than the brown mice.
Just after about 20 years, all the mice on the
hill would turn into the dark color. This is the
power of just purely random mutation, and
the selection is done by the environment.
Mutation has no intelligence to target
the mutation to fit the environment.
Now we have the evolution under our belt, we
can come back to talk in biological terms.
Evolution teaches us the fittest survives, and
it's a nature law that survival of a species
requires survival of the current
generation and the reproduction
of the future generations. For survival we
ask ourselves is hunger a normal sensation?
Is eating a normal response to hunger? If
we want to survive, then defying eating is
not a normal behavior. Therefore, defying
eating, eating disorder is not a normal behavior.
Using evolution to judge whether
biologically defying hunger is normal
or abnormal makes a lot of sense. Why do we use
eating disorder as an example to study neural
visualization? It's because eating disorder
is  probably the most sophisticated disorder,
and also it's the most deadly and costly. There
are about nine percent of the world population
suffering from some forms of eating disorder.
As the next step, we would like to
visualize which part of the brain manages
hunger, and after we have this hunger
sensation appears on our consciousness,
which part of our brain, which set
of neurons, defies hunger? If we can
locate the neurons defying hunger, maybe
we can find treatments by turning them off.
In the middle of our brain there's a structure
called Hypothalamus, which manages our survival
functions. If you look at the picture on the
screen it's an orange structure buried in the
middle. The functions it manages include releasing
hormones, maintaining our daily physiological
cycles, and controlling our appetite including
thirst hunger, and also managing our sleep.
Hypothalamus also manages our sexual behavior,
emotional responses, and body temperature.
Again all these are basic survival
functions (our biological needs)
and with optogenetics we can successfully
identify the neurons in this region, which
manages each of these functions.
So precisely for eating disorder,
we can identify the neurons which manages
appetite and neuroscientists already show that
they can successfully turn on or off the mice
neurons for hunger. But here turning on or off
the neurons for managing appetite is not helpful
for curing eating disorder because if we turn
hunger off, just getting the situation worse. And
keeping the hunger sensation up, the person is not
going to eat anyway. Let's visit these competing
forces that cause eating disorder. First of all,
Hypothalamus, which manages appetite broadcasts
the hunger sensation to all the neurons.
It's a conscious decision for the individual
to defy the eating needs because of
his/her value system---for the sake of
beauty, the person insists in not eating.
Only the person with strong will
would persist this defiance.
And in time this defiance is able to collect
or recruit sufficient armies in other areas
of the brain to join this resistance.
We call this army as the "second self."
The second self competes with the first self,
constantly fighting for eating or not eating.
Let us now making some observations. First
of all a patient with eating disorder
was first convinced of that losing
weight is positive and rewarding;
then the person turns defying hunger
into a mission and a challenge,
and neurons are then recruited to tackle these
challenges. There's a strong correlation
between a top performer at school or at work
with a person suffering from eating disorder,
because both top performer and eating disorder
patient, they are goal oriented, they are
strong-willed, they can formulate plans,
and they can persist to tackle the
challenge. Through neuron visualization,
we (Deisseroth's team) have two findings.
The first finding is: although the structure of
hypothalamus manages the hunger sensation and it
broadcasts the hunger signal to all the neurons.
the neurons that participate in defying
hunger is only a small minority.
If we can somehow turn off these resistant
neurons, we can perhaps cure eating disorder.
And also for other mental conditions,
like the stress regulating brain area
becomes larger in patients of depression
and the bipolar. We may be able to
manipulate the neurons responsible for
stress regulation to mitigate the illness.
Now we understand mental disorders
much better, and we appreciate
these visualization tools, which can let
us identify each neuron's functionality
either positive or negative with respect to their
biological function. And next we come back to our
central mission: where is consciousness?
the question we impose in the middle.
Fortunately through visualization,
neuroscientists already
are able to roughly identify the brain
regions that manage our consciousness.
The method of visualization is the following.
First, we can assume the area manages
consciousness can be constantly busy
and can be task independently busy.
And secondly, if a person is put
into a meditation state---thinking
nothing and be very calm. If still there's an area
of neurons being active, then that particular area
may be the managing neurons and they could
possibly be the region's managing consciousness.
Neuroscientists have already identified two areas
in the brain where consciousness are managed
or you can say consciousness resides. The first
area is in this blue rectangle area which is our
Prefrontal cortex, and the second area is
in the red circle its name is Retrosplenial
cortex. These two cortexes work in concert to
manage our consciousness. The scientists right now
continue conducting experiments on lab animals to
see turning on or off neurons in these two areas,
what would be the effect to the animal
behaviors. Now, we have located consciousness,
and we would like to probe further questions.
The first question is "is consciousness
computational only?" There was a debate between
Roger Penrose and Yoshua Bengio  (via me).
Yoshua considers that consciousness should be
computation all the way, and Penrose agrees that
our cerebellum, which manages unconsciousness,
is computational only; but he disagrees that our
consciousness is merely computational. My question
is if it's not a computational, then what is it?
We could conduct further visualization
to see the neuron patterns in these two
areas (prefrontal and retrosplenial cortexes).
For computational activities, there could
be one (or some) unique neuron activity
patterns. If the consciousness area also
exhibits the same pattern, then yes we can
consider consciousness is only computational.
But if there are other patterns emerge,
then there is a possibility that there
are other activities going on.
We can then conduct further investigation.
For optogenetics this technology is not
without challenges. Before we can widely
use the technology to be a therapeutic
tool, we need to tackle a list of
obstacles listed on the slide. I'm
not going to get into details and
if you conduct research in the area
you can look into the problems and
potential solutions. Finally i'd like to challenge
you guys with discussion question number two.
We know evolution involves in satisfying
our fundamental needs, otherwise a species
would extinct. For wants and we consider
those are optional---those are luxuries.
To preserve a species requires satisfying
the needs managed by hypothalamus including
maintaining organ operations,
maintaining our body temperature,
balancing body hormones, managing
eating, drinking, rest, and sleep.
My question is "how about the
wants?" All wants should be optional.
"Is crying a need or crying a want?" We know
subjective values like having good grades
should be a want. If we all have poor grades,
human species can still survive. But crying is an
interesting trait. From the theory of evolution,
crying does not help us to survive.
But why crying is a common trait.
One hint is the notion of evolution bottleneck,
which was explained by Deisseroth as follows.
About 70,000 years ago there was a major volcano
eruption occurred on earth, and that eruption
caused not only earthquake tsunami but also much
ash dust and vapor in the air covered the sun
for six years and also disrupted the seasonal
rain. So lots of people vanished during the
disaster. The earth suffered from a huge reduction
in population. You could consider this is a
biased sampling process. In the extreme case
let's think about this Noah Ark. Noah just
selected a pair of animals for all the species
and the pair got selected is a minority sample
of the original species population and this
sampling is highly unrepresentative so suppose
you pick a pair which happened to have the trait
of crying, and crying was not the popular traits
of the particular species. Then we (human)
get into this so-called founder's effect.
This may be the reason we have some traits right
now which are not really equipped for survival.
They are with us because of
this biased selection process.
The slide shows a biased sampling
example. The population with a lot of
white dots representing people without disease.
But with the small samples (right-hand side)
maybe the selected instances all suffer from
disorders. So, when we today talking about
some people may have disorders and ourselves may
be normal and we have to be quite careful because
the truth may be the opposite. This kind of
"founder effect" should make us more humble....
And further reading I include two very good
books. One is again Deisseroth's Projections
and Roger Penrose's Emperor's New Mind.
Roger's book depicts his vision about what
is consciousness and where is consciousness.
In the next lecture dr duvvuri will come back
to continue the coverage of psychiatry topics.
The final lecture of the series i will cover
ethics, love, and mind. My attempt is to quantify
these three elements so therefore when we build
a robot we can build a robot with good ethics,
loving, and rich mind. Thank you for attending
today's lecture. Hopefully your project
is in good progress, and i see you on Wednesday.