OK.
Hi, everyone.
So we'll get
started again, we're
now into week seven of CS224N.
If you're following along
the syllabus really closely,
we actually did a little bit
of a rearrangement of classes.
And so today it's
me, and I'm going
to talk about coreference
resolution, which
is another chance we get to
take a deeper dive into a more
linguistic topic.
That will also show you a couple
of new things for deep learning
models at the same time.
And then the lecture
that had previously
been scheduled at
this point, which
was going to be John on
explanation in neural models,
is being shifted later down
into week 9, I think it is.
But you'll still get him later.
Before getting underway, just
a couple of announcements
on things.
Well first of all,
congratulations
on surviving
assignment five I hope,
I know it was a bit of a
challenge for some of you,
but I hope it was a rewarding
state of the art learning
experience on the
latest in neural nets.
And in any rate, this was
a brand new assignment
that we used for the
first time this year.
So we'll really
appreciate later on when
we do the second survey,
getting your feedback on that.
We've been busy reading people's
final project proposals,
thanks.
Lots of interesting stuff there.
Our goal is to get them
back to you tomorrow.
But as soon as you've had a good
night's sleep after assignment
5, now is also a great
time to get started
working on your final
projects, because there's
just not that much time
till the end of quarter.
And I particularly want
to encourage all of you
to chat to your mentor
regularly, go and visit
office hours and keep in
touch, get advice, just
talking through things is a
good way to keep you on track.
We also plan to be getting
back assignment 4 grades
later this week.
There's sort of, the work
never stops at this point.
So the next thing for
the final project,
is the final project milestone.
So that we handed out the
details of that last Friday,
and it's due a week from today.
So the idea of this
final project milestone
is really to help
keep you on track,
and keep things
moving towards having
a successful final project.
So our hope is that
sort of most of what
you write for the final project
milestone is material you can
also include in
your final project,
except for a few
paragraphs of here's
exactly where I'm up to now.
So the overall hope is that
doing this in two parts
and having a milestone
before the final thing,
it's just making you
make progress and be
on track for having a
successful final project.
Finally, the next
class on Thursday
is going to be Colin
Raffel, and this
is going to be super exciting.
So he's going to be
talking more about the very
latest in large pre-trained
language models, both
what some of their
successes are and also what
some of the
disconcerting, not quite
so good aspects, of
those models are.
So that should be a really
good interesting lecture, when
we had him come and
talk to our NLP seminar,
we had several hundred
people come along for that.
And so for this
talk again, we're
asking that you write a
reaction paragraph following
the same instructions as
last time about what's
in this lecture.
And someone asked
in the questions,
well what about last Thursday's?
The answer to that is no.
So the distinction here is,
we're only doing the reaction
paragraphs for outside
guest speakers,
and although it
was great to have
Antoine Bosselut for
last Thursday's lecture,
he's a postdoc at Stanford.
So we don't count him as
an outside guest speaker,
and so nothing needs to
be done for that one.
So there are three classes
for which you need to do it.
So there was the one before,
from Danqi Chen, Colin Raffel
which is Thursday, and then
towards the end of the course
there's Yulia Tsvetkov.
OK.
So this is the plan today,
so in the first part of it
I'm actually going to
spend a bit of time talking
about what coreference is.
What different kinds of
reference in language are.
And then I'm going to move
on and talk about some
of the kind of methods that
people have used for solving
coreference resolution.
Now there's one bug in
our course design, which
was a lot of years we've
had a whole lecture on doing
convolutional neural nets
for language applications.
And that slight bug
appeared the other day
when Danqi talked
about the I to F model,
because she sort of slipped
in oh, there's a character CNN
representation of words, and we
hadn't actually covered that.
And so that was a
slight oopsie, I
mean actually for
applications and coreference
as well people commonly make
use of character level ConvNets.
So I wanted to sort
of spend a few minutes
sort of doing basics of
ConvNets for language.
The sort of reality here
is that, given that there's
no exam week this
year, to give people
more time for final projects,
we sort of shortened the content
by a week this year, and so
you're getting a little bit
less of that content.
Then going on from
there, say some stuff
about the state of the art
neural coreference system,
and right at the end, talk
about how coref is evaluated
and what some of
the results are.
Yeah, so first of all, what is
this conference resolution term
that I've been
talking about a lot.
So coreference
resolution is meaning
to find all the mentions
in a piece of text that
refer to the same entity.
And so that's a typo.
It should be in the
world not in the word.
So let's make this
concrete, so here's
part of a short story by
Shruthi Rao called The Star.
Now I have to make
a confession here,
because this is an NLP class,
not a literature class,
I crudely made some
cuts to the story
to be able to have relevant
parts appear on my slide,
in a decent sized font for
illustrating coreference.
So it's not quite the
full original text,
but it basically is a
piece of this story.
Right, so what we do in
coreference resolution is,
we're working out what
people are mentioned, OK.
So here's a mention
of a person, Vanaja,
and here's a mention of
another person, Akhila.
And well, mentions don't
have to be people, right,
so the local park,
that's also a mention.
And then here's Akhila
again, and Akhila's son,
and then there's
Prajwal, then there's
another son here, and
then her son, and Akash,
and they both went
to the same school.
And then there's
a pre-school play,
and there's Prajwal
again, and then
there's a naughty
child, Lord Krishna.
And there's some that are
a bit complicated like,
the lead role, is
that a mention?
It's sort of more of a
functional specification
of something in the play.
There's Akash, and it's a tree.
I won't go through
the whole thing yet,
but I mean in general,
there are noun phrases
that are mentioning
things in the world.
And so then what we want to
do for coreference resolution
is work out which
of these mentions
are talking about the
same real world entity.
So if we start off,
so there's Vanaja.
And so Vanaja is the
same person as her there,
and then we can read through.
She resigned herself,
so that's both Vanaja.
She bought him a brown T-shirt
and brown trousers, then oops,
then she made a large cutout
tree, she attached, right.
So all of that's about Vanaja.
But then, we can
have another person.
So here's Akhila,
and here's Akhila,
and maybe those are the
only mentions of Akhila.
So then we can go on from there.
OK and so then, there's Prajwal,
but note that Prajwal is also
Akhila's son.
So really Akhila's
son is also Prajwal.
And so an interesting
thing here is
that you can get nested
syntactic structure,
so that we have these
sort of noun phrases.
So that if overall, we have sort
of this noun phrase Akhila's
son Prajwal, which consists of
two noun phrases in apposition,
here's Prajwal.
And then for the noun
phrase Akhila's son,
it sort of breaks down to itself
having an extra possessive noun
phrase in it and then a noun,
so that you have Akhila's, and
then this is son.
So that you have these
multiple noun phrases
and so that you can
then be sort of having
different parts of this be
one person in the coreference
but this noun phrase
here referring
to a different person
in the coreference.
OK so back to Prajwal.
All right, so well, there's
some easy other Prajwals, right,
so it's Prajwal
here, and then you've
got some more
complicated things.
So one of the
complicated cases here
is that, we have they
went to the same school.
So that 'they' there
is what gets referred
to as split antecedents,
because the 'they' refers
to both Prajwal and Akash.
And that's an
interesting phenomenon,
and so I could try and
show that somehow, I
could put some splashes
in or something
and I might get a
different color.
Akash, we have
Akash and her son,
and then this one's sort
of both of them at once.
Right, so human languages
have this phenomenon
of split antecedents,
but one of the things
that you should notice when we
start talking about algorithms
that people use for doing
coreference resolution
is, that they make some
simplified assumptions
as to how they go about
treating the problem.
And one of the simplifications
that most algorithms make
is for any noun phrase
like this pronoun, they,
that's trying to work out
what does it coreference with.
And the answer is one thing, and
so actually most NLP algorithms
for coreference resolution just
cannot get split antecedents
right, any time it occurs in
a text, they guess something,
and they always get it wrong.
So that's the bit of
a sad state of affairs
but that's the
truth of how it is.
OK so then going ahead,
we have Akash here,
and then we have
another tricky one.
So moving on from there,
we then have this 'a tree'
so well in this
context of this story,
Akash is going to be the tree.
So you could feel that it was
OK to say well this tree is also
Akash.
You could also feel that
that's a little bit weird
and not want to do
that, and I mean
actually, different
people's coreference data
sets differ in this.
So really that we're predicating
an identity relationship here
between Akash and the
property of being a tree,
so do we regard the tree as
the same as Akash or not,
and people make different
decisions there.
OK but then going ahead,
we have here's Akash
and she bought him,
so that's Akash.
And then we have Akash
here, and so then we go on.
OK.
So then, if we don't regard
the tree as the same as Akash,
we have a tree here.
But then note that the
next place over here,
where we have a mention of a
tree, the best tree, that's
sort of really a functional
description of possible trees,
making someone the
best tree it's not
really referential to a tree.
And so it seems like that's
not really coreferent.
But if we go on,
there's definitely
more mention of a tree, so when
she has made the tree, truly
the nicest tree, or well I'm not
sure, is that one coreferent?
It is definitely
referring to our tree,
but maybe this one
again is a sort
of a functional description that
isn't referring to the tree.
OK, and so maybe this
one though where's a tree
is referring to the tree.
What I hope to have
illustrated from this,
is most of the time when
we do coreference in NLP
we just make it look sort of
like the conceptual phenomenon
is kind of obvious.
That there's a mention of
Sarah and then it says she,
and you say ah, they're
coreferent, this is easy.
But if you actually start
looking at real text,
especially when you're
looking at something
like this that is a
piece of literature.
The kind of phenomena you get
for coreference and overlapping
reference, and various other
phenomena that I'll talk about,
they actually get
pretty complex.
And there are a
lot of hard cases
that you actually
have to think about as
to what things you think
about as coreferent or not.
OK, but basically we do want
to be able to do something
with coreference because it's
useful for a lot of things
that we'd like to do in
natural language processing.
So for one task that we've
already talked about,
question answering but
equally for other tasks,
such as summarization
information extraction.
If you're doing
something like reading
through a piece of
text, and you've
got a sentence like
'he was born in 1961'
you really want to
know who 'he' refers
to, to know if this is a good
answer to the question of when
was Barack Obama born
or something like that.
It turns out also that it's
useful in machine translation.
So in most languages,
pronouns have
features for gender and
number and in quite a lot
of languages, nouns
and adjectives
also show features of
gender, number and case.
And so when you're
translating a sentence,
you want to be aware
of these features
and what is coreferent
with want to be able to get
the translations correct.
So if you want to be able
to work out a translation
and know whether saying
Alicia likes Juan because he's
smart or Alicia likes
Juan because she's smart,
then you have to be sensitive
to coreference relationships
to be able to choose
the right translation.
When people build
dialogue systems,
dialogue systems also have
issues of coreference a lot
of the time.
So if it's sort of book
tickets to see James Bond,
and the system replies, Spectre
is playing near you at 2.00
and 3.00 today.
Well there's actually
coreference relation, sorry,
there's a reference relation
between Spectre and James Bond
because Spectre is
a James Bond film,
I'll come back to
that one in a minute.
But then it's how many
tickets would you like?
Two tickets for the
showing at 3.00.
That 3 is not just the number
3, that 3 is then a coreference
relationship back to the 3.00
PM showing that was mentioned
by the agent in the
dialogue system.
So again, to
understand these, we
need to be understanding the
coreference relationships.
So how now can you go
about doing coreference?
So the standard
traditional answer
which I will present
first is, coreference
is done in two steps.
On the first step,
what we do is detect
mentions in the piece of
text, and that's actually
a pretty easy problem.
And then in the second
step, we work out
how to cluster the
mentions, so as
in my example from
the Shruthi Rao text,
basically what you're
doing with coreference
is, you're building up these
clusters, sets of mentions that
refer to the same
entity in the world.
So if we explore a
little how we could
do that, it's a 2-step
solution, the first part
was detecting the mentions.
And so pretty much,
there are three kinds
of things, different
kinds of noun phrases
that can be mentions.
There are pronouns like
I, your, it, she, him
and also some demonstrative
pronouns like this and that
and things like that.
There are explicitly
named things,
so things like Paris,
Joe Biden, Nike.
And then there are
plain noun phrases
that describe things, so a
dog, the big fluffy cat stuck
in the tree.
And so all of these
are things that we do
like to identify as mentions.
And the straightforward way
to identify these mentions
is to use natural
language processing
tools, several of which
we've talked about already.
So to work out pronouns,
we can use what's
called a part of speech tagger.
I'll change this twice.
We can use a part
of speech tagger
which we haven't really
explicitly talked about,
but you use when you
build dependency parsers.
So that first of all assigns
parts of speech to each word,
and so that we can just
find the words that
are pronouns For
named entities, we
did talk just a little bit
about named entities recognizers
as a use of sequence
models for neural networks.
So we can pick out things like
person names and company names.
And then for the ones
like a big fluffy dog,
we could then be
sort of picking out
from syntactic
structure, noun phrases
and regarding them as
descriptions of things.
So we could use
all of these tools
and those would give us
basically our mentions,
it's a little bit
more subtle than that.
Because it turns out there are
some noun phrases and things
of all of those kinds
which don't actually refer,
so that they're not
referential in the world.
So when you say 'it is sunny'
it doesn't really refer,
when you make universal claims
like 'every student', well
'every student' isn't referring
to something you can point
to in the world.
And more dramatically when you
have 'no student' and making
a negative universal claim, it's
not referential to anything.
There are also things that you
can describe functionally which
don't have any clear reference.
So if I say 'the best
donut in the world'
that that's a functional claim,
but it doesn't necessarily
have reference.
Like if I've
established that I think
a particular kind of donut is
the best donut in the world,
I could then say to you I ate
the best donut in the world
yesterday, and you know what I
mean, it might have reference.
But if I say something
like, I'm going around
to all the donut stores
trying to find the best
donut in the world, then it
doesn't have any reference yet,
it's just a sort of a
functional description
I'm trying to satisfy.
You also then have
things like quantities,
'100 miles' it's that quantity
that is not really something
that has any
particular reference,
you can mark out 100
miles all sorts of places.
So how do we deal
with those things
that aren't really mentions.
Well one way is, we could train
a machine learning classifier
to get rid of those
spurious mentions,
but actually mostly
people don't do that.
Most commonly if you're using
this kind of pipeline model,
where you use the parser and
the Named Entity Recognizer,
you regard everything that you
found as a candidate mention,
and then you try and
run your coref system.
And some of them,
like those ones,
hopefully aren't made
coreferent with anything else.
And so then you just discard
them at the end of the process.
Hi Chris?
Yeah.
Got an interesting question that
linguists experience on this,
a student asks,
can we say that 'it
is sunny' has its
referent to the weather?
I think that's--
So that's a fair question.
Yeah, so people
have actually tried
to suggest that when
you say 'it is sunny'
it means the weather
is sunny, but I
guess the majority opinion at
least is that isn't plausible.
And I mean for I
guess many of you
aren't native
speakers of English,
but similar phenomena occur
in many other languages.
I mean it just intuitively
doesn't seem plausible
when you say it's sunny
or it's raining today,
that you're really saying that
as a shortcut for the weather
is raining today, it just seems
like really what the case is.
English likes to have something
filling the subject position,
and when there's nothing better
to fill the subject position,
you stick it in there
and get, it's raining.
And so in general,
it's believed that you
get this phenomenon of having
these empty dummy 'it's' that
appear in various places.
I mean another place in which
it seems like you clearly
get dummy 'it's' is that,
when you have clauses that
are subjects of a
verb, you can move them
to the end of the sentence.
So if you have a sentence where
you put a clause in the subject
position, they normally, in
English, sound fairly awkward.
So you have a
sentence, something
like 'that CS224N
is a lot of work
is known by all students'
people don't normally
say that, the normal
thing to do is
to shift the clause to
the end of the sentence.
But when you do that, you
stick in the dummy 'it' to fill
the subject position, so you
then have 'it is known by all
students that CS224N
is a lot of work'.
So that's the general
feeling that this
is a dummy 'it' that
doesn't have any reference.
OK, there's one more
question, so if someone
says it is sunny
among other things,
and we ask how is the weather?
OK good point, you've
got me on that one.
If someone says
'how's the weather'
and you answer 'it
is sunny' it then
does seem like the 'it' is
in reference to the weather.
I'll buy that, well
you know I guess,
this is what our coreference
systems are built trying to do,
in situations like that they're
making a decision if it's
coreference or not.
And I guess, what you'd
want to say in that case is,
it seems reasonable to
regard this one as coreferent
to that weather that
did appear before it.
I mean but that also
indicates another reason
to think that in the normal
case it's not coreferent, right,
because normally
pronouns are only used
when their reference
is established.
That you've referred to a
noun like 'John is answering
questions' and then you can
say, 'he types really quickly'.
And it'd seem odd to just start
the conversation by 'he types
really quickly' because it
doesn't have any established
reference words.
Whereas that doesn't
seem to be the case,
it seems like you can
just start a conversation
by saying 'it's raining
really hard today'
and that doesn't
sound odd at all.
OK so I've presented
the traditional picture,
but this traditional
picture doesn't
mean something that was done
last millennium before you
were born.
I mean, essentially that was
the picture until about 2016.
That essentially every
coreference system
that was built used tools like
part of speech taggers, NER
systems and parsers
to analyze sentences,
to identify mentions,
and to give you
features to
coreference resolution,
and I'll show a bit
more about that later.
But more recently in
our neural systems,
people have moved to avoiding
traditional pipeline systems,
and are doing one shot end
to end coreference resolution
systems.
So if I skip directly
to the second bullet,
there's a new generation
of neural systems
where you just start with
your sequence of words,
and you do the
maximally dumb thing.
You just say let's
take all spans commonly
with some heuristics
for efficiency,
but conceptually all
subsequences of this sentence,
they might be mentions.
Let's feed them in to
a neural network which
will simultaneously
do mention detection
and coreference resolution
end to end in one model.
And I'll give an example
of that kind of system
later in the lecture.
OK is everything good to
there and I should go on?
OK.
So I'm going to get on to how
to do conference resolution
systems, but before I
do that, I do actually
want to show a little bit
more of the linguistics
of coreference.
Because there are actually a
few more interesting things
to understand and
know here, I mean
when we say coreference
resolution, we really
confuse together two
linguistic things which
are overlapping, but different.
And so it's really actually good
to understand the difference
between these things.
So there are two
things that can happen.
One is that you
can have mentions
which are essentially
standalone,
but happen to refer to the
same entity in the world.
So if I have a
piece of text that
said Barack Obama traveled
yesterday to Nebraska,
Obama was there to open
a new meat processing
plant or something like that.
I've mentioned with
Barack Obama and Obama,
there are two mentions there.
They refer to the same person in
the world, they are coreferent.
So that is true coreference.
But there's a different but
related linguistic concept
called anaphora.
And anaphora is when you
have a textual dependence
of an anaphor on another
term which is the antecedent.
And in this case, the
meaning of the anaphor
is determined by the antecedent
in a textual context.
And the canonical case
of this is pronouns.
So when it's, Barack Obama
said he would sign the bill,
'he' is an anaphor,
it's not a word
that independently
we can work out
what its meaning is in the world
apart from knowing the vaguest
feature that it's referring
to something probably male.
But in the context
of this text, we
have that this anaphor is
textually dependent on Barack
Obama, and so then we have
an anaphoric relationship,
which sort of means they refer
to the same thing in the world.
And so therefore you can
say they are coreferent.
So the picture we have
is like this, right.
So for coreference, we
have these separate textual
mentions, which are
basically standalone,
which refer to the same
thing in the world.
Whereas, in anaphora we actually
have a textual relationship.
And you essentially have
to use pronouns like he
and she in legitimate ways,
in which the hearer can
reconstruct the
relationship from the text,
because they can't
work out what 'he'
refers to if that's not there.
And so, that's a fair
bit of the distinction,
but it's actually
a little bit more
to realize because there are
more complex forms of anaphora
which aren't coreferents.
Because you have a
textual dependence,
but it's not actually
one of reference.
And so this comes back to things
like these quantifier noun
phrases, that don't
have reference.
So when you have
sentences like these ones,
every dancer twisted
her knee, well
this 'her' here has an anaphoric
dependency on every dancer.
Or even more clearly
with, no dancer
twisted her knee, the 'her'
here has an anaphoric dependence
on no dancer.
But for, no dancer
twisted her knee,
'no dancer' isn't
referential, it's
not referring to
anything in the world.
And so there's no
coreferential relationship
because there's no
reference relationship.
But there's still an
anaphoric relationship
between these two noun phrases.
And then you have this
other complex case
that turns up quite
a bit, where you
can have for the things being
talked about do have reference,
but an anaphoric relationship
is more subtle than identity.
So you commonly get
constructions like this one,
we went to a concert
last night, the tickets
were really expensive, well
the concert and the tickets
are two different things,
they're not coreferential.
But in interpreting this
sentence, what this really
means is the tickets
to the concert right,
and so there's sort of
this hidden, not said,
dependence where this is
referring back to the concert.
And so what we say is
that the tickets does
have an anaphoric
dependence on the concert,
but they're not coreferential.
And so that's referred
to as bridging anaphora.
And so overall, there's the
simple case and the common case
which is pronominal
anaphora, where it's
both coreference and anaphora.
You then have other
cases of coreference
such as every time you see a
mention of the-- every time
the United States has said it's
coreferential with every other
mention of the United States.
But those don't have any textual
dependence on each other.
And then you have
textual dependencies
like bridging anaphora,
which aren't coreference.
Phew, that's probably about as--
I was going to say that's
probably as much linguistics
as you wanted to
hear, but actually I
have one more point
of linguistics.
One or two of you,
but probably not many,
might have been
troubled by the fact
that the term anaphora
as a classical term
means that you are looking
backward for your antecedent.
That the 'ana' part
of anaphora means
that you're looking backward
for your antecedent,
and in sort of
classical terminology
you have both anaphora
and cataphora.
And it's cataphora
where you look forward
for your antecedent.
Cataphora isn't that
common, but it does occur.
Here's a beautiful
example of cataphora,
so this is from Oscar Wilde.
"From the corner of the
divan of Persian saddlebags
on which he was lying,
smoking, as was his custom,
innumerable cigarettes,
Lord Henry Wotton
could just catch the
gleam of the honey-sweet
and honey-colored
blossoms of a laburnum."
OK so in this
example here, right,
that 'he' and then
this 'his' actually
referring to Lord Henry Wotton.
And so these are both
examples of cataphora.
But in modern linguistics
even though most reference to
pronouns is backwards,
we don't distinguish on
in terms of order.
And so the term
anaphor in anaphora
is used for textual dependence
regardless of whether it's
forward or backwards.
OK.
A lot of details
there, but taking
stock of this, so the basic
observation is language
is interpreted in context.
That in general you can't work
out the meaning or reference
of things without
looking at the context
of the linguistic utterance.
So we've seen some
simple examples before,
so for something like
word-sense disambiguation.
So if you see just
the words, 'the bank'
you don't know what
it means, and you
need to look at a context to
get some sense as to whether it
means a financial institution,
or the bank of a river,
or something like that.
And so anaphora and coreference
give us additional examples
where you need to be doing
contextual interpretation
of language.
So when you see a
pronoun, you need
to be looking at the context
to see what it refers to.
And so if you think
about text understanding
as a human being does it,
reading a story or an article,
that we progress through the
article from beginning to end,
and as we do it we build up a
pretty complex discourse model
in which new entities are
introduced by mentions,
and then they're
referred back to
and relationships between
them are established
and they take actions
and things like that.
And it sort of seems
like in our head
that we sort of build up a
complex graph-like discourse
representation of
a piece of text
with all these relationships.
And so part of that is these
anaphoric relationships
and coreference that
we're talking about here.
And indeed in terms of
CS224N, the only kind
of whole discourse meaning
that we're going to look at
is, looking a bit at
anaphora and coreference.
but if you want to
see more about higher
level, natural
language understanding,
you can get more of this
next quarter in CS224U.
So I want to tell you a bit
about several different ways
of doing coreference.
So broadly, there are
four different kinds
of coreference models.
So the traditional
old way of doing it
was, rule-based systems.
And this isn't the
topic of this class,
and this is pretty
archaic at this point,
this is stuff from
last millennium.
But I wanted to say a
little bit about it,
because it's actually
interesting, a food for thought
as to how far along
we are and in solving
artificial
intelligence and really
being able to understand texts.
Then there is sort of classic
machine learning methods
of doing it, which you
can sort of divide up as,
mention pair methods,
mention ranking methods,
and really clustering methods.
And I'm going to sort of skip
the clustering methods today,
because most of the
work, especially
most of the recent work,
implicitly makes clusters
by using either mention pair
or mention ranking methods.
And so I'm going to talk about
a couple of neural methods
for doing that.
OK but first of all,
let me just tell you
a little bit about
rule-based coreference.
So there's a famous
historical algorithm
in NLP for doing pronoun
anaphora resolution, which
is referred to as
the Hobbs algorithm.
So everyone just refers to
it as the Hobbs algorithm,
and if you look up a
textbook like Jurafsky
and Martin's textbook,
it's referred to
as the Hobbs algorithm.
But actually, if you go
back to Jerry Hobbs, that's
his picture over
there in the corner,
if you actually go back
to his original paper,
he refers to it as
the naive algorithm.
And then this naive algorithm
for pronoun coreference,
was this sort of intricate
handwritten set of rules
to work out coreference.
So this is the start of
the set of the rules,
but there are more rules, or
more clauses of these rules
for working out coreference.
And this looks like a hot
mess, but the funny thing
was, that this set of rules
for determining coreference
were actually pretty good.
And so in the sort of 1990s
and 2000s decade, even
when people were using
machine learning based systems
for doing coreference,
they'd hide
into those machine
learning based
systems, that one
of their features
was the Hobbs' algorithm.
And that the predictions it
made with a certain weight,
was then a feature in
making your final decisions.
And it's only really
in the last five years
that people have moved away
from using the Hobbs algorithm.
Let me give you a little bit
of a sense of how it works, OK.
So from the Hobbs algorithm,
here's is our example.
This is an example from
a Guardian book review,
Niall Ferguson is prolific,
well-paid and a snappy dresser,
Stephen Moss hated him.
OK.
So what the Hobbs algorithm does
is, we start with the pronouns,
we start with the
pronoun, and then it
says step one, go to the
NP that's immediately
dominating the pronoun.
And then it says go up
to the first NP or S,
call this X, and
the path P. Then
it says traverse all
branches below X,
to the left of P,
left-to-right breadth first.
So then it's saying to go left
to right for other branches
below breadth first, so that's
sort of working down the tree,
so we're going down and left
to right, and look for an NP.
OK, and here is an NP, but then
we have to read more carefully
and say, propose as
antecedent any NP
that has an NP or S
between it and X. Well
this NP here has no NP
or S between NP and X.
So this isn't a
possible antecedent.
So this is all very
complex and handwritten,
but basically he sort
of fit into the clauses
of this kind of a lot
of facts about how
the grammar of English works.
And so what this
is capturing is,
if you imagine a
different sentence,
if you imagine the sentence,
Stephen Moss's brother
hated him, well then
Stephen Moss would naturally
be coreferent with him.
And in that case, well
precisely what you'd have is,
the noun phrase with
the noun brother,
and you'd have another
noun phrase inside it
for the Steven
Moss, and then that
would go up to the sentence.
So in the case of
Steven Moss's brother,
when you looked at
this noun phrase,
there would be an
intervening noun phrase
before you got to the
node X. And therefore,
Steven Moss is a possible,
and in fact good,
antecedent of him,
and the algorithm
would choose Steven Moss.
But the algorithm correctly
captures that when you have
the sentence, Steven
Moss hated him,
that 'him' cannot
refer to Steven Moss.
OK, so having worked
that out, it then
says if X is the highest
S in the sentence,
OK, so my X here is definitely
the highest S in the sentence,
because I wrote
the whole sentence.
What you should do
is then traverse
the parse trees of
previous sentences
in the order of recency.
So what I should do
now is, work backwards
in the text, one
sentence at a time,
going backwards looking
for an antecedent.
And then for each tree,
traverse each tree
left to right, breadth first.
So then within each
tree, I'm doing
the same of going breadth first,
so working down and then going
left to right with
an equal breadth.
And so hidden inside
these clauses,
it's capturing a lot
of the facts of how
coreference typically works.
So what you find in
English I'll say,
but in general, this is true
of lots of languages is,
that there are
general preferences
and tendencies for coreference.
So a lot of the
time, a pronoun will
be coreferent with something
in the same sentence
like, Stephen Moss's
brother hated him,
but it can't be if
it's too close to it.
So you can't say, Stephen Moss
hated him, and have the 'him'
be Stephen Moss.
And if you're then looking
for coreference that's further
away, the thing it's coreferent
with is normally close by,
and so that's why you work
backwards through sentences one
by one.
But then once you're looking
within a particular sentence,
the most likely thing it's
going to be coreferent to is,
a topical noun phrase, and
default topics in English
are subjects.
So by doing things breadth
first left-to-right,
a preferred antecedent
is then a subject.
And so this algorithm I won't go
through all the complex clauses
5 through 9, ends up saying,
OK, what you should do
is propose Niall
Ferguson as what
is coreferent to him, which
is the obvious correct reading
in this example.
OK, phew.
We probably didn't want to
know that, and in some sense
the details of that
aren't interesting.
But what is I think, actually
still interesting in 2021 is,
what point Jerry
Hobbs was actually
trying to make last millennium.
And the point he
was trying to make
was the following,
so Jerry Hobbs
wrote this algorithm, the naive
algorithm, because what he said
was, well look if you want
to try and crudely determine
coreference, well there are
these various preferences,
right.
There's the preference
for same sentence,
there's the preference
for recency,
there's a preference for
topical things like subject,
and there are things
where if it has gender,
it has to agree in gender.
So there are sort of strong
constraints of that sort.
So I can write an algorithm
using my linguisticness, which
captures all the
main preferences,
and actually it
works pretty well.
Doing that is a pretty
strong baseline system.
But what Jerry Hobbs
wanted to argue
is that this algorithm
just isn't something
you should believe in.
This isn't a solution
to the problem,
this is just sort of making
a best guess according
to the preferences of what's
most likely without actually
understanding what's going
on in the text at all.
And so actually what Jerry
Hobbs wanted to argue
was the so-called
Hobbs' algorithm now.
He wasn't a fan of
the Hobbs algorithm,
he was wanting to
argue that the Hobbs
algorithm is completely
inadequate as a solution
to the problem.
And the only way we'll
actually make progress
in natural language
understanding,
is by building systems that
actually really understand
the text.
And this is actually something
that has come to the fore
again more recently.
So the suggestion is
that in general you
can't work out coreference
or pronominal anaphora
in particular, unless
you're really understanding
the meaning of the text.
And people look at pairs of
examples like these ones,
so she poured water from
the pitcher into the cup
until it was full, so think
for just half a moment.
Well, what is it in that example
that is full, so what's full
there is the cup.
But then if I say, she
poured water from the pitcher
into the cup until it was
empty, well what's empty,
well that's the pitcher.
And the point that is being
made with these examples is
the only thing that's been
changed in these examples
is the adjective right here.
So these two
examples have exactly
the same grammatical structure.
So in terms of the
Hobbs naive algorithm,
the Hobbs naive
algorithm necessarily
has to predict the same
answer for both of these,
but that's wrong.
You just cannot determine the
correct pronoun antecedent
based on grammatical preferences
of the kind that are used
in the naive algorithm, you
actually have to conceptually
understand about pitchers,
and cups, and water, and full,
and empty to be able to
choose the right antecedent.
Here's another famous example
that goes along the same lines,
so Terry Winograd shown
here as a young man.
So long, long ago Terry
Winograd came to Stanford
as the natural language
processing faculty.
And Terry Winograd
became disillusioned
with the symbolic
AI of those days,
and just gave it up altogether.
And he reinvented himself
as being an HCI person,
and so Terry was
then essentially
the person who established
the HCI program at Stanford.
But before he lost
faith in symbolic AI,
he talked about the
coreference problem
and pointed out a similar
pair of examples here.
So we have, the city
council refused the women
a permit because
they feared violence,
versus the city council
refused the women
a permit because they
advocated violence.
So again, you have this
situation where these two
sentences have identical
syntactic structure
and they differ only in
the choice of verb here.
But once you add
commonsense knowledge
of how the human
world works, well,
how this would pretty
obviously be interpreted that
in the first one that 'they' is
referring to the city council,
whereas in the second
one that 'they'
is referring to the women.
And so coming off of
that example of Terry,
these have been referred
to as Winograd schemas.
So a Winograd schema challenge
is choosing the right reference
here, and so it's basically
just doing pronominal anaphora.
But the interesting
thing is, people
have been interested in what are
tests of general intelligence,
and one famous general test of
intelligence that I won't talk
about now is the Turing test.
And there's been a lot of debate
about problems with the Turing
test and is it good?
And some particular
Hector Levesque
is a very well-known
senior AI person.
He actually proposed
that a better alternative
to the Turing test might
be to do what he then
dubbed Winograd schema.
And Winograd schema is just
solving pronominal coreference
in cases like these where
you have to have knowledge
about the situation in the
world to get the answer right,
and so he's basically
arguing that you can review
really solving
coreference and solving
artificial intelligence.
And that's the position that
Hobbs wanted to advocate,
so what he actually said
about his algorithm was
that "the naive approach is
quite good, computationally
speaking, it will be a long
time before a semantically based
algorithm is sophisticated
enough to perform as well.
And these results set
a very high standard
for any other
approach to aim for".
And he was proven
right about that,
because there was sort of
really talk to around 2015
before people thought they could
do without the Hobbs algorithm.
But then he notes, "yet
there is every reason
to pursue a semantically
based approach,
the naive algorithm
does not work.
Anyone can think of
examples where it fails.
In these cases,
it not only fails,
it gives no indication
that it has failed,
and offers no help in
finding the real antecedent".
And so I think this is actually
still interesting stuff
to think about, because
really for the kind of machine
learning based coreference
systems that we're building,
they're not a hot mess of
rules like the Hobbs algorithm.
But basically,
they're still sort
of working out statistical
preferences of what
patterns are most likely,
and choosing the antecedent.
That way, they really have
exactly the same deficiencies
still what Hobbs was
talking about, right.
That they fail in
various cases, it's
easy to find places
where they fail,
the algorithms give you
no idea of when they fail,
they're not really
understanding the text in a way
that a human does to
determine the antecedent.
So we still actually have
a lot more work to do,
before we're really doing
full artificial intelligence.
But I'd best get
on now and actually
tell you a bit about some
coreference algorithms, right.
So the simple way of
thinking about coreference,
is to say that you're making
just a binary decision
about a reference pair.
So if you have your
mentions, you can then say,
well I've come to
my next mention
'she' I want to work out
what it's coreferent with.
And I can just look at
all of the mentions that
came before it and say,
is that coreferent or not,
and do a binary decision.
So at training time,
I'll be able to say
I have positive
examples, assuming
I've got some data labeled
for what's coreferent to what,
and so these ones
are coreferent.
And I've got some negative
examples of these ones
are not coreferent.
And what I want to
do is build a model
that learns to predict
coreferent things.
And I can do that fairly
straightforwardly in the kind
of ways that we
have talked about.
So I train with the regular kind
of cross entropy loss, where
I'm now summing over every
pairwise binary decision,
as to whether two mentions
are coreferent to each other
or not.
And so then when I'm at
test time, what I want to do
is cluster the mentions that
correspond to the same entity,
and I do that by making
use of my pairwise scorer.
So I can run my
pairwise scorer and it
will give a
probability or a score
that any two mentions
are coreferent.
So by picking some
threshold like 0.5,
I can add coreference links
for when the classifier says
it's above the threshold.
And then I do one more step
to give me a clustering,
I then say OK, let's also
make the transitive closures
to give me clusters.
So it thought that 'I'
and 'she' were coreferent
and 'my' and 'she' were
coreferent therefore,
I also have to regard 'I'
and 'my' as coreferent.
and so that's sort of the
completion by transitivity.
And so since we always
complete by transitivity,
note that this algorithm is very
sensitive to making any mistake
in a positive sense.
Because if you make one
mistake, for example
you say that, 'he' and
'my' are coreferent, then
by transitivity all of the
mentions in the sentence
become one big cluster.
And that they're all
coreferent with each other.
So that's a workable algorithm
and people have often
used that.
But often people go a
little bit beyond that,
and prefer a mention
ranking model.
So let me just explain
the advantages of that.
That normally, if you
have a long document where
it's Ralph Nader, and he
did this and some of them
did something to him
and we visited his house
and blah, blah,
blah, blah, blah,
and then somebody voted
for Nader because he--
In terms of building a
coreference classifier,
it seems like it's easy
and reasonable to be
able to recover this
'he' refers to Nader.
But in terms of building
a classifier for it
to recognize that
this he' should
be referring to
this Nader, which
might be three paragraphs back.
Seems unreasonable how you're
going to recover that, so
those far away ones
might be almost
impossible to get correct.
And so that suggests
that maybe we
should have a different way
of configuring this task.
So instead of doing it that
way, what we should say is,
well this 'he' here has
various possible antecedents,
and our job is to just
choose one of them.
And that's almost sufficient.
Apart from we need to
add one more choice which
is, while some mentions won't
be coreferent with anything that
proceeds, because we are
introducing a new entity
into the discourse.
So we can add one more dummy
mention, the NA mention,
so it doesn't refer to anything
previously in the discourse.
And then our job
at each point is
to do mention ranking to
choose which one of these
she refers to.
And then at that point, rather
than doing binary yes/no
classifiers, that what we
can do is say, a-ha, this
is choose one classification.
And then we can use
the softmax classifiers
that we've seen at
many points previously.
OK.
So that gets us in business
for building systems
and either of these
kind of models,
there are several ways in
which we can build the system.
We could use any kind
of traditional machine
learning classifier, we could
use a simple neural network,
we can use more advanced
ones with all of the tools
that we've been learning
about more recently.
Let me just quickly show
you a simple neural network
way of doing it.
So this is the model that
my Phd student Kevin Clark
did in 2015, so
not that long ago.
But what he was doing was
doing coreference resolution
based on the mentions
with a simple feed
forward neural network, kind
of in some sense like we
did dependency parsing
with a simple feed forward
neural network.
So for the mention, it
had word embeddings,
antecedent had word embeddings.
There were some
additional features
of each of the mention,
the candidate antecedent.
And then there was some
final additional features
that captured things
like distance away,
which you can't see from either
the mentions of the candidate.
And all of those
features were just
fed into several feed forward
layers of a neural network,
and it gave you a score of are
these things coreferent or not?
And that by itself just
worked pretty well.
And I won't say more
details about that.
But what I do want
to show is sort
of a more advanced and modern
neural coreference system.
But before I do that, I
want to take a digression
and sort of say
a few words about
convolutional neural networks.
So, the idea of when you apply
a convolutional neural network
to language i.e. to sequences,
is that what you're going to do
is you're going to compute
vectors, features effectively,
for every possible
word subsequence
of a certain length.
So that if you have
a piece of text
like, "tentative deal reached
to keep government open"
you might say, I'm going to
take every three words of that,
i.e. tentative deal
reached, deal reached to,
reached to keep.
And I'm going to
compute a vector based
on that subsequence
of words, and use
those computed
vectors in my model
by somehow grouping
them together.
So the canonical case of
convolutional neural networks
is envision, and so if
after this, next quarter
you go along to CS231N
you'll be able to spend
weeks doing convolutional
neural networks for vision.
And so the idea
there is that you've
got these convolutional filters
that you slide over an image
and you compute a
function of each place.
So there are little red
numbers are showing you
what you're computing,
but then you'll
slide it over to the next
position and fill in this cell,
and then you'll slide it
over the next position,
fill in this cell, and then
you'll slide it down and fill
in this cell.
And so you've got
this little function
of a patch which you're
sliding over your image
and computing a convolution,
which is just a dot
product effectively,
that you're then
using to get an extra
layer of representation.
And so by sliding things over,
you can pick out features
and you've got a
feature identifier
that runs across every
piece of the image.
Well, for language we've
just got a sequence,
that you can do
basically the same thing
and what you then have is
a 1D convolution for text.
So if here is my
sentence, "tentative deal
reached to keep the government
open," that, what I can do
is have, so these words
have our word representation
which if so, this is my
vector for each word.
And then I can have a filter,
sometimes called a kernel,
which I use for my convolution.
And what I'm going
to do is slide
that down the text so I can
start with the first three
words, and then I
sort of treat them
as sort of elements I
can dot product and sum.
And then I can compute a value
as to what they all add up to,
which is minus 1, it turns out.
And so then I might have
a bias that I add on,
and get an updated value
if my bias is plus 1.
And then I'd run it
through a non-linearity,
and that will give
me a final value.
And then I'll slide
my filter down,
and I'd work out a computation
for this window of three words,
and take 0.5 times 3 plus
0.2 times 1, et cetera,
and that comes
out as this value.
I add the bias, I'm going to
put it through my non-linearity.
And then I keep on sliding
down and I'll do the next three
words, and keep on going down.
And so that gives
me a 1D convolution
and computes a
representation of the text.
You might have noticed
in the previous example,
that I started here
with seven words,
that because I wanted to have a
window of 3 for my convolution,
the end result is
that things shrunk.
So in the output I only
had five things, that's
not necessarily desirable.
So commonly, people will
deal with that with padding.
So if I put padding
on both sides,
I can then start my 3 by 3
convolution, my 3 size, not 3
by 3, my 3 convolutional
here and compute this one,
and then slide it down
1, and compute this one.
And so now my output is the
same size as my real input,
and so that's a
convolution with padding.
OK.
So that was the start
of things but how
you get more power of
the convolutional network
is, you don't only
have one filter,
you have several filters.
So if I have three
filters, each of which
will have their own
bias and non-linearity,
I can then get a three
dimensional representation
coming out the end.
And sort of you can think of
these as conceptually computing
different features of your text.
OK, so that gives us a sort of
a new feature re-representation
of our text.
But commonly, we then want to
somehow summarize what we have.
And a very common way of
summarizing what we have
is to then do pooling.
So if we sort of think
of these features
as detecting different things
in the text, so they might even
be high level features
like, does this show
signs of toxicity
or hate speech,
is there a reference
to something.
So if you want to be interested
in does it occur anywhere
in the text, what
people often then do
is, the max pooling operation.
Where for each
feature, they simply
sort of compute
the maximum value
it ever achieved in any position
as you went through the text
and say that, this
vector ends up
as the sentence representation.
Sometimes for other purposes,
rather than max pooling,
people use average
pooling, where
you take the averages
of the different vectors
to get the sentence
representation.
But in general max
pooling has been
found to be more successful.
And that's kind
of because if you
think of it as feature
detectors, that are wanting
to detect was this
present somewhere,
then something like
positive sentiment
isn't going to be present in
every three word subsequence
you choose.
The first there are
somewhere there, and so often
max pooling works better.
And so that's a very quick
look at convolutional neural
networks, except to
say, this example
was doing 1D
convolutions with words.
But a very common place that
convolutional neural networks
are being used in
natural language,
is actually using
them with characters.
And so what you can do is,
you can do convolutions
over subsequences of the
characters in the same way.
And if you do that, this allows
you to compute a representation
for any sequence of characters.
So you don't have any problems
with being out of vocabulary,
or anything like that, because
for any sequence of characters
you just compute your
convolutional representation
and max pool it.
And so quite commonly, people
use a character convolution
to give a
representation of words,
perhaps as the only
representation of words.
But otherwise it's something
that you use in addition
to a word vector and so on.
And so in both by
depth in the model
I'm about to show,
that at the base level
it makes use of both a
word vector representation
that we saw right at the
beginning of the text,
and a character
level convolutional
representation of the words.
OK.
With that said, I
now want to show you
before time runs out an
end-to-end neural coref model.
So the model I'm going to
show you is Kenton Lee's
one from University
of Washington 2017,
this is no longer
the state of the art,
I'll mention the state
of the art at the end.
But this was the
first model that
really said, get rid of all
of that old stuff of having
pipelines and mention
detection first, just build
one end-to-end big
model, that does
everything and returns
coreference so it's a good one
to show.
So compared to the earlier
simple thing I saw,
we're now going to process
the text with BiLSTMs.
We're going to make
use of attention,
and we're going to do
all of mention detection
and coreference in
one step, end-to-end.
And the way it tells
that is by considering
every span of the text
up to a certain length
as a candidate mentioned,
and just figures out
a representation for
it and whether it's
coreferent to other things.
So what we do at
the start is, we
start with the
sequence of words,
and we calculate from those
our standard word embedding,
and a character level
CNN's embedding.
We then feed those as inputs
into a bidirectional LSTM
of the kind that we saw
quite a lot of before,
but then after this, what we do
is we compute representations
for spans.
So when we have a
sequence of words,
we're then going to work
out a representation
of a sequence of words
which we can then
put into our coreference model.
So I can't fully
illustrate in this picture,
but sort of subsequences of
different lengths, so like,
General, General Electric,
General Electric said,
will all have a
span representation,
which I've only shown a
subset of them in green.
So how are those computed?
Well the way they're computed
is that the span representation
is a vector that
concatenates several vectors,
and it consists of four parts.
It consists of
the representation
that was computed for the start
of the span from the BiLSTM.
The representation for
the end from the BiLSTM
that's over here, and
then it has a third part
that's kind of interesting.
This is an attention
based representation
that is calculated
from the whole span,
but particularly sort of
looks for the head of a span.
And then there are still
a few additional features.
So it turns out that some
of these additional things
unlike length and so on
are still a bit useful.
So to work out the
final part, is not
the beginning and
the end, what's done
is to calculate an attention
weighted average of the word
embeddings.
So what you're doing is,
you're taking the X star
representation of the
final word of the span,
and you're feeding that
into a neural network
to get attention scores for
every word in the stand, which
are these three.
And that's giving you an
attention distribution
as we've seen previously.
And then you're calculating
the third component
of this as an attention weighted
sum of the different words
in the span.
And so therefore
you've got the sort
of the soft average
of the representations
of the words of the span.
OK.
So then once you've got
that, what you're doing
is then feeding
these representations
into having scores for where the
spans are coreferent mentions.
So you have a representation
of the two spans,
you have a score
that's calculated
for whether two different
spans look coreferent,
and that overall
you're getting a score
for are different spans
looking coreferent or not.
And so this model is just
run end-to-end models spans,
now sort of would
get intractable
if you scored literally every
span in a long piece of text.
So they do some pruning,
they sort of only allow
spans up to a
certain maximum size,
they only consider
pairs of spans
that aren't too distant
from each other, et cetera,
et cetera.
But basically, it's sort
of an approximation to just
a complete comparison of spans.
And this turns into a
very effective coreference
resolution algorithm.
Today it's not the best
coreference resolution
algorithm, because
maybe not surprisingly
like everything else that
we've been dealing with,
there's now been these
transformer models
like BERT have come
along, and that they
produce even better results.
So the best coreference
systems now make use of BERT.
In particular, when
Danqi spoke, she briefly
mentioned SpanBERT which
is a variant of BERT which
blanks out for reconstruction
subsequences of words,
rather than just a single word.
And SpanBERT has actually proven
to be very effective for doing
coreference, perhaps
because she didn't
blank out whole mentions.
People have also gotten
gains actually, finally,
by treating coref as a
question answering task.
So effectively you can find a
mention like he or the person
and say what is its antecedent,
and get on the question
answering answer, and
that that's a good way
to do coreference.
So if we put that together,
as time is running out,
let me just sort of
give you some sense
of how results come out
for coreference systems.
So I'm skipping a
bit actually that you
can find in the slides, which
is how coreference is scored.
But essentially it's scored
on a clustering metric,
so a perfect clustering
will give you 100,
and something that makes
no correct decisions
would give you 0.
And so this is sort of how
the coreference numbers have
been panning out.
So back in 2010, actually
this was a Stanford system.
This was a state of the
art system for coreference
that won a competition, it was
actually a non-machine learning
model, because again we
wanted to sort of prove
how these rule based methods in
practice worked kind of well.
And so its accuracy was around
55 for English, 50 for Chinese.
Then gradually,
machine learning,
this was sort of statistical
machine learning models
got a bit better.
Wiseman was the very first
neural coreference system,
and that gave some gains.
Here's a system that
Kevin Clark and I did,
which gave a little
bit further gains.
So Lee is the model
that I've just
shown you, as the
end to end model
and it got a bit
of further gains.
But then again what gave
the huge breakthrough just
like question answering, was
that the use of SpanBERT.
So once we moved to here
we're now using SpanBERT,
but that's giving you
about an extra 10% or so.
The coref QA technique
proved to be useful.
And then the very latest
best results are effectively
combining together
SpanBERT and well,
a larger version of SpanBERT and
coref QA and getting up to 83.
So you might think
from that, that coref
is sort of doing really well,
and is getting close to solved
like other NLP tasks.
Well it's certainly true
that in neural times
the results have been
getting way, way better
than they had been before.
But I would caution you that
these results that I just
showed were on a corpus
called OntoNotes,
which is mainly newswire.
And it turns out that newswire
coreference is pretty easy.
I mean in particular,
there's a lot
of mention of the
same entities, right?
So the newspaper articles are
full of mentions of the United
States and China, and leaders
of the different countries,
and it's sort of
very easy to work out
what they're coreferent to.
And so the coreference
scores are fairly high,
whereas if what you
do is take something
like a page of
dialogue from a novel
and feed that into a system
and say, OK, do the coreference
correctly, you'll
find pretty rapidly
that the performance of the
models is much more modest.
If you'd like to try
out a coreference system
for yourself, there are
pointers to a couple of them
here where the top one Al's
from sort of Kevin Clark's
neural coreference,
and this is one
that goes with the
Hugging Face repository
that we've mentioned.