OK.
So for today, we're
actually going
to take a bit of
a change of pace
from what the last couple
of lectures have been about,
and we're going to focus
much more on linguistics
and natural language processing.
And so in particular,
we're going
to start looking at the
topic of dependency parsing.
And so this is the plan of
what to go through today.
So I'm going to start out by
going through some ideas that
have been used for the syntactic
structure of languages,
of constituency and dependency
and introduce those.
And then focusing in more
on the dependency structure,
and then going to look
at dependency grammars
and dependency treebanks.
And then having done
that, we're then
going to move back
into thinking about how
to build natural language
processing systems.
And so I'm going to
introduce the idea
of transition-based
dependency parsing.
And then in particular
having developed that idea,
I'm going to talk
about a way to build
a simple but highly effective
neural dependency parser.
And so this simple
and highly effective
neural dependency
parser is essentially
what we'll be asking you to
build in the third assignment.
So in some sense, we're getting
a little bit ahead of ourselves
here because in
week 2 of the class
we teach you how to do both
assignments two and three.
But all of this material
will come in really useful.
Before I get underway, just
a couple of announcements.
So again for assignment
2, you don't yet
need to use the
PyTorch framework.
But now's a good time to work
on getting PyTorch installed
for your Python programming.
Assignment 3 is in part also an
introduction to using PyTorch.
It's got a lot of scaffolding
included in the assignment.
But beyond that, this Friday
we've got a PyTorch tutorial
and I thoroughly encourage you
to come along to that as well.
Look for it under the Zoom tab.
And in the second half of
the first day of week 4,
we have an explicit
class that partly
focuses on the final
projects and what
the choices are for those.
But it's never too
late to start thinking
about the final project
and what kind of things
you want to do for
the final project.
So do come meet with people.
There are sort of resources
on the course pages
about what different
TAs know about.
I've also talked to a number
of people about final projects,
but clearly I can't
talk to everybody.
So I encourage you to also
be thinking about what you
want to do for final projects.
OK.
So what I wanted to
do today was introduce
how people think about the
structure of sentences,
and put structure on top
of them to explain how
human language conveys meaning.
And so our starting point
for meaning and essentially
what we've dealt
with word vectors up
until now is we have words.
And words are obviously
an important part
of the meaning of
human languages.
But for words in
human languages,
there's more that we can do
with them in thinking about how
to structure sentences.
So in particular, the
first most basic way
that we think
about words when we
are thinking about how
sentences are structured
is we give to them what's
called a part of speech.
We can say that cat is a
noun, by is a preposition,
door is another noun,
cuddly is an adjective.
And then for the
words the, if it
was given a different
part of speech,
if you saw any parts of speech
in school, it was probably
you were told was an article.
Sometimes that is just put
into the class of adjectives.
In modern linguistics and what
you'll see in the resources
that we use, words like the
are referred to as determiners.
And the idea is that there's
a bunch of words includes
a and that.
But also other words like
this and that, or even every,
which are words that occur
at the beginning of something
like the cuddly cat, which
have a determinative function
of sort of picking out which
cats that they're referring to.
And so we refer to
those as determiners.
But it's not the
case that when we
want to communicate with
language that we just
have this word salad, where
we say a bunch of words.
We just say, whatever,
leaking, kitchen,
tap and let the other
person put it together.
We put words together
in a particular way
to express meanings.
And so therefore,
languages have larger units
of putting meaning together.
And the question is how
we represent and think
about those.
Now in modern work, in
particular in modern United
States linguistics or even what
you see in computer science
classes when thinking about
formal languages, the most
common way to approach
this is with the idea
of context-free grammars, which
you see at least a little bit
of in 103 if you've done 103.
What a linguist would often
refer to as free structure
grammars.
And the idea there
is to say, well,
there are bigger
units in languages
that we refer to as phrases.
So something like
the cuddly cat is
a cat with some other
words modifying it.
And so we refer to
that as a noun phrase.
But then we have
ways in which phrases
can get larger by building
things inside phrases.
So the door, here is
also a noun phrase.
But then we can build
something bigger around it
with a preposition,
such as the preposition
and then we have a
prepositional phrase.
And in general,
we can keep going.
So we can then make something
like the cuddly cat by the door
and then the door
is a noun phrase.
The cuddly cat is a noun phrase.
By the door is a
prepositional phrase.
But then when you
put it all together,
the whole of this thing
becomes a bigger noun phrase.
And so it's working with these
ideas of nested phrases, what
in context free
grammar terms you would
refer to as non-terminals.
So noun phrase and
prepositional phrase
would be non-terminals in
the context free grammar.
We can build up a bigger
structure of human languages.
So let's just do
that for a little bit
to review what happens here.
So we start off saying, OK you
can say the cat and the dog.
And so those are noun
phrases, and so we want
a rule that can explain those.
So we could say a noun phrase
goes to determine a noun.
And then somewhere over the
side, we have a lexicon.
And in our lexicon
we would say that dog
is a noun and cat is a
noun and a is a determiner,
and the is a determiner.
OK.
So then we notice you can
do a bit more than that.
So you can say things like
the large cat, a barking dog.
So that suggests
we can have a noun
phrase after the determiner.
It can optionally
be an adjective
and then there's the noun.
And that can explain
some things we can say.
But we can also say the cat
by the door or a barking
dog in a crate.
And so we can also put
a prepositional phrase
at the end, and that's optional.
But you can combine it
together with an adjective.
For the example I gave like
a barking dog on the table.
And so this grammar
can handle that.
So then we'll keep on, and
say, well, actually you
can use multiple adjectives.
So you can say a large barking
dog, or a large barking cuddly
cat.
Maybe not.
Well, sentences like that.
So we have any number
of adjectives, which
we can represent with the star.
What's referred to
as the clinging star.
So that's good.
But I forgot a bit actually.
For by the door, I
have to have a rule
for producing by the door.
So I also need a rule that's
a prepositional phrase,
goes to a preposition
followed by a noun phrase.
And so then I also have to
have prepositions and that
can be in, or on, or by.
OK.
And I can make other
sentences of course with this
as well like, the large crate
on the table or something
like that.
Or the large crate
on the large table.
OK.
So I chug along and then well,
I could have something like talk
to the cat.
And so now I need more stuff.
So talk is a verb and to is
still looks like a preposition.
So I need to be able to make
up something with that as well.
OK.
So what I can do
is say I can also
have a rule for a verb
phrase that goes to a verb.
And then after that, for
something like talk to the cat
that it can take a
prepositional phrase after it.
And then I can say that the
verb goes to talk or walked.
OK.
then I can cover those
sentences, whoops.
OK.
So that's the end
of what I have here.
So in this sort of a way,
I'm handwriting a grammar.
So here is now I have this
grammar and a lexicon.
And for the examples that
I've written down here,
this grammar and this lexicon
is sufficient to parse
these sort of fragments
of showing expansion
that I just wrote down.
I mean, of course, there's
a lot more to English
than what you see here, right?
So if I have something like the
cat walked behind the dog, then
I need some more grammar rules.
So it seems then
I need a rule that
says I can have a sentence that
goes to a noun phrase followed
by a verb phrase.
And I can keep on doing
things of this sort.
That's the one
question that Ruthanne
asked, was about what
the brackets mean
and is the first NP
different from the second?
So for this notation on
the brackets here, I mean,
this is actually
a common notation
that's used in linguistics.
It's sort of in some
sense a little bit
different to traditional
computer science notation
since the star is used in both
to mean 0 or more of something.
So you could have 0, 1,
2, 3, 4, or 5 adjectives.
Somehow it's usual
in linguistics
that when you're using the
star you also put parentheses
around that to
mean it's optional.
So sort of parentheses
and star are used together
to mean any number of something.
When it's parentheses
just by themselves,
that's then meaning 0 or 1.
And then four, are these
two noun phrases different?
No, they're both
noun phrase rules.
And so in our
grammar we can have
multiple rules that expand
noun phrase in different ways.
But actually in my example
here, my second rule
because I wrote it
quite generally,
it actually covers the
first rule as well.
So actually at that point, I
can cross out this first rule
because I don't actually
need it in my grammar.
But in general,
you have a choice
between writing multiple
rules for a noun phrase goes
to categories, which effectively
gives you a disjunction
or working out by various
syntactic conventions
how to compress them together.
OK.
So that was what gets referred
to in natural language
processing as
constituency grammars,
where the standard form
of constituency grammar
is a context free
grammar of the sort
that I trust you saw at least
a teeny bit of either in CS103
or something like a
programming languages,
compilers, formal
languages class.
There are other forms of
grammars that also pick out
constituency.
There are things like
tree adjoining grammars,
but I'm not going to really
talk about any of those now.
What I actually
want them to present
is a somewhat different
way of looking
at grammar, which is referred
to as dependency grammar, which
puts the dependency
structure over sentences.
Now actually, it's
not these two ways
of looking at grammar have
nothing to do with each other.
I mean, there's a
whole formal theory
about the relationships between
different kinds of grammars.
And you can very precisely state
relationships and isomorphisms
between different grammars
of different kinds.
But on the surface, these
two kinds of grammars
look sort of different and
emphasize different things.
And for reasons of this sort
of closeness to picking out
relationships in sentences
and their ease of use,
it turns out that in modern
natural language processing,
starting I guess around 2000,
so really in the last 20 years,
NLP people have really swung
behind dependency grammar.
So if you look around
now where people
are using grammars
in NLP, by far
the most common thing
that's being used
is dependency grammars.
So I'm going to teach us
today a bit about those
and what we're going to
build in assignment 3
is building using
supervised learning
a neural dependency parser.
So the idea of
dependency grammar
is that when we have a
sentence, what we're going to do
is we're going to say for each
word what other words modify
it.
So what we're going to do is
when we say the large crate,
we're going to say OK, well,
large is modifying crate
and that is modifying crate.
In the kitchen, that
is modifying kitchen.
By the door, that
is modifying door.
And so I'm showing a
modification, the dependency
or an attachment relationship by
drawing an arrow from the head
to what's referred to
in dependency grammar
as the dependent.
The thing that modifies,
further specifies or attaches
to the head.
OK.
So that's the start of this.
Well, another dependency
is look in the large crate.
That where you're looking
is in the large crate.
So you're going to want
to have in the large crate
as being a dependent of look.
And so that's also going to be
a dependency relationship here.
And then there's
one final bit that
might seem a little bit
confusing to people,
and that's actually when
we have these prepositions.
There are two ways that you
can think that this might work.
So if it was something
like, look in the crate.
It seems like the is
a dependent of crate.
But you could think that
you want to say, look in
and it's in the crate and give
this dependency relationship
with the sort of
preposition as sort
of thinking of it
as the head of what
was before our
prepositional phrase.
And that's a possible strategy
in the dependency grammar.
But what I'm going
to show you today
and what you're going
to use in the assignment
is dependency grammars that
follow the representation
of universal dependencies.
And universal dependencies
is a framework
which actually is
involved in creating,
which was set up to try and
give a common dependency grammar
over many different
human languages.
And in the design
decisions that were
made in the context of designing
universal dependencies, what
we decided was that for
what in some languages
you use prepositions,
lots of other languages
make much more use
of case markings.
So if you've seen
something like German,
you've seen more case markings
like genitive and dative cases.
And in other languages
like Latin or Finnish.
Lots of Native
American languages,
you have many more
case markings again
which cover most of the
role of prepositions.
So in universal dependencies,
essentially in the crate
is treated like a
case marked noun.
And so what we say is
that the in is also
a dependent of crate, and then
you're looking in the crate.
So in the structure we adopt
in is a dependent of crate.
This in is a
dependent of kitchen.
This by is a dependent of door.
And then we have these
prepositional phrases
in the kitchen by the door
and we want to work out well
what they modify.
Well, in the kitchen is
modifying crate, right,
because it's a crate
in the kitchen.
So we're going to say that this
piece is a dependent of crate.
And then well, what
about by the door?
Well, it's not really meaning
that's the kitchen by the door.
And it's not meaning
to look by the door.
Again, it's a crate by
the door, and so what
we're going to have is the crate
also has door as a dependent.
And so that gives us our
full dependency structure
of this sentence.
OK.
And so that's a
teeny introduction
to syntactic structure.
I'm going to say a
bit more about it
and give a few more examples.
But let me just for
a moment sort of say
a little bit about
why are we interested
in syntactic structure?
Why do we need to know the
structure of sentences?
And this gets into how
does human languages work.
So human languages can
communicate very complex ideas.
I mean in fact,
anything that humans
know how to communicate
to one another,
they communicate pretty
much by using words.
So we can structure and
communicate very complex ideas,
but we can't communicate
a really complex idea
by one word.
We can't just choose
a word like empathy
and say it with
a lot of meaning.
Say empathy and
the other person is
meant to understand everything
about what that means, right?
We have to compose a complex
meaning that explains things
by putting words together
into bigger units.
And the syntax of a language
allows us to put words together
into bigger units, where
we can build up and convey
to other people a
complex meaning.
And so then the listener doesn't
get this syntactic structure,
right?
The syntactic structure
of the sentence
is hidden from the listener.
All the listener gets
is a sequence of words
one after another
bang, bang, bang.
So the listener has to be
able to do what I was just
trying to do in this example.
That as the sequence
of words comes in,
that the listener
works out which
words modify which other words.
And therefore, can construct
the structure of the sentence
and hence the meaning
of the sentence.
And so in the same
way, if we want
to build clever neural net
models that can understand
the meaning of sentences,
those clever neural net models
also have to understand what is
the structure of the sentence
so that they can interpret
the language correctly.
And we'll go through some
examples and see more of that.
OK.
So the fundamental
point that we're
going to spend a
bit more time on
is that these choices
of how you build up
the structure of a language
change the interpretation
of the language.
And a human listener or
equally a natural language
understanding
program has to make
in a sort of probabilistic
fashion choices
as to which words modify i.e.,
depend upon which other words,
so that they're coming up
with the interpretation
of the sentence that
they think was intended
by the person who said it.
OK.
So to get a sense of this
and how sentence structure is
interesting and difficult. What
I'm going to go through now
is a few examples of
different ambiguities
that you find in
natural language.
And I've got some funny examples
from newspaper headlines.
But these are all real
natural language ambiguities
that you find throughout
natural language.
Well, at this
point I should say,
this is where I'm being
guilty of saying for language,
but I'm meaning in English.
Some of these ambiguities you
find in lots of other languages
as well, but which ambiguities
that syntactic structure partly
depend on the details
of the language?
So different languages
have different
syntactic constructions,
different word orders
different amounts of words,
having different forms
of words, like case markings.
And so depending
on those details
there might be
different ambiguities.
So here's one
ambiguity, which is
one of the commonest
ambiguities in English.
So San Jose cops
kill man with knife.
So this sentence
has two meanings.
Either it's the San Jose
cops who are killing a man,
and they're killing
a man with a knife.
And so that corresponds
to a dependency structure,
where the San Jose cops
are the subject of killing,
the man is the object
of killing and then
the knife is then the
instrument with which
they're doing the killing.
So that the knife is
an oblique modifier
for the instrument of killing.
And so that's one possible
structure for this sentence.
But it's probably
not the right one.
So what it actually
probably was,
was that it was a man with a
knife and the San Jose cops
killed the man.
So that corresponds to
the knife then being
a noun modifier of the man.
And then kill is
still killing the man,
so the man is the
object of killing
and the cops are
still the subject.
And so whenever you have a
prepositional phrase like this
that's coming further
on in a sentence,
there's a choice of
how to interpret it.
It could be either interpreted
as modifying a noun phrase that
comes before it, or it can
be interpreted as modifying
a verb that comes before it.
So systematically in English you
get these prepositional phrase
attachment ambiguities
throughout all
of our sentences.
But to give two
further observations
on that, the first observation
is you encounter sentences
with prepositional phrase
attachment ambiguities
every time you read
a newspaper article,
every time you talk to somebody.
But most of the time,
you never notice them.
And that's because
our human brains
are incredibly
good at considering
the possible interpretations and
going with the one that makes
sense according to context.
The second comment, as I said
different human languages
expose different ambiguities.
So for example,
this is an ambiguity
that you normally
don't get in Chinese.
Because in Chinese,
prepositional phrases
modifying a verb are normally
placed before the verb.
And so therefore, you don't
standardly get this ambiguity.
But there are different
other ambiguities
that you find commonly
in Chinese sentences.
OK.
So this ambiguity
you find everywhere,
because prepositional
phrases are
really common at the
right ends of sentences.
So here's another one.
Scientist count
whales from space.
So that gives us these two
possible interpretations
that there are whales
from space and scientists
are counting them.
And then the other one
is how the scientists
are counting the whales is
that they're counting them
from space and they're
using satellites
to count the sails, which is
the correct interpretation
that the newspaper hopes
that you're getting.
And this problem gets
much, much more complex.
Because many
sentences in English
have prepositional phrases
all over the place.
So here's the kind
of boring sentence
that you find in
the financial news.
The board approved
its acquisition
by Royal Trustco Limited
of Toronto for $27 a share
at its monthly meeting.
And well, if you look at the
structure of this sentence what
we find is here is a verb then
here is the object noun phrase.
So you've got the
object noun phrase here.
And then after that,
what do we find?
Well, we find a
prepositional phrase,
another prepositional phrase,
and another
prepositional phrase.
And how to attach each of
these is then ambiguous.
So the basic rule of how
you can attach them is you
can attach them to things to
the left providing you don't
create crossing attachments.
So in principle by
Royal Trustco Limited
could be attached to either
approved or acquisition.
But in this case, by
Royal Trustco Limited
it's the acquirer.
So it's a modifier
of the acquisition.
OK.
So then we have of Toronto.
So of Toronto could be
modifying Royal Trustco Limited.
It could be modifying
the acquisition,
or it can be modifying
the approved.
And in this case, the of
Toronto is telling you more
about the company,
and so it's a modifier
of Royal Trustco Limited.
OK.
So then the next one
is for $27 a share.
And that could be modifying
Toronto Royal Trustco
Limited, the acquisition
or the approving.
And well, in this case,
that's talking about the price
of the acquisition.
So this one jumps
back, and this is now
a prepositional phrase that's
modifying the acquisition.
And then at the end, at
its monthly meeting. ,
Well that's where the approval
is happening by the board.
So rather than any of these
preceding four noun phrases,
at its monthly meeting is
modifying the approval.
And so it attaches
right back there.
And this example
is kind of too big
and so I couldn't
fit it in one line.
But as I think maybe you can see
that none of these dependencies
cross each other, and they
connect at different places
ambiguously.
So because we can chain
these prepositions like this
and attach them at
different places like this,
human language sentences are
actually extremely ambiguous.
If you have a sentence
with k prepositional
phrases at the end of it,
where here we have k equals 4.
The number of parses
this sentence has,
the number of different ways
you can make these attachments
is given by the Catalan numbers.
So the Catalan numbers are an
exponentially growing series,
which arises in many
treelike contexts.
So if you're doing something
like triangulations
of a polygon, you
get Catalan numbers.
If you're doing triangulation
and graphical models in CS228,
you get Catalan numbers.
But we don't need to worry
about the details here.
The central point is this
is an exponential series.
And so you're getting
an exponential number
of parses in terms of the
number of prepositional phrases.
And so in general, the number
of parses human languages
have is exponential
in their length, which
is kind of bad news.
Because if you're then trying
to enumerate all the parses,
you might fear that you really
have to do a ton of work.
The thing to notice
about structures
like these prepositional
phrase attachment ambiguities
is that there's
nothing that resolves
these ambiguities in terms of
the structure of the sentence.
So if you've done
something like looked
at the kind of grammars
that are used in compilers,
that the grammars
used in compilers
for programming languages are
mainly made to be unambiguous.
And to the extent that
there are any ambiguities,
there are default
rules that are used
to say, choose this
one particular parse
tree for your piece of
a programming language.
And human languages
just aren't like that.
They're globally ambiguous,
and the listening human
is just meant to be smart
enough to figure out
what was intended.
So the analogy would be that
in programming languages
when you're working out what
does an else clause modify,
well, you've got the answer.
That you can either
look at the curly braces
to work out what the
else clause modifies
or if you're using Python,
you look at the indentation
and it tells you what
the else clause modifies.
Where by contrast for human
languages, it would be just
write down else something.
Doesn't matter how you do it.
You don't need parentheses,
you don't need indentation.
The human being
will just figure out
what the else clause is
meant to pair up with.
OK.
Lots of other forms of
ambiguities in human languages.
So let's look at a few others.
Another one that is very common
over all sorts of languages
is coordination and
scope ambiguities.
So here's a sentence,
shuttle veteran and long time
NASA executive Fred
Gregory appointed to board.
Well, this is an
ambiguous sentence.
There are two possible
readings of this.
One reading is that
there are two people,
there's a shuttle
veteran and there's
a long time NASA
executive Fred Gregory
and they were both
appointed to the board.
Two people.
And the other
possibility is there's
someone named Fred
Gregory, who's
a shuttle veteran and
long time NASA executive
and they're appointed
to the verb.
One person.
And these two
interpretations again,
correspond to having
different parse structures.
So in one structure, we've got
a coordination of the shuttle
veteran and the long time
NASA executive, Fred Gregory,
coordinated together.
In one case, these
are coordinated
and then Fred Gregory specifies
the name of the NASA executive.
So it's then specifying
who that executive is.
Where the what in the other
one, the shuttle veteran
and longtime NASA executive,
altogether is then something
that is a modifier
of Fred Gregory.
OK.
So one time, this is the unit
that modifies Fred Gregory.
In the other one up here,
just long time NASA executive
modifies Fred Gregory.
And then that's
conjoined together
with the shuttle veteran.
And so that also gives
different interpretations.
So this is a slightly
reduced example.
Newspaper headlines tend
to be more ambiguous
than many other pieces
of text, because they're
written in this shortened
form to get things to fit.
And this is an especially
shortened form,
where it's actually left
out an explicit conjunction.
But this headline says doctor:
no heart, cognitive issues.
And this was I guess after
Trump's first physical.
And well, this is an ambiguity,
because there are two ways
that you can read this.
You can either read
this as saying doctor:
no heart and cognitive
issues, which
gives you one interpretation.
Instead of that, the
way we should read it
is that it's heart or cognitive.
And so it's then saying no
heart or cognitive issues.
And we have a different narrower
scope of the coordination,
and then we get a
different reading.
OK.
I want to give a couple more
examples of different kinds
of ambiguities.
Another one you
see quite a bit is
when you have modifiers that
are adjectives and adverbs,
that there are different
ways that you can have
things modifying other things.
This example is a little bit not
safe for work, but here goes.
Students get first
hand job experience.
So this is an
ambiguous sentence.
And again, we can think of
it as a syntactic ambiguity
in terms of which things
modify which other things.
So the nice polite way
to render this sentence
is that first is modifying hand.
So we've got first hand.
It's job experience, so job
is a compound noun modifying
experience.
And it's first hand
experience, so first hand
is then modifying experience.
And then get is the
object of -- sorry,
first hand job experience
is the object of get.
And the students are
the subject of get.
But if you have a
smuttier mind you
can interpret this
a different way.
And in the alternative
interpretation you
then have hand going
together with job.
And the first is then a
modifier of experience and job
is still a modifier
of experience.
And so then you get this
different parse structure
and different
interpretation there.
OK.
One more example.
In a way this example's
similar to the previous one.
It's having modifier pieces that
can modify different things.
But rather than it just being
with individual adjectives
or individual adverbs, it's
then much larger units,
such as verb phrases can often
have attachment ambiguities.
So this sentence headline
is mutilated body washes up
on Rio beach to be used for
Olympics beach volleyball.
So we have this big
verb phrase here of,
to be used for Olympic
beach volleyball.
And then again, we have
this attachment decision
that we could either
say that that big verb
phrase is modifying, i.e.,
is attached to the Rio beach.
Or we could say
no, no, the to be
used for Olympic beach
volleyball, that is modifying
the mutilated body.
And it's a body that's to be
used for the Olympics beach
volleyball, which gives
the funny reading.
Yeah, so I hope that's given
you at least a little bit
of a sense of how human language
syntactic structure is complex,
ambiguous.
And to work out the
intended interpretations,
you need to know something
about that structure.
In terms of how much
you need to understand,
I mean, this isn't
a linguistics class.
If you'd like to learn more
about human language structure,
you can go off and
do a syntax class.
But we're not really going to
spend a lot of time working
through language structure.
But there will be some questions
on this in the assignment.
And so we're expecting that
you can be at the level
that you can have sort of
some intuitions as to which
words and phrases are modifying
other words and phrases.
And therefore, you could choose
between two dependency analyses
which one's correct.
OK.
I've spent quite a
bit of time on that.
So better keep going.
OK.
So the general idea
is that knowing
this sort of syntactic
structure of a sentence
can help us with
semantic interpretation.
I mean, as well as
just generally saying,
we can understand
language it's also
used in many cases for
simple, practical forms
of semantic extraction.
So people such as in
biomedical informatics
often want to get out
particular relations,
such as protein-protein
interactions.
And well, here's a sentence
the results demonstrated
that KaiC interacts rhythmically
with SasA, KaiA and KaiB.
And commonly that people can get
out those kind of relationships
by looking at patterns
of dependency relations
with particular verbs.
So for the interacts
verb, if you
have a pattern of something
being the subject and something
else being the noun
modifier of interacts,
well that's an
interaction relationship.
But it gets a bit
more complicated
than that as in this
example, because often there
are conjunctions.
So you also have another
pattern where you have also
interactions between the
subject and the noun modifiers
conjunct, which will allow us
to also find the KaiA and KaiB
examples.
OK.
So I've given an informal
tour of dependency grammar
to just try and quickly
say a little bit more
about formally what a
dependency grammar is.
So in dependency
syntax, what we say
is that the syntactic
structure of a sentence
consists of relations
between pairs of words.
And it's a binary
asymmetric relation i.e.
we draw arrows between
pairs of words,
which we call dependencies.
Now normally dependency
grammars then type
those grammatical
relation, type those
arrows to express what kind
of relation that there is.
And so that they have
some kind of taxonomy
of grammatical relation.
So we might have a subject
grammatical relation,
a verbal auxiliary grammatical
relation, an oblique modifier
grammatical relation.
We have some kind of typology
of grammatical relations.
And we refer to the arrow
as going between the head,
is the head here, and something
that is dependent of that.
So the subject of a verb is
the dependent of the verb.
Or when you have
a noun modifier,
like sort of cuddly
cat, we say that cuddly
is a dependent of cat.
And cat is the
head of cuddly cat.
And so normally dependencies,
like in these examples form
a tree, which is formal.
So it's not just any
graph with arrows.
We have a graph which is
connected, acyclic, and has
a single root.
So here is the
root of the graph.
And so that gives us the
dependency tree analysis.
Dependency grammars have a
really, really long history.
So the famous first
linguist was Panini,
who wrote about the
structure of Sanskrit.
And mainly he worked on the
sound system of Sanskrit
and how sounds change in
various contexts, which is
what linguists call phonology.
And the different forms
of Sanskrit words.
Sanskrit has rich morphology
of inflecting nouns and verbs
for different cases and forms.
But he also worked a little
on the syntactic structure
of Sanskrit sentences.
And essentially what he
proposed was dependency grammar
over Sanskrit sentences.
And it turns out that sort of
for most of recorded history
when people have then gone on
and tried to put structures
over human sentences,
what they have used
is dependency grammars.
So there was a lot of work
in the first millennium
by Arabic grammarians trying
to work out the grammar
structure of sentences.
And effectively what they
used was akin to I've
just presented as a
dependency grammar.
So compared to 2,500
years of history,
the ideas of having
context-free grammars
and having constituency grammars
is actually a really, really
recent invention.
So it was really sort of in
the middle of the 20th century
that the ideas of
constituency grammar
and context-free grammars
were developed first
by Wells in the 40s,
and then by Noam Chomsky
in the early 50s leading
to things like the Chomsky
hierarchy that you might see
in CS103, or a formal languages
class.
So for modern work
on dependency grammar
using the terminology
and notation
that I've just
introduced, that's
normally attributed to
Lucien Tesniere, who
was a French linguist in
around the sort of the middle
of the 20th century as well.
Dependency grandma was widely
used in the 20th century
in a number of places.
I mean, in particular
it tends to be much more
natural and easier to
think about for languages
that have a lot of different
case markings on nouns.
Like nominative, accusative,
genitive, dative, instrumental
kind of cases like you get in a
language like Latin or Russian.
And a lot of those languages
have much freer word
order than English.
In English, the
subject has to be
before the verb and the object
has to be after the verb.
But lots of other languages
have much freer word order,
and instead use different
forms of nouns to show you
what's the subject or the
object of the sentence.
And dependency grammars can
often seem much more natural
for those kinds of languages.
Dependency grammars
were also prominent
in the very beginnings of
computational linguistics.
So one of the first
people working
in computational linguistics
in the US was David Hayes.
So the professional society
for computational linguistics
is called the Association for
Computational Linguistics,
and he was actually one of the
founders of the Association
for Computational Linguistics.
And he published in the
early 1960s and early perhaps
the first dependency
grammar --parser,
sorry, dependency parser.
OK.
Yeah, a little teeny note just
in case you see other things.
When you have these
arrows, you can draw them
in either direction.
You could either draw
arrows from the head
or to the dependent, or from
the dependent to the head.
And actually, different people
have done one and the other,
right?
So the way Tesniere
drew them was
to draw them from the
head to the dependent
and we're following
that convention.
But if you're
looking at something
that somebody else has written
with dependency arrows,
the first thing you
have to work out
is are they using
the arrow heads
at the heads or the dependence.
Now one other thing
here is that a sentence
is seen as having
the overall head
word of the sentence,
which every other word
of the sentence hangs off.
It's a common convention to
add this sort of fake root
to every sentence
that then points
to the head word of the whole
sentence here completed.
That just tends to make
the algorithm stuff easier.
Because then you can say that
every word of the sentence
is dependent on precisely
one other node, where
what you can be
dependent on is either
another word on the sentence or
the fake root of the sentence.
And when we build our parses, we
will introduce that fake root.
OK.
So that's dependency grammars
and dependency structure.
I now want to get us
back to natural language
processing and starting to build
parses for dependency grammars.
But before doing that, I
just want to say, where do we
get our data from?
And that's actually
an interesting story
in some sense.
So the answer to that
is, well, what we do
is get human beings, commonly
linguists or other people
who are actually
interested in the structure
of human sentences.
And we get them to sit around
and hand parse sentences
and give them
dependency structures.
And we collect a
lot of those parses
and we call that a treebank.
And so this is something
that really only started
happening in the late
-80s and took off
in a bigger way in the -90s.
Until then, no one had
attempted to build treebanks.
Lots of people had
attempted to build parsers.
And it seemed like,
well, if you want
to build a parser,
the efficient way
to do it is to start
writing a grammar.
So you start writing
some grammar rules
and you start
writing the lexicon
with words and parts
of speech, and you sit
around working on your grammar.
When I was a PhD student,
one of my first summer jobs
was spending the summer
hand-writing a grammar.
And it seems like writing
and grammar is more efficient
because you're writing this one
general thing that tells you
the structure of
a human language.
But there's just been this
massive sea change partly
driven by the adoption of
machine learning techniques,
where it's now seen as axiomatic
that the way to make progress
is to have annotated
data, namely here
a treebank that shows you
the structure of sentences.
And so what I'm
showing here is a teeny
extract from a universal
dependencies treebank.
And so that's why
I mentioned earlier
that this has been this
effort to try and have
a common dependency grammar
representation that you
can apply to lots of
different human languages.
And so you can go
over to this URL
and see that there's about
60 different languages
at the moment, which have
universal dependencies
treebanks.
So why are tree banks good?
I mean, it seems
like it's bad news
if you have to have
people sitting around
for weeks and months
hand parsing sentences.
It seems a lot slower and
actually a lot less useful
than having somebody
writing a grammar, which
just has a much bigger
multiplier factor
in the utility of their effort.
It turns out that although
that initial feeling seems
sort of valid, that in practice
there's just a lot more
you can do with the treebank.
So why are tree banks great?
One reason is that tree
banks are highly reusable.
So typically, when people
have written grammars,
they've written grammars
for one particular parser
and the only thing
that was ever used in
is that one particular parser.
But when you build a treebank,
that's just a useful data
resource and people use that
for all kinds of things.
So the well-known
treebanks have been
used by hundreds and
hundreds of people.
And although all
treebanks were initially
built for the purposes of, hey
let's help natural language
processing systems.
It turns out that
people have actually
been able to do lots of
other things with tree banks.
So for example these days
psycholinguists commonly
use treebanks to get various
kinds of statistics about data
for thinking about
psycholinguistic models.
Linguists use tree
banks for looking
at patterns of different
syntactic constructions that
occur.
That there's just been a
lot of reuse of this data
for all kinds of purposes.
But they have other advantages
that I mentioned here.
When people are just
sitting around saying,
what sentences are good.
They tend to only think
of the core of language,
where lots of weird
things happen in language.
And so if you actually
just have some sentences
and you have to go
off and parse them,
then you actually have to deal
with the totality of language.
Since you're parsing actual
sentences, you get statistics.
So you naturally get
the kind of statistics
that are useful to
machine learning systems
by constructing a treebank,
where you don't get them
for free if you hand
write a grammar.
But then a final way which
is perhaps the most important
of all is if you
actually want to be
able to do science
of building systems,
you need a way to evaluate
these NLP systems.
I mean, it seems
hard to believe now
that back in the -90s and -80s
when people built NLP parsers,
it was literally the case that
the way they were evaluated
was you said to your friend,
I've built this parser.
Type in a sentence
on the terminal
and see what it gives you back.
It's pretty good, hey?
And that was just the
way business was done.
Whereas what we'd
like to know is well
as I showed you earlier,
English sentences
can have lots of different
parsers commonly.
Can this system choose the right
parses for particular sentences
and therefore have the
basis of interpreting them
as a human being would?
And well, we can only
systematically do
that evaluation if we have a
whole bunch of sentences that
have been hand parsed by
humans with their correct
interpretations.
So the rise of treebanks
turn parser building
into an empirical science,
where people could then
compete rigorously on the
basis of, look, my parser
has 2% higher accuracy
than your parser
in choosing the correct
parses for sentences.
OK.
So well, how do
we build a parser
once we've got dependencies?
So there's sort of a bunch
of sources of information
that you could hope to use.
So one source of
information is looking
at the words on either
end of the dependency.
So discussing issues that seems
a reasonable thing to say,
and so it's likely
that issues could
be the object of discussing.
Whereas, if it was
some other word, right,
if you are thinking
of making outstanding
the object of discussion,
discussing outstanding.
That doesn't sound right.
So that wouldn't be so good.
A second source of
information is distance.
So most dependencies are
relatively short distance.
Some of them are.
Some have long
distance dependencies
but they're relatively rare.
The vast majority of
dependencies are nearby.
Another source of information
is the intervening material.
So there are certain things
that dependencies rarely span.
So clauses and
sentences are normally
organized around verbs.
And so dependencies rarely
span across intervening verbs.
We can also use punctuation
in written language, things
like commas which can give some
indication of the structure.
And so punctuation may
also indicate bad places
to have long distance
dependencies over.
And there's one final
source of information,
which is what was referred
to as valency, which
is for a head what
kind of information
does it usually have around it?
So if you have a
noun, there are things
that you just know about what
kinds of dependence nouns
normally have.
So it's common that it
will have a determiner
to the left, the cat.
On, the other hand,
it's not going
to be the case that there's a
determiner to the right, cat
the.
That's just not what
you get in English.
On the left, you're also likely
to have an adjectival modifier.
That's why we had cuddly.
But again, it's not
so likely you're
going to have the
adjectival modifier
over on the right for cuddly.
So there are sort of
facts about what things
different kinds of words take
on the left and the right.
And so that's the
valency of the heads,
and that's also a useful
source of information.
OK.
So what do we need to do
using that information
to build a parser?
Well, effectively what
we do is have a sentence,
I'll give a talk tomorrow
on neural networks.
And what we have to do
is say for every word
in that sentence, we have
to choose some other word
that it's the dependent
of, where one possibility
it's a dependent of root.
So we're giving it a structure,
where we're saying OK,
for this word, I've decided
that it's dependent on networks.
And then for this word, it's
also dependent on networks.
And for this word, it's
a dependent on give.
So we're choosing
one for each word.
And there are usually
a few constraints.
So only one word is
a dependent of root.
We have a tree.
We don't want cycles.
So we don't want to say that
word A is dependent on word B,
and word B is
dependent on word A.
And then there's one final
issue, which is where
the arrows can cross or not.
So in this particular
sentence, we actually
have these crossing
dependencies you can see there.
I'll give a talk tomorrow
on neural networks.
And this is the correct
dependency parse
for this sentence.
Because what we have
here is that it's a talk
and it's a talk
on neural network.
So the on neural networks
modifies the talk,
but which leads to these
crossing dependencies.
I didn't have to
say it like that.
I could have said, I'll give
a talk on neural networks
tomorrow.
And then on neural networks
would be next to the talk.
So most of the
time in languages,
dependencies are
projective, the things
stay together so
the dependencies
have a kind of a nesting
structure of the kind
that you also see in
context free grammars.
But most languages have
at least a few phenomena
where you ended up with
these ability for phrases
to be split apart, which lead
to non-projective dependencies.
So in particular, one
of them in English
is that you can take modifying
phrases and clauses like the
on neural networks
here, and shift them
right towards the
end of the sentence,
and get I'll give a talk
tomorrow on neural networks.
And that then leads to
non-projective sentences.
So a parse is
projective if there
are no crossing dependency arcs
when the words are laid out
in their linear order with
all arcs above the words.
And if you have a
dependency parse that
corresponds to a context
free grammar tree,
it actually has to be projective
because context-free grammars
necessarily have this sort of
nested tree structure following
the linear order.
But dependency grammars normally
allow non-projective structures
to account for
displaced constituents.
And you can't easily
get the semantics
of certain constructions right
without these nonprojective
dependencies.
So here's another
example in English
with question
formation with what's
called preposition stranding.
So the sentence is, who did Bill
buy the coffee from yesterday?
There's another way I
could have said this.
It's less natural
in English, but I
could have said, from who did
Bill buy the coffee yesterday?
In many languages
of the world, that's
the only way you
could have said it.
And when you do that,
from who is kept together
and you have a projective
parse for the sentence.
But English allows and
indeed it much prefers
you to do what is referred
to as preposition stranding,
where you move for
who but you just
leave the preposition behind.
And so you get who did Bill
buy the coffee from yesterday?
And so then we're ending up with
this non-projective dependency
structure as I've shown there.
OK.
I'll come back to non
projectivity in a little bit.
How do we go about building
dependency parsers?
Well, there are a whole
bunch of ways that you
can build dependency parsers.
Very quickly, ought to say a
few names and I'll tell you
about one of them.
So you can use dynamic
programming methods
to build dependency parsers.
So I showed earlier that you
can have an exponential number
of parsers for a
sentence and that
sounds like really bad
news for building a system.
Well, it turns out
that you can be clever
and you can work out a way
to dynamic program finding
that exponential
number of parsers
and then you can have
an O(n) cubed algorithm.
So you could do that.
You can use graph algorithms and
then I'll say a bit about that
later.
But that may spill
into next time.
So you can see, since we're
wanting to kind of connect up
all the words into a
tree using graph edges,
that you could think
of doing that using
a minimum spanning tree
algorithm of the sort
that you hopefully saw in CS161.
And so that idea has
been used for parsing.
Constraint satisfaction
ideas that you
might have seen
in CS221 have been
used for dependency parsing.
But the way I'm
going to show now
is transition based
parsing, or sometimes
referred to as deterministic
dependency parsing.
And the idea of
this is one's going
to use a transition
system, so that's
like shift reduce parsing.
If you've seen a shift
reduce parsing in something
like a compilers class or
a formal languages class,
that's shift and reduce
transition steps.
And so you use a
transition system
to guide the
construction of parses.
And so let me just
explain about that.
So let's see.
So this was an idea
that was made prominent
by Joakim Nivre, who's a Swedish
computational linguist who
introduced this idea of greedy
transition based parsing.
So his idea is well,
what we're going
to do for dependency
parsing is we're
going to be able
to parse sentences
by having a set of transitions,
which are like shift
reduce parse.
And it's going to just
work left or right,
bottom up and
parse the sentence.
So we're going to say we
have a stack sigma, a buffer
beta of the words that
we have to process.
And we're going to build
up a set of dependency arcs
by using actions, which are
shift and reduce actions.
And putting those
together, this will give us
the ability to put parse
structures over sentences.
And let me go through
the details of this.
And this is a little bit
hairy when you first see it.
That's not so complex, really.
And this kind of transition
based dependency parser
is what will use
in assignment 3.
So this is our
transition system.
We have a starting
point, where we
start with a stack that just
has the root symbol on it,
and a buffer that
has the sentence
that we're about to parse.
And so far, we haven't
built any dependency arcs.
And so at each point
in time, we can
choose one of three actions.
We can shift, which moves
the next word onto the stack.
We can then do actions that
are the reduce actions.
So we do two reduce actions to
make it a dependency grammar.
We can either do a left arc
reduce or a right arc reduce.
So when we do either of those,
we take the top two items
on the stack and
we make one of them
a dependent of the other one.
So we can either say, OK, let's
make w_i a dependent of w_j.
Or else we can say OK, let's
make w_j a dependent of w_i.
And so the result of
when we do that is
the one that's the dependent
disappears from the stack.
And so in the stacks over
here, there's one less item.
But then we add a dependency
arc to our arc set
so that we say that we've got
either a dependency from j to i
or a dependency from i to j.
And commonly when we
do this, we actually
also specify what
grammatical relation
connects the two, such as
subject, object, noun modifier.
And so we also have
here a relation.
That's probably
still very abstract,
so let's go through an example.
So this is how a
simple transition based
dependency parser, what's
referred to as an arc standard,
transition-based dependency
parser would parse up I
ate the fish.
So remember these are
the different operations
that we can apply.
So to start off
with, we have root
on the stack and the
sentence in the buffer,
and we have no dependency
arcs constructed.
So we have to choose one
of the three actions.
And when there's only
one thing on the stack,
the only thing we
can do is shift.
So we shift.
And now the stack
looks like this.
So now we have to
take another action.
And at this point
we have a choice,
because we could
immediately reduce.
So we could say, OK, let's
just make I a dependent of root
and we'd get a stack
size of 1 again.
But that would be
the wrong thing
to do because I isn't
the head of the sentence.
So what we should
instead do is shift again
and get I ate on the stack
and fish still in the buffer.
Well, at that point we keep
on parsing a bit further.
And so now what we can do
is say, well, wait a minute.
Now I is a dependent of ate and
so we can do a left arc reduce
and so I disappears
from the stack.
So here's our new stack.
But we add to the set
of arcs that we've added
that I is the subject of ate.
OK.
Well after that, we
could reduce again
because there's still
two things on the stack
but that would be the
wrong thing to do.
The right thing to
do next would be
to shift fish onto the stack.
And then at that point,
we can do a right arc
reduce saying that ate
is the object of fish
and add a new dependency
to our dependency set.
And then we can one
more time do a right arc
reduce to say that ate is the
root of the whole sentence,
and add in that extra root
relation with our pseudo root.
And at that point, we've
reached the end condition.
So the end condition
was the buffer was empty
and there's one thing,
the root on the stack.
And at that point,
we can finish.
So this little
transition machine
does the parsing
up of the sentence.
But there's one thing that's
left to explain still here,
which is how do you
choose the next action?
So as soon as you have two
things or more on the stack,
what do you do next?
You've always got a choice.
You could keep shifting,
at least if there are still
things on the buffer or
you can do a left arc
or you can do a right arc.
And how do you know
what choice is correct?
And well, one answer
to that is to say well,
you don't know what
choice is correct.
And that's why parsing is hard
and sentences are ambiguous.
You can do any of those things.
You have to explore all of them.
And well, if you naively
explore all of them,
then you do an
exponential amount of work
to parse the sentence.
So in the early 2000s,
Joakim Nivre's--
and that's essentially what
people had done in the 80s
and 90s is explore every path.
But in the early 2000s, Joakim
Nivre's essential observation
was, but wait a minute.
We know about
machine learning now.
So why don't I try
and train a classifier
which predicts what the
next action I should take
is given this stack and
buffer configuration.
Because if I can write a machine
learning classifier, which
can nearly always correctly
predict the next action given
a stack and buffer, then I'm
in a really good position.
Because then I can
build what's referred
to as a greedy dependency
parser, which just goes bang,
bang, bang, word at a time.
OK, here's the next thing.
Run classifier,
choose next action.
So that the amount of
work that we're doing
becomes linear in the
length of the sentence
rather than it being cubic
in the length of the sentence
using dynamic programming,
or exponential in the length
of the sentence if you don't
use dynamic programming.
So at each step, we predict
the next action using
some discriminative classifier.
So starting off he was using
things like support vector
machines, but it can be
anything at all like softmax
classifier that's closer
to our neural networks.
And there are either for what
I presented three classes
if you're just thinking of
the two reducers in the shift,
or if you're thinking of you're
also assigning a relation
and you have a set of R
relations, like 20 relations,
then there'd be sort of 41
moves that you could decide on
at each point.
And the features are
effectively the configurations
I was showing before.
What's the top of
the stack word?
What part of speech is that?
What's the first
word in the buffer?
What's that word's
part of speech?
Et cetera.
And so on the simplest
way of doing this,
you're now doing
no search at all.
You are just sort of
taking each configuration
and turn, decide the most likely
next move and you make it.
And that's a greedy dependency
parser, which is widely used.
You can do better if you
want to do a lot more work.
So you can do what's
called a beam search, where
you maintain a number of
fairly good parsed prefixes
at each step.
And you can extend
them out further
and then you can
evaluate later on which
of those seems to be the best.
And so beam search
is one technique
to improve dependency parsing
by doing a lot of work.
And it turns out that although
these greedy transition based
parsars are a fraction worse
than the best possible ways
known to parse sentences
that they actually
work very accurately.
Almost as well and they have
this wonderful advantage
that they give you
linear time parsing
in terms of the length of
your sentences and text.
And so if you want to do
a huge amount of parsing,
they're just a
fantastic thing to use,
because you've then
got an algorithm that
scales to the size of the web.
OK.
So I'm kind of a little
bit behind so I guess
I'm not going to get through
all of these slides today
and we'll have to finish out
the final slides tomorrow.
But just to push a
teeny bit further,
I'll just say a couple
more on the sort
of what Nivre did for
the dependency parser
and then I'll sort of introduce
the neural form of that
in the next class.
So conventionally you had this
stack and buffer configuration
and you wanted to build a
machine learning classifier.
And so the way that was done
was by using symbolic features
of this configuration.
And what kind of symbolic
features did you use?
You use these indicator
features that picked out
a small subset
normally one to three
elements of the configuration.
So you'd have a feature
that could be something
like the thing on
the top of the stack
is the word good,
which is an adjective.
Or it could be the
thing on the top
of the stack is an adjective
and the thing that's
first in the buffer is a noun.
Or it could just be
looking at one thing
and saying the first thing
in the buffer is a verb.
So you'd have all
of these features.
And because these features
commonly involved words
and commonly
involve conjunctions
of several conditions,
you had a lot of features.
And having mentions of words
and conjunctions of conditions
definitely helped to make
these parsers work better.
But nevertheless, because you
had all of these sort of 1 0
symbolic features that you
had a ton of such features.
So commonly these parsers
were built using something
like a million to 10
million different features
of sentences.
And I mentioned already the
importance of evaluation.
Let me just sort
of quickly say how
these parsers were evaluated.
So to evaluate a parser
for a particular sentence,
our test set was hand
parsed in the treebank.
So we have gold
dependencies of what
the human thought were right.
And so we can write
those dependencies down
as statements of
saying the first word
is a dependent of the second
word via subject dependency.
And then the parser
is also going
to make similar claims as to
what's a dependent on what.
And so there are two common
metrics that are used.
One, is just are you getting
these dependency facts right.
So both of these
dependency facts match.
And so that's referred to as
the unlabeled accuracy score,
where we just sort of
measuring accuracies,
which are of all
of the dependencies
in the gold sentence.
Remember, we have one dependency
per word in the sentence.
So here we have five.
How many of them are correct and
that's our unlabeled accuracy
score of 80%.
But a slightly more rigorous
evaluation is to say,
well, no, we're also
going to label them
and we're going to say
that this is the subject.
That's actually called the root.
This one's the object.
So these dependencies
have labels
and you also need to get
the grammatical relation
label right and so that's then
referred to as labeled accuracy
score.
And although I got those
two right for that--
I guess according
to this example,
actually this is wrong,
it looks like I got--
Oh, no.
This is wrong there.
Sorry, that one's wrong there.
OK.
So I only got two
of the dependencies
correct in the sense that I
both got what depends on what
and the label correct.
And so my labeled accuracy
score is only 40%.
OK.
So I'll stop there now
for the introduction
for dependency parsing.
And I still have
an IOU, which is
how we can then bring neural
nets into this picture
and how they can be used to
improve dependency parsing.
So I'll do that at
the start of next time
before then proceeding further
into neural language models.