So we're now starting in
week three with lecture five.
So unfortunately, the
last class, I guess,
I really got behind
and went a bit slowly.
I guess, I must just enjoy
talking about natural languages
too much and so I
never really got
to the punchline
of showing how you
could do good things with
the neural dependency parser.
So today for the first
piece I'll in some sense
be finishing the
content of last time
and talk about neural dependency
parsing, which also gives us
the opportunity to introduce
a simple feed forward
neural net classifier.
That will then lead into a
little bit of just background
things that you need to know
about neural networks content
because the fact
of the matter is
there is a bunch
of stuff you need
to know about neural networks.
And then after both
of those things,
I'll get into
what's really meant
to be the topic of
today's lecture, which
is looking at language modeling
and recurrent neural networks.
And that's then going to
lead into those two things
are important topics that we'll
then be talking about, really,
for the whole of
next week as well.
So the couple of reminders
before we get underway,
the first is that you should
have handed in assignment 2
before you joined this class
and in turn assignment 3
is out today.
And this is an
assignment where you're
going to build essentially
the neural dependency parser
that I'm just about
to present in PyTorch.
So part of the role
of this assignment
is actually to get you
up to speed with PyTorch.
So this assignment is
highly scaffolded with lots
of comments and hints
about what to do.
And so the hope is that by the
time you come to the end of it,
you'll feel fairly familiar
and comfortable with PyTorch.
Don't forget there was also a
tutorial on PyTorch last week.
If you didn't catch
that at the time,
you might want to go back
and look at the video.
Another thing to mention
about the assignments
is that assignment 3 is
the last assignment where
our great team of TAs are
happy to look at your code
and sort out your bugs for
you, so maybe take advantage
of that but not too much.
But starting in assignment
4 for assignments 4,
5 and the final
project, the TAs are
very happy to help in
general but it's just not
going to be their job
to be actually sorting
out bugs for you.
You should be
looking at your code
and discussing ideas
and concepts and reasons
why things might
not work with them.
OK, so if you remember
where we were last time,
I'd introduced this
idea of transition
based dependency
parsers and that these
were an efficient linear
time method for giving
the syntactic structure
of natural language text.
And that they worked pretty well
before neural nets came along
and took over NLP again.
But they had some disadvantages,
and their biggest disadvantage
is that like most machine
learning models of that time,
they worked with
indicator features.
So that means that you are
specifying some condition
and then checking whether it
was true of a configuration.
So something like the word on
the top of the stack is good
and its part of
speech is adjective
or the next word coming
up is a personal pronoun.
That those are
conditions that would
be features in a
conventional transition based
dependency parser.
And so what are the
problems with doing that?
Well, one problem is that
those features are very sparse.
A second problem is the
features are incomplete.
Well, what I mean
by that is depending
on what words and configurations
occurred in the training data,
there are certain
features that will
exist because you sort of
saw a certain word preceding
a verb and certain features
that just won't exist
because that word never
occurred before a verb
in the training data.
But perhaps the biggest
problem and opportunity
for doing better with the
neural dependency parser
is that it turns out that in
a symbolic dependency parser,
computing all these features
just turns out to actually
be pretty expensive.
That although the
actual transition system
that I showed last time is
fast and efficient to run,
you actually have to compute
all of these features.
And what you found
was that about 95%
of the parsing time
of one of these models
was spent just computing
all of the features
of every configuration.
So that suggests that
perhaps we can do better
with a neural
approach where we're
going to learn a dense and
compact feature representation.
And so that's what I
want to go through now.
So this time we're
still going to have
exactly the same configuration
of a stack and a buffer
and running exactly the
same transition sequence.
Except this time, rather than
representing the configuration,
the stack and the buffer
by having several million
symbolic features,
we're instead going
to summarize this
configuration as a dense vector
of dimensionality, perhaps
approximately 1,000.
And our neural approach
is going to learn
this dense compact
feature representation.
And so quite
explicitly, what I'm
going to show you
now briefly and what
you're going to
implement is essentially
the neural dependency
parser that was developed
by Danqi Chen in 2014.
And to skip to the
advertisement right
at the beginning as to
how this works so well,
these are the
results that you got
from it using the measures that
I introduced at the last time.
The unlabeled attachments score,
whether you attach dependencies
correctly to the right word and
the labeled attachment score
as to whether you also get the
type of grammatical relation
of that dependency correct.
And so essentially, this
Chen and Manning parser
gave a natural
version of something
like a transition
based dependency parser
like MaltParser in yellow.
And the interesting
thing was that
taking advantage of a
neural classifier in ways
that I'm about to explain that
that could produce something
that was about 2% more accurate
than the symbolic dependency
parser.
And because of the
fact that it's not
doing all of the symbolic
feature computation
despite the fact that you might
think at first that there's
a lot of real number math
and matrix vector multiplies
in a neural dependency
parser, it actually
ran noticeably faster than
the symbolic dependency parser
because it didn't have all
of feature computation.
The other major
approach to dependency
parsing that I'm
also showing here
and I'll get back to at the end
is what's referred to as graph
based dependency parsing.
And so that's a different
approach to dependency parsing.
And so these are two symbolic
graph based dependency parsers.
And in the pre-neural
world, they
were somewhat more accurate than
the transition based parsers
as you could see.
But on the other hand, they
were close to two orders
of magnitude slower.
And so essentially, with
the Chen and Manning parser,
we were able to provide
something that was basically
as accurate as the best graph
based dependency parsers which
were the best dependency
parsers while operating
about two orders of
magnitude more quickly.
So how did we do it?
It was actually a very
straightforward implementation,
which is part of what makes it
great for doing assignment 3.
But this is how we
did it and we got win.
So the first win which
is what we've already
talked about extensively
starting in week one,
is to make use of
distributed representations.
So we represent each
word as a word embedding.
And you've had a lot of
experience with that already.
And so that means
when words weren't
seen in a particular
configuration,
we still know what
they're like because we'll
have seen similar words in
the correct configuration.
But we don't stop only
with word embeddings.
The other things
that are central
to our dependency
parser, are the parts
of speech of words and
the dependency labels.
And so what we decided to do
is that although those are much
smaller sets, so the dependency
labels are about 40 in number
and the parts of speech are of
around that order of magnitude,
sometimes less,
sometimes more, that even
within those sets
of categories, there
are ones that are
very strongly related.
So we also adopted distributed
representations for them.
So for example,
there might be parts
of speech for singular
nouns and plural nouns.
And basically, most of the
time, they behave similarly
and there are
adjectival modifiers
and numerical modifiers
that these are just
numbers like 3, 4, or 5.
And again, a lot
of the time they
behave the same that you have
both three cows and brown cows.
OK, so everything is going to be
represented in the distributed
representation.
So at that point, we have
exactly the same kind
of configuration where we
have our stack, our buffer,
and we've started
to build some arcs.
And so the
classification decisions
of the next transition
are going to be made out
of a few elements of
this configuration,
so we're looking
at the top thing
on the stack, the
second on the stack,
the first word on the buffer.
And then we actually added
in some additional features
that are then--
to the extent that we've
already built arcs for words
on the stack that
we can be looking
at the dependents on the
left and right of those words
that are on the stack that are
already in the sets of arcs.
And so for each of those
things, there is a word,
there is a part of speech.
And for some of them there is
a dependency where it's already
connected up to something else.
So for example, the
left corner of S2
here has an in
sub-dependency back
to the second
thing on the stack.
So we can take these
elements of the configuration
and look up the
embedding of each one.
So we have word embeddings,
part of speech embeddings,
and dependency embeddings
and just concatenate them
all together, kind of like
we did before with the window
classifier and that will give
us a neural representation
of the configuration.
Now, there's a
second reason why we
can hope to win by using a deep
learning classifier to predict
the next transition.
And we haven't really
said much about that yet.
So I just wanted to detour
and say a little bit more
about that.
So the simplest
kind of classifier
that's close to what we've been
talking about in neural models
is a softmax classifier.
So that if we have d dimensional
vectors x and we have
y classes to assign
things to, also y
is an element of a set of c
classes to assign things to,
then we can build a softmax
classifier using the softmax
distribution that
we've seen before,
where we decide
the classes based
on having a weight
matrix that's c by d.
And we train on supervised data
the values of this W, weight
matrix to minimize our
negative log likelihood
loss that we've seen before.
A loss is also commonly referred
to as cross-entropy loss,
a term that you'll see in
PyTorch among other places.
So that is a straightforward
machine learning classifier.
And if you've done 229, you've
seen softmax classifiers.
But a simple softmax
classifier like this shares
with most traditional
machine learning
classifiers some
models that include
Naive Bayes model,
support vector
machines, logistic regression.
That at the end of
the day, they're
not very powerful
classifiers, they're
classifiers that only give
linear decision boundaries.
And so this can
be quite limiting.
So if you have a
difficult problem
like the one I'm indicating in
the picture in the bottom left,
well, there's just no way you
can divide the green points
from the red points by simply
drawing a straight line.
So you're going to have a
quite imperfect classifier.
So the second big win
of neural classifiers
is that they can be much
more powerful because they
can provide nonlinear
classification.
So rather than only being
able to do something
like in the left
picture, we can come up
with classifiers
that do something
like in the right picture
and therefore can separate
the green and the red points.
As an aside, these pictures I've
taken from Andrej Karpathy's
ConvNetJS software, which
is kind of a fun little tool
to play around with if you've
got a bit of spare time.
And so there's something
subtle going on here
is because our more powerful
neural net classifiers
at the end of the day, what
they have at the top of them
is the softmax layer.
And so this softmax layer is
indeed a linear classifier
and it's still a
linear classifier.
But what they have below that
is other layers of neural net.
And so effectively what happens
is that the classification
decisions are linear as
far as the top softmax is
concerned but nonlinear in the
original representation space.
So precisely what a neural net
can do is warp the space around
and move the representation
of data points
to provide something that
at the end of the day
can be classified by
a linear classifier.
And so that's what a
simple feed forward
neural network multi-class
classifier does.
So it starts with an
input representation.
So these are some dense
representation of the input.
It puts it through a hidden
layer h with a matrix multiply
followed by a non-linearity.
So that matrix multiply can
transform the space and map
things around.
And so then the
output of that, we
can then put into
a softmax layer
and get out softmax
probabilities
from which we make our
classification decisions.
And to the extent that our
probabilities don't assign one
to the correct class, we
then get some log loss
or cross entropy
error, which we back
propagate towards the parameters
and embeddings of our model.
And as the learning that
goes on via back propagation,
we increasingly will
learn parameters
of this hidden layer of
the model, which learn
to re-represent the input.
They move the inputs around in
an intermediate hidden vector
space so it can be
easily classified
with what at the end of the
day is the linear softmax.
So this is basically the
whole of a simple feed forward
neural network
multi-class classifier.
But and if we had something
like a visual signal,
we'll just sort of feed
straight in here real numbers
and we'll be done.
But normally with human
language material,
we actually effectively
have one more layer
that we're feeding in
before that because really
below this dense input
layer we actually
have one hot vectors for
what words or parts of speech
were involved.
And then we're doing
a lookup process,
which you can think of as
one more matrix multiply
to convert the one hot features
into our dense input layer.
OK, in my picture here, the one
other thing that's different
is I've introduced a
different non-linearity
in the hidden layer, which
is a rectified linear unit.
And that's what we'll be
using in our neural dependency
parses.
It looks like the picture
in the bottom right
and I'll come back to
that in a few minutes.
That's one of the extra neural
net things to talk about.
OK, So our neural net dependency
parser model architecture
is essentially exactly
that but applied
to the configuration
of our transition based
dependency parser.
So based on our transition
based dependency parser
configuration, we
construct an input layer
embedding by looking
up the various elements
as I discussed previously.
And then we feed it through
this hidden layer to the softmax
layer to get probabilities
out of which we can
choose what the next action is.
And it's no more
complicated than that.
But what we found is that
just simply in some sense
using the simplest
kind of feed forward,
neural classifier could
provide a very accurate
dependency parser
that determines
the structure of
sentences supporting
meaning interpretation
the kind of way
that I suggested last time.
Indeed despite the fact that it
was quite simple architecture,
in 2014 this was the first
successful neural dependency
parser.
And the dense representations
especially, but also
partly the non-linearity
of the classifier
gave us this good result
that it could both outperform
symbolic parsers in
terms of accuracy
and it could outperform
them in terms of speed.
So that was 2014.
Just quickly here a
couple more slides
on what's happened since then.
So lots of people got
excited by the success
of this neural dependency
parser And a number of people,
particularly at Google,
then set about building
a bigger fancier
transition-based
neural dependency parser.
So they explored
bigger, deeper networks.
There's no reason to only
have one hidden layer.
You can have two hidden layers.
You can do beam search that I
briefly mentioned last time.
Another thing that I'm not
going to talk about now
is adding conditional
random field style inference
over the decision sequences.
And that then led
in 2016 for a model
that they called Parsey
McParseface which
is hard to say with
a straight face.
Which was then about 2 and 1/2,
3% more accurate than the model
that we had produced.
But still in basically
the same family
of transition-based
parser with the neural net
classifier to choose
the next transition.
The alternative to
transition-based parsers
is graph-based
dependency parsers.
And for a graph-based dependency
parser, what you're doing
is effectively considering
every pair of words
and considering a word
as a dependent of root.
And you're coming
up with a score
as to how likely is that
big is a dependent of root
or how likely is big to
be a dependent of cat.
And similarly for
every other word.
For the word sat,
how likely is it
to be a dependent of root or
a dependent of the, et cetera.
Well, to do that well, you need
to know more than just what
the two words involved are.
And so what you want to do
is understand the context.
So you want to have
an understanding
of the context of big,
what's to the left
or what's to the right of it to
understand how you might get up
into the dependency
representations
of the sentence.
And so while there
have been previous work
in graph-based
dependency parsing,
like the MST parser I showed
on the earlier results slide,
it seemed appealing
that we could come up
with a much better
representation of context
using neural nets
that look at context.
And how we do that
is actually what
I'll be talking about in
the end part of the lecture.
And so at Stanford, we
became interested in trying
to work out how to come up with
a better graph-based dependency
parser using context.
Sorry, I forgot this
was showing that.
If we can score each
pairwise dependency,
we can simply
choose the best one.
So we can say probably
big is a dependent of cat.
And your first
approximation, we're
going to want to
choose for each word
that it is a dependent
of the word that seems
most likely to be a dependent.
But we want to do that
with some constraints,
because we want to
get out something
that is the tree with a single
root as I discussed last time.
And you can do that by making
use of a minimum spanning tree
algorithm that uses
these scores of how
likely different
dependencies are.
OK.
So then in 2017, another
student, Tim Dozat
and me then worked
on saying, well,
can we now also build
a much better neural
graph-based dependency parser?
And we developed a novel method
for scoring dependency parsers
in a graph-based
model, which I'm not
going to get into the
details of right now.
But' that also had
a very nice result.
Because getting back to
graph-based parsing we could
then build a graph-based parser
that performed about a percent
better than the best of the
Google transition-based neural
dependency parses.
But I should point out
that this is a mixed win.
Because although its
accuracy is better,
these graph-based
parses are just
n squared in performance
rather than linear time.
So kind of like the earlier
results they showed.
They don't operate nearly
as quickly when you're
wanting to parse
large amounts of text
with complex long sentences.
OK.
So that's everything you need
to know about dependency parsers
and to do assignment 3.
So grab it this evening
and start to work.
But I did want to sort of before
going on to the next topic
just mention a few more
things about neural networks
since some of you know
this well already.
Some of you have
seen less of it,
but you know there just
are a bunch of things
you have to be aware of for
building neural networks.
Now again for assignment
3, essentially we
give you everything.
And if you follow the recipe,
your parser should work well.
But what you should
have minimally do
is actually look carefully
at some of the things
that this parser does,
which is questions
like, how do we initialize our
matrices of our neural network?
What kind of
optimizers do we use?
And things like that.
Because these are all
important decisions.
And so I wanted to say just
a few words about that.
OK.
So the first thing that we
haven't discussed at all
is the concept of
regularization.
So when we're building
these neural nets,
we're now building models with
a huge number of parameters.
So essentially just about
all neural net models
that work well, actually
their full loss function
is a regularized loss function.
So for this loss
function here of J, well,
this part here is
the part that we've
seen before where we're
using the softmax classifier
and then taking a
negative log likelihood
loss, which we're then averaging
over the different examples.
But actually, we then
stick on the end of it
this regularization term.
And so this
regularization term sums
the square of every
parameter in the model.
And so what that
effectively says is you only
want to make parameters
non-zero if they're
really useful, right?
So to the extent that the
parameters don't help much,
you're just being penalized
here by making them non-zero.
But to the extent that
the parameters do help,
you'll gain in your
estimation of likelihood.
And therefore, it's OK
for them to be non-zero.
In particular, notice that this
penalty is assessed only once
per parameter.
It's not being assessed
separately for each example,
OK?
And having this kind
of regularization
is essential to build neural
net models that regularize well.
So the classic problem is
referred to as overfitting.
And what overfitting
means is that if you
have a particular
training data set and you
start training your
model, your error
will go down because you'll
shift the parameters so they
better predict the
correct answer for data
points in the model.
And you can keep on doing
that and it will keep
on reducing your error rate.
But if you then look at your
partially trained classifier
and say, how well does
this classifier classify
independent data, different
test data that you
weren't training the model on?
What you'll find is up
until a certain point,
you'll get better at classifying
independent test examples
as well.
And after that, commonly
what will happen
is you'll actually
start to get worse
of classifying
independent test examples,
even though you're continuing
to get better at predicting
the training examples.
And so this was then referred
to as your overfitting
the training
examples, that you're
fiddling the
parameters of the model
so they're really good at
predicting the training
examples, which aren't
useful things that can then
predict on independent examples
that you'd come to at run time.
OK.
That classic view
of regularization
is sort of actually
outmoded and wrong
for modern neural networks.
So the right way to
think of it for the kind
of modern big neural
networks that we build
is that overfitting on the
training data isn't a problem.
But nevertheless, you need
regularization to make sure
that your models generalize
well to independent test data.
So what you would
like is for your graph
not to look like this example
with test error starting
to head up.
You'd like to have it
at worst case flat line
and best case still
be gradually dropping.
It will always be higher
than the training error,
but it's not actually showing
a failure to generalize.
So when we train big
neural nets these days,
our big neural nets always
overfit on the training data.
They hugely overfit
on the training data.
In fact, in many
circumstances our neural nets
have so many parameters
that you can continue
to train them on
the training data
until the error on the
training data is zero.
They get every
single example right
because they can just
memorize enough stuff about it
to predict the right answer.
But in general, providing the
models are regularized well,
those models will still also
generalize well and predict
well in independent data.
And so for part of what
we want to do for that
is to work out how
much to regularize.
And so this Lambda
parameter here
is the strength
of regularization.
So if you're making
that Lambda number big,
you're getting more
regularization.
And if you make it small,
you're getting less.
And you don't want to have
it be too big or else you
won't fit the data well.
And you don't want
to be too small,
or else you have the problem
that you don't generalize well.
OK.
So this is classic
L2 regularization
and it's a starting point.
That our big neural nets
are sufficiently complex
and have sufficiently
many parameters
that essentially L2
regularization doesn't cut it.
So the next thing that
you should know about
and is a very
standard good feature
for building neural nets is
a technique called dropout.
So dropout is
generally introduced
as a sort of a
slightly funny process
that you do when training to
avoid feature co-adaptation.
So in dropout what you do
is that the time that you're
training your model,
that for each instance
or for each batch
in your training,
then for each
neuron in the model,
you drop 50% of its inputs.
You just treat them as zero.
And so that you can do
by sort of zeroing out
elements of the sort of layers.
And then at test time, you don't
drop any of the model weight.
You keep them all.
But actually you have
all the model weights
because you're now keeping
twice as many things
as you used at training data.
And so effectively,
that little recipe
prevents what's called
feature co-adaptation.
So you can't have
features that are only
useful in the presence of
particular other features,
because the model
can't guarantee
which features are going to be
present for different examples.
Because different features
are being randomly dropped
all of the time.
And so effectively
dropout gives you
a kind of a middle ground
between Naive Bayes
and a logistic regression model.
In Naive Bayes models, all the
weights are set independently.
In a logistic regression
model, all the weights
are set in the context
of all the others.
And here you are aware
of other weights,
but they can randomly
disappear from you.
It's also related to ensemble
models like model bagging,
because you're using different
subsets of the features
every time.
But after all of
those explanations,
there's actually
another way of thinking
about dropout which was actually
developed here at Stanford,
this paper by Percy
Liang and students, which
is to argue that really
what dropout gives
you is a strong
regularizer that isn't
a uniform regularizer like L2
that regularizes everything
with an L2 loss, but
can learn a feature
dependent regularization.
And so that dropout
has just emerged
as in general the best way to do
regularization for neural nets.
I think you've already
seen and heard this one,
but just have it
on my slides once.
If you want to have your
neural networks go fast,
it's really essential
that you make
use of vectors,
matrices, tensors and you
don't do things with for loops.
So here's a teeny
example, where I'm
using timeit, which is a useful
thing that you can use too
to see how fast
your neural nets run
in different ways of writing it.
And so when I'm doing
these dot products here,
I can either do the dot product
in a for loop against each word
vector, or I can do the dot
product with a single word
vector matrix.
And if I do it in a for
loop, doing each loop
takes me almost a second.
Whereas if I do it
with a matrix multiply,
it takes me an order
of magnitude less time.
So you should always be looking
to use vectors and matrices,
not for loops.
And this is a speed
up of about 10 times
when you're doing
things on a CPU.
Heading forward, we're
going to be using GPUs
and they only further
exaggerate the advantages
of using vectors and matrices,
where you'll commonly
get two orders of
magnitude speed
up by doing things that way.
Yeah, so for the
backward parse, you
are running backward
parses before on the
dropped out examples, right?
So for the things
that were dropped out
no gradient is
going through them
because they weren't present.
They're not affecting things.
So in a particular
batch, you're only
training weights for the
things that aren't dropped out.
But then since for
each successive batch
you drop out different things
that over a bunch of batches,
you're then training all of
the weights of the model.
And so feature
dependent regularizer
is meaning that the
different features can
be regularized different
amounts to maximize performance.
So back in this
model, every feature
was just sort of being penalized
by taking Lambda times that
squared value.
So this is sort of uniform
regularization, where
the end result of this
dropout style training
is that you end up with some
features being regularized much
more strongly and some other
features being regularized
less strongly.
And how much they
are regularized
depends on how much
they're being used.
So you're regularizing
more features
that are being used less.
But I'm not going to get through
into the details of how you can
understand that perspective.
That's outside of the
context of what I'm
going to get through right now.
So the final bit
is I just wanted
to give a little
bit of perspective
on non-linearities
in our neural nets.
So the first thing
to remember is
you have to have non-linearity.
So if you're building a
multi-layer neural net
and you've just got W1x plus
b1 then you put it through W2x
plus b2 and then
put it through W3x--
Well, I guess they're
different hidden layers.
So I shouldn't say x.
That should be hidden
1, hidden 2, hidden 3.
W3 hidden 3 plus b3.
That multiple linear
transformations
composed so they can
be just collapsed down
into a single linear
transformation.
So you don't get any power
as a data representation
by having multiple
linear layers.
There's a slightly longer story
there because you actually
do get some interesting
learning effects,
but I'm not going to
talk about that now.
But standardly, we have to
have some kind of non-linearity
to do something interesting
in a deep neural network.
OK.
So a starting point is the
most classic non-linearity
is the logistic.
Often just called the
sigmoid non-linearity
because of its S
shape, which we've seen
before in previous lectures.
So this will take any
real number and method
on to the range of 0, 1.
And that was sort of
basically what people used
in sort of 1980s neural nets.
Now one disadvantage
of this non-linearity
is that it's moving everything
into the positive space
because the output is
always between 0 and 1.
So people then decided
that for many purposes,
it was useful to have
this variant sigmoid shape
of hyperbolic tan,
which is then being
shown in the second picture.
Now you know logistic
and hyperbolic tan,
they sound like they're
very different things.
But actually, as you maybe
remember from a math class,
hyperbolic tan can be
represented in terms
of exponentials as well.
And if you do a bit of
math, which possibly we
might make you do
on an assignment,
it's actually the case that
a hyperbolic tangent is just
a rescaled and shifted
version of the logistic.
So it's really exactly the same
curve, just squeezed a bit.
So it goes now symmetrically
between minus 1 and 1.
Well, these kind of
transcendental functions
like hyperbolic
tangent, they're kind of
slow and expensive
to compute, right,
even on our fast
computers, calculating
exponentials is a bit slow.
So it's something people
became interested in was well,
could we do things with much
simpler non-linearities?
So what if we used a
so-called hard tanh?
So the hard tanh,
up to some point
it just flatlines
at minus 1, then
it is y equals x up until 1.
And then it just
flat lines again.
And that seems a
slightly weird thing
to use because if your
input is over on the left
or over on the right,
you're sort of not
getting any discrimination.
And everything's
giving the same output.
And somewhat
surprisingly, I mean,
I was surprised when
people started doing this.
These kind of models proved
to be very successful.
And so that then led
into what's proven
to be kind of the most
successful and generally widely
used non-linearity in a
lot of recent deep learning
work, which is what was being
used in the dependency powers
model I showed is what's
called the Rectified Linear
Unit or ReLU.
So a ReLU is the simplest
kind of non-linearity
that you can imagine.
So if the value of x is
negative, its value is 0.
So effectively it's just dead.
It's not doing anything
in the computation.
And if its value of x is greater
than 0, then it's just simply y
equals x.
The value is being
passed through.
And at first sight, this might
seem really, really weird
and how could this be
useful as a non-linearity?
But if you sort of think a bit
about how you can approximate
things with piecewise linear
functions very accurately,
you might kind of
start to see how
you could use this to
do accurate function
approximation with
piecewise linear functions.
And that's what
ReLU units have been
found to do extremely,
extremely successfully.
So logistic and tanh are
still used in various places.
You use logistic when you
want a probability output.
We'll see tanh's again
very soon when we get
to recurrent neural networks.
But they're no
longer the default
when making deep networks.
That in a lot of
places, the first thing
you should think about trying
is ReLU nonlinearities.
And so in particular
part of why they're good
is that ReLU networks
train very quickly,
because you get this sort
of very straightforward
gradient back flow.
Because providing you're on
the right hand side of it,
you're then just getting this
sort of constant gradient back
flow from the slope 1.
And so they train very quickly.
The somewhat surprising fact
is that almost the simplest
non-linearity
imaginable is still
enough to have a very good
neural network, but it just is.
People have played around
with variants of that.
So people have
then played around
with leaky ReLUs, where rather
than the left-hand side just
going completely to 0, it goes
slightly negative on a much
shallower slope.
And then there's been
a parametric ReLU
where you have an extra
parameter where you learn
the slope of the negative part.
Another thing that's
been used recently
is this swish non-linearity,
which looks almost like a ReLU,
but it sort of curves down
just a little bit there
and starts to go up.
I mean, I think it's fair
to say that none of these
have really proven
themselves vastly superior.
There are papers saying I can
get better results by using
one of these and maybe you can.
But it's not night and
day and the vast majority
of work that you see
around is still just using
ReLUs in many places.
OK.
Couple more things.
Parameter initialization.
So in almost all
cases, you must, must,
must initialize the
matrices of your neural nets
with small random values.
Neural nets just don't work
if you start the matrices
off as zero, because effectively
then everything is symmetric.
Nothing can specialize
in different ways.
And you just don't have an
ability for a neural net
to learn.
You sort of get this
defective solution.
So standardly, you
are using some methods
such as drawing random numbers
uniformly between minus r and R
for a small value
r and just filling
in all the parameters with that.
Exception is with bias weights.
It's fine to set bias weights
to 0 and in some sense that's
better.
In terms of choosing
what the r value
is, essentially for
traditional neural nets,
what we want to set
that r range for is
so that the numbers
in our neural network
stay of a reasonable size.
They don't get too big and
they don't get too small.
And whether they kind of
blow up or not depends
on how many connections there
are in the neural networks.
I'm looking at the
fan in and fan out
of connections in
the neural network.
And so a very common
initialization
that you'll see in
PyTorch is what's
called Xavier initialization,
named after a person who
suggested that.
And it's working
out a value based
on this fan in fan
out of the layers
that you can just
sort of ask for it,
say initialize with this
initialization and it will.
This is another area
where there have been
some subsequent developments.
So around week 5,
will start talking
about layer normalization.
And if you're using
layer normalization,
then it sort of
doesn't matter the same
how you initialize the weights.
So finally, we have
to train our models.
And I've briefly introduced
the idea of stochastic gradient
descent.
And the good news is that
most of the time that
training neural networks with
stochastic gradient descent
works just fine, use it and
you will get good results.
However, often that requires
choosing a suitable learning
rate, which is my final slide
of tips on the next slide.
But there's been an
enormous amount of work
on optimization
of neural networks
and people have come up
with a whole series of more
sophisticated optimizers.
And I'm not going to get into
the details of optimization
in this class.
But the very loose idea
is that these optimizers
are adaptive in that they
can kind of keep track
of how much slope there
was, how much gradient there
is for different parameters.
And therefore,
based on that, make
decisions as to how much
to adjust the weights when
doing the gradient update
rather than adjusting it
by a constant amount.
And so in that
family of methods,
there are methods that include
Adagrad, RMSprop, Adam.
And then a variance of Adam
including SparseAdam, AdamW, et
cetera.
The one called Adam is a
pretty good place to start.
And a lot of the time,
that's a good one to use.
And again from the
perspective of PyTorch,
when you're initializing
an optimizer,
you can just say please use
Adam and you don't actually
need to know much more
about it than that.
If you are using simple
stochastic gradient descent,
you have to choose
the learning rate.
So that was the eta value that
you multiplied the gradient
by for how much to
adjust the weights.
And so I talked
about that slightly
how you didn't want
it to be too big
or your model could
diverge or bounce around.
You didn't want it to be too
small or else the training
could take place
exceedingly slowly
and you'll miss the
assignment deadline.
How big it should
be, depends on all
sorts of details of the model.
And so you want
to sort of try out
some different order
of magnitude numbers
to see what numbers seem to
work well for it training stably
but reasonably quickly.
Something around 10 to the
minus 3 or 10 to the minus 4
isn't a crazy place to start.
In principle, you
can do fine just
using a constant
learning rate in SGD.
In practice, people
generally find
they can get better results
by decreasing learning rates
as you train.
So a very common recipe is that
you halve the learning rate
after every k epochs,
where an epoch means
that you've made a pass through
the entire set of training
data.
So perhaps something
like every three epochs,
you have the learning rate.
And a final little
note there in purple
is when you make a
pass through the data,
you don't want to go through
the data items in the same order
each time.
Because that leads
you to to kind of
have a sort of patterning
of the training examples
that the model will sort of
fall into that periodicity
of those patterns.
So it's best to shuffle the data
before each pass through it.
OK.
There are more sophisticated
ways to set learning rates
and I won't really
get into those now.
Fancier optimizers like Adam
also have a learning rate.
So you still have to choose
a learning rate value.
But it's effectively
it's an initial learning
rate, which typically the
optimizer shrinks as it runs.
And so you commonly want to
have the number it starts off
with beyond the larger
size because it'll
be shrinking as it goes.
OK.
So that's all by
way of introduction,
and I'm now ready to start
on language models and RNNs.
So what is language modeling?
I mean, as two words of
English, language modeling
could mean just about anything.
But in the natural language
processing literature,
language modeling has a very
precise technical definition,
which you should know.
So language modeling is
the task of predicting
the word that comes next.
So if you have some context
like the students opened there,
you want to be able to predict
what words will come next.
Is that their books, their
laptops, their exams,
their minds.
And so in particular,
what you want to be doing
is being able to
give a probability
that different words will
occur in this context.
So a language model is a
probability distribution
over next words given
a preceding context.
And a system that does that
is called a language model.
So as a result of that, you can
also think of a language model
as a system that
assigns a probability
score to a piece of text.
So if we have a piece
of text, then we
can just work out
its probability
according to a language model.
So the probability of
a sequence of tokens,
we can decompose via
the chain of probability
of the first times probability
of the second given
the first et cetera, et cetera.
And then we can work that
out using what our language
model provides as a product of
each probability of predicting
the next word.
OK.
Language models are
really the cornerstone
of human language technology.
Everything that you
do with computers
that involves human language,
you are using language models.
So when you're using
your phone and it's
suggesting, whether
well or badly,
what the next word that you
probably want to type is,
that's the language model
working to try and predict
the likely next words.
When the same thing
happens in a Google Doc
and it's suggesting a next
word or a next few words,
that's a language model.
The main reason why
the one in Google Docs
works much better than
the one on your phone
is that for the
keyboard phone models,
they have to be very compact
so that they can run quickly
on not much memory.
So they're sort of only
mediocre language models, where
something like Google Docs
can do a much better language
modeling job.
Query completion, same thing.
There's a language model.
And so then the
question is, well, how
do we build language models?
And so I briefly wanted
to first again give
the traditional answer
since you should
have at least some
understanding of how NLP was
done without a neural network.
And the traditional answer
that powered speech recognition
and other applications
for at least two decades,
three decades really, was what
were called n-gram language
models.
And these were a very simple,
but still quite effective idea.
So we want to give
probabilities of next words.
So what we're gonna
work with is what
are referred to as n-grams.
And so n-grams is just a
chunk of n consecutive words
which are usually referred to
as unigrams, bigrams, trigrams.
And then 4-grams and 5-grams.
A horrible set of names, which
would offend any humanist
but that's what
people normally say.
And so effectively what
we do is just collect
statistics about how often
different n-grams occur
in a large amount
of text and then
use those to build
a probability model.
So the first thing we
do is what's referred to
as making a Markov assumption.
So these are also referred
to as Markov models.
And we decide that the word
in position t plus 1 only
depends on the preceding
n minus 1 words.
So if we want to
predict t plus 1
given the entire preceding
text, we actually
throw away the early words
and just use the preceding n
minus 1 words as context.
Well, once we made
that simplification,
we can then just
use the definition
of conditional
probability and say all
that conditional probability
is the probability
of n words divided by the
preceding n minus 1 words.
And so we have the
probability of an n-gram
over the probability
of an n minus 1 gram.
And so then how do we
get these n-gram and n
minus 1 gram probabilities?
We simply take a large amount
of text in some language
and we count how often the
different n-grams occur.
And so our crude
statistical approximation
starts off as the count of
the n-gram over the count
of the n minus 1 gram.
So here's an example of that.
Suppose we are learning
a 4-gram language model.
OK.
So we throw away all words
apart from the last three words
and they're our conditioning.
We look in some large--
We use the counts from
some large training corpus
and we see how
often did students
open their books occur,
how often did students
open their minds occur.
And then for each
of those counts,
we divide through by the
count of how often students
open their occurred and that
gives us our probability
estimates.
So for example,
if in the corpus,
students open their
occurred 1,000 times,
students opened their
books occurred 400 times,
we'd get a probability
estimate of 0.4 for books.
If exams occurred 100 times,
we'd get 0.1 for exams.
And we sort of see here
already the disadvantage
of having made the
Markov assumption
and have gotten rid of all of
this earlier context, which
would have been useful
for helping us to predict.
The one other point
that I'll just
mention that I
confused myself on
is this count of the
n-gram language model.
So for a 4-gram
language model, it's
called a 4-gram language model.
Because in its
estimation, you're
using 4 grams in the
numerator and trigrams
in the denominator.
So you use the size
of the numerator.
So that terminology is
different to the terminology
that's used in Markov models.
So when people talk about
the order of a Markov model,
that refers to the amount
of context you're using.
So this would correspond to
a third order Markov model.
Yeah, so someone said is this
similar to a Naive Bayes model?
Sort of.
Naive Bayes models, you also
estimate the probabilities
just by counting.
So they're related and
they're sort of in some sense
two differences.
The first difference
or specialization
is that Naive Bayes
models work out
probabilities of words
independent of their neighbors.
So what in one part that a
Naive Bayes language model is
a unigram brand language model.
So you're just using the
counts of individual words.
But the other part of
a Naive Bayes model
is you're learning a different
set of unigram counts
for every class for
your classifier.
And so effectively
a Naive Bayes model
is you've got class specific
unigram language models.
Okay, I gave this as a
simple statistical model
for estimating
your probabilities
with an n-gram model.
You can't actually get away
with just doing that because you
have sparsity problems.
So it often will be the
case that for many words,
students open their
books or students opened
their backpacks just never
occurred in the training data.
That if you think about it,
if you have something like 10
to the 5th different words
even and you want to have then
a sequence of four
words and there
are 10 to the 5th
of each, there's
sort of 10 to the 20th
different combinations.
So unless you're seeing this
truly astronomical amount
of data, most four word
sequences you've never seen.
So then your numerator will be
0 and your probability estimate
will be 0.
And so that's bad.
And so the commonest
way of solving
that is just to add a little
delta to every count and then
everything is non-zero.
And that's called smoothing.
But well, sometimes
it's worse than that
because sometimes you won't even
have seen students open theirs.
And that's more
problematic, because that
means our denominator here
is 0 and so the division
will be ill-defined.
And we can't usefully calculate
any probabilities in a context
that we've never seen.
And so the standard solution to
that is to shorten the context
and that's called back off.
So we condition only
on opened their.
Or if we still haven't
seen the opened their,
we'll condition only on their.
Or we could just
forget all conditioning
and actually use a unigram
model for our probabilities.
Yeah, and so as you
increase the order n
of the n-gram language model,
these sparsity problems become
worse and worse.
So in the early days
people normally worked
with trigram models.
As it became easier to collect
billions of words of text,
people commonly moved
to 5-gram models.
But every time you go up
an order of conditioning,
you effectively need
to be collecting
orders of magnitude
more data because
of the size of the vocabularies
of human languages.
There's also a problem
that these models are huge.
So you basically
have to be caught
storing counts of all
of these word sequences
so you can work out
these probabilities.
And I mean, that's
actually had a big effect
on what terms of what
technology is available.
So in the 2000s decade up until
that, whenever it was, 2014,
that there was already
Google Translate using
probabilistic models that
included language models
of the n-gram
language model sort.
But the only way they could
possibly be run is in the cloud
because you needed to have these
huge tables of probabilities.
But now we have
neural nets and you
can have Google Translate just
actually run on your phone.
And that's possible,
because neural net models
can be massively more compact
than these old n-gram language
models.
But nevertheless, before we
get onto the neural models,
let's just sort of look at
an example of how these work.
So it's trivial to
train an n-gram language
model because you
really just count
how often word sequences
occur in a corpus,
and you're ready to go.
So these models can
be trained in seconds.
That's really good.
That's not like sitting around
for training neural networks.
So if I train on my laptop a
small language model, about 1.7
million words as
a trigram model,
I can then ask it
to generate text.
If I give it a couple
of words, today the,
I can then get it
to sort of suggest
a word that might come next.
And the way I do that
is the language model
knows the probability
distribution
of things that can come next.
Know that there's a kind of a
crude probability distribution.
I mean, because effectively over
this relatively small corpus,
there were things that occurred
once, Italian and emirate.
There are things that
occurred twice, price.
There were things that occurred
four times, company and bank.
It's sort of fairly
crude and rough.
But I nevertheless get
probability estimates.
I can then say,
OK, based on this,
let's take this
probability distribution
and then we'll just
sample the next word.
So the two most likely words
to sample are company or bank.
But we're rolling
the dice and we
might get any of the
words that had come next.
So maybe I sample price.
Now I will condition
on the price
and look up the
probability distribution
of what comes next.
The most likely thing is of.
And so again, I'll sample
and maybe this time I'll
pick up of.
And then I will now
condition on price of,
and I will look up the
probability distribution
of words following that.
And I get this
probability distribution.
And I'll sample randomly
some word from it
and maybe this time I'll
sample a rare but possible one
like gold.
And I can keep on
going, and I'll
get out something like this.
Today the price of gold per ton,
while production of shoe lasts
and shoe industry,
the bank intervened
just after it considered
and rejected the IMF demand
to rebuild depleted
European stocks, Sep 30 end
primary $0.76 a share.
So what just a
simple trigram model
can produce over
not very much text
is actually already
kind of interesting.
It's actually surprisingly
grammatical, right?
There are whole pieces of
it while production of shoe
lasts and shoe
industry, the bank
intervened just after it
considered and rejected
an IMF demand is really actually
pretty good grammatical text.
So it's sort of amazing that
these simple n-gram models
actually can model a
lot of human language.
On the other hand, it's not
a very good piece of text.
It's completely incoherent
and makes no sense.
And so to actually
be able to generate
text that seems
like it makes sense,
we're going to need a
considerably better language
model.
And that's precisely what neural
language models have allowed
us to build as we'll see later.
OK.
So how can we build a
neural language model?
And so first of all, we're
going to do a simple one
and then we'll see where we get.
But to move into
recurrent neural nets
might still take us
to the next time.
So we can have input
sequence of words
and we want a
probability distribution
over the next word.
The simplest thing
that we could try
is to say, well,
kind of the only tool
we have so far is a
window based classifier.
So what we've done previously,
either for our named entity
recognizer in lecture three
or what I just showed you
for the dependency parser is
we have some context window,
we put it through a neural
net and we predict something
as a classifier.
So before we were
predicting a location.
But maybe instead, we can reuse
exactly the same technology.
And say we're going to have
a window based classifier.
So we're discarding
the further away
words just like in a
n-gram language model,
but we'll feed this fixed
window into a neural net.
So we concatenate the
word embeddings, we put it
through a hidden layer and then
we have a softmax classifier
over our vocabulary.
And so now rather than
predicting something
like location or left arc
in the dependency parser,
we're going to have a softmax
over the entire vocabulary.
Sort of like we did with the
skip gram negative sampling
model in the first two lectures.
And so we're going
to see this choice
as predicting what
word that comes next,
whether it produces laptops,
minds, books, et cetera.
OK, so this is a fairly
simple fixed window
neural net classifier.
But this is essentially
a famous early model
in the use of neural nets
for NLP applications.
So first a 2000 conference
paper and then somewhat later,
journal paper.
Yoshua Bengio and colleagues
introduced precisely this model
as the neural probabilistic
language model.
And they were
already able to show
that this could give
interesting, good results
for language modeling.
And so it wasn't a great
solution for neural language
modeling, but it
still had value.
So it didn't solve the
problem of allowing
us to have bigger
contexts to predict what
words are going to come next.
It's in that way limited
exactly like an n-gram language
model is, but it does
have all the advantages
of distributed representations.
So rather than
having these counts
for words sequences that are
very sparse and very crude,
we can use distributed
representations of words
which then make predictions
that semantically similar words
should give similar
probability distributions.
So the idea of that is if
we use some other word here,
like maybe the pupils
opened their, well,
maybe in our training data we'd
seen sentences about students,
but we've never seen
sentences about pupils.
An n-gram language
model then would sort of
have no idea what
probabilities to use.
Whereas a neural
language model can say,
well pupils is kind of
similar to students.
Therefore, I can
predict similarly
to what I would have
predicted for students.
OK.
So there's now no
sparsity problem.
We don't need to store
billions of n-gram counts,
we simply need to
store our word vectors
and our W and new matrices.
But we still have the remaining
problems that our fixed window
is too small.
We can try and make
the window larger.
If we do that W, the
W matrix gets bigger.
But that also points out
another problem with this model.
Not only can the
window never be large
enough, but W is just
a trained matrix.
And so therefore, we're learning
completely different weights
for each position of context,
the word minus 1 position,
the word minus 2, the word
minus 3, and the word minus 4.
So that there's no sharing in
the model as to how it treats
words in different positions,
even though in some sense
they will contribute
semantic components
that are at least somewhat
position independent.
So again, if you
sort of think back
to either a Naive
Bayes model or what
we saw with the Word2Vec
model at the beginning,
the Word2Vec model
or Naive Bayes
model completely
ignores word order.
So it has one set of
parameters regardless of what
position things occur in.
That doesn't work well
for language modeling,
because word order is really
important in language modeling.
If the last word is the,
that's a really good predictor
of there being an adjective
or noun following where
the word four back is
the, it doesn't give you
the same information.
So you do want to somewhat
make use of word order.
But this model is
at the opposite
extreme that each
position is being modeled
completely independently.
So what we'd like to have
is a neural architecture
that can process an
arbitrary amount of context
and have more sharing
of the parameters
while still be
sensitive to proximity.
And so that's the idea of
recurrent neural networks.
And I'll say about five
minutes about these today.
And then next time we'll return
and do more about recurrent
neural networks.
So for the recurrent
neural network,
rather than having
a single hidden
layer inside our classifier
here that we compute each time,
for the recurrent
neural network we
have the hidden layer,
which is often referred
to as the hidden state.
But we maintain it over time
and we feed it back into itself.
So that's what
the word recurrent
is meaning, that you're sort of
feeding the hidden layer back
into itself.
So what we do is based
on the first word
we compute a hidden
representation, like before,
which can be used to
predict the next word.
But then for when
we want to predict
what comes after
the second word,
we not only feed
in the second word,
we feed in the hidden layer
from the previous word
to have it help predict
the hidden layer
above the second word.
And so formally the way
we're doing that is we're
taking the hidden layer
above the first word,
multiplying it by a
matrix W. And then
that's going to be going in
together with x2 to generate
the next hidden step.
And so we keep on
doing that at each time
step so that we're repeating
a pattern of creating
a next hidden layer
based on the next input
word and the
previous hidden state
by updating it by
multiplying it by a matrix W.
OK.
So on my slide here.
I've still only got
four words of context
because it's nice for my slide.
But in principle, there
could be any number
of words of context now.
OK.
So what we're doing
is that we start off
by having input
vectors, which can
be our word vectors that
we've looked up for each word.
So sorry, yeah, so we can
have the one hot vectors
for word identity.
We look up our word embedding,
so then we got word embeddings
for each word.
And then we want to
compute hidden states.
So we need to start
from somewhere.
h0 is the initial hidden
state, and h0 is normally
taken as a 0 vector.
So this is actually
just initialized to 0s.
And so for working out
the first hidden state,
we calculated based
on the first word's
embedding by multiplying this
embedding by a matrix, W_e,
and that gives us the
first hidden state.
But then as we go on, we want
to apply the same formula over
again.
So we have just two
parameter matrices
in the recurrent neural network.
One matrix for multiplying
input embeddings and one matrix
for updating the hidden
state of the network.
And so for the second word
from its word embedding,
we multiply it by
the W_e matrix.
We take the previous
time steps in state
and multiply it
by the W_h matrix.
And we use the two of those to
generate the new hidden state.
And precisely how we generate
the new hidden state is then
be shown on this
equation on the left.
So we take the previous hidden
state, multiply it by W_h.
We take the input embedding,
multiply it by W_e.
We sum those two, we add
on a learn bias weight.
And then we put that
through a non-linearity.
And although on this
slide that non-linearity
is written as sigma by far
the most common non-linearity
to use here actually is
a tanh non-linearity.
And so this is the core equation
for a simple recurrent neural
network.
And for each
successive time step,
we're just going
to keep on applying
that to work out hidden states.
And then from those
hidden states,
we can use them just like
in our window classifier
to predict what would
be the next word.
So at any position, we can
take this hidden vector, put it
through a softmax layer, which
is multiplying by u matrix
and adding on another bias
and then making a softmax
distribution out of that.
And that will then give the
probability distribution
over next words.
What we saw here, right,
this is the entire math
of a simple recurrent
neural network.
And next time I'll come back
and say more about them,
but this is the
entirety of what you
need to know in some
sense for the computation
of the forward model of a
simple recurrent neural network.
So the advantages we have
now as it can process
a text input of any length.
In theory at least,
it can use information
from any number of steps back.
We'll talk more
about in practice
how well that actually works.
The model size is fixed.
It doesn't matter how much
of a past context there is.
All we have is that
W_h and W_e parameters.
And at each time step, we
use exactly the same weights
to update our hidden state.
So there's asymmetry in
how different inputs are
processed in producing
our predictions.
RNNs in practice though,
the simple RNNs in practice
aren't perfect.
So a disadvantage is that
they're actually kind of slow.
Because with this recurrent
computation, in some sense
we are sort of stuck
with having to have
on the outside of for loop.
So we can do vector matrix
multiplies on the inside here,
but really we have to do
for time step equals 1
to n calculate the
success of hidden states.
And so that's not a perfect
neural net architecture
and we'll discuss
alternatives to that later.
And although in
theory this model
can access information
any number of steps
back, in practice
we find that it's
pretty imperfect at doing that.
And that will then lead
to more advanced forms
of recurrent neural
network that I'll
talk about next time that are
able to more effectively access
past context.
OK.
I think I'll stop
there for the day.