CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is part 5 in our
series on contextual word
representations.
We're going to be talking
about the ELECTRA model.
ELECTRA stands for efficiently
learning an encoder that
classifies token
replacements accurately,
which is a helpfully descriptive
breakdown of a colorfully
named model.
Recall that I finished
the BERT screencast
by identifying some known
limitations of the BERT model.
ELECTRA is really keying
into 2 and 3 in that list.
So the second one identified
by the BERT authors
is just that of
the MLM objective,
they say we're creating a
mismatch between pre-training
and fine-tuning since the MASK
token that we use is never
seen during fine-tuning.
So ideally for the
model we fine-tune,
we would make no
use of a MASK token.
Devlin et al also observed
of the MLM objective
that it has a downside.
We make predictions
about only 15%
of the tokens in each batch.
We have an intuition that
that's a pretty inefficient use
of the data we have
available to us.
Ideally, we would
make more predictions,
and ELECTRA seeks to make good
on that intuition as well.
So let's dive into the
core model structure.
Here we'll use a simple example.
We have an input
token sequence x.
The chef cooked the meal.
And as usual with BERT, we can
MASK out some of those tokens,
and then have a BERT
or BERT-like model
try to reconstruct
those MASK tokens.
However, we're going to
do that with a twist.
Instead of always trying to
learn the actual input token,
we're going to sample tokens
proportional to the generator
probabilities so that sometimes
the actual token will be input
as with the case
with "the" here.
And sometimes it will
be some other token,
as the case with "cook" going
to "ate" in this position.
Now the job of ELECTRA,
the discriminator here,
is to figure out
which of those tokens
were in the original
input sequence
and which have been replaced.
So that's a binary
prediction task,
and we can make it about all
of the tokens in our input
sequence if we choose to.
Actual loss for ELECTRA is
the sum of the generator loss
and a weighted version
of the ELECTRA, that
is the discriminator loss.
However, that's kind of
masking an important asymmetry
in this model here.
Once we have trained
the generator,
we can let it fall away and
do all of our fine-tuning
on the discriminator.
That is on the
ELECTRA itself, which
means that we'll be
fine-tuning a model that never
saw any of those MASK tokens.
So we address that first
limitation of BERT.
And we're also going to make
a prediction with ELECTRA
about every single one of
the input tokens, which
means that we're making more
use of the available data.
One thing I really like
about the ELECTRA paper
is that it offers a really
rich set of analyses
of the efficiency of the model
and of its optimal design.
So I'm going to highlight some
of those results here starting
with this
generator/discriminator
relationship results.
So the authors observe
that where the generator
and discriminator
are the same size,
they can share all their
transformer parameters.
They can kind of be
one model in essence.
And they find that more
sharing is indeed better, which
is encouraging.
However, they also observed
that the best results
come from having a
generator that is small
compared to the discriminator.
And this plot kind of
summarizes the evidence there.
So we have our GLUE
score as the goal posts
that we're going to use
to assess these models.
That's along the y-axis.
Along the x-axis, we
have the generator size.
And then they've
plotted out a few sizes
for the discriminator.
And I think what you
can see quite clearly
is that, in general, you get
the best results on GLUE where
the discriminator is
two to three times
larger than the generator.
And that's true even for this
very small model in green
down here.
The results are
overall not very good,
but we see that
same relationship
where the optimal
discriminator is
at size 256 and the
generator at size 64.
That's where we reach
our peak results.
And it's kind of comparable to
this very large model in blue
where our optimal size
for the discriminator
is 768 compared to
256 for the generator.
They also do a bunch of
really interesting efficiency
analyses.
One thing I like
about the paper is
that it's kind of oriented
toward figuring out
how we can train these models
more efficiently with fewer
compute resources.
And this is a kind of
summary of central evidence
that they offer that ELECTRA
can be an efficient model.
So again we're going
to use along the y-axis
the GLUE score as
our goal posts.
Along the x-axis, here we
have pre-training FLOPs.
So this would be the number
of compute operations
that you need to
pre-train the model.
In blue, along the
top here, is ELECTRA.
It's the very best model.
In orange, just below it,
is adversarial ELECTRA,
which is an interesting approach
to ELECTRA where we essentially
train the generator to try
to fool the discriminator as
opposed to having the two
cooperate as in core ELECTRA,
and that turns out
to be pretty good.
And also these green lines
are really interesting.
So two-stage ELECTRA is where
I start by training just
against the BERT objectives.
And at a certain
point, switch over
to training the
ELECTRA objective.
And you can see that even that
is better than just continuing
on with BERT all the
way up to the maximum
for our compute budget here.
The paper also explores a bunch
of variations on the ELECTRA
objective itself.
So I presented to
you full ELECTRA.
And it's full
ELECTRA in the sense
that over here on
the right we're
making predictions
about every single one
of the tokens in the input.
We could also explore something
that was analogous to BERT.
ELECTRA 15% would be the case
where we make predictions
only about tokens that were
way back here in the input
x-masked actually masked out.
Another variant that the
team considered actually
relates to how we train BERT.
So recall that for BERT
we train both by masking
and by replacing some
tokens with other randomly
chosen tokens.
And we could try training
the generator just
with that approach, which
would eliminate the MASK
token entirely.
So that's this
area here where we
have no masking on x-masked
but rather just randomly
replace tokens from
the actual vocabulary.
And then finally all tokens
MLM would adopt some ideas
from ELECTRA into
the BERT model.
So recall that for
the MLM object,
we essentially turned it off
for tokens that weren't masked.
But there's no principal
reason why we're doing that.
We could, of course,
have the loss
apply to every single one of
the tokens in the input stream.
And that gives us all tokens
MLM on the generator side.
And the central finding
of the paper I suppose
is that ELECTRA is the best
of all of these models.
You also have a
really good model
if you do all-tokens MLM, which
is something that might inform
development on the BERT
side, in addition to
BERT in the context of ELECTRA.
Replace MLM is less good.
And ELECTRA 15% kind of down
there at the bottom there.
BERT, I think this is
kind of showing us that we
should make more predictions.
That was a guiding
intuition for ELECTRA.
And it seems to be borne
out by these results.
And finally, as is
common in the space,
the ELECTRA team did
some model releases
of pre-trained parameters
that you can make use of.
They did ELECTRA base
and ELECTRA large,
which is kind of comparable
to the corresponding BERT
releases.
I think an
interesting thing they
did is also released this
ELECTRA small model which
is designed to quickly be
trained on a single GPU,
again tying into the idea
that we ought to be thinking
about how we can train models
like this when we have highly
constrained compute resources.
ELECTRA was keyed into that
idea from the very beginning.
I think the small model shows
that it can be productive.