CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome back, everyone.
This is part 6 in our
series on Contextual Word
Representations.
We're going to be talking
about practical fine tuning.
It's time to get hands-on
with these parameters we've
been talking about.
So here's the guiding idea.
Your existing architecture, say,
for the current original system
and bake off
probably can benefit
from contextual representation.
We've seen that in
many, many contexts
and I know you
know these things.
The notebook fine
tuning shows you
how to bring in transformer
representations in two ways.
First, with simple
featurization, and then
with full-on fine tuning.
And I'm going to talk about both
of those in this screencast.
The heart of this idea is
that by extending existing
PyTorch modules from the
course code distribution,
you can very easily create
customized fine tuning models
with just a few lines of code.
And that should be really
empowering in terms
of exploring lots
of different designs
and seeing how best to use these
parameters for your problem.
I just want to
mention that really
and truly, this is only possible
because of the amazing work
that the Hugging
Face team has done
to make these parameters
accessible to all of us.
So let's start with
simple featurization.
And I actually want to
rewind to our discussion
of recurrent neural networks
and think about how we represent
examples for those models.
In the standard mode, we have
as our examples lists of tokens
here.
We convert those into
lists of indices,
and those indices
help us look up
vector representations of those
words in some fixed embedding
space.
And the result of that is that
each example is represented
by a list of vectors.
That's important
to keep in mind.
We tend to think of
the model as taking
as its inputs lists of tokens
and having an embedding.
But from the point of
view of the model itself,
it really wants to process
as inputs lists of vectors.
And that's the empowering
idea because if we use it
in fixed embedding, of course,
then these two occurrences of A
will be the same
vector, and these two
occurrences of B across examples
will be the same vector.
But the model
doesn't really care
that there's a same vector.
We could, if we wanted
to, convert directly
from token sequences into
lists of vectors using
a device like a BERT model.
And that would allow that
A in the first position
and A in the third
could correspond
to different vectors, or B
across these two examples
might correspond to
different vectors.
That would be the
contextual representation
part of these models.
And again, from the
point of view of the RNN,
we can feed these indirectly.
That's straight forward.
This is a complete
recipe for doing
that using the SST
code and the PyTorch
modules from the course
code distribution.
So you can see that beyond
the setup stuff which we've
done a few times, the
feature function is just
going to use BERT functionality
to look up the example's
indices and then convert them
into vector representations.
And here, as a
summary, we're going
to use the representation
above the class token.
But lots of things are
possible at that point.
And then when we have
our model wrapper here,
we set up a Torch
RNN Classifier.
And there're just
two things of note.
First, we say use
embedding equals false,
because we're going to
feed vectors in directly.
There's no embedding
involved here.
And we also don't need
to have a vocabulary.
You could specify
one, but it's not
involved because
fundamentally, again,
the model deals
directly with vectors.
And then at SST
experiment, you, again,
say vectorized equals false.
And that is a complete
recipe for bringing
in BERT representations
with the standard RNN.
This isn't quite
fine tuning though,
so let's think about how
we might get added benefits
from actually updating those
BERT parameters as opposed
to just using them as
frozen representations
inputs to another model.
What I'd encourage
you to do is think
about subclassing the
PyTorch modules that
are included in our
course code distribution.
Because then, you will be able
to write code, just oriented
toward your model
architecture, and a lot
of the details of optimization
and data processing
will be handled for you.
This is, I hope, a
powerful example of that.
It comes from the tutorial
PyTorch models notebook.
It's a Torch Softmax
Classifier, and the only thing
we have to do is rewrite this
build_graph function to specify
one single dense layer.
We are using as our base
class the Torch Shallow Neural
Classifier which
handles everything else
about setting up this
model and optimizing it.
If we wanted to go in
the other direction
and instead fit a
really deep model,
we could, again, begin from
Torch Shallow Neural Classifier
and rewrite the build_graph
function so that it just
has more layers, essentially.
And then what's happening
in this init method
is we're just giving
the user access
to the various hyperparameters
that they could
choose to set up this model.
Finally, here's a
more involved example.
This one, we start with a
PyTorch NN module, kind of all
the way down at the base here.
This is a Torch Linear
Regression model.
We set up the weight
parameters here
and then we have this
single forward pass,
which corresponds
to the structure
of a simple linear regression.
Now, for the actual
interface, we
need to do a little
bit more work here.
So we set up the
loss so that it's
appropriate for our
regression model.
So most of the classifiers we've
been looking at up until now.
build_graph just
uses the NN module
that I showed you a second ago.
We need to do a little bit
of work in build_dataset
and rewrite that so we
process linear regression
data correctly.
And then we do need to
rewrite the predict and score
functions to be kind of good
citizens of the code base
and allow for hyperparameter
optimization and cross
validation and so forth.
But that's, again,
straightforward,
and fundamentally for predict
we're actually making use
of the base class's _predict
method for the heavy lifting
there.
And then score, of course, is
just moving us out of the mode
of evaluating classifiers and
into the mode of evaluating
regression models.
That's all you need to do.
And again, conspicuously
absent from this
is most of the aspects
of data processing
and all of the details
of optimization.
The base class Torch
model base here
has a very full
featured fit method
that you can use to
optimize these models
and do hyperparameter
exploration.
And that brings us to the
star of the show, which
would be BERT fine tuning
with Hugging Face parameters.
Here we'll start with
a PyTorch nn.module.
We load in a BERT module
as we've done before,
and make sure to set it to
train so that it can be updated.
And then the new
parameters here are really
just this classifier
layer, a dense layer
that's going to be oriented
toward the classification
structure that we want
our model to have.
The forward method
calls the forward method
of the BERT model, and you get
a bunch of representations.
There are a lot of options here.
What I've decided to do is just
use the Hugging Face Pooler
Output, which is some
parameters on top
of the class token as the
input to the classifier.
When we optimize this model,
with luck in a productive way,
not only will these classifier
parameters be updated, but also
all the parameters
of this BERT model
that you loaded
in in train mode.
The interface is a
little bit involved here.
So what we do is
provide the user
with some flexibility
about what choices to make.
build_graph, again just
loads in the module
that I showed you
just a second ago.
And then build_dataset
is a bit involved.
But what we do fundamentally is
use the BERT tokenizer to batch
encode our data.
And then we do a little bit
of processing on the output
labels to make sure PyTorch
can make sense of them.
That's really it.
In the heart of this, it's
just that we're, again,
using Hugging Face
functionality to represent
our data to the BERT model.
And then this is the
really interesting part.
Calling the forward
method and then fitting
the classifier on top is
pretty much all you need to do.
And of course, that opens
up a world of options.
Reps here has lots
of other things
that you could use as the
input to this classifier layer.
And many of them
actually might be
more productive than the simple
approach that I've taken here.