CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is part two in our
series on grounded language
understanding.
Our task for this unit is
essentially a natural language
generation task.
And I've called those
speakers, the idea
is that speakers go
from the world, that
is some non-linguistic
thing that they're
trying to communicate
about, into language.
Those are really the central
agents that will be explored.
To ground all this, we're
going to have a simple task.
I'm going to start with the
most basic version of the task
that we'll ultimately tackle
in our assignment and bake-off.
And that is color reference.
So these are examples taken from
a corpus that was originally
collected by Randall
Munroe of XKCD fame,
and processed into an NLP task
by McMahan and Stone 2015.
And it's a simple
formulation in that
the state of the world we
want to communicate about
is a color patch.
And the task is simply
to produce descriptions
of those color patches.
Now I've given
some examples here.
And you can see that they
range from simple one word
descriptions, all
the way up to things
that are kind of complicated
both cognitively and
linguistically, and I
think point to the idea
that even though this is a
simple and constrained domain,
it's a pretty cognitively and
linguistically interesting one.
So our speakers, at least
our baseline speakers,
are standard versions of
encoder decoder models.
We're going to have for this
initial formulation a very
simple encoder.
The task of the
encoder is simply
to take a color
representation, which
is going to be a list of floats
embedded in some embedding
space, and then learn some
hidden representation for that
color.
And that's all that
needs to happen.
So it's just one step.
The decoder is where the
speaking part happens.
So the initial token produced
by the decoder, by the speaker,
is always the start
token which is looked up
in an embedding space.
And then we get our first
decoder hidden state,
which is created from
the color representation
of the initial hidden
state in the sequence we're
going to build, together
with an embedding.
And both of those have
weight transformations.
And it's an additive
combination of them
that delivers this
value h1 here.
Then we use some
softmax parameters
to make a prediction
about the next token.
Here we've predicted "dark."
And we get our error signal
by comparing that prediction
with the actual token that
occurred in our training data.
In this case, it was
the word "light."
So since we made a
wrong prediction,
we're going to get a substantive
error signal that will then,
we hope, update the
weight parameters
throughout this
model in a way that
leads them to produce better
generations the next time.
In a little more detail,
just as a reminder.
So we have an embedding
for that start token,
and indeed for all tokens.
The hidden state is derived
from the embedding via a weight
transformation, and the
color representation, which
is state h0 in the recurrence
that we're building.
And that too has
a transformation
applied to it, to travel
through the hidden layer.
That gives us the state H1.
And then we have
softmax parameters
on top of that h1 that
make a prediction.
The prediction that they
make is a prediction
over the entire vocabulary.
And the probability
of the actual token
gives us our error signals.
So the probability of
"light" is the error signal
that we'll use here to
update the model parameters.
And then we begin with
the next timestep.
I've called this
teacher forcing,
because in the standard mode,
which is the teacher forcing
mode, even though we
predicted 'dark' at timestep 1
we're going to have
as our second token,
the token "light" which is the
actual token in the underlying
training data.
And we'll proceed as though
we did not make a mistake.
So again, we do an
embedding look up,
we get our second hidden
state for the decoder, that's
a combination of
the embedding x 37
and the previous student state,
and we make another prediction.
And in this case, our
prediction is "blue"
and that's the actual token.
And life is good
for a little bit.
And then we proceed
with a third timestep.
The actual token is "blue" h3.
We predict "green."
And in this case, we
should have predicted
the stop token which
would cause us to stop
processing the sequence.
We're just going to get an error
signal as we steadily would
and propagate that back down
through the model in hopes
that the next time,
when we want to stop,
we'll actually produce this stop
token that I've given up here.
At prediction time, of course
the sequence is not given.
That doesn't change the
encoder because the color
representation is part
of the model inputs.
So then we have
to decode and just
describe without any feedback.
So we proceed as we did before
and we predict "dark" here.
And then "dark" has to become
the token at the next timestep
because we don't know
what the ground truth is.
And we proceed as
before and say "blue."
And then that becomes
the third time step,
and with luck, there
in that third position,
we predict the stop token.
And the decoding
process is completed.
That is the fundamental model.
Even though it's
simple, it admits
of many interesting
modifications.
Let me just mention
a few of them.
First, the encoder and
the decoder, of course,
could have many
more hidden layers.
Mine just had one.
But they could be
very deep networks.
We would expect that
the layer counts
for the encoder and
the decoder match
so that you have this even
handoff from encoder to decoder
across all the hidden layers.
But even that's not
a hard constraint.
I can imagine that some
pooling or copying could
accommodate different numbers
of layers and these two
components.
It's very common at
present for researchers
to tie the embedding and
classifier parameters, right?
The embedding gives
us a representation
for every vocabulary item.
And the transpose
of that can serve
as the set of parameters
for a softmax classifier
when we predict tokens.
And tying those weights seems
to be very productive in terms
of optimization effectiveness.
So you might consider that.
And finally, during
training, we might
drop that teacher
forcing assumption,
which would mean that in a
small percentage of cases,
we would allow the model to just
proceed as though its predicted
token was the correct token
for the next time step,
even if that was a faulty
assumption, on the idea
that that might help the
model explore a wider
range of the space
and inject generations
with some helpful diversity.
And then there's one
other modification
that I want to
mention, because you'll
see this as part of the
homework and the system
that you're developing.
So we found that
in Monroe et al.
2016, it was helpful
to remind the decoder
at each one of its
timesteps about what
it was trying to describe.
So in more detail, we had
HSV color representations
as our inputs.
We did a Fourier transform
to get an embedding.
And that was processed
into a hidden state.
And then during
decoding, we appended
to each one of the embeddings
the Fourier transformation
representation of the color
as a kind of informal reminder
at each timestep about what
the input was actually like,
on the assumption that for
long sequences where we get all
the way down to the
end, the model might
have a hazy memory of what
it's trying to describe.
And this functions as a kind
of reminder at that point.
And that proved to
be very effective,
and I'll encourage you to
explore that in the homework.
And then I hope you can see
that even though this task
formulation is simple, it's
an instance of a wide range
of tasks that we might explore
under the heading of grounding.
After all, for
grounding in this sense,
we just need some non-linguistic
representation coming in,
and the ideas that will
generate language in response
to that input.
So image captioning is
an instance of this.
Scene description, of
course, is another instance.
Visual question answering
is a slight modification
where the input is
not just an image,
but also a question
text and the idea
is that you want to produce
an answer to that question
relative to the image input.
And then instruction giving
would be a more general form
where the input is some
kind of state description
and the idea is that we want to
offer a complicated instruction
on that basis.
And I think we can think
of many others that
would fit into this
mold and benefit
not only from the encoder
decoder architecture,
but also from
conceptualization explicitly
as grounded natural
language generation tasks.