CHRIS POTTS: Welcome, everyone.
This is part 4 in our series
on Natural Language Inference.
We're going to be talking about
different modeling strategies.
You might think of this
screencast as a companion
to the associated
notebook that explores
a lot of different
modeling ideas
and suggests some architectural
variations that you
might explore yourself.
I thought we would start by just
considering hand-built feature
functions because they can still
be quite powerful for the NLI
problem.
So some standard
hand-built feature ideas
include, as a kind
of baseline, word
overlap between the
premise and hypothesis.
This is giving you a kind of
pretty small feature space,
essentially measuring how the
premise and hypothesis are
alike.
If you want to
step it up a level,
you could consider the word
cross-product features,
which you just consider
as its feature space
every pairing of a word
in the premise and a word
in the hypothesis.
This will give you a
massive feature space.
Very large.
Very sparse, but the
intuition behind it
might be that you're
allowing your model a chance
to discover points of
alignment, and disalignment
between the premise
and the hypothesis.
And so that could
be very powerful.
You might also consider
additional WordNet relations,
bringing those in.
These would be things
like entailment,
and contradiction,
antonomy, synonymy.
And those of course,
could be nicely keyed
into the underlying
logic of the NLI problem.
Edit distance is another
common feature and just
a raw float valued between
premise and hypothesis
as a kind of high level way
of comparing those two texts.
Word differences might
be a nice juxtaposition
with word overlap.
You could be considering
ways in which
the premise and the
hypothesis contrast
with each other in
that feature space.
And we have had also moved
to alignment-based features.
I mentioned that
word cross-product
is kind of an attempt
to have the model learn
points of alignment between
the premise and hypothesis.
But of course, we can also
do some things kind of
even before we begin to
learn feature rates, trying
to figure out which
pieces in the premise
correspond to which
pieces in the hypothesis.
We could consider negation.
We've seen of course that that's
an important indicator function
in a lot of NLI data sets.
There's a powerful
intuition behind that,
especially as it pertains
to contradiction.
And so maybe, we would
write some feature functions
that were explicitly
keyed in to the presence
or absence of negation
in various spots
in the premise and hypothesis.
And we can also step
that up a level as well
and consider, more
generally, all kinds
of different interesting
quantifier relationships that
would hold possibly at the level
of an alignment as in item 6
here between the
premise and hypothesis.
And this is kind of keyed into
the underlying logic of the NLI
problem.
And then finally, named
entity recognition.
We've seen that
these features might
be important in
figuring out which
entities co-refer across
the premise and hypotheses.
And so having some devices
for figuring that out
could be useful as a kind
of low level grounding
for your system.
Now let's move
into a mode that's
more like the deep learning
mode because as we saw earlier
in this screencast series,
these models have proven that
at this point to be the most
powerful models for the NLI
problem.
So it's productive to think also
about different deep learning
architectures.
And I'd like to start with
what I've called here,
sentence encoding models.
And the most basic
form of that would
return to the idea of
distributed representations
as features.
So the idea here is that we
have in this diagram the premise
and the hypothesis.
So the premise is,
"Every dog danced,"
then the hypothesis is,
"Every poodle moved."
And our approach using
distributed representations,
the simplest one,
would be that we're
going to simply look
up all of those words
in some fixed embedding space,
which would be like a GloVe
embedding space, for example.
And then we're
going to separately
encode the premise and
hypothesis by, for example,
doing the sum or
average of the vectors
in each of those two texts.
And so that gives us
a vector xp and xh.
And then we might
concatenate those two
or do something, some
other kind of comparison
like difference,
or max, or mean,
to get a single
fixed dimensional
representation x that is
then the input to a kind of,
could be a simple
softmax classifier.
So all we've done here
is take our old approach
using distributed
representations as features
and move it into
the NLI problem,
where we have both the
premise and hypothesis.
And I've called this a
sentence encoding model
because we are separately
encoding the two sentences.
And then the model is
going to learn, we hope,
something about how those
two representations interact.
On this slide and the next,
I've given a complete recipe
for doing exactly
what I just described.
I'm not going to
linger over it here
because it's also
in the notebooks.
And it just shows you how
using our course code--
it can be relatively easy
to set up models like this.
Most of the code is devoted
to doing the low level
processing of the words
into their embedding space.
Here's the rationale for
sentence-encoding models.
I think this is kind
of interesting, right?
We might want to encode
the premise and hypothesis
separately in order to
give the model a chance
to find rich abstract
relationships between them.
The sentence encoding approach
might also facilitate transfer
to other kinds of tasks,
right, to the extent
that we are separately
encoding the two sentences.
We might have sentence
level representations
that are useful
even for problems
that don't fit into the
specific NLI mode of having
a single premise and
a single hypothesis
for the sake of classification.
And that can be
an important part
of that vision from
Dagan et al that NLI
is a kind of source of
effective pretraining for more
general problems.
Let's move to a
more complex model.
We'll follow the same narrative
that we've used before.
We just had that
simple fixed model
that was going to
combine the premise
and hypothesis via
some fixed function,
like sum, or average, or max.
Here, we're going
to have functions
that learn about how those
interactions should happen,
but we're going to follow
the sentence encoding mode.
So I have our same example.
"Every dog danced," and,
"Every poodle moved."
And the idea is that
each one of those
is processed by its own,
separate recurrent neural
network.
And I've indicated in green that
although these two models would
have the same structure,
these are different parameters
for the premise and hypothesis.
So they function separately and
then in the simplest approach,
we would take the final hidden
representation from each
of those and combine
them somehow,
probably would be
a concatenation.
And that would be the input
to the final classifier
layer or layers that actually
learn the NLI problem.
So it's a sentence-encoding
approach in the sense
that h3 and hd are taken to
be kind of separate summary
representations of the premise
and hypothesis respectively.
And we have a vision that
those representations
might be independently useful
even outside of the NLI
context.
Now, in the associated
notebook, nli_02_models,
there are a bunch of different
implementations including
a full PyTorch implementation
using R PyTorch based classes
of the sentence-encoding
RNN approach
that I just described to you.
And I thought I would just
briefly give you a high level
overview of how that
modeling approach works
because they're actually
just a few moving pieces.
And the rest is kind of low
level implementation details.
So the first thing
that you need to do
is modify the dataset class
so that conceptually, it
is going to create lists
of pairs of examples
with their lengths and
their associated labels.
By default, the underlying
code that we're using
expects one sequence of tokens,
one length, and one label.
And here, we just
need to raise that
up so that we have two
as you can see here.
Every dog danced.
Every poodle moved.
Both happened to have length 3,
and their label is entailment.
So we make some changes
to the dataset class
to accommodate that change
in format, essentially.
Then the core model for this
is conceptually just two RNNs.
And the forward method
is just essentially,
bringing those two pieces
together and feeding them
to the subsequent
classifier layers.
And so that's very
conceptually natural,
and it's just down to having
two separate RNNs that you
implement using the raw
materials that are already
there in the code.
And then finally for the actual
interface, the TorchRNNSentence
EncoderClassifier,
this is basically
unchanged with the
one modification
that you need to change
the predict problem
method, the fundamental
method for prediction,
because it too needs to deal
with this different dataset
format that we've
established up here.
And that is, again, a
kind of low level change.
And so what I hope
you're seeing is
that the first and third steps
are kind of managing the data.
And the middle step is
the one that actually
modifies the computation graph.
But that step is very intuitive
because we're basically,
just reflecting encode--
our idea that we have
separate RNNs for the premise
and hypothesis.
And then finally, I
just want to mention
that a common approach
you see, especially
in the early literature, is a
sentence-encoding TreeNN that
has exactly the same intuition
behind it as the RNNs
that we just looked at, except
that the premise and hypothesis
are processed by tree structured
recursive neural networks.
And since the
underlying dataset often
have full parse representations,
this is an avenue
that you could explore.
It can be tricky to
implement these efficiently,
but conceptually, it's a kind
of very natural thing, where
you just repeatedly
have a dense layer
at every one of the
constituent nodes
on up to a final
representation here, pb and pd.
That is then then fed
into the classifier layer
in just the way we've done
for the previous models.
So those are the sentence
including RNNs, now let's move
to a different vision.
And I've called
these change models
because they're going
to just mush together
the premise and hypothesis, as
opposed to separately encoding
the two.
Of course, the simplest thing
we could do in the chain mode
would be to essentially
ignore the fact that we
have two text, the
premise and hypothesis
and just feed them in
as one long sequence
into a standard
recurrent neural network.
And since that
involves no changes
to any of the code we've been
using for RNN classifiers,
it seems like a pretty
natural baseline.
And so that's depicted
here and actually this
can be surprisingly
effective, all right?
The rationale for doing this?
In this context here, you could
say that the premise is simply
establishing context for
processing the hypothesis.
And that seems like
a very natural notion
of conditioning on one text
as you process the second one.
And correspondingly, at
the level of human language
processing, this might actually
correspond to something
that we do as we read through
a premise hypothesis text,
and figure out what
the relationship is.
And here's a simple
recipe for doing this.
The one change from the diagram
that you might think about
is that I did when
representing the examples here.
Flatten them, out
of course, but also,
insert this boundary marker.
That would at least
give the model
a chance to learn that
there was a separation
happening, some kind of
transition between the premise
and hypothesis.
But that's at just the
level of feature causation
and in terms of modeling.
You hardly need to make
any changes in order
to run this kind of experiment.
We can also think
about a modification
that would bring together
sentence encoding with chains.
And this would be where we have
two sets of RNN parameters--
one for the premise and
one for the hypothesis.
But we nonetheless
chain them together
instead of separately
encoding them.
So as before, I have a
premise RNN in green.
I have a hypothesis
RNN in purple.
They have the same structure but
different learned parameters.
And the handoff is essentially,
that the initial hidden
state for the hypothesis--
is the final output
state for the premise.
And then that way, you
get a seamless transition
between these two models.
And this would allow
the models in space
to learn that premise,
tokens, and premise sequences,
have a different
status than those
that appear in the hypothesis.
And let me just
close by mentioning
a few other strategies because
this is by no means exhaustive,
but it's kind of interesting at
the high level of architecture
thinking about sentence encoding
versus these chained models.
So first, the
TorchRNN Classifier
feeds its hidden state directly
to the classifier layer.
But we have options like
bidirectional equals true,
which would use as the summary
representation-- both the final
and the initial hidden states,
essentially, and feed those
into the classifier.
So it's a different notion
of sentence encoding
or of sequence encoding.
And other ideas here, right?
So we could, instead
of restricting,
just to one or a few
of the final states
do some kind of pooling
with max or mean across all
of the output states.
And different
pooling options can
be combined with
different versions
of these models, either
sentence encoding or chained.
We could also, of course,
have additional hidden layers
between the classifier
layer and the embedding.
I've shown you just one
for the sake of simplicity,
but deeper might be better
especially for the very large
NLI datasets that we have.
And finally, an important
source of innovation
in this and many other
spaces is the idea
of adding attention
mechanisms to these models.
And that's such
an important idea
that I'm going to save it
for the next screencast
in the series.