Welcome, everyone, to
the first screencast
in our NLU and information
retrieval series.
The goal of this introductory
screencast is twofold.
I will first
introduce the IR area.
Then I will discuss ways
in which NLU and IR can
interact productively and
focus on how retrieval
can be an effective component
in defining our NLU tasks
and building our NLU systems.
So what is information
retrieval or IR?
To a first approximation,
this is the field
concerned with search.
The first example that typically
comes to mind is web search.
But as we'll see
today, this field
extends richly beyond web search
and has strong connections
to our work with NLU.
Let's now attempt to
define IR more formally.
Here is a simplified
version of the definition
used by the Introduction to
IR book by Manning et al.
They define IR as the process of
finding material that fulfills
an information need from
within a large collection
of unstructured documents.
Let's unpack this definition.
Starting on the
left-hand side here,
the definition says that we're
concerned with finding material
from a large collection.
In other words, large scale
search is at the essence of IR.
On the right-hand
side, the definition
restricts this to unstructured
documents, basically items
like text, media,
and products, ones
that lack the clear
cut structure of things
like database tables or graphs.
Structure-based search or
structure-based traversal
of graphs and databases are
not typically considered
IR problems for our purposes,
although, of course,
they're interesting
on their own right.
This leads us to
the term that was
at the center of our definition,
namely the information need.
It is difficult to think
of IR without thinking
of the user at the
center of the system.
And the information need
is what the user has in
mind to solve a task or
otherwise learn or reach
the material that
they are looking for.
The goal of a search system is
first to identify and fulfill
the user's information need.
So whatever we
retrieve is only going
to be considered
relevant to the extent
that it advances this goal.
In most IR tasks, the
user would explicitly
provide us with a query that
summarizes and expresses
their information need.
It is very important to note
that this query may contain
ambiguity, may miss
some important details,
or might even sometimes
ask the wrong question.
And that's completely normal.
The user may not even be
sure what precisely they're
looking for.
That's why they're
searching for something.
And so, we must rely on
our knowledge of the task
and whatever we know about the
user within the constraints
of our application in
order to solve IR problems.
The second thing is that typical
information needs vary by task.
And so the typical
information need that we have
and how to best interpret
and deal with that,
these are factors
that vary greatly
by task and by
collection type in IR.
I'll take it you've already
made the connection between IR
and searching the web,
searching your email,
and also finding files in your
desktop buried in deep folders
or something.
But there are plenty of other IR
tasks where search is crucial.
For instance, you
might want to find
recent papers related to the
BERT paper by Devlin et al.
Of course, this is
not the best example
because there are many,
many papers related
to BERT these days.
But in any case, in
this case, your query
might be the full text
of the BERT paper,
and the system might
try to search the ACL
anthology and the
computational language
section of archives for some
of their papers to BERT.
Recommendation is
another key IR topic.
In recommendation, we still
seek relevant material
from a large collection
of unstructured items,
but, in this case, the
user has no explicit query.
And instead, the
previous interactions
enabled the recommendation
system to suggest the matches.
Patent search is
yet another IR task.
And unlike the others
we've mentioned so far,
it's often used by experts,
not by average users,
and it has very strong
emphasis on hierarchy.
So unlike the average
web query where
you might be completely content
with one very good match
at the top, patent
search may need
to find every relevant patent
to a query or something that
approximates that.
Lastly, even buying a new
laptop can be an IR problem.
And in particular, a
conversation of an IR problem.
Here, the system may go
in a back and forth style
between searching
for relevant products
and asking the user for their
preferences about cost, screen
quality, and storage,
and other factors
on online e-commerce platforms.
Having looked at all
of these IR tasks,
it's important to keep in
mind that each of those tasks
poses its own unique challenges.
So even though we're always
interested in relevance
and in finding relevant
items, each of those tasks
has its own challenges
and its own components.
To underscore this,
let's use web search
as a frame of reference.
While standard web search might
pose considerable challenge
when it comes to the massive
scale involved in terms
of documents and also
queries, even something
as seemingly mundane as
searching for conversations
on your Slack
workspace often lacks
key features that
makes web search
tractable in the
first place and makes
it work the way it does
in the first place.
For one, so many web searches
ask frequently searched or head
queries.
The sheer popularity
of head queries
makes them an easy target
for large search engines.
Of course, there's always a long
tail of various search queries
that still pose considerable
challenge, especially
in highly technical
domains, but it still
stands that, in a
domain like web search,
solving the head queries
gets you a very big part,
a very big share of
answering most user queries.
There's another factor.
Web search enjoys highly
redundant documents
out there that
address common topics,
where each document is written
in a slightly different way.
This often shifts the search
problem into a precision one--
basically finding some
documents, at least
one, that definitely match
the query, as opposed
to a recall one--
finding every document
that matches the query
because there's already
too many of them.
Clearly, this is
not always the case
if you're looking for a very
specific item in your Slack
conversation and history.
Yet another factor in web search
is the rich link structure
that links between existing
related web pages, which
again introduces more hierarchy
and might make this task more
tractable in practice.
The idea here is definitely
not that web search is easy
because it's not easy.
But the different tasks
pose different challenges
for our IR systems.
So that is IR.
Where does our work
on NLU fit in IR?
Well, of course,
queries and documents
are often expressed in natural
language, a decent part.
So we naturally want to
understand a query's meaning
and its intent and understand
the document's contents
and their topics to be able
to effectively match queries
to documents.
This form of
understanding is critical,
although you can go pretty
far for many IR tasks
with intelligently matching
terms at a lexical level.
The vocabulary mismatch problem
makes this quite unattractive
in practice.
To explain, vocabulary
mismatch happens
when queries and documents
use different terms
to refer to the same thing.
So I have here on the
slide an example query
that shows this
happening in practice.
So the question
is, or the query is
what compounds protect
the digestive system
against viruses?
And the snippet that we
are interested in finding
says in the stomach
gastric acid and proteases
serve as powerful
chemical defenses
against ingested pathogens.
You can see that the
passage that we found here
uses pathogens instead
of viruses, which
is a bit more general,
stomach instead
of the digestive system,
which is a bit more specific,
and chemical instead
of compound, defenses
instead of protect.
But it's pretty clear that it
still answers the same question
and answers it
very well, in fact.
So, where does NLU fit in IR?
I guess a nice quote here
is Jimmy Lin's statement.
Jimmy Lin is an IR researcher
who says IR makes NLP useful
and NLP makes IR interesting.
Of course, we do think
NLP is useful anyway,
and also IR is
interesting anyway.
So I added more
between brackets here,
but we do get Jimmy's point.
OK.
Onto our more central
question, where does IR
fit into our study of NLU,
and how can IR serve us?
In thinking about
this, I believe
it's helpful to appreciate
that as our models become
more advanced in NLU, they
too, like humans, start
to have complete information
needs in solving their tasks.
More concretely, retrieval can
contribute to our NLU tasks
and systems in
three exciting ways.
First, retrieval
provides a rich source
for creating challenging and
realistic NLU tasks, ones
where finding information from
a large corpus is essential.
We will look closely at
this bullet in the remainder
of these slides.
Second, retrieval
offers a powerful tool
to make NLU models for existing
tasks more accurate and more
effective.
We'll touch upon this today, but
we'll discuss it in more depth
later.
Third, retrieval
can often lend us
a nice framework for evaluating
NLU systems whenever the output
domain is large,
just like in search
or whenever low
latency is important,
which are key
characteristics in IR.
We will expand on this in
a later screencast as well.
In the remainder
of the screencast,
we'll explore how
retrieval allows
us to pose very challenging
and very realistic
open-domain NLU tasks.
Chris has briefly introduced
SQuAD before in the overview
lecture.
To remind you of this
question answering task,
the input that we
are given in SquAD
is a context message which
was obtained from Wikipedia
and a question that tests
our model's understanding
of this one passage.
This is an interesting
task on its own right, one
that has enjoyed tons of work
and lots of recent progress
due to pre-trained
language models.
But with retrieval in mind,
we can move from standard QA
like SQuAD to open-domain
question answering.
Specifically, in open-domain
question answering,
we can ask what if
we want to answer
the same kinds of factoid
questions as SQuAD
or other types of questions
but without the perhaps
unrealistic hint of receiving
the particular passage
in Wikipedia that already
contains the answer?
In this case, you can take all
of the English Wikipedia, just
as an example, as our context.
And then again, pose
the same question
as SQuAD over all of
Wikipedia and build
models that can answer
these open questions
over large corpora.
So how would we
answer such questions?
The literature, in
particular, a nice EMNLP 2020
paper by Roberts et al.,
introduces a nice analogy
for how we might attempt
to tackle this task
and how we could think about it.
The first, perhaps more familiar
and perhaps simpler solution,
is to pose the question to
one of our usual transformers,
and specifically to
generate a sequence
to sequence model, something
like T5, GPT-2 or GPT-3.
In this case, we're
relying on the knowledge
stored internally and implicitly
in the model parameters.
So the model
memorizes these facts
just like you would do when
you enter a closed book exam.
Often, this knowledge is
memorized the same way language
is learned as a result of
language model pre-training
or other similar tasks.
Closed book approaches to these
characteristically open-domain
problems offer a
particularly consistent way
of improving quality
and coverage.
Well, just take a model,
train a larger version of it
on more data and hope that
that includes more knowledge
and gives you more
accurate results.
As an alternative
to this, you could
think about open book approaches
to open-domain question
answering.
So there's the analogy of
doing an open book exam, which
tests not really your memory
but your awareness of where
to look for answers and
how to use them quickly
and productively.
In this case, we will
build what are typically
called retrieve-and-read
architectures.
As shown at the bottom of the
slide, we take the question
and first feed it to
a retrieval model.
The retriever searches
our collection of facts,
in this case, Wikipedia
as an example,
and extracts a bunch of
passages or other contexts
that seem useful in trying to
answer the original question.
These passages are then
fed to a downstream reader.
So that could just be a
small BERT-like model,
which studies these passages to
answer the original question.
In this pipeline,
we've essentially
relied on this new
retrieval component
to reduce the original
open-domain question answering
problem to a much smaller scale
standard question answering
task, where the
downstream model sees
a question and the relevant
passages or a few passages
before extracting
a short answer.
Importantly, you could say that
the reader in this architecture
is a user that has
an information need.
And it's the retriever's task
to satisfy this need accurately
and efficiently.
We will study various methods
for building retrievers
in the subsequent
screencasts and look
at how these retrievers interact
with downstream readers.
But for now, let's
just explore some
of the higher-level
differences between open book
and closed book solutions
to open-domain problems.
Our open book
solutions often get
to be much smaller while
being very accurate still.
The reason is that we
have decoupled knowledge
from reasoning and stored the
knowledge outside the model.
Thus the model
itself does not need
to store all of these facts
inside its parameters,
and it gets to be much
smaller as a result.
As we will see later, this
has great implications
for efficiency.
Moreover, the knowledge can
be easily updated by modifying
the collection as the facts
in Wikipedia, for example,
evolve over time.
Or alternatively,
suppose that you
want to switch from answering
questions over Wikipedia
to posing questions
over the NLP literature
or perhaps posing questions
over the documentation
of your favorite
software library.
You can often do that
by simply swapping
the collection with
a new one and keeping
the question-answering model
as is to answer questions
in this new domain.
Lastly, because we can see
the actual documents that
are retrieved and the documents
that are read by the reader
to extract answers, we are
often better positioned
to explain how these
models know some facts
or why they make
particular mistakes.
On the downside,
though, all of a sudden,
we now need to worry
about the interactions
between two components, the
retriever and the reader.
But I hope that the
subsequent set of screencasts
will convince you that
working with retrievers in NLU
is very rewarding.
All of this
discussion so far has
been in the context of
open-domain question answering.
But there are many
other NLU tasks
that either inherently subsume
retrieval or at least can
directly benefit
from interacting
with a large collection
of relevant facts.
One of those is claim
verification or fact-checking.
Here, the model receives
as input, a disputed claim,
and its goal is to verify
or refute this claim
and to return documents
that justify its decision.
Two other tasks
are query focused
summarization and
informative dialogue,
where we might also work with
a large collection of facts,
and given a topic or in the
context of a conversation,
generate a useful summary of
the resources about that topic,
perhaps as part of a
conversation with the user
interested to learn
about the new topic.
Lastly, entity
linking is the task
that can be posed over a large
textual knowledge base as well.
Given an utterance that
refers to any number
of ambiguous entities
or events, we
should resolve this
ambiguity and map dimensions
of these entities to
their descriptions
in a large knowledge
base like Wikipedia.
So that would be a
form of entity linking.
KILT or Knowledge
Intensive Language Tasks
is a recent effort
aimed at collecting
a number of different datasets
for retrieval based NLP.
Incidentally, all of
these tasks in KILT
explicitly have a
knowledge component,
like answering a question
or verifying a claim.
An open question in
this exciting area
is whether retrieval can improve
performance for standard NLU
tasks as well, ones where
the knowledge challenge is
less explicit.
Think, for example, sentiment
analysis, natural language
inference, or any of the other
tasks we've studied so far.
Well, this remains
an open question.
But I think that accurate
knowledge matters
for most, if not all,
of our language tasks.
And that converting
many of these tasks
to an open book format or
bring your own book approach
may be a promising way to
tackle these tasks in practice.
In the remainder
of this unit, we
will dig deeper into
traditional methods and metrics
for information retrieval and
then explore recent advances
in neural IR, which will make
a lot of use of our NLU models
like BERT in new
and creative ways.
And then, we will finally
discuss open-domain question
answering in more depth as one
of the most mature applications
of NLU plus IR.