OMAR KHATTAB: Hello, everyone.
Welcome to part 4 of our
series on NLU and IR.
This screencast will be
the second among three
of our videos on neural
information retrieval.
Just to recap, this is the
functional view of neural IR
that we left in the
previous screencast.
Our model will take a
query, and a document,
and will then
output a score that
will estimate the relevance
of this document to the query.
We will sort the documents
by the decreasing score
to get the top K results.
Let's begin with a
very effective paradigm
for building neural
IR models, namely
query-document interaction.
So given a query and a
document we'll tokenize them.
Then we'll embed
the tokens of each
into a static vector
representation.
So these could be GloVe
vectors, for example,
or the initial
representations of BERT.
We'll then build what is called
a query document interaction
matrix.
This is typically nothing but
a matrix of cosine similarities
between each pair of
words across the query
and the document.
Now that we have
this matrix, we just
need to reduce it to
a single score that
estimates the relevance of
our document to this query.
To do this, we'll
just learn a bunch
of neural layers like
convolutional or linear layers
with pooling until we end
up with a single score
for this query-document pair.
Many IR models out there fall
in this category, especially
ones that were introduced
between 2016 through 2018
or 2019.
With enough training
data, query-document human
interaction models can achieve
considerably better quality
than Bag-of-Words
models like BM 25.
And they can actually do that
at a reasonable increase,
moderate increase in
computational cost.
So as discussed in the
previous screencasts,
these models are typically
used as the last stage
of every ranking pipeline.
And in particular,
in this figure
here, they're used to
re-rank the top 1,000
messages retrieved by BM25.
And this is done to make sure
that the latency is acceptable
while still improving
the MRR and the quality
over BM25 retrieval.
More recently, in
2019, the IR community
discovered the power
of BERT for ranking.
Functionally, this is very
similar to the paradigm
that we just saw with
query-document interactions.
So here, we're going
to feed BERT the query
and the document as one
sequence with two segments.
One segment for the query and
one segment for the document as
shown.
We'll run this through
all the layers of BERT.
And we'll finally extract the
class token embedding from BERT
and reduce it to a single score
through a final linear head
on top of BERT.
As you can probably tell, this
is nothing but a standard BERT
classifier, where
we're going to take
the scores or the
confidence that's
the output of the
classifier and use it
for ranking our passages.
And like any other
task with BERT,
we should first
fine-tune this BERT model
with appropriate training data
before we use it for our task.
We've discussed how
to train our models
in the previous screencasts,
so refer to that if you'd like.
So this really simple
model on top of BERT
was the foundation for
tremendous progress in search
over the past two years.
And in particular,
it's worth mentioning
the first public
instance of this,
which was in January of 2019
on the MS MARCO Passage Ranking
task.
Here, Nogueira and Cho made a
simple BERT-based submission
to the leaderboard of MS
MARCO that demonstrated
dramatic gains over the previous
state of the art submitted
just a few days prior.
By October of 2019,
almost exactly one year
after BERT originally
came out, Google
had publicly discussed
the use of BERT in search.
And Bing followed soon after
in November of the same year.
But the story is actually
a bit more complicated.
These very large
gains in quality
came at a drastic increase
in computational cost,
which dictates
latency, and which
is very important for user
experience in search tasks
as we have discussed before.
So over a simple query
document interaction
models like Duet or ConvKNRM,
Nogueira and Cho's BERT models
increase MRR by over 8 points
but also increase latency
to multiple seconds per query.
And so here it is natural for us
to ask ourselves the question,
if we could achieve high
MRR and low latency at once.
And it turns out that
the answer is yes,
but it will take a lot
of progress to get there.
And we'll try to cover that
in the rest of the screencast
in the next one.
So let's get started with that.
So to seek better trade offs
between quality and latency,
which is our goal,
let's think about why
BERT rankers are so slow.
Our first observation
here will be
that BERT rankers
are quite redundant
in their computations.
If you think about
what BERT rankers do,
they need to compute a
contextualized representation
of the query for each
document that we rank.
So that's 1,000 times
for 1,000 documents.
And they also must
encode each document
for every single
query that comes along
that needs a score
for that document.
Of course, we have the documents
in our collections in advance,
and we can do as
much preprocessing
as we want on them offline
before we get any queries.
So the question becomes,
can we somehow precompute
some form of document
representations
in advance once and for all
using these powerful models
that we have like BERT, and
store these representations
or cache them somewhere so
we can just use them quickly
every time we have
a query to answer?
This will be our
guiding question
for the remainder of this
and the next screencasts.
Of course, it is not actually
obvious yet, at least,
if we can pre-compute such
representations in advance
without much loss in quality
for all we know so far,
there might be a lot
of empirical value
in jointly representing
queries and documents at once.
But we'll put this
hypothesis to the test.
The first approach to tame the
computational latency of BERT
for IR is learning term weights.
The key observation here is that
Bag-of-Words models like BM25,
it composed the score
of every document
into a summation of
term document weights,
and maybe, we can do the same.
So can we learn these
term weights with BERT
in particular?
A simple way to do this
would be to tokenize
a query and the document.
Feed BERT, only the
document, and use
a linear layer to project
each token in the document
into a single numeric score.
The idea here is that we
can save these document term
weights to the inverted
index just like we
did with BM25 and classical IR
and quickly look up these term
weights when answering a query.
This makes sure we do not
need to use BERT at all when
answering a query as we just
shifted all of our BERT work
offline to the indexing stage.
So this can be really great.
We now get to use BERT to
learn much stronger term
weights than BM25.
And DeepCT and doc2query
are two major models
under this efficient paradigm.
As the figure shows
at the bottom,
they indeed greatly
outperform BM25 and MRR,
but actually, they
have comparable latency
because we're still
using an inverted index
to do that retrieval.
However, the downside
is that our query
is back to being a
Bag-of-Words, and we
lose any deeper understanding
of our queries beyond that.
So our central question
remains whether we can jointly
achieve high MRR and
low computational cost.
And as we said before,
the answer is yes.
And to do this, we'll discuss
in the next screencast
two very exciting paradigms
of neural IR models
that get us close to this goal.