BILL MACCARTNEY: Our topic
for today and Wednesday
is relation extraction.
And this is an
exciting topic both
because it's a great
arena to explore
a variety of NLU and
machine learning techniques.
And because it has so many
real world applications
as we'll see in a moment.
So here's an overview of
the next two lectures.
I'm going to start by
describing the task of relation
extraction, what it
is, why it matters,
and how we might approach it.
Then I'll describe
the data resources
we'll need to make
headway on the problem.
Next, I'll provide a
more precise formulation
of the prediction problem
that we're taking on
and I'll propose a strategy
for quantitative evaluation.
Then we'll establish some
lower bounds on performance
by evaluating some very simple
approaches to this problem.
And finally, will point
toward some directions
for future exploration.
In the first section,
I'll start by defining
the task of relation
extraction, then
I'll try to provide
some motivation for why
it's an important
and exciting problem.
I'll describe both the vision
that originally inspired
research in this
area and a range
of current practical
applications
for relation extraction.
Then I'll describe
three paradigms
that correspond to three stages
in the evolution of approaches
to relation extraction.
Hand-built patterns, which were
dominant in the '80s and '90s.
Supervised learning, which
became dominant in the 2000s.
And distant supervision, which
has dominated since about 2010
and will be our main focus.
So let's dive in.
So the task of
relation extraction
is about extracting structured
knowledge from natural language
text.
We want to be able to start
from a document like this.
This could be a new
story or a web page.
And extract relational
triples like founders, PayPal,
Elon Musk, and founders,
SpaceX, Elon Musk.
Next, we find this
document and we
want to be able to
extract, has_spouse,
Elon Musk, Talulah Riley.
We keep reading
another document and we
want to extract worked_at,
Elon Musk, Tesla Motors.
If we can accumulate
a large knowledge
base of relational
triples, we can use it
to power question answering
and other applications.
Building a knowledge
base like this
manually is slow and expensive.
But much of the knowledge
that we'd like to capture
is already expressed in
abundant text on the web.
So the aim of
relation extraction
is to accelerate knowledge
base construction
by extracting relational triples
from natural language text.
Here's a nice
articulation of the vision
for relation extraction.
This is from Tom
Mitchell, who is
the former chair of the machine
learning department at CMU.
He's also the author of
one of the first textbooks
on machine learning.
By the way, he was
also the PhD advisor
of Sebastian Thrun
and Oren Etzioni.
He wrote this piece
in 2005 describing
a vision for machine reading.
And he offered to bet a
lobster dinner that by 2015, we
will have a computer program
capable of automatically
reading at least 80% of the
factual content on the web,
and placing those facts in
a structured knowledge base.
I think we've come pretty
close to achieving that goal.
And this is exactly the goal
that relation extraction
aims at to extract
structure knowledge
from unstructured text.
One of the things that
makes relation extraction
an exciting topic
is the abundance
of real world applications.
For example, nowadays
intelligent assistants
like Siri or Google can answer
lots of factual questions
like who sang "Love Train?"
To do this, they rely on
knowledge bases or KB's
containing thousands
of relations,
millions of entities and
billions of individual facts.
There are many
different strategies
for building and maintaining
and extending these KB's,
but considering how
enormous they are
and how quickly the world
is creating new facts.
It's a process that you want to
automate as much as possible.
So more and more relation
extraction from the web
is hugely strategic for Apple
and Google and other companies.
In fact in 2017, Apple spent
$200 million to acquire
a startup called Lattice, which
was co-founded by Stanford
Professor Chris Ré, whom
some of you may know,
specifically for this purpose.
Another example is
building ontologies.
If you're running
an app store, you're
going to need a
taxonomy of categories
of apps, and which apps
belong to which categories.
One category of
apps is video games.
But if you're a gamer,
you know that there
are subcategories and sub,
subcategories and sub,
sub subcategories
of video games.
And new ones keep appearing
and new games appear every day.
How are you going to keep
your ontology up to date?
Well, there's a lot
of people writing
about video games on the web.
So maybe relation
extraction can help.
The relation between a
category and a subcategory,
or between a category and
an instance of the category
can be a target for
relation extraction.
And similarly, you can imagine
using relation extraction
to help build or maintain
ontologies of car
parts or companies or viruses.
Another example comes
from bioinformatics.
So every year,
there are thousands
of new research
articles describing
gene regulatory networks.
If we can apply relation
extraction to these articles
to populate a database of
gene regulation relationships,
then we can begin
to apply existing,
well understood data
mining techniques.
We can look for
statistical correlations
or apply clever graph algorithms
to activation networks.
The sky's the limit.
We've turned something
that a machine
can't understand into something
that a machine can understand.
So let's turn to the question
of how you'd actually
solve this problem.
The most obvious way to start
is to write down a few patterns
which express each relation.
So for example, if we
want to find new instances
of the founders relation.
So we can use patterns like
X is the founder of Y or X,
who founded Y or Y
was founded by X.
And then if we search
a large corpus,
we may find sentences like
these that match these patterns
and allow us to extract the fact
that Elon Musk founded SpaceX.
So this seems promising
and, in fact, this
was the dominant paradigm
in relation extraction
in the early days.
But this approach
is really limited.
The central challenge
of relation extraction
is the fantastic
diversity of language.
The multitude of possible ways
to express a given relation.
For example, each
of these sentences
also expresses the fact that
Elon Musk founded SpaceX.
But in these
examples, the patterns
which connect Elon
Musk with SpaceX
are not ones that we could
have easily anticipated.
They might be ones that
will never recur again.
So to do relation
extraction effectively,
we need to go beyond
hand-built patterns.
So around the turn
of the century,
the machine learning revolution
came to the field of NLP
and people began to try
a new approach, namely
supervised learning.
So you start by
labeling your examples.
So these three examples
are positive instances
of the founders relation.
So these are the
positive examples.
And these two are
negative examples.
Now that we have
labeled training data,
we can train a model.
And it could be a
simple linear model that
uses a bag of words
representation
and assigns higher weights
to words like founder
and established that are likely
to indicate the founder's
relation, or it could be
something more complicated.
In any case, this was a
hugely successful idea.
Even simple machine
learning models
are far better at
generalizing to new data
than static patterns.
But there's a big
problem, manually labeling
training examples is
laborious and time consuming
and expensive.
And as a consequence,
the largest
labeled data sets that
were produced had only tens
of thousands of examples, which
by modern standards seems puny.
If we want to apply modern
machine learning techniques,
we need a lot more data.
We need a way to leverage vastly
greater quantities of training
data.
The answer appeared
around 2010 with an idea
called distant supervision,
and this is a really big idea.
Instead of manually labeling
individual examples,
we're going to
automatically derive
the labels from an
existing knowledge base.
So let's say we
already have a KB that
contains many examples
of the founders relation.
So we've got SpaceX and Elon
Musk, Apple, and Steve Jobs
and so on.
And let's say we have
a large corpus of text.
It can be unlabeled text,
raw text, which means
that it can be truly enormous.
It can be the whole web.
What we're going to do is,
we're going to simply assume
that every sentence which
contains a pair of entities
which are related in the KB
like Elon Musk and SpaceX
is a positive example
for that relation.
And we're going to assume that
every sentence which contains
a pair of entities that
are unrelated in a KB
like Elon Musk and Apple
is a negative example.
Genius.
This gives us a way to generate
massive quantities of training
data practically free.
However, you might have some
doubts about the validity
of those assumptions.
So hold that thought.
Distant supervision is
a really powerful idea,
but it has two
important limitations.
The first is a consequence
of making the unreliable
assumption that all sentences
where related entities co-occur
actually express that relation.
Inevitably, some of them don't.
Like this example, we labeled
it as a positive example
for the founder's
relation, but it doesn't
express that relation at all.
This doesn't say that Elon
Musk is a founder of SpaceX.
So this label is a lie,
a dirty, dirty lie.
Making this
assumption blindly has
the effect of introducing
noise into our training data.
Distant supervision is effective
in spite of this problem,
because it makes it
possible to leverage
vastly greater quantities
of training data.
And the benefit of
more data outweighs
the harm of noisier data.
By the way, I feel like
I've waited my whole life
for the right opportunity
to use the Pinocchio emoji.
The day finally came
and it feels good.
The second limitation is
that we need an existing KB
to start from.
We can only train
a model to extract
new instances of the
founder's relation,
if we already have many
instances of the founder's
relation.
So while distant
supervision is a great way
to extend an
existing KB, it's not
useful for creating
a KB containing
new relations from scratch.