CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is the first
screencast in our series
on Analysis Methods in NLP.
This is one of my favorite
units in the course
because it's directly
oriented toward helping you
do even better final projects.
Now there's a lot we could
discuss under the rubric
of analysis methods in NLP.
I've chosen four things.
The first two, fall
under the heading
of behavioral evaluations.
We'll talk about
adversarial testing, which
is a very flexible
way for you to expose
that your system might
have some weaknesses
or fail to capture some
linguistic phenomenon in a very
systematic way.
And then at this point, we
also have the opportunity
for a number of tasks to
do adversarial training
and testing, and these
would be large dataset that
are full of examples
that we know
are difficult for present
day architectures.
So for every architecture
you're exploring,
this would be a chance to really
stress test that architecture.
And then we're going to move
beyond behavioral evaluations
to talk about what I've called
structural evaluation methods.
And these include probing
and feature attribution.
And these are
techniques that you
could use to peer
inside your system
and gain an understanding of
what its hidden representations
are like, and how those
representations are impacting
the model's predictions.
The motivations
for this are many.
Here are just a
few high-level ones
that are kind of
oriented toward projects.
The first, is just
that we might want
to find the limits of the
system that you're developing.
All our systems have
limitations and finding
them is always
scientifically useful.
We might just also
want to understand
your system's behavior better.
What are its internal
representations like,
and how are they feeding
into its final predictions
and its overall behaviors?
That's also just
incredibly rewarding.
And both of these things
might feed into just
achieving more robust systems.
To the extent that we can
find weaknesses and understand
behaviors, we can
possibly take steps
toward building even
more robust systems.
And as I said, all
of this is oriented
toward your final projects.
The techniques that
we're discussing
are powerful and easy ways
to improve the analysis
section of a paper.
Analysis sections
are important, but it
can be difficult to write them.
It feels very open ended
and often very unstructured.
People talk in general
ways about doing
error analysis and
so forth, but it
can be hard to pinpoint exactly
what would be productive.
I think the methods that
we're talking about here
are very generally
applicable and can
lead to really productive
and rich analysis sections.
Let's begin with
adversarial testing,
this is a mode that we've
talked about before.
The examples on this slide are
from this now classic paper
Glockner et al., 2018,
called "Breaking NLI."
And what they did is only
really mildly adversarial.
It's just kind of a challenge.
And it exposes some lack of
systematicity in certain NLI
models.
So here's what they did.
They began from SNLI
examples like, "a little girl
is kneeling in the
dirt crying" entails
"a little girl is very sad."
And they simply use
lexical resources
to change the
hypothesis by one word.
So that it now reads, "a
little girl is very unhappy."
We would expect a system
that truly understood
the reasoning involved
in these examples
to continue to predict
entail in the second case
because these examples
are roughly synonymous.
But what they found, is that
systems would often start
to predict
contradiction, possibly
because of the negation
that occurs here.
The second example is similar.
We begin from the SNLI
example, "an elderly couple
are sitting outside a
restaurant enjoying wine"
entails "a couple
drinking wine."
And here they just
changed wine to champagne.
What we would expect
is that a system that
knew about these lexical
items and their relations,
would flip to predicting
neutral in this case.
But as you might
imagine, systems
continue to predict
entails because they
have only a very fuzzy
understanding of how
wine and champagne are
related to each other.
Here is the results table, and
recall this is a 2018 paper.
And what they're
mainly testing here,
are models that we might
regard as precursors
to the transformers that
we've been so focused on.
And the picture is very clear.
These models do well on the
SNLI test set, mid-to-high 80s,
but their performance plummets
on this new adversarial test
set.
There are two exceptions down
here, this WordNet baseline
and the KIM architecture.
But it's important to note
that these models effectively
had access directly
in the case of WordNet
and indirectly in
the case of KIM,
to a lexical resource
that was used
to create the adversarial test.
And so they don't see such a
large performance drop here.
But even still, all
of these numbers
are kind of modest
at this point.
And I told you that this
was an interesting story.
Here's the interesting twist.
At this point in 2021, you can
simply download RoBERTA-MNLI--
that's the RoBERTA parameters
fine-tuned on the MultiNLI data
set--
and run this adversarial test.
And what you find is that
model does astoundingly well
on the Breaking NLI data set.
I would focus on
these two f1-scores
here for the two classes where
we have a lot of support,
contradiction and entailment.
The numbers are above 90
as is the accuracy here,
which is directly
comparable to the numbers
that Glockner et al. reported.
An amazing
accomplishment-- recall
that the original examples
from the adversarial test
are from SNLI,
this is multi-NLI.
It was not developed
specifically
to solve this adversarial test.
And nonetheless, it
looks like RoBERTA
has systematic knowledge of
the lexical relations involved
and required to solve
this adversarial test--
so possibly a mark
of real progress.
As I said, you can also,
for selective tests,
move into the mode of
doing adversarial training
and testing.
Here are the cases I know where
the dataset is large enough
to support training
and testing on examples
that were created via
some adversarial dynamic--
common sense reasoning,
natural language inference,
question answering,
sentiment and hate speech.
And as I said, this is a
really exciting opportunity
to see just how
robust your system is
when exposed to
examples that we know
are difficult for
modern architectures,
because that's how these
datasets were designed.
Now let's move into the
more behavioral mode.
We'll start with probing of
internal representations.
Probes are little
supervised models typically,
that you fit on the
internal representations
of your model of
interest to expose
what those hidden
representations latently
encode.
This is from a classic paper
by Ian Tenney et al., 2019.
And what we have
along the x-axis
is the BERT layers, starting
from the embedding layer
and going to 24.
This is BERT large, so
there are 24 layers.
And the picture
is quite striking.
As you start from the
top here and move down,
you can see that as we move
from more syntactic things, up
into more discourse-y
semantic content,
like co-ref and
relation extraction,
you find that the higher
layers of the BERT model
are encoding that
information latently.
That's what these probing
results reveal in this picture.
Quite striking look at what
the pretraining process
in this case, of BERT,
is learning latently
about the structures
of language.
And then we'll finally talk
about feature attribution,
which is one step further in
this more introspective mode,
because here as
you'll see, I think
we can get a really deep picture
at how individual features
and representations
are directly related
to the model's predictions.
And what I've done here, is
use the Integrated Gradients
model, which is the model
that we'll focus on.
I ran it on a sentiment model.
And you can see here,
we have the true label,
the predicted model
with the probability,
and then we have word
level importances,
as measured by Integrated
Gradients, where blue means
it's a bias toward
positive predictions,
and red means it's a bias
toward negative predictions.
And I've picked an example
that I think kind of stress
tests the model.
It's a little bit adversarial
because it's-- all these
examples involve mean
in the sense of good,
as in a mean apple pie, meaning
a delicious or a good one.
And you can see that by and
large, this model's predictions
are pretty systematic.
It's mostly predicting positive
for variants, like "they sell,"
"they make," "he makes,"
although this last one,
"he sells," might worry
us a little bit because it
has flipped to negative, despite
the changes to the example
being truly incidental.
And this might point to a way in
which the model does or doesn't
have knowledge of how
the individual components
of these examples should
be predict-- should
be feeding into the
final predictions
that the model makes.
I think that's a
wonderful opportunity
to get a sense for how
robust the model is actually
going to be to variations,
like the one that you see here.