CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is part two in our series
on analysis methods in NLP.
We're going to be talking
about adversarial testing.
This is an exciting mode because
as you'll see with a few dozen
carefully created
examples, you can
learn something really
interesting about the systems
that you're developing.
To start, let's remind ourselves
of how evaluation standardly
work in our field.
At step one you create a dataset
from some single homogeneous
process.
It could be that you've
scraped data from the web
or crowd-sourced a dataset,
or labelled examples yourself,
but the important thing
is that we, typically,
do this as one single process.
And then in step two
we divide that dataset
into disjoint train
and test sets,
and we set the test set aside.
And you do all your
development on the train set
and, only after all
development is complete,
you do an evaluation of
your system usually based
on accuracy or some similar
metric on that held out test
set.
And then finally, and this
is the important part,
you report the results of
that test set evaluation
as providing an estimate of the
system's capacity to generalize
to new experiences.
I hope you can hear in that
that we're being awfully
generous to our systems.
At step one we create a single
data set from a single process.
We hold out the test set, and we
use that test set as our device
for measuring how
well the system is
going to do if deployed
out in the real world.
But, of course, we know
that the real world is not
created from some single
homogeneous process.
We know in our heart of hearts
that if we deploy the system,
it will encounter
examples that are entirely
unlike those that it saw
in training and assessment
in the standard mode,
and that might worry us,
that we're overstating the
capacity of our systems
to actually deal with the
complexity of the world.
And adversarial
evaluations are one way
that we can begin to
close this gap here.
So in adversarial evaluations
we create a dataset
by whatever means you
like, at step one,
and you develop and assess
the system using that dataset
according to whatever
protocols you choose.
It could be the standard
evaluation mode, if you like.
Here's the new part.
At step three you develop
a new test set of examples
that you suspect, or
know, will be challenging
given your system and
the original data set
that it was trained on.
And then, as usual, after
all your system development
is complete you evaluate
the system, usually based
on accuracy, again, on
that new test dataset.
And that's the result
that you report
as your system's
capacity to generalize
to new experiences,
at least of the sort
that you carved out in
your adversarial test set.
And the idea here
is that in having
a distinction between the data
that we develop our system on
and the challenge
problems that we pose,
we'll get a better estimate
of how our systems perform
on examples that are presumably
important examples that it's
likely to encounter when it's
deployed in the real world.
A brief historical
note, I think it's
fair to say that the idea
of adversarial testing
traces all the way back
to the Turing test,
which is introduced by Turing
in this classic paper, Computing
Machinery and intelligence.
The Turing test has an
inherently adversarial flavor
to it because, of
course, a computer
is trying to trick a
human into thinking
that the computer is human.
We also hear echoes
of adversarial testing
in this classic
article slash book
from Terry Winograd called
Understanding Natural Language.
There are discussions
in that book
of the idea of constructing
examples that we know
will stress test our systems
by probing to see whether they
have knowledge of
what the world is like
and the true
complexity of language.
And then I think Hector Levesque
really elevated those Winograd
ideas into a full-fledged
testing mode in his paper,
On Our Best Behavior.
Let's look briefly at
those Winograd sentences,
or Winograd schema, because
they're kind of interesting.
The idea is that they will
key into whether a system has
deep knowledge of the
world and of language.
So we start with an
example like, the trophy
doesn't fit into
the brown suitcase
because it's too small.
What's too small?
And the human answer
is, the suitcase.
There's a minimally
contrasting example,
the trophy doesn't fit
into the brown suitcase
because it's too large.
What's too large?
Here we answer the trophy.
And presumably, we
do this because we
can do a kind of
mental simulation
involving suitcases and
trophies and figure out
how to answer these
questions on that basis.
This next pair of
examples is similar,
but it keys more into
normative social roles.
The council refused
the demonstrators
a permit because
they feared violence.
Who feared violence?
And our standard answer, drawing
on standard social roles,
is the council.
Again, we have a minimally
contrasting example.
The council refused
the demonstrators
a permit because they
advocated violence.
Who advocated violence?
And here, again drawing
on default social roles,
we're inclined to answer,
the demonstrators.
The intuition, as I
said, is that to resolve
these questions, given
how minimally different
these examples are, you need
to have a deep understanding
of the questions and
the context and also
a deep understanding of
what our world is like.
And then, as I said, Levesque
kind of continues this
and begins to systematize it.
So he says, we should pose
questions to our systems like,
could a crocodile
run a steeplechase?
And the intuition is clear.
The question can be answered
by thinking it through.
A crocodile has short legs.
The hedges in a
steeplechase would
be too tall for the
crocodile to jump over.
So no.
A crocodile cannot
run a steeplechase.
Again, a mental
simulation that leads us
to an answer to this
surprising question.
And the idea is that
questions like this
will not be susceptible
to cheap tricks.
As Levesque says,
can we find questions
where cheap tricks
like this will not
be sufficient to produce
the desired behavior?
This, unfortunately,
has no easy answer.
The best we can do,
perhaps, is to come up
with a suite of multiple
choice questions
carefully, and then study the
sorts of computer programs
that might be able
to answer them.
I think you can hear in
that what we now call
the adversarial testing mode.
Now, I'm encouraging you
to pose adversarial tests
to your systems.
And as I said, you can
do that by constructing
just a few novel
examples, but we should
be aware of what we're doing.
Primary question, what can
adversarial testing tell us,
and what can't it tell
us about the systems
that we're developing?
Here are just a
few considerations
that should guide your
work in this area.
First, you don't need
to be too adversarial.
It could just be that you're
posing a challenge problem
to assess whether
your system has
an understanding of a
particular set of phenomena.
Has my system learned anything
about numerical terms?
Does my system understand
how negation works?
Does my system work with
a new style or genre?
These are challenge
problems that you
could pose
open-mindedly, and you
might find that your system
is surprisingly good at them.
Second consideration, we should
be thoughtful about the metrics
we use.
As I signaled to you
before, the limitations
of accuracy-based metrics,
like F1 and so forth,
are generally left unaddressed
by the adversarial paradigm.
And that's because we
want a minimal contrast
with our standard
evaluation modes.
But I think you can hear
in the mission statements,
especially from Levesque,
that we might at some point
want to break free of
that very restrictive mode
and pose more open-ended complex
evaluations for our systems
that would involve requiring
them to offer their evidence
and interact with us to resolve
uncertainty about what they're
supposed to be doing.
All of that is left aside in
the standard adversarial mode,
and we should be aware
that it's a limitation.
This next question is really
fundamentally important.
In adversarial testing, if
you see a model failure,
is it actually a failure of
the model or of the dataset
that the model was trained on?
Liu, et al. posed this nicely.
What should we
conclude when a system
fails on a challenge dataset?
In some cases, the challenge
might exploit blind spots
in the design of the
original dataset.
That would be a
dataset weakness.
In others, the challenge might
expose an inherent inability
of a particular model family to
handle certain natural language
phenomenon.
That would be a model weakness.
Now, these are interestingly
different from the point
of view of development
in our field.
We're apt to hope, I think,
that we find model weaknesses
because those are really
fundamental discoveries,
but we should be aware that it
might be that the system could
have done well on
our adversarial test
if it had just been trained
on the right kind of examples.
And that would be
a dataset weakness.
Data set weaknesses are
presumably relatively
easy for us to address.
We can just supplement
the training data
with examples of
the relevant kind,
whereas model
weaknesses are forcing
us to confront
something that might
be an inherent limitation of
the set of approaches that we're
taking, a much more
fundamental insight.
Atticus Geiger, et
al., in this paper
offers a similar
insight in the context
of being fair to our models.
For any evaluation method, we
should ask whether it's fair.
Has the model been shown
data sufficient to support
the kind of generalization
we're asking of it?
Unless we can say yes
with complete certainty,
we can't be sure whether
a failed evaluation traces
to a model limitation
or a data limitation
that no model could overcome.
And I'm emphasizing this
because it's surprisingly easy
to fall into the
trap of thinking
you have imposed an unambiguous
learning target when,
in fact, you have not.
Just think about the
simple example here.
Human to human, suppose I
begin the sequence 3, 3, 5, 4,
and I say to you, what
comes next in the sequence?
Now, I might have
in mind the number 7
But the evidence
that I have offered
you wildly underdetermines
how to continue the sequence.
And so I think it's fair
to say that no learning
agent, without a
lot of ambiguity,
could figure out what my
intended continuation is.
And sometimes our
adversarial tests
have this quality that the
available data and experiences
of these systems
just don't fully
disambiguate what our
intended learning targets are.
So we should be aware of that.
Those are dataset failings,
rather than model failings.
Now, I can offer you
a constructive set
of techniques to figure
out whether you're
dealing with a dataset
weakness or a model weakness,
and that falls under the
heading of inoculation
by fine tuning from
this wonderful paper,
Liu, et al., that I
quoted from before.
So Liu, et al.,
just to remind us
that in the standard
challenge evaluation mode
we train our system on
some original dataset
and then we test it on
both the original test
set and our challenge test set.
And our expectation is
that we'll see outcomes
like this where the
system does really
well on the original data,
the original test set,
and really poorly on
the challenge test set.
But when we see this
outcome we should ask,
why this is happening?
In particular, is it a model
weakness or a dataset weakness?
And their proposed method,
this inoculation method,
works as follows.
We're going to
fine-tune our system
on a few of our
challenge examples,
and then retest on both the
original test set and the held
out parts of the
challenge test set.
When we do this, there are
three classes of outcome
that you might see.
The first would point
to a dataset weakness.
If via this little bit of fine
tuning on the challenge dataset
we can get good performance on
the original and the challenge
data set, that shows us that in
this original evaluation mode
the system just
didn't see enough
of the relevant
kinds of examples
from your adversarial tests to
have any hope of succeeding,
but a modest amount of
training on those examples
leads it to do fine.
That's a dataset weakness.
A model weakness
is what we might
have in the back of our minds
for our adversarial testing,
and this would be
the case where,
even though we have
fine-tuned our system on some
of these challenge examples, its
performance remains really low,
even though the system can
maintain good performance
on the original dataset.
And this is just like there is
something special about these
new examples and the model
simply cannot get traction.
And there's a third outcome
that might be really worrisome,
and they would trace this
to kind of like annotation
artifacts or label shift
or something like that.
And that's where, in doing this
fine-tuning on some challenge
examples, we see
degraded performance
on both the original dataset
and the challenge dataset.
And that would show that there
is something fundamentally
confusing about these
adversarial testing examples
that are causing a lot of
problems for the system
that we've developed,
because even
a modest amount of fine tuning
causes kind of consequences
to ripple through
the system that
are impacting even performance
on the original dataset.
All right to close
out this screen cast,
let me offer you two examples
of interesting adversarial tests
in our field beginning with the
SQUaD question answering data
set.
I showed you this
leaderboard from SQUaD 2.0
at the start of the quarter,
and the funny thing, of course,
is that you have to go
all the way to place 13
on the leaderboard
to find a system that
is worse than our estimate
of human performance.
So we have superhuman
performance on SQUaD,
but what does that really mean?
SQUaD was also the site of one
of the first really systematic
adversarial testing
efforts in our field.
This is from Jia and Liang 2017.
What they did is quite simple.
We begin with SQUaD
examples, where
we have passages and
questions as inputs,
and the system task is
to answer the question,
and we can count
on the answer being
a literal substring
in the passage
that the system was given.
The adversarial thing
that Jia and Liang did
was simply to append
misleading sentences
to the ends of those passages.
And what they found is that
systems were systematically
misled by those final sentences.
Whereas humans could
easily ignore them,
systems were now
inclined to answer
drawing on information from
those misleading new sentences.
And this is kind of
an interesting dynamic
because you might think, well,
we'll just train our system now
on passages that have these
augmented misleading sentences,
and then surely our systems
will be more robust.
That might be true
in some sense,
but, of course,
we could then just
append sentences to the
start of the passages,
and Jia and Liang found
that systems were now
confused by the appended
initial sentences,
and they started to give wrong
answers in that mode, as well.
And you could kind
of go back and forth
in this adversarial mode showing
that systems were worrisomely
easy to trick based on
these simple appending
of misleading sentences.
Now, that's very interesting
about adversarial evaluation
mode.
What I think is more
interesting about the outcomes
is that they begin to
show us just how different
adversarial testing can be.
So here's the SQUaD
leaderboard, the original,
at the time of the paper,
as well as the results
of this adversarial test.
And you can see, first of
all, that system performance
has really plummeted.
So this turns out to be highly
adversarial to these systems,
for whatever reason.
I think it's more interesting
to note that the system ranking
has really been mixed up.
So it's not like the systems
uniformly drop in performance.
Now, as we move from
the original rank
to the adversarial rank, we
have the first place system
is now in place five.
The second has dropped
all the way to place 10,
but the seventh place system
is now in first place.
It looks kind of chaotic.
Here's a scatterplot where
we have the original system
performance along the x-axis
and the adversarial system
performance along the y-axis.
And you can see that
it's kind of chaotic.
There's no way that
one predicts the other.
So something very
interesting has happened,
and that's noteworthy
because it looks
like that's meaningfully
different from what we do when
we do standard evaluations.
I don't have direct
evidence of this from SQUaD,
but here's a case where people
took two classic image datasets
and simply created new
test sets according
to the same protocols that were
used for the original dataset
and test sets.
And what you find is a
very strong correlation.
Even though the
examples are new,
because it's the same
protocol, system performance
is highly predictive, in the
sense that the original test
accuracy is perfectly
correlated with accuracy
on these new testsets.
Very different from
this adversarial mode
where something much
more chaotic happened.
So adversarial testing is
meaningfully different it seems
from standard evaluations.
Let's move to NLI now.
This will tell us
two different lessons
about how adversarial
testing can be informative.
So we saw at the
start of the course
that we now have
superhuman performance
on the SNLI data set.
That's certainly noteworthy.
And we're reaching
superhuman performance
on the MultiNLI testset.
We're sure to be there,
if we're not already,
at the time of this screencast.
But we've also seen that
systems that perform really
well on these datasets are often
susceptible to adversaries.
In the first screen
cast I showed you
these examples from Glockner,
et al.'s, Breaking NLI
paper, where they make
simple modifications
to these hypotheses and
find that systems do not
behave systematically with
respect to human intuitions
about the modified examples.
And that's the worrisome
part, when they quantify that,
of course, and that you
can see that the best
systems at the time up here
were doing pretty well on SNLI,
and their performance plummeted
on these new test sets,
showing that this was,
for whatever reason,
truly adversarial when it
comes to those systems.
But I also presented this
as a story of progress,
right, because I showed you
that in simply downloading
RoBERTA-multi-NLI,
that is, RoBERTA fine
tuned on the MultiNLI
data set, you now
have a device
where, with no work,
you can essentially solve
this adversarial test.
I think that's really striking,
and it points to the fact
that RoBERTA, unlike
those earlier models,
might truly have
systematic understanding
of the relevant kinds
of lexical relationships
that you need to solve
this adversarial test set.
So that's an exciting outcome.
Here's a second outcome
that you might see,
and this is from the Naik,et al.
paper that does a wide battery
of different adversarial
tests on multi-NLI data.
They did a bunch of
things like antonyms--
"I love the Cinderella
story" contradicts
"I hate the Cinderella
story" just drawing
on lexical knowledge.
They asked about
numerical reasoning
across these two premises.
Word overlap, and this is a
little bit different, in that,
you're doing something like
just inserting material
that you might think is
going to be distracting
in the mode of the
SQUaD adversary,
and seeing what
effects that has,
and the same thing for negation.
Adding on to the end
information that's
going to be misleading
for a system
and also includes a lot
of negation elements.
There are a few other modes
that I didn't have space for.
It's a very rich paper with
a very fine-grained breakdown
of how systems do on these
different adversarial problems.
Here's a picture of the
dataset and here's a breakdown,
and I think the
overall takeaway is
that the numbers
across the board
are very low on
these adversaries.
And so that's interesting,
and it looks like even
top performing
systems from multi-NLI
are stumbling with
these problems
that we surely want our
systems to be able to solve,
if we're going to call them
true common sense reasoners.
However, this was
actually the basis
for a number of the
experiments in that Inoculation
By Fine Tuning paper that
I quoted from before.
Here's a kind of rough picture
of the performance results
that they report on
different subsets
of that adversarial
test on MultiNLI.
And you can see that it shows
all the different outcomes
that we discussed under
the heading of Inoculation
By Fine Tuning.
To simplify things, just
focus in on the green lines.
The ones with dots are the
original system performance,
and the ones with crosses
are on the challenge dataset.
So this first column here is
identifying dataset weaknesses.
What you're seeing is
that, as we fine-tune
on more examples from
the challenge dataset
going along the x-axis
here, we very quickly
get a system that's actually
good at this challenge problem,
right.
After just about 50
examples, the system
is, basically, learning to solve
the word overlap and negation
problem.
So the negation takes a little
bit longer at 400 examples.
So that's a case where the
original systems were failing,
not because of any intrinsic
property of the models being
used, but rather
because the data
clearly just didn't
have enough information
to resolve these
learning targets.
We also see outcome two,
which is a model weakness.
Again, follow the green
lines, and you can see here
that, for spelling errors
and length mismatch,
no amount of fine tuning
on challenge examples
helps these systems get
traction on these problems.
That's these flat lines here.
And that's showing that there's
something fundamentally wrong,
possibly, with these models.
They are just unable to solve
these two challenge problems.
And then we also see
the third artifact.
For numerical
reasoning, you'll notice
that system performance is
kind of really chaotic here,
and that's suggesting
that there is
something importantly
and problematically
different about these challenge
examples because fine tuning
on them causes the
system to become really
chaotic in its predictions, and
we get degraded performance,
not only on the
challenge set, but also
on the original dataset.
showing that we've done
something quite disruptive.
So this is really interesting
that in this case,
from this battery of
adversarial tests,
we see all these different
outcomes pointing us
to all sorts of
different lessons
about what action we should
take to make these systems more
robust.