CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone
to part 3 in our series on
analysis methods in NLP.
We're going to be talking about
adversarial training as well
as testing of systems.
This is the second of the
behavioral evaluation methods
that we're considering.
We've previously talked
about adversarial testing.
Adversarial training
and testing, of course,
implies that we have much
larger datasets, that this
is more difficult to do.
But for selected tasks
where we have such datasets,
this can be very
exciting and push
you to address all sorts
of interesting cutting edge
questions.
I'll start with SWAG.
This is an early entry into the
space of adversarial training
sets.
SWAG stands for Situations
With Adversarial Generations.
There's actually two data sets,
SWAG and the colorfully named
HellaSWAG.
And you'll see why there
are two in a second.
This is fundamentally, again,
another interesting story
of very rapid
progress in our field.
Here's how SWAG examples work.
We're given as a system input
a context like, "he is throwing
darts at a target" and
another system input, which
is the start of a sentence,
here it's, "another man."
And the task of the system
is to figure out what
the continuation should be.
So the actual continuation
that we predict might be,
"throws a dart at
the target board."
And this is fundamentally
a classification task,
the system is given
some distractors like,
"comes running in and shoots
an arrow at a target,"
or "is shown on
the side of men,"
or "throws darts at a disk."
And the system is
tasked with figuring out
which of the options is
the actual continuation
for the sentence,
given the context.
The data sources for this are
ActivityNet and the Large Scale
Movie Description Challenge.
I think the idea
here is that we're
going to key in to all
sorts of interesting notions
of common sense reasoning.
Now here's where the adversarial
part of this comes in,
we're going to do adversarial
filtering for SWAG.
For each of the
examples in our corpus,
and there are over
100,000 examples in SWAG,
we're going to be given the
system input like, "the mixture
creams the butter.
Sugar."
And then we'll have a generator
model- in the case of SWAG,
this was an LSTM produce some
distractors for the target.
So let's suppose that the actual
target continuation is added,
we'd have a model produce "is
sweet" and "is in many foods."
And then we have
the filtering model.
If it guesses correctly
for "is added,"
then we're going to drop
out this entire example
and we'll create some
new distractors like
"is sprinkled on top"
or "is in many foods."
And in this case, if the
model guesses incorrectly
like suppose it
chooses b in this case,
then we'll keep this example
because relative to the current
models for the thing
we're using to generate
these distractors and the thing
that we're using to filter,
this is a challenging example.
And the idea is
that we can repeat
this for a bunch of iterations,
continually retraining
the filtering model
so that it gets
better and better and therefore,
ending up with a dataset that
is really, really difficult
in terms of the current models
that we had available to us.
Here's a picture
of test accuracy.
This is interesting here.
They actually did an
ensemble of filtering models
to try to key into
different notions that
might be indicating which
is the correct continuation.
So they start by using just
a multi-layer perceptron
for efficiency,
and then they bring
in all of these ensembles.
And you can see
the test accuracy
as we do this iterative
filtering very quickly goes
down so that by iteration
140 we're at 10% accuracy.
So that's the
sense in which this
is a very difficult dataset
because given the generator
model and the filtering model
that we have available to us,
we have a dataset that is
very difficult in terms
of a classification task.
So that looks really
exciting and challenging
and I think the authors
expected this dataset
to last for a very long time.
However, the BERT paper,
the original BERT paper,
did evaluations on SWAG and
essentially solved the problem.
BERT Large got 86.6 and 86.3%
on the dev and test sets
for SWAG respectively, a
very unexpected result given
that I just showed you that
the SWAG authors got about 10%
with their current models.
And even closely related models
to BERT like this ESIM model
here, were really pretty
low in their performance.
So BERT looked like
a real breakthrough
and you can see that it's
in some sense superhuman
relative to the SWAG estimates.
So wow.
So, of course, we know what the
response should be given that
we're talking essentially about
model-in-the-loop adversarial
dataset creation.
That leads us to HellaSWAG.
They made some
changes to the dataset
that they use for
HellaSWAG, but I
would say the
fundamental thing is
that we do the same adversarial
filtering with the generator,
except now we have much
more powerful filtering
and generator models,
thanks to developments
related to transformers.
So for HellaSWAG, we again
have human performance
that's really good.
This is very
reassuring because we
are using much more
powerful models at step 4.
As you can expect, BERT
is no longer easily
able to solve this problem.
Here's a further summary of
the results with BERT Large
before I remember that it's
essentially solved SWAG.
Now it's down around 50%
which shows that it still gets
traction but is nothing like
the superhuman performance
that we saw for SWAG.
OK.
Now let's move into a
slightly different mode,
and this is going to be a
kind of human-in-the-loop
adversarial dataset
creation method.
The first entry in this space
was the adversarial NLI data
set, I think this is a really
visionary and exciting paper.
Adversarial NLI is a direct
response to the previous things
that we've seen with the
SNLI and multi-NLI datasets
where models seem to do
well on those benchmarks
but are easily susceptible
to simple adversaries.
With adversarial
NLI, we're going
to hopefully push
systems to be much more
robust to those
adversaries and explore
a much wider range of
the space of things
you might see under the heading
of natural language inference.
So here's how it worked.
There's a human in the loop,
an annotator, and the annotator
is presented with a premise
sentence and a condition
that they need to be in,
which is just an NLI label-
entailment,
contradiction, or neutral.
The annotator writes a
hypothesis to go along with
the premise and the condition
and then a state-of-the-art
model comes in and makes a
prediction about the premise
hypothesis pair.
If the model's prediction
matches the condition, that
is, if the model
was correct, then
the annotator needs to return
to step 2 and try again
with a new hypothesis.
And we could continue
in that loop.
If the model was fooled,
the premise-hypothesis pair
is independently validated by
other annotators, of course.
So what we get out of this
is we hope a dataset that
is intuitive for humans,
because of the check in step 5,
but assuming we continue to
loop around through 2, 3 and 4,
an example that is really
difficult for whatever
model is in the loop.
And the expectation is that as
we put better and better models
in the loop here, we're going to
get even more challenging data
sets as an outcome.
NLI examples tend to be
impressively complex.
You can see that this example
has a very long premise.
The hypothesis was
relatively shorter.
And an intriguing aspect
of adverserial NLI
is that annotators
also constructed
a reason or a rationale
for their label
holding between the
premise-hypothesis pair.
To date, as far as I know,
relatively little use
has been made of
these texts, but I
think they could bring in other
aspects of natural language
inference reasoning
and that could
be an exciting new direction.
Adversarial NLI is a
difficult dataset indeed.
We have a similar
sort of leaderboard
that we've seen throughout
this adversarial regime where
across different rounds
of NLI- there are three,
or cumulatively
for the data set,
even really excellent models
that do really well on SNLI
and multi-NLI are posting
really low numbers for all
of these variants of the
dataset and that shows you
that this is truly
a difficult problem.
And as far as I know,
not much progress
has been made since this
dataset was released
on boosting these numbers.
So it stands as an
interesting challenge.
Stepping back here, I'd just
like to say that I think we
find in this paper a real vision
for future development and that
you see this also in the SWAG
and HellaSWAG papers as those
authors say this adversarial
dataset creation is "a path
for NLP progress going
forward: toward benchmarks that
adversariallly co-evolve with
evolving state-of-the-art
models."
Right, with SWAG and
HellaSWAG, we saw this.
SWAG got solved but
the response was clear,
bring the best
model in and use it
to create the successor
dataset set that
stands as a real challenge.
You have the similar picture
from the adversarial NLI paper.
This process of having iterative
rounds with humans in the loop
yields a moving post-dynamic
target for natural language
understanding systems, rather
than the static benchmarks
that eventually saturate.
And we've seen repeatedly
that our benchmarks saturate
very quickly these days, so we
need this kind of moving post
to make sure we continue to
make meaningful progress.
The Nie et al project
gave rise, I believe,
to this Dynabench platform, an
open source platform for model
and human-in-the-loop creation.
As of this writing, there are
four datasets available that
have been created on
Dynabench, an NLI data
set which is a
successor to ANLI,
a question-answering dataset,
a sentiment dataset, and a hate
speech dataset.
So if you're working on
problems of this form
or you have a model that would
fit into this mold for one
of these tasks,
I would encourage
you to explore some training of
the systems on these datasets
to see whether you're
making progress
or whether they stand as
true adversaries for whatever
innovative thing you're doing.
Finally, I want to close with
a really important question
for this area that
kind of remains open,
can adversarial training
improve systems?
There is a course of
concern that as we construct
ever harder data sets,
we're pushing systems
into stranger parts of the
linguistic and conceptual space
which could actually degrade
their real world performance.
We have to keep an eye on that.
And the evidence so
far, I think is pointing
to yes as an answer
to this question
but the evidence is a bit mixed.
So I've mentioned that in
the SQuAD adversarial paper
from Jia and Liang, training
on adversarial examples
makes them more robust
to of those examples
but not to simple variants, so
it's hardly very much progress.
In this paper, they found that
adversarial training provided
no additional robustness
benefit in the experiments
using the testset, despite the
fact that the model achieved
near 100% accuracy classifying
adversarial examples included
in the train set.
So that's a more
worrisome picture.
But this is more hopeful.
Fine-tuning with a few
adversarial examples
improved systems in some
cases, especially where
you bring in inoculation.
And this is hopefully
yet again, adversarially
generated paraphrases
improve model robustness
to syntactic variation.
That's really the dream
there- that as a result
of doing this new
kind of training,
we get systems that
are truly more robust.
But I think we might need more
evidence on this picture, which
means more datasets
of this form,
and more and interesting use
of the available resources
and I would just love to see
what the emerging picture is
over the next year or two.