CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is part 4 in our series
on analysis methods in NLP.
We're going to be
talking about probing.
This is the first of the two
structural evaluation methods
that we're going to consider.
It's time to get really
introspective about what
our models are doing.
Here's an overview
of the probing idea.
The core thing is that we're
going to use supervised models,
those are the probe
models, to determine
what's latently encoded in
the hidden representations
of our target models.
This is often applied in the
context of BERTology, which
should be like, I have BERT
as a pre-trained artifact
and I would like to
understand the nature
of its hidden representations.
What do they latently encode?
And for that you might
use probe models.
Probing, as you will
see, can be a source
of really valuable and
interesting insights,
but we do need to proceed with
caution on two major issues
here.
First, a very
powerful probe model
since it is a
supervised model might
lead you to see things
that aren't really
in your target model,
but rather just things
that your probe
model has learned.
And you might, therefore,
overdiagnose latent information
in your target model
when, in fact, it's
all being stored in the probe.
And I'm going to offer you
a technique for navigating
around that issue.
And the second one is that
probes cannot tell us about
whether the information that
we identify has any causal
relationship with the
target model's behavior.
It will be very tempting
for you to say, Oh,
I have discovered that this
representation layer includes
part of speech information.
And you might therefore conclude
that part of speech information
is important for whatever
task you have set,
but we can't actually
make that inference.
It could be that the part
of speech information
is simply latently
encoded, but not actually
especially relevant to your
model's input/output behavior.
Final section of
the slide show, I'm
going to just talk briefly
about unsupervised probes, which
seek to address this first
problem here that the probe
model might actually
be the thing that's
encoding all of this
information that we
claimed to have discovered.
And then when we talk about
future attribution methods,
we'll get closer to
being able to address
some of these causal questions.
Let's begin with the
core method for probing.
And just because this is a
typical framing of these ideas,
I've got depicted here what
you might think of as a,
kind of, generic
transformer-based model, where
we have three layers
with all of these blocks.
These maybe are the
output representations
from each of the
transformer blocks.
And you can see that I've got an
input sequence coming in here.
And the idea would
be that we could
pick some hidden
representation in this model,
like this middle one, h here.
And decide that we're going
to fit a small linear model
presumably on that
hidden representation,
and see whether
we can figure out
whether that
representation encodes
some information about some
task that we care about.
So for example, if you
wanted to figure out
whether sentiment or
lexical entailment
was encoded at that point,
you'd need a labeled data set
for sentiment or entailment.
And then you would
fit the probe model
on this representation
and use that
to determine the extent to which
that information is encoded
there.
This depiction is a
little bit poetical.
So it's worth just walking
through mechanically
what you'd actually be doing.
You would use this BERT model
and process different examples,
like for the sequence here.
And get an output
representation,
which should be paired
with some task label.
And you would repeatedly do
that for different inputs.
You're essentially
using this BERT model
as an engine for
creating representations
that will become your
feature representation matrix
x paired with your labels y.
And it is this
model that will be
the basis for your linear probe
model, this small linear model
as I've identified in here.
So you're kind of
using BERT as an engine
to create a data
set that is then
the input to a supervised
learning problem.
Another perspective
would be that you're
kind of using frozen BERT
parameters in this case,
and fitting a model
on top of them.
It's just that instead of
picking an output point,
you've picked possibly one of
the internal representations.
And this is very general.
And in fact, most
often, when you
read without quotes
in the literature,
they're actually
sequence problems
like part of speech tagging
or named entity recognition.
And therefore, you might
use an entire layer or even
a set of layers as the
basis for your probe model.
Now you can hear in
my description there,
that there is a interesting
judgment call that you're
making about whether you are
probing or simply learning
a new model, right?
Probes, in the sense that
I just presented them,
are supervised
models whose inputs
are frozen parameters of the
models that we're probing,
our target models, right?
This is hard to
distinguish from simply
fitting a supervised
model as usual
with some particular
choice of featurization.
As a result of this,
it is essentially
a foregone conclusion
that at least some
of the information that
we identify with our probe
is actually stored in the
probe model parameters
and it's just that we provided
useful input features that
allow this probe
to be successful.
And that's the sense in
which the inputs are latently
encoding this information.
But with the probe,
we have not determined
that it is truly latently
there, but rather
that it's a stepping-- a
stepping stone toward a model
that could be
successful at this as
conceived of as a
supervised learning task.
So those are important
distinctions to keep in mind.
As a result of this,
more powerful probes,
like deep neural networks,
might find more information
than simple linear models.
But that's not because
they're able to tease out
more information from the
representations themselves,
but rather because
the probe model now
has so much more capacity
for storing information
about the task that
you're probing for.
So there are a bunch of
different judgment calls here.
And that's difficult. But
a very productive entry
into this space is this
really lovely paper
from Hewitt and
Liang 2019, where
they introduce the
notion of a control task
and the corresponding
metric of probe selectivity.
So here's the idea.
A control task will
be some random task
with the same input/output
structure as the target task
that we want to use
for our probing.
Like for example, for
word-sense classification,
you might have words assigned
random fixed words senses
independent of their context.
Or for part of speech
tagging, instead
of using the actual
part of speech tags,
you might randomly
assigned words
to fixed tags from
the same tag space.
Or for parsing, it gets a
little bit more nuanced,
but you might have some
edge assignment strategies
that you use semirandomly to
link different pairs of words
into a kind of pseudo-parse.
And that would serve
as a control task
for trying to surface latent
actual parsing information.
So those are control tasks.
And then selectivity is
simply the difference
between your probe
performance on the task
and your identical probe model
structure on these control
tasks.
And Hewitt and Liang used this
to tease out what, I think,
is a pretty clear
intuition, which
is that as you get
more powerful probes,
they simply become
less selective.
So along the x-axis here,
we have MLP hidden units.
So we have model complexity
from left to right,
where we have very
complicated, powerful models
at the right-hand side.
And here we have accuracy.
And we're measuring
our control task in red
and our actual probe task
in this light blue here.
And selectivity is the
difference between those two.
So you can see, for example,
that the very weak models,
the ones with two hidden units
have very high selectivity.
Whereas by the time I have
this very powerful NLP
with lots of hidden
units, selectivity
has gone almost to 0.
And it's very hard to say that
you've uncovered any latent
information.
Because even the control task
is fully solvable with a model
that has this much capacity.
So I think what this
is pushing us toward
is always having control
tasks as part of the picture
and always reporting
selectivity so
that we can control for the
complexity of the probe model
itself.
That's an important and
easy, practical step
that will give you a clearer
picture of what you've actually
surfaced with your probe.
That's the first issue.
The second issue is just
something that you should keep
in mind as a theoretical
fact about probing,
which is that it is
fundamentally limited
in the sense that it cannot tell
you that the information you
discover has any causal impact
on the model's input/output
behavior.
To illustrate that,
I'm just going
to show you a simple example
that kind of proves this.
So imagine over
here on the left,
I have a simple model that's
going to take in three integers
and sum them.
So the output here will be
the sum of three integers.
Like if I put in 1, 2,
3, it will output 6.
And it does that by representing
each one of those integers
as the single-dimensional vector
that just is that integer.
And then we have a whole
bunch of transformer
like model parameters,
dense connections here
that will lead us finally
to the output layer.
So you can easily imagine that
you probe this position L1 here
and you find that it computes x
plus y, which might be starting
to reveal for you that
there's some kind of tree
structure to this model
even though it was densely
connected.
It has learned a structured
solution to the problem.
And you might probe L2 and
find that it computes z.
And that would really
lead you to think
that you've got a, kind
of, interesting tree
structure with constituents
for this addition problem.
And that's certainly suggestive.
However, here is an
example of a model that
shows that neither L1 nor L2 has
anything to do with the model's
output predictions.
It is entirely that
middle state that
tells the complete
story about the output.
I'll leave you to work through
the details if you choose to,
but a shortcut
way to see that is
that the final parameters
that take us from these output
representations
to the predictions
have zeroed out the first
and third positions,
leaving only the
second one as having
any kind of causal efficacy.
Even though in this
model, if you probe,
you do indeed find that it
looks like those representations
perfectly encode these
two pieces of information.
That's a dramatic and
clear, simple illustration
of how a probe
could get divorced
from the actual causal
behavior of the model.
Again, something that's
worth keeping in mind.
And finally, to close
this out, of course,
for that first problem about
distinguishing between probe
capacity and actually
latently encoded
information, one
response to that that's
developing in the
literature now is
to develop unsupervised probes.
These would be models
like these that
seek to find in actual
facts about the model
with no additional supervision,
the latent information
that we hope to find.
And this would come
from simply doing
linear transformations
of the parameters
and measuring distance
between parameters
as a way of getting a sense
for what's actually there
without the
complications that come
from having this additional
supervised probe model.
And finally, for much more
information about probes,
and what we think we've
learned from them,
and what they can
tell us, I encourage
you to check out
this paper by Rogers
et al, a primer on BERTology.
It has a large and
interesting subsection
entirely devoted to what
probes have told us.
Certainly worth a look, and a
great overview of the space.