CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome back, everyone.
This is part 2 in our series
on methods and metrics.
We're going to be talking
about classifier metrics.
I'm sort of assuming that the
metrics I'll be discussing
are broadly familiar to us.
I think that's a chance
for us to step back and be
reflective about what values
these familiar metrics actually
encode.
Because that really is
the name of the game here.
No matter what kind of
task you're working on
or what the structure
of your model
is like, it's just fundamentally
true that different evaluation
metrics will encode different
values, different goals
you have for your system, and
different kinds of hypotheses
that you might be pursuing.
You can hear in that, that
really fundamentally choosing
a metric is a crucial aspect to
any kind of experimental work.
It's a fundamental step
in how we operationalize
hypotheses in terms of data, and
models, and model comparisons.
As a result, you should
feel free, for whatever task
you're working on, to motivate
new metrics or specific uses
of existing metrics,
depending on what
your actual goals for your
experiments actually are.
Relatedly, for
established tasks,
you'll probably
feel some pressure
to use specific
well-established metrics.
But you should always,
as a scientist,
feel empowered to push back
if you feel that the accepted
metrics are not reflective
of your hypothesis
or are distorting our
notions of progress somehow.
Because remember,
areas of research
can stagnate due
to poor metrics.
And so we have to be vigilant.
We have to be on the
lookout for cases
in which the metrics
we've accepted
might be at odds with
the actual goals we have
for the research we're doing.
Let's begin our discussion
of classifier metrics
by talking about confusion
matrices, a pretty fundamental
data structure for a
lot of the calculations
that we'll perform.
So by convention, for
my confusion matrices,
I'll have the actual labels
going across the rows here.
And across the columns,
I'll have the predictions
from some classifier model.
So you can see in
this confusion matrix,
that there were 15 cases in
which the model predicted
positive.
And the actual
label was positive.
Where there-- whereas there are
10 cases where the actual label
was positive and
the model predicted
negative, and so forth for the
other values in this table.
I think that seems familiar.
It's something we
can take for granted.
But we should remember that
behind the scenes here,
a threshold was imposed
in order to create
these categorical predictions.
By and large, classifier
models that we use today
predict probability
distributions over the labels.
And so in order to create an
actual categorical prediction,
we decided, for
example, that the label
with the maximum probability
would be the true one.
And that was-- the result
of that decision was
used to aggregate this table.
But, of course, different
choices of that threshold
might give very
different results.
And there might be
contexts in which
we want to explore
the full range
of probabilistic predictions.
That's something I'll return to
at the end of the screencast.
Final note about this.
It can be helpful in the
context of confusion matrices
to add a column for what's
called support, which is simply
the number of actual
true instances
that fall into each class.
So there are 125
positive instances
in this corpus, 35 negative,
and over 1,000 that's
all in the neutral category.
And that's already illuminating
about how specific metrics
might deal with that extremely
imbalanced vector of support
values.
So let's start with
accuracy-- by far,
the most famous and familiar
of all the classifier metrics.
Accuracy is simply the number
of correct predictions divided
by the total number of examples.
In terms of our
confusion matrices,
that is just the sum
of all the values
along the diagonal divided
by the sum of all the values
that are in this table.
The bounds are 0 and 1, of
course, with 0 the worst
and 1 the best.
In terms of the value
encoded by accuracy,
I would say it's an attempt
to answer the question,
how often is the system correct?
And that kind of feeds
into the weaknesses here.
So the weaknesses are,
first, there's no per class
notions of accuracy.
Not directly.
We just get a single
holistic number.
And relatedly, there is
just a complete failure
to control for class size.
So you can see, for example,
in this confusion matrix,
that performance on
the neutral class
will completely dominate
the accuracy values.
And it's to the
point, in this table,
where no matter
how much progress
we make on the positive
and negative classes
because they are so much smaller
in terms of their support
for neutral, that progress
is unlikely to be reflected
in our accuracy values.
And that's why if you
return to the value encoded,
you can see that just at
a raw fundamental level,
it is simply answering how
often is the system correct?
Another thing to keep in mind
is that for many classifier
models, the loss
for those models
is what's called the
cross-entropy loss.
It's also called the negative
log-loss in Scikit-learn.
And that value is inversely
proportional to accuracy.
The takeaway there
is that even as we
might choose other metrics to
compare models and evaluate
models, we should keep in mind
that our classifiers themselves
are kind of engines for
trying to maximize accuracy.
And so they are likely to
inherit whatever properties,
and values, and
strengths, and weaknesses
are inherent in the
accuracy calculation, which
as we'll see, could be at
odds with our actual values
for the system that
we're developing.
And that kind of feeds nicely
into precision, recall,
and F scores which are
attempts to make up
for some of the weaknesses
that you see in accuracy.
We'll start with precision.
This is a per class notion.
For a class k, it's
the correct predictions
for k divided by the sum
of all the guesses for k
that were made by your model.
So in terms of this
confusion matrix,
if we focus on the
positive class here,
the numerator is the number
of correct predictions
for that class divided by
the sum of all the values
that are in this column.
And for the negative class,
we would repeat that.
The numerator would be 15, and
we would sum over the column.
And finally, for neutral,
the numerator would be 1,000.
And we would again
sum over this column.
And that leads to this
vector of precision values
that you see along
the bottom here.
The bounds of precision
are 0 and 1 approximately.
With 0 the worst and 1 the best.
There is an important
caveat here though.
Precision is technically
undefined in situations
where a model makes no
predictions about a given
class.
Because in that situation,
you're dividing by 0.
And that's
technically undefined.
It is common practice
to map those to 0,
but we should keep
in mind that we
are making that extra decision.
The value encoded is a
kind of conservative one.
We're going to penalize
incorrect guesses
for a certain class.
So you can imagine that a
failure mode there is to just
rarely guess a certain class.
That is the core weakness.
You can achieve high
precision for a class k
simply by rarely guessing k.
So we'll obviously
need to offset
that with some other pressure.
And by and large, the
offset pressure is recall.
Recall is, again,
a per class notion.
For a class k, it's going to be
the correct predictions for k
divided by the sum of all
the true members of k.
So now we're going
to operate row--
rowwise.
We focus on the positive class.
Our numerator is 15, the
number of true predictions
for the positive class, divided
by the sum of all the values
along the rows.
That is all the true members
of that class for positive.
That gives us a
recall value of 0.12.
And we can repeat that
for the other two rows.
The bounds of 0 and 1.
0 the worst and 1 the best.
The value encoded
is a permissive one.
We want to penalize
missed true cases.
We would like to make a lot
of predictions about a class
in order to avoid leaving
any out, so to speak.
And that leads into
the core weakness.
We can achieve higher
recall for a class k
simply by always guessing k.
Never mind the mistakes.
As long as we get all the actual
cases into our predictions,
we're doing well by recall.
And you can hear
in that that it's
important to offset this
pressure by something else.
And that's standard precision.
And the way we offset
these two pressures
is typically with F scores.
So F scores are a harmonic mean
of the precision and recall
scores.
It's again a per class notion.
And it has this
weighting value, beta.
If we want to evenly balance
precision and recall,
then we set beta to 1.
So here's that
confusion matrix again.
And along this column here,
I've given the per class
F1 values here.
The bounds are 0 and
1 as before with 0
the worst and 1 the best.
And you can count on the fact
that the F1 score for a class
will always fall between the
precision and recall classes,
because it's a,
kind of, an average.
It's the harmonic mean.
What's the value encoded?
The best way I can say this
is that we're essentially
trying to answer the
question, for a given class
k, how much do
predictions for k align
with a true instance of k?
That is aligning with
both precision and recall
as pressures.
And then we can
use the beta value
to control how much
weight we place
on precision versus recall.
What are the
weaknesses of F scores?
Well, I can really think of two.
The first is that
there's no normalization
for the size of
the dataset because
of the way we use the
denominators for the row
and column sums.
And relatedly, for a given class
that we decide to focus on,
we actually ignore most of
the data that's in the table.
Consider the fact
that if we decided
to calculate the F1 score
for the positive class,
we pay attention to
these column values
and these are row
values, but we completely
ignore these four values here.
They're just not involved
in the calculation at all.
And as a result, the
positive class F1 score
might give a distorted picture
of what the model's predictions
are actually like in
virtue of the fact
that they leave out so much of
the data here as you can see.
Now because F scores
are a per class notion,
I think, that's
useful in the sense
that it gives us a perspective
on each one of the classes
separately.
But for many kinds
of model evaluations,
we need a summary
number, a single number
that we can use to
compare models and assess
overall progress.
So we're going to do
some kind of averaging.
And I'd like to
offer you three ways
that we might average
these F scores.
Macro-averaging, weighted
averaging, and micro-averaging.
And as you'll see, these
encode quite different
values about how we want to
think about the F scores.
Macro-averaging is a
averaging that we've
done at various points
throughout the quarter.
It is simply the
arithmetic mean of all the
per category F1 scores.
So it's just the mean of the
values along this column.
Its bounds are 0 and 1 with
0 the worst and 1 the best.
What value does encode?
Well, it's the same values
that we get from F scores,
plus the additional and
non-trivial assumption
that all of the
classes are equal
regardless of size differences
between them, right?
And that kind of feeds
into the weaknesses here.
A classifier that does well
only on the small classes
might not actually do
well in the real world.
If you imagine counterfactually
that for our given model here,
we had really
outstanding F1 scores
for positive and negative
and really low for neutral.
That might really be at odds
with how this classifier would
behave in the world,
assuming that most
of the examples that
are streaming in
are in the neutral category.
Relatedly, a classifier that
does well only on large classes
might do poorly on the
small, but nonetheless vital
classes that are in our data.
And that just reflects the fact
that very often in NLP, it's
the small classes that are the
most precious, the ones that we
care about the most.
And we're not reflecting that
kind of asymmetry in our values
by simply taking the average
of all these F scores.
Weighted average
F scores will give
a very different perspective
on model performance.
In this case, we
are again just going
to take an average
of the F1 scores,
but now weighted by
the amount of support
for each one of the classes.
That, again, has bound
0 to 1 with 0 the worst
and 1 the best.
The value encoded is
the same as the values
that we get for the F scores,
but now with the added
assumption that the size of the
class as the amount of support
really does matter.
And that's going to feed
into the weaknesses.
And the fundamental thing
here is that large classes
will dominate.
Just as with accuracy,
the larger our classes,
the more it's
going to contribute
to our overall summary number.
And that can lead to the kind
of problematic situation,
where the small classes are just
not relevant for the evaluation
metric.
That could reflect
your values because.
If what you really
care about is raw rate
of correct
predictions, you might
want to weight the larger
classes more heavily.
But again, for many
contexts in NLP
we really care about
how much progress
we can make on the small, but
nonetheless important classes.
And so in those contexts,
weighted averaging
is probably not
the right choice.
The final averaging scheme
that I would like to consider
is micro-average F scores.
This will be very similar to
weighted averaging of F1 scores
and is directly
connected to accuracy.
The way this works is
a little bit involved.
We start with this
core confusion matrix.
And we're going to break it down
into three smaller confusion
matrices, one per class.
So you can see this
one on the left
here is for the positive class.
The yes'es are 15 and the no's
are the sum of these two values
here along this row.
The no's are the 20, which is
the sum of these two values.
And then there's
no no categories,
for all the remaining data
in this quadrant here.
We repeat that same procedure
for the negative class
and for the neutral class.
And then we simply sum
up those three smaller
tables into one big
yes-no confusion matrix
and calculate the F1
scores per category.
That gives us two scores here.
One for yes and one for no.
The bounds on this are 0 and 1.
With 0 the worst and 1 the best.
The value encoded is
really easy to state.
Macro-averaged F1 scores
for the yes category
are equivalent to accuracy
scores numerically.
So this is identical in
terms of that metric.
And we have this additional
problem now that--
well, we have the same
kind of value reflected
as we have for the weighted
F scores or for accuracy,
but now we have brought
in an additional source
of uncertainty, which is we
have a number for the yes
category and the no category.
And hence, no single
summary number.
The convention in
the literature is
to focus on the yes category,
but that simply brings us back
to accuracy with a more
involved calculation.
So that's obviously
not very productive.
And I would say
as a result here,
the two real choices
that you want to make
are between macro-averaging
and weighted averaging
of your F1 scores.
And again, that will
come down to what
your fundamental
values are and what
hypotheses you're pursuing.
The final point I want to
make is that thus far, we
have operated in terms of
the confusion matrix, which
involved imposing a threshold
on probabilistic predictions
in order to create categorical
values that we could then
compare with precision,
and recall, and so forth.
Precision and recall curves
offer a fundamentally different
perspective.
In this case, instead of
imposing one threshold,
we'll take every
possible value that's
predicted by our classifier
to be a potential threshold,
and essentially create a
bunch of confusion matrices
based on that successive
series of thresholds.
And then we can plot the
trade-offs between precision
here along the y-axis
and recall along
the x-axis for all those
different notions of threshold.
And that can be really
illuminating in terms
of helping us see how our
system trades precision
and recall against each other.
And help us find based
on values that we
have about our
problem and our goals,
what the optimal balance
between precision and recall
actually is.
And then if you
do need to summary
a number of this entire
table, average precision,
which is implemented
in Scikit-learn
is a standard way of
summarizing the entire curve
with a single number
without, though, imposing
that single threshold
that was so much shaping
all of the previous
metrics that we discussed.