CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to part 2 in our series
on presenting your research.
We're going to be talking about
writing papers in our fields.
To start, let's look at the
outline of a typical NLP paper.
By and large, these are either
four or eight page papers
in a two-column format that
you get from the style sheets.
Those links don't
include the references.
And there are a
bunch of conventions
for how the papers are
typically organized.
So you have your title
in abstract on page one.
Usually, you have
an intro section
that kind of fits on that
first page, maybe a little bit
onto the second.
In place two, you
discuss the related work
or prior literature
or background
that's needed to
kind of contextualize
the work that you're doing.
Then there's typically
a data section, followed
by a section on a
model or this could
be thought of as the
kind of core proposal
section of the paper.
Then there'll be some methods
related to the experiments.
The reporting of the
results of the experiments.
And then some analysis of what
the experimental results mean.
And then possibly
a short conclusion.
It's not set in
stone that you have
to follow these conventions,
but if you do follow them,
I think it will be
easier on your readers
and also easier
on you as a writer
because you can kind
of slot your ideas
into this familiar format.
Let's look at those sections
in a little bit of detail.
So starting with the intro,
the ideal intro, to my mind,
really tells the full story
of your paper at a high level.
We don't need all the details,
but it is very helpful
to know from beginning to end
what the paper accomplishes.
And good intros provide
all of that information
and really tell the reader
precisely what they'll
learn as they go through
the rest of the paper.
In place two as I
said, is the discussion
of background material
or related work
or prior literature.
And this is an opportunity for
you to contextualize your work,
and provide insights
into the major themes
of the literature as a whole.
What you should really
be thinking about doing
is using each
paper or each theme
that you identify as a chance
to kind of contextualize
your ideas, and
especially articulate
what's special about
the contribution
that you're making.
So this kind of sets the
stage for the reader.
The data section,
this could vary a lot.
This could be very detailed if
you're offering a new dataset,
or using a dataset in some
unfamiliar way the community is
not used to.
But of course, if you're
just adopting some data
off the shelf, then this
section might be pretty short.
Then you get to the heart of
your proposal, your model.
You want to flesh
out your own approach
and really help us understand
your core contribution.
Then we turn to
supporting your ideas
with some experimental evidence.
You report the methods,
your experimental approach,
including descriptions
of the metrics.
And again, that will
be long or short
depending on whether the metrics
are familiar or unfamiliar.
You want to describe your
baseline models and anything
else that's relevant to kind
of understanding precisely
what's going to happen
in your experiments.
I will say that for details
about hyperparameters
and optimization choices and
so forth, you can probably
move those to an
appendix, unless they're
really central to the argument.
What you want to offer here are
kind of the crucial pieces that
will help the reader
understand precisely what you
did for your experiments.
Then we get our results.
This could be a no-nonsense
report of what happened.
It's probably mainly
going to be supported
by figures and tables that
report a summary of your core
findings according to your
data models and metrics.
And then things open up a bit.
You have an analysis section.
I think this is
really important.
You should articulate for the
reader what your results mean,
what they don't
mean, where they can
be improved, where their limits
are, and so forth, right?
These sections vary a lot
depending on the nature
of the paper and the findings.
But I think they're
always important
and they can be very rewarding.
It is intimidating because
this is awfully open ended.
But I'm hoping that the previous
unit on analysis methods
in our field offer some really
good general purpose tools
and techniques for doing
rich analyses of this sort
and really helping us
understand precisely what you
accomplished.
Now this is, as I said,
is not set in stone,
and different projects will call
for different variants on it.
And one really prominent
variant that you see
is that, if you have
multiple experiments
with multiple datasets
you might want
to repeat that method's results
analysis rhythm across all
of your experiments
to give them kind
of separate sections
in your paper.
But again, it really
depends on what
you think the most natural
way to express your ideas is.
These things aren't
set in stone,
they're just
conventions that help us
as readers and as authors.
Then finally, you
have a conclusion.
This is probably a quick
summary of what the paper did,
and then an opportunity
for you to chart out
future directions that you
or others might pursue.
So it's a chance to be more
outward looking and expansive.
Let me close the screen cast
with some general advice
on scientific
writing that I think
can be helpful kind
of in the background
as you think about
expressing your ideas.
First, I just want to review
this really nice piece
from Stuart Shieber,
where he advocates
for what he calls the
"rational reconstruction"
approach to scientific writing.
And to build up to that, he
offers two contrasting styles
that you might think about.
The first is what he calls
the continental style.
This is in which one
states the solution with as
little introduction or
motivation as possible,
sometimes not even saying
what the problem was.
He says, "Readers will have
no clue as to whether you're
right or not without
incredible efforts
in close reading of the paper.
But at least, they'll
think you're a genius."
At the other end
of the extreme, you
have what he calls
the historical style.
And this is a whole history of
false starts, wrong attempts,
near misses, redefinitions
of the problem.
This is a kind of
genuine history
of maybe the struggles
that you endured
as you built up to the final
product for your paper.
And Shieber says,
"This is much better
than the continental style,
because a careful reader can
probably follow the
line of reasoning
that the author went through
and use this as motivation.
But the reader
will probably think
you're a bit addle-headed."
We don't need to hear
about every dead end
and every false start,
what we would like, rather,
is what Shieber calls the
rational reconstruction.
You don't present the actual
history that you went through,
but rather, an idealized
history that perfectly motivates
each step in the solution.
You might selectively
choose models
that you abandoned as a way
of helping the other reader
understand how you built toward
your actual core set of methods
and findings and results.
So it's going to be a kind
of streamlined version
of that historical style.
The goal in pursuing the
rational reconstruction style
is not to convince
the reader that you're
brilliant, or addle-headed
for that matter,
but that your
solution is trivial.
Shieber says it takes a
certain strength of character
to take that as one's goal.
Right, the goal of writing
a really excellent paper
is that the reader
comes away thinking,
that was clear and obvious,
and even I could have done it.
That's an act of
genuine communication.
And it does take a
strength of character.
But in the end, this is what
we should all be striving for,
this kind of really clear
and open communication.
This is also a nice
document from David Goss.
He has some hints on
mathematical style.
There's a bunch of
low level details
in there, especially related
to presenting very formal work.
The piece that I
wanted to pull out
is just "Have mercy
on the reader."
This is, again, recalling
the rational reconstruction
approach that Shieber advocated
for, where you're really
thinking about what it's like
to be a reader encountering
the ideas for the first
time and genuinely
trying to understand
what you accomplished.
You have to really
think about what
it's like to be in
that position in order
to have a successful
and clear paper.
I also really like this piece
from the novelist Cormac
McCarthy which was
published in Nature.
It's full of great advice.
The one piece that I wanted
to highlight is this.
Quote-unquote,
McCarthy says, "Decide
on your paper's theme
and two or three
points you want every
reader to remember.
This theme and these points
from the central thread
that runs through your piece.
The words, sentences,
paragraphs,
and sections are the needlework
that holds it together.
If something isn't needed to
help the reader understand
the main theme, omit it."
This is helpful to
me because I think
it not only results
in a better paper,
but it will also be easier
for you to write your paper.
Because the themes you
choose will determine
what to include and exclude,
and resolve a lot of low level
questions about your narrative.
And conversely, I've often found
that when I'm really struggling
to write a paper, it's because
I haven't figured out what
these core themes are and
I'm kind of casting about,
unsure of what's relevant
and what's irrelevant.
And if you step back
and really figure out
what you're trying
to communicate,
then the act of writing kind
of all falls into place.
And then the final bit of
advice that I wanted to offer,
which I'm going to return to
when we talk about presenting
work at conferences.
This comes from
Patrick Blackburn.
It's about talks,
but it really extends
to any kind of
communication and science,
is fundamental insight, he asks.
"Where do good talks,
and I think good papers,
where do they come from?"
And he says, "Honesty."
A good talk or a good
paper should never
stray far from simple,
honest communication.
And you can hear this
in the way that we talk
about evaluating your work.
That fundamentally
for us, we're looking
for papers that offer open,
clear, honest communication
about what happened,
and what it means.
And that's really a
fundamental value.
And I think it's
inspiring to think
about this as your
kind of guiding light
when you report your scientific
results to the community.