Hello, everyone.
This video kicks off our
series of screencasts
on supervised
sentiment analysis.
I just want to provide you
with an overview of the problem
and of the kind of work
we'll be doing, and also
a rationale for why
we'll be doing it.
So here's an overview
of the entire unit.
I want to, in this
screencast, motivate for you
the idea that
sentiment analysis is
a deep problem and an
important problem for NLU,
not only scientifically but also
for industrial applications.
In the next screencast,
I'll give you
some practical general tips
for doing sentiment analysis.
Following that, we'll have
two short screencasts that
introduce our core data sets,
the Stanford Sentiment Treebank
and a new data set
called DynaSent.
After that, I'll
introduce the code base
that will be working with on
the assignment in the bake-off.
That's sst.py, which is
included in the course code
distribution.
And I'm going to use
that code to illustrate
some important methodological
issues surrounding
supervised analysis in general,
which would be hyperparameter
tuning and comparison
of different classifiers
to see whether they are
different in some significant
statistical sense.
Then we'll talk about
feature representation,
both for large sparse linear
models with handbuilt features,
and also with more
deep learning oriented
distributional representations.
And that will be a nice segue
into the final unit, which
is on using recurrent neural
networks as classifiers
for supervised
sentiment analysis.
My hope is that this unit
can provide a refresher
on core concepts in
supervised learning,
introduce you to the problem
of sentiment analysis, which
I think is, as I said, a central
problem for natural language
understanding, and also
set you on your way
toward doing the
assignment and the bake-off
and possibly building
projects in this space.
For the associated
materials, as I said,
we've got a bunch of code.
sst.py is the core module.
And then we have a
notebook introducing
the Stanford Sentiment
Treebank as a dataset.
We have a second
notebook that's on what
I've called handbuilt features
and mostly linear models,
and then a third notebook that's
on using neural networks, which
more or less pushes you to using
distributional representations
instead of handbuilt features,
although, as you'll see,
the notebooks explore various
combinations of these ideas.
The homework in the bake-off
is in the notebook homework
sentiment.
And I'm going to
introduce that probably
in a separate screencast.
The core readings
are the two papers
that are oriented around
our data sets, the Standard
Sentiment Treebank and DynaSent.
And as supplementary
readings, you
might enjoy this compendium
from Pang and Lee.
It's a kind of overview of
the whole field of sentiment
analysis.
And it poses challenges
and questions that
are still relevant to this day.
And then Goldberg 2015
is an excellent overview
of using neural networks
in NLP, very generally.
But with lots of helpful
notation and so forth that
we're aligned with.
And that might
help you get a feel
for the landscape
of modeling choices
that you might
make in this space
and in subsequent
units for this course.
So I want to start
by just motivating
the idea that sentiment analysis
is an interesting problem.
Because you often hear people
say things like sentiment
analysis is solved or it's
overly simplistic or just too
easy.
And I think none of
those things are true.
And to motivate that, I just
want to do a little data driven
exercise with you.
So for these examples,
you should ask yourself,
which of these sentences
expresses sentiment at all?
And for the ones that you
think do express sentiment,
what is that sentiment?
Is it positive or
negative or maybe neutral
or something else?
So you might think those are
straightforward questions
but this is going to get
difficult really fast.
Consider the first example.
There was an earthquake
in California.
This is probably going to
sound like bad news to you.
And many sentiment
analysis systems
will assign this
negative sentiment.
But we should ask
ourselves, is this actually
a sentiment-laden sentence?
It is on the face of it
merely stating a fact.
And we might hold that for
sentiment to be expressed,
we need some kind of subjective
evaluative perspective
to be included in here, like
it was bad that there was
an earthquake in California.
And absent the "it
was bad" clause,
this might just be a neutral
statement of something
that had happened.
But the important point here
is that unless we settle
these questions, we'll have
continued indeterminacy
about what we're actually doing.
The team failed to
complete the challenge.
Is that positive or negative?
We might agree that it's more
than just a statement of fact,
although it's a borderline
case even for that question.
But if we did decide
it was sentiment-laden,
we would need to figure out
the perspective of the speaker.
Is the speaker
advocating for this team
or advocating for a
different team, right?
We win.
We lose.
It's really going to depend on
how the speaker is involved.
And that, of course,
is going to have
to become part of our definition
of what we're doing when
we assign sentiment labels.
They said it would be great.
On the face of it, this
expresses no speaker
perspective at all.
This is merely reporting
what somebody else said.
And we need to decide for
those obviously different
perspectives what
we're going to do
in terms of sentiment analysis.
Because after all,
this could continue.
They said it would be great
and they were right, which
is straightforwardly positive.
But it could also continue,
they said it would be great
and they were wrong.
And I think that reveals that
sentence 3 is not so obviously
encoding a particular
speaker perspective,
whereas these clauses are what
really tell the story for us
as sentiment analysts.
And then we get into
things that you might call
non-literal use of language.
The party fat cats are sipping
their expensive imported wines.
This has a lot of
positive language in it.
Maybe only fat cats
is the thing that
sounds like a direct smear.
But I think we could agree
that overall, this is probably
negative in its valence.
And that will be a
challenge for our systems
and also a challenge
for us in just
characterizing precisely
what was done here
in terms of sentiment.
Here's a similar example,
oh, you're terrible.
This might be a criticism.
And it might therefore be
straightforwardly negative.
On the other hand,
it could be a kind
of teasing form
of social bonding
that overall has a positive
effect on the discourse.
How are we going to resolve
that kind of context dependence?
Here's another one.
"Here's to ya, ya bastard."
It's got some negative
language, even something
that's kind of like a swear.
But this could be a friendly,
jocular phrase of some kind.
And we'll have to sort out
whether it's friendly and fun
because of its negativity,
or whether this
is straightforwardly
just a positive sentence.
And then here's a
case that's just
going to be a challenge
for our systems.
This is out of the movie 2001.
This is from an actual review.
"Many consider the
masterpiece bewildering,
boring, slow moving,
or annoying."
There is lot of
negative language there.
In fact, there's
very little that's
positive except "masterpiece."
But I think we can all
anticipate that overall this
is probably going to be a
positive review of that movie.
So that just shows
you that even if we're
clear about what we're
doing in terms of sentiment,
the linguistic challenge
here is significant.
And we could also
extend that to sentiment
like long suffering fans,
bittersweet memories,
hilariously
embarrassing moments.
These are things that are
going to blend positivity
and negativity and all sorts
of other emotional dimensions
in ways that just make sentiment
analysis very difficult to do
reliably.
And that's a nice segue
into this topic of sentiment
analysis in industry.
Because of course,
sentiment analysis
is one of the first tasks
that was really transformed
by data-driven approaches.
And it was the first
task to really make
an impact in industry.
There are lots of
startups and companies
that offer sentiment
analysis tools.
And it has obvious
import for things
like marketing, and customer
experience, and so forth.
And I would say
the first thing I
would say is that to this day,
the sentiment from industry,
so to speak, is that
sentiment analysis tools still
fall short.
This is from an
article from 2013.
And the gist of
it is, anyone who
says they're getting
better than 70% today
is lying, generally speaking.
From whatever notion
of 70% we have here,
I think we can agree that that's
too low and that we as a field
ought to be offering
tools that are better.
This is another kind
of equivocal headline.
Emotion AI technology has great
promise when used responsibly.
Affective computing knows
how you feel, sort of.
The sort of is kind of like
the equivalent of 70% here.
I think it shows that there's a
lot of work to be done if we're
going to have the
kind of impact we
want to have in the
technological sphere.
And then there's
another dimension
to this which we're not going
to really get to capture
but is worth planting
in your minds
because this could
become projects, right?
We're going to do
classification of sentiment
into positive,
negative, and neutral.
And that's often the starting
point for these industry tools.
Many business leaders
think they want
these pie charts to point
out like 30% negative,
70% positive.
And then in Q2, the
negativity is slightly up.
And that's surely a leading
indicator of something.
It looks like negativity
is on the rise.
But the issue is,
what do you do?
How does this help
with decision making?
Merely classifying these texts
and showing change over time
is not enough for any business
leader to take action.
But we need to know why this is
happening, what the underlying
factors are, basically what
are the customers saying
beyond these gross
classifications
into positive,
negative, and neutral.
And we should be
pushing ourselves
to design tools that can offer
that next layer of insight.
Affective computing, this
is a kind of transition
into the wider world here.
We're going to focus on
just sentiment analysis.
But you could think
about emotional analysis
and all other kinds of kind of
context dependent expression
in language, put that under the
heading of affective computing.
This is a diagram from a paper I
did a few years ago with Moritz
Sudhof.
It's a diagram of emotions
and other kinds of moods
that people feel.
The arcs give you a transition.
So they show that people
tend to transition
systematically from one
emotional state to another.
So what we're seeing
here is basically
just that this is a very
high dimensional space.
It's not just positive,
negative, neutral.
We have a wide
range of feelings,
and moods and emotions and
states that we go into.
And there's a lot of
structure to how we experience
those moods in our lives.
And it would be
great to break out
of the simple,
positive, negative mode
and tackle all of
these dimensions.
And in that spirit, here
what I've done on this slide
is just list out a whole
bunch of other tasks
that you might consider
adjacent to sentiment analysis.
But they are meaningfully
different from sentiment
analysis, things
like subjectivity,
bias, stance taking, hate
speech, microaggressions,
condescension, sarcasm,
deception and betrayal,
online trolls,
polarization, politeness,
and linguistic alignment.
These are all deeply social
things that are influenced by
and shape our language.
And I've selected these
papers in particular
because all of them have really
nice either crisp statements
of the problem and/or really
great public data sets
that you could use for
experiments in this wide world.
I think that's a
very exciting space
to explore as a
kind of next step
from what we're
doing in this unit.
But back down to Earth here.
Our primary data
sets, as I said,
are going to be the ternary
formulation of the Stanford
Sentiment Treebank which is just
positive, negative, neutral.
And also the DynaSent data set,
which has that same ternary
formulation.
The SST is movie reviews.
DynaSent is mostly reviews
of products and services,
I think heavily biased
toward restaurants
because the underlying
data is from Yelp.
And then for the
bake-off, we're going
to have a new dev/test split.
We'll use SST-3 as
well as this new one
of a corpus of sentences
from restaurant reviews.
So you can see that DynaSent
might be an asset here.
They all have this
ternary formulation.
And I'm hoping that the
combination of these data sets
gives us a really
interesting perspective,
not only on sentiment
analysis but also on kind
of how we design systems
that effectively transfer
across domains and maybe
learn simultaneously
in multiple domains.