CHRIS POTTS: Welcome, everyone,
to our first screencast
on contextual word
representations.
My goal here is to give you
an overview for this unit
and also give you a sense
for the conceptual landscape.
Let's start with the
associated materials.
You might think that the name
of the game for this unit
is to get you to the point
where you can work productively
with this notebook
called finetuning,
which shows you how to fine-tune
contextual word representations
for classification problems.
I think that could be a
very powerful mode for you
as you work on the current
assignment and bakeoff.
For background and intuitions,
I highly recommend this paper
by Noah Smith.
The beating heart of
this unit is really
the Transformer
architecture, which
was introduced by Vaswani,
et al., 2017 in a paper
called "Attention
is All You Need."
It's a highly readable paper.
But I recommend that
if you want to read it,
you instead read Sasha Rush's
outstanding contribution,
"The Annotated Transformer."
What this does is literally
reproduce the text of Vaswani,
et al., 2017 with
PyTorch code woven in,
culminating in a
complete implementation
of the Transformer as
applied to problems
in machine translation.
This is a wonderful
contribution in the sense
that to the extent that
there are points of unclarity
or uncertainty in
the original text,
they are fully resolved
by Sasha's code.
And of course, this can give
you a really good example
of how to do efficient and
effective implementation
of model architectures
like this using PyTorch.
In practical terms,
we're going to make
extensive use of the
Hugging Face Transformers
library, which has
really opened up access
to a wide range of pretrained
transformer models.
It's very exciting.
And it's enabled
lots of new things.
For us, the central
architecture will be BERT.
We'll have a separate
screencast on that.
And we're also going to have
a screencast on RoBERTa, which
is Robustly Optimized BERT.
I think it's an interesting
perspective in the sense
that they explored more deeply
some of the open questions
from the original BERT paper.
And they also released very
powerful pretrained parameters
that you could, again,
use in the context
of your own fine-tuning.
And then for a slightly
different perspective
on these transformers,
we're going
to look at the ELECTRA
architecture, which
came from Kevin
Clark and colleagues
at Stanford and Google.
I really like this
as a new perspective.
There are, of course,
many different modes
of using the transformer
at this point.
I'm going to mention a few
at the end of the screencast.
And just for the
sake of time, I've
decided to focus on ELECTRA.
And you can explore the
others in your own research.
Let's begin with
some intuitions.
And I'd like to begin with a
linguistic intuition, which
has to do with word
representations
and how they should be
shaped by the context.
Let's focus on the
English verb break.
We have a simple
example, the vase broke,
which means it
shattered to pieces.
Here's a superficially
similar sentence, dawn broke.
Now the sense of break is
something more like begin.
The news broke.
Again, a simple
intransitive sentence.
But now the verb
break means something
more like publish, or up
here, or become known.
Sandy broke the world record.
This is a transitive
use of the verb break.
And it means, surpass
the previous level.
Sandy broke the law is
another transitive use.
But now it means,
Sandy transgressed.
The burglar broke into the
house is a physical act
of transgression on its face.
The newscaster broke
into the movie broadcast
is a sense that it's
more like interrupt.
And we have idioms
like break even, which
means we neither
gained nor lost money.
And this is just a
few of the many ways
that the verb break
can be used in English.
How many senses
are at work here?
It's very hard to say.
It could be one.
It could be two.
It could be ten.
It's very hard to
delimit word senses.
But it is very
clear from this data
that our sense
for the verb break
is being shaped by the
immediate linguistic context.
Here are a few
additional examples,
things like flat tire, flat
beer, flat note, flat surface.
It's clear that there is
a conceptual core running
through all of these uses.
But it's also true
that a flat tire
is a very different
sense for flat
than we get from flat
note or flat surface.
I have something similar for
throw a party, throw a fight,
throw a ball, throw a fit.
We have a mixture of
what you might call
literal and metaphorical here.
But again, a kind of common
core that we're drawing on.
But the bottom line is that the
sense for throw, in this case,
is very different depending on
what kind of linguistic context
it's in.
And we can extend this to
things that seem to turn more
on world knowledge.
So if you have something
like, a crane caught a fish,
we have a sense that the
crane here is a bird.
Whereas, if we have a crane
picked up the steel beam,
we have a sense that it's
a piece of equipment.
This seems like
something that's guided
by our understanding of birds,
and equipment, and fish,
and beams.
And when we have relatively
unbiased sentences like,
I saw a crane,
we're kind of left
guessing about which
object is involved,
the bird or the machine.
And we can extend this
past world knowledge
into things that are more
like discourse understanding.
So if you have a sentence
like, "are there typos?
I didn't see any."
The sense of "any"
here, we have a feeling
that something is elided but
probably localized on "any."
And "any" here means any typos
as a result of the preceding
linguistic context.
"Are there any
bookstores downtown?
I didn't see any."
Same second sentence.
But now the sense
of "any" is probably
going to be something
more like bookstores,
as a result of the discourse
context that it appears in.
So all of this is
just showing how much
individual linguistic units
can be shaped by context.
Linguists know this deeply.
This is a primary thing that
linguists try to get a grip on.
And I think it's a wonderful
point of connection
between what linguists
do and the way we're
representing examples in
NLP using contextual models.
This is a very
exciting development
for me as a linguist,
as well as an NLPer.
Here's another set of intuitions
that's related more to things
like model architecture and what
you might call inductive biases
for different model designs.
Let's start off
here in the left.
This is a high-bias
model in the sense
that it makes a lot of a
priori decisions about how
we will represent our examples.
The idea is that we have
three tokens, which we look up
in a fixed embedding space.
And then we have decided to
summarize those embeddings
by simply summing them together
to get a representation
for the entire example.
Very few of these components are
learned as part of our problem.
We've made most of the
decisions ahead of time.
As we've seen, as we move to
a recurrent neural network,
we relax some of
those assumptions.
We're still going to look
upwards in a fixed embedding
space.
But now instead of deciding
that we know the proper way
to combine them
is with summation,
we're going to
learn from our data
a very complicated function
for combining them.
And that will
presumably allow us
to be more responsive, that is,
less biased about what the data
are likely to look like.
The tree structured
architecture down here
is an interesting
mixture of these ideas.
It's like the recurrent
neural network.
Instead of assuming that I can
process the data left-to-right,
the data get processed
into constituents,
like "the Rock" is a
constituent, as excluded
from "rules" over here.
Now this is probably
going to be very powerful
if we're correct that the
language data are structured
according to these constituents.
Because it will give us a
boost in terms of learning.
It could be counterproductive,
though, to the extent
that constituent
structure is wrong.
And I think that's
showing that biases
that we impose at the
level of our architectures
can be helpful, as well
as a hindrance, depending
on how they align with
the data-driven problem
that we're trying to solve.
In the bottom right here, I
have the least biased model
in all these sentences, of
all the ones depicted here.
I've got a recurrent neural
network like this one,
except now I'm assuming
that information
can flow bidirectionally,
so no longer
a presumption of left-to-right.
And in addition, I've added
these attention mechanisms,
which we'll talk a lot
about in this unit.
But essentially,
think of them as ways
of creating special connections
between all of the hidden
units.
And the idea here is that we
would let the data tell us
how to weight all of
these various connections
and, in turn,
represent our examples.
We're making very few
decisions ahead of time
about what connections
could be made,
and instead of just listening
to the data and the learning
process.
And we are, at this
point, on the road
toward the Transformer,
which is kind
of an extreme case of connecting
everything with everything else
and then allowing the data
to tell us how to weight all
of those various connections.
And that does bring us to this
notion of attention, which
we've not discussed before.
But I think I can introduce the
concepts and a bit of the math.
And then we'll see them
again throughout this unit.
So let's start with the
simple sentiment example
and imagine we're dealing with
a recurrent neural network
classifier.
Our example is
really not so good.
And we're going to fit the
classifier, traditionally,
on top of this final
hidden state over here.
But we might worry
about doing that.
That by the time we've
gotten to this final state,
the contribution of
these earlier words,
which are clearly
important linguistically,
might be sort of forgotten
or overly diffuse.
So attention mechanisms
would be a way for us
to bring that information
back in and infuse
this representation,
hc, with some
of those previous
important connections.
So here's how we do that.
We're going to first have
some attention scores, which
are simply dot products of
our target vector with all
the preceding hidden states.
So that gives us a vector of
scores which are traditionally
softmax normalized.
And then what we do
is create a context
vector by weighting each of
the previous hidden states
by its attention
weight, and then taking
the average of those to give
us the context vector K.
And then we're going to have
this special layer here, which
concatenates K with our
previous final hidden state,
and feeds that through this
layer of learned parameters
and a nonlinearity to give us
this new hidden representation,
h tilde.
And it is h tilde
that is finally
the input to our
softmax classifier.
Whereas before, we would
have simply directly input hc
up here, we now input
this more refined version
that is drawing on all of
these attention connections
that we created with
these mechanisms.
And again, as you'll
see, the transformer
does this all over the place
with all of its representations
at various points
in its computations.
Here's another guiding
idea that really
shapes how these models work.
I've called this word pieces.
And we've seen this before.
These models typically do
not tokenize data in the way
that we might expect.
I've loaded in a BERT tokenizer.
And you can see
that for a sentence,
like "this isn't too surprising"
the result is some pretty
familiar tokens, by and large.
But when I feed in
something like "encode me"
the intuitive word
"encode" is split apart
into two-word pieces.
And clearly, we're
implicitly assuming
that the model, because
it's contextual,
can figure out that these pieces
are in some conceptual sense
one word.
And you might extend that up to
idioms like "out of this world"
where we treat them as a
bunch of distinct tokens.
But we might hope
the model can learn
that there's an idiomatic
unity to that phrase.
And this also has
the side advantage
that for unknown tokens
like "Snuffleupagus"
it can break them apart
into familiar pieces.
And we at least have
a hope of getting
a sensible representation for
that out-of-vocabulary item.
The result of all this is
that these models can get away
with having very
small vocabularies,
precisely because we are
relying on them implicitly
to be truly contextual.
Here's another inspiring
idea that we've not
encountered before.
This is called
positional encoding.
And it's another way in which
we can capture sensitivity
of words to their contexts.
So as you'll see, when
you go all the way down
inside the transformer
architecture,
you do have a traditional
static embedding
of the sort we discussed in
the first unit for this course.
Those are in light gray
here, fixed representations
for the words.
However, in the context
of a model like BERT,
what we traditionally think of
as its embedding representation
is actually a combination
of that fixed embedding
and a separate
embedding space called
the positional embedding, where
we have learned representations
for each position in a sequence.
This has the intriguing property
that one and the same word,
like the, will have
a different embedding
in the sense of the green
representation here,
depending on where it
appears in your sequence.
So right from the
get-go, we have a notion
of context sensitivity
even before we've
started to connect things in
all sorts of interesting ways.
Now let's move to some
current issues and efforts,
some high-level things
that you might think about
as you work through this unit.
This is a really nice
graph from the ELECTRA
paper from Clark, et al.
Along the x-axis here, we have
floating point operations,
which you could think of
as a kind of basic measure
of compute resources needed to
create these representations.
And along the y-axis,
we have GLUE score.
So that's like a
standard NLU benchmark.
And the point of
this plot here is
that we're reaching kind
of diminishing returns.
So we had rapid increases
from GloVE, GPT,
and up through to BERT,
where we're really
doing much better on
these GLUE scores.
We're increasing the
floating point operations.
But it seems to be
commensurate with how
we're doing on the benchmark.
But now with these larger
models like XLNet and RoBERTa,
it's arguably the
case that we're
reaching diminishing returns.
RoBERTa involves more than
3,000 times the floating point
operations of GloVe.
But it's not that much
better along this y-axis
than some of its simpler
variants like BERT-Base.
And so this is something
we should think about
when we think about the
costs in terms of money,
and in the environments,
and energy,
and so forth when we think about
developing these large models.
And here's a really
extreme case.
Who knows how long we
can train these things
or how much benefit
we'll get when we do so.
But at a certain point,
we're likely to incur
costs that are
larger than any gains
that we can justify on the
problems we're trying to solve.
And that goes and leads
us to this lovely paper,
which talks about the
environmental footprint
of training these
really big models.
And it just shows that by
training a big transformer
from scratch, it really incurs
a large environmental cost.
That's certainly
something we should
have in mind as we think
about using these models.
For me, it's a complicated
question though.
Because it's offset by the fact
that, by and large, all of us
aren't training these from
scratch, but rather, benefiting
from publicly available
pretrained representations.
So while the pretraining
for that one version
had a large
environmental cost, it
feels like it's kind of offset
by the fact that a lot of us
are benefiting from it.
And it might be that
in aggregate, this
is less environmentally
costly than the old days
when all of us always
trained all of our models
literally from scratch.
I just don't know how to
do the calculations here.
But I do know that increased
access has been empowering
and is likely offsetting
some of the costs.
And a lot of that is due to the
contributions of the Hugging
Face library.
There are a lot of efforts
along these same lines
to make BERT smaller
by compressing it
literally fewer dimensions than
other kinds of simplifications
of the training process,
and BERT distillation,
and so forth.
Here are two outstanding
contributions,
kind of compendiums of lots of
different ideas in this space.
And I also highly
recommend this lovely paper
called "A Primer in
BERTology," which
explores a lot of
different aspects of what
we know about BERT and how
it works, various variations
people have tried,
various things
that people have done
to probe these models,
and understand their
learning dynamics,
and so forth and so on.
It's a very rich
contribution, certainly can
be a resource for you as you
think about these models.
And just because we don't
have time to cover them all,
there are a bunch of
interesting Transformer variants
that we will not be able
to discuss in detail.
I thought I'd mention them here.
SBERT is an attempt to develop
sentence-level representations
from BERT that are particularly
good at finding which sentences
are similar to which
other sentences according
to cosine similarity.
And I think that could
be a powerful mode
of thinking about
these representations
and also of practical
utility if you
need to find which sentences
are similar to which others.
You have probably heard of
GPT, the Generative Pre-trained
Transformer, in
various of its forms.
You can get GPT-2
from Hugging Space--
and Hugging Face.
And you have unfettered
access to it.
And of course, there's
more restrictive access
at this point to GPT-3.
These are conditional
language models,
so quite different from BERT.
And they might be
better than BERT
for things like truly
conditional language
generation.
XLNet is an attempt to
bring in much more context
into these models.
It stands for Xtra
Long Transformer.
So if you need to
process long sequences,
this might be a good choice.
And this is also
an attempt to bring
in some of the benefits of
conditional language models
into a mode that is more
bidirectional, the way BERT is.
T5 is another conditional
language mode, as is BART.
These models might be
better choices for you
if you need to actually
generate language.
What I think the
standard wisdom is
that models like
BERT and RoBERTa
are better if you simply
need good representations
for fine-tuning on a
classification problem,
for example.
More models will
appear every day.
And I think it's worth
trying to stay up
to speed on the various
developments in this space.
Because this is probably just
the tip of the iceberg here.