CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is part two in our
series on contextual word
representations.
We're going to be talking about
the transformer architecture,
which is the central piece
for all the models we'll
be exploring in this unit.
Let's dive into the
model structure,
we'll work through this
using a simple example.
At the bottom here I've got
the input sequence, "the Rock
rules" and I've indicated
in red that we're
going to be keeping
track of the positions
of each one of those
tokens in the sequence.
But the first step
is a familiar one.
We're going to look at both
the words and the positions
in separate embedding spaces.
Those are fixed embedding
spaces that we'll
learn as part of learning all
the parameters in this model.
I've given the word
embeddings in light
gray and the positional
embeddings in dark gray.
To form what we think of
as the actual embedding
for this model, we do
an elementwise addition
of the word embedding with
the positional embedding.
And that gives us
the representations
that are in green here,
and you can see that
on the right side
of the slide, I'm
going to be keeping track of all
of the calculations with regard
to this C column here
and they're completely
parallel for columns A and B.
So to form C input, we do
elementwise addition of X34,
the embedding for
the word "rules"
and P3 which is the embedding
for position 3 in this model.
The next layer is really the
hallmark of this architecture
and what gives the
paper its title,
Attention is All You Need.
We're going to form a
bunch of dense dot product
connections between all
of these representations.
So you can think
of those as forming
these connections
that look like there's
a dense thicket of them.
On the right here, I've
given the core calculation
and it should be familiar
from part one in this unit.
It's exactly the calculation
I've presented there
with just two small changes,
but fundamentally if our target
vector is the C
input here, we're
attending to inputs A
and B, and we do that
by forming the
dot products here.
And the one twist from before
is that instead of just taking
those dot products,
we'll normalize them
by the square root of the
dimensionality of the model dk.
dk is an important value
here because of the way
we combine representations
in the transformer.
All of the outputs and
all the layers we look at
have to have the same
dimensionality as given by dk.
And so what we're doing
here is essentially
scaling these dot products
to kind of keep them
within a sensible range.
That gives us a score
vector off the tilde,
we softmax normalize that.
And then the other
twist is that instead
of using mean here as we did
before, we use summation.
But the actual vector is the
one we calculated before, we're
going to take weighted
versions of A input and B input
according to this vector of
weights that we created here.
That gives us the
representation C attention
as given in orange
here, and we do
that of course for all the
other positions in the model.
The next step is
kind of interesting,
we're creating what's called
a residual connection.
So to get CA layer
here in yellow,
we add up C input and this
attention representation
that we just created
and apply dropout
as a regularization step there.
And that gives us CA layer,
the interesting thing
there of course is this
residual connection.
Instead of simply feeding
forward C attention,
we feed forward
actually a version of it
that's combined with our initial
positionally encoded embedding.
If we follow that with a step
of layer normalization, which
should help with
optimization, it's
going to kind of
scale the weights
in these representations.
The next step is
more meaningful.
This is a series of
two dense layers,
so we'll take Ca
norm here and feed it
through this dense layer
with a non-linearity followed
by another linear
layer to give us Cfx
that's given in dark blue here.
And that's followed
by another one
of these interesting
residual connections,
so we'll apply dropout to Cff.
And then add that
in with Ca norm,
as given down here
at the bottom,
and that gives us the second
yellow representation.
And we follow that by one more
step of layer normalization
and that gives us the output
for this block of transformer
representations.
And you can imagine
of course as you'll
see that we can stack up
these transformer blocks,
and the way that we
do that is essentially
by taking these dark green
representations at the top
here and using them as inputs
and all the calculations
are the same.
So you might imagine that
we could continue here
by just doing a dense
series of attention
connections across
these and then
continuing on with the
calculations I just presented.
And in that way, we could
stack up transformer blocks.
And I'll return
to that later on.
There are a few
other things that
are worth pointing
out that are kind
of noteworthy about this model.
It looks like a complicated
series of calculations,
but I would say that
fundamentally what's
happening here is we're doing
positional encoding to get
embeddings, so that they
are position-sensitive
representations of words.
We follow that within
an attention layer
which creates that dense
thicket of connections
between all of the words
as positionally encoded.
Then we have these
optimization things woven in,
but fundamentally we're
following that attention step
with two series of
feed-forward layer steps
here, followed by the same
process of dropout and layer
normalization.
So if you kind of elided
the yellow and the purple,
you would see that
what we're really doing
is attention followed
by feed-forward.
And then as we stack
these things that
would be attention
feed-forward, attention
feed-forward as we climbed up.
And interwoven into
there are some things
that I would say help
with optimization.
Another noteworthy
thing about this model
is that the only
sense in which we
are keeping track of the
linear order of the sequence
is in those
positional embeddings,
if not for them the column order
would be completely irrelevant.
Because of course,
we've created all
of these symmetric connections
at the attention layer.
And there are no
other connections
across these columns.
So the only sense in
which column order, that
is word order matters here,
is via those positional
embeddings.
Here's a more detailed look
at the attention calculations
themselves.
I just want to bring
up how this actually
works at a mechanical level.
So this is the calculation
as I presented it
on the previous slide and
in part one of this unit.
In the paper, and
now commonly it's
presented in this matrix format.
And if you're like
me, it's not obvious
right away that these are
equivalent calculations.
So what I've done for
these next two slides
is to show you via
worked out examples
how those calculations
work and how they arrive
at exactly the same values.
I'm not gonna spend too
much time on this here,
this is really just
here for you if you
would like to work through
the calculations in detail,
which I strongly encourage
because this is really
the fundamental
step in this model.
And here's all the
details that you
would need to get hands
on with these ideas.
Now so far, I've
presented attention
in a kind of simplified way.
A hallmark of attention
is in the transformer
is that it is typically
multi-headed attention.
So let me unpack that idea
a little bit concretely.
We'll start with our
input sequence from before
and we'll be looking at these
green representations here.
And the idea behind the
multi-headed attention
mechanisms that
we're gonna inject
a bunch of learned parameters
into this process to encourage
diversity as part of
the learning process,
and are really diverse and
interesting representations.
So here's how that works.
We're gonna form three
representations here using
that same dot product
mechanism as before.
And fundamentally it's the
same calculation except now
we're gonna have a bunch of
learned weight parameters
that's given in orange here.
And those will help
us with two things.
First injecting diversity
into this process,
and also smushing
the dimensionality
of the representations down
to one third of the size
that we're targeting SDK for
our model dimensionality.
And you'll see why that
happens in a second.
But fundamentally
what we're doing
is exactly the calculation
we did before but now
with these learned
parameters injected into it.
So if you squint, you can
see that this is really
the dot product of c input
with a input as before.
But now, it's transformed
by these learned parameters
that are given in orange.
And that repeats for
these other calculations.
So we're going to do
that for position a.
And we do it also
for position b.
And it's the same
calculation, but now it's
new parameters for
the second position.
And then for the third head,
exactly the same calculation
but new learned parameters
up at the top here.
So this is
three-headed attention.
And then we actually form
the representations that
proceed with the rest of the
calculation of the transformer
architectures presented before
is by concatenating the three
representations we created
for each one of these units.
So the A column is the
first representation
in each one of these heads.
The B column is the second
representation in each head
and similarly for
the C column it's
the third representation
in each one of these heads.
And that's why each
one of these needs
to add one-third
the dimensionality
of our full model so that we
can concatenate them and then
feed those into the
subsequent calculations.
The idea here, of course, is
that injecting all of these
learned parameters into all
of these different heads we're
providing the model a chance
to learn lots of diverse ways
of relating the words
in the sequence.
The final point is one I've
already mentioned before,
which is that typically we
don't have just one transformer
block but rather a
whole stack of them,
we can repeat them N times.
For models you're working with
you might have 12 or 24 or even
more blocks in the
transformer architecture.
And the way we do that
as I said is simply
by taking the dark green
representations of the output
layer here and using them as
inputs to subsequent blocks
so they get attended
to, and we proceed
with the subsequent
regularization
and feed-forward
steps just as before.
And when you work with these
models in Hugging Face,
if you ask for all of the hidden
states, what you're getting
is a grid of representations
corresponding to these output
blocks in green here.
And of course,
just as a reminder
I'm not indicating it
here but there is actually
multi-headed attention of
each one of these blocks
through each one of the layers.
So there are a lot of learned
parameters in this model,
especially if you have
12 or 24 attention heads.
At this point, I'm hoping
that you can now fruitfully
return to the original
Vaswani, et al paper
and look at their model
diagram and get more out of it.
For me, it's kind of
hyper compressed but now
that we've done a deep
dive into all the pieces,
I think this serves as a kind
of useful shorthand for how
all the pieces fit together.
So let's just do that quickly.
As before we have positional
encodings and input word
embeddings, and
those get added up
to give us the intuitive notion
of an embedding in this model.
That's followed by the
attention layer as we discussed,
and it has a residual
connection here into that layer
normalization part.
That's fed into the
feed-forward blocks
and that's followed by that
same process of kind of dropout
attention layer normalization.
And this is essentially
saying each one
of these is repeated for
every step in the encoder
process, every one of the
columns that we looked at.
And if because
then in the paper,
they're working with an
encoder/decoder model.
Each decoder state self attends
with all of the fellow decoder
states and with all of the
encoder states, so right?
Imagine this double sequence,
we have a dense area
to potentially connect some
connections across both parts
of the representation.
On the right side when
we're doing decoding,
again, we repeat this block
for every decoder state.
And if every state there
has an output as for machine
translation or some kind
of generation process,
then we'll have something
like this output
stack at every one of
those output states.
If by contrast we're
doing something
like NLI or sentiment
classification problem,
maybe just one of
those states will have
one of these outputs on them.
And then the attention gets
a little bit complicated
if you are doing decoding for
a model like natural language
generation or machine
translation, in the decoder,
you can't attend into the future
as you're doing generation.
So there's a
masking process that
limits self-attention to the
preceding words in the sequence
that you're creating.