CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome back, everyone.
This screencast is an overview
of the homework and bakeoff
associated with our unit
on grounded language
understanding.
More than any of the
other assignments,
what we're asking
you to do here,
is essentially develop a
fully integrated system,
that addresses our task.
So the distinction
between homework
questions and original
system questions
is kind of getting blurred here
in the interest of having you
devote all your
energy to developing
a cool original system
for this problem.
So because of that
I'm going to use
some slides to give you an
overview of the entire problem.
And how we're thinking
about evaluation
and how the questions feed
into these overall goals.
So recall that our core task is
the Stanford colors and context
task.
And we're going to take
the speaker's perspective
primarily.
And what that means is that
the inputs to our model
are sequences of
three color patches.
One of them designated
as the target,
and the task is to generate
a description of the target,
in that particular context.
The core model
that will be using,
which is in
torch_color_describer
is an Encoder/Decoder
architecture.
And the way it works
is on the encoder side
you have a sequence
of three colors.
And we always put the target
color in the third position.
So those are the inputs,
and then the decoding step
is essentially to describe
the target in that context.
So that's the natural
language generation part
and we've covered
this core architecture
in previous screencasts.
And I'll return to some
of the modifications
that you see here in the
context of question four.
There's a separate notebook
called Colors Overview
that you should start with.
It gives you a sense for
what the dataset is like,
and also what our
modeling code is like.
Here you can see that I've
loaded in the corpus itself,
it's got about 47,000
examples in it.
And each one of
those examples has
a number of different attributes
that you should be aware of.
So here's a typical example,
the first one in the corpus.
Fundamentally, you have
these three color patches.
And you can see this display is
marking out the target, as well
as an utterance.
Each one of these colors is
encoded as a triple and HSV
values.
That is a sequence
of three floats,
and you can see here that you
can also access the utterance.
There are three conditions
in the underlying corpus
that vary in their difficulty.
In the far condition,
all three of the colors
are quite different
from each other.
And so the task of
identifying the target
is typically pretty
easy, here the person
just had to say purple.
In the split condition,
two of the colors
are highly confusable.
So you can see here that
we have two green colors.
And that pushed the
speaker to choose
a kind of more specified
form of green in saying lime.
And the hardest condition
is the close condition,
and that's where all
three of the colors
are highly similar
to each other.
This tends to lead to
the longest descriptions.
You can see here
that the speaker even
took two turns, as indicated
by this boundary marker.
To try to give their full
description; medium pink,
the medium dark one.
Because these colors
are so confusable.
So you should be aware of this
difference in the conditions.
And it might affect how you
do different kinds of modeling
based on what the
color sequence is like.
Now evaluation for natural
language generation systems
is always challenging.
And there are some
automatic metrics
that we can use as guideposts.
In fact we're going to use
BLEU in various places.
But our primary
evaluation metric
will be this task oriented
one, which brings in a listener
perspective.
So at a mechanical level here's
how we'll make predictions.
For a given context, c,
consisting of three colors.
Capital C here is
all the permutations
of those three colors.
Suppose that you have trained
a speaker model, PS here,
it's a probabilistic agent.
We're going to
think about how it
makes predictions for all of
those different permutations.
And take as its
prediction the level
of a full sequence, the sequence
that it assigns the highest
probability to.
Given the message that
your system produced.
And then we say
that a speaker is
accurate in its prediction
about some context c.
Just in case the best
sequence that it predicts,
the highest probability
one, has the target
in the final position.
As designated by
our model structure.
So in a little bit
more detail, here's
how this works with an example.
Suppose that our
context looks like this,
it has these three
color patches.
The target is always
in third position,
and our message was blue.
Here on the right we
have all the permutations
of these three colors.
And we're going to say that
your system was correct,
if its highest probability
context given that message
was one of these two.
That is one of the two that has
the target in final position.
And the system is
inaccurate to the extent
that it stands higher
probability to one
of these other sequences.
Essentially, we're
saying that it's
assigning higher probability
to some other target.
But we do operate at the
level of these full sequences.
All right, now let's move
into the questions here,
and we first start
with the tokenizer.
You're unconstrained in how
you design your tokenizer.
You should just make sure
that you have a start
symbol and an end symbol.
The start symbol is important
conditioning context
for the model.
And the end symbol
is the crucial signal
that your model will actually
stop producing tokens.
So don't forget those pieces,
but in terms of what else
you do in there,
it's unconstrained.
And I think you can see
from the Monroe et al. work
that making smart choices
about tokenization
might be really meaningful.
Question two asks you
to think about how
you're representing colors.
By default they're just going
to be those three float values,
but that's probably not optimal.
In the Monroe et al. paper, we
explored a Fourier transform
as a way of embedding colors.
And I've given you a
little recipe for that
in the context of the notebook.
In case you want to explore
that it is highly effective,
but this is optional.
And there might be other
representation schemes
that are even better
and worth exploring.
Question three asks you to
think about rich initialization
or pre-training for your model.
We've worked a lot with
pre-trained GloVe embeddings.
And this is a chance for you
to bring those into your model
and see how well they do.
You should be aware
that this step
is going to interact
in non-trivial ways,
with choices you make
for your tokenizer.
And question four is
the most involved,
it involves some real
PyTorch wrangling.
Conceptually, what
we're asking you to do
is borrow a trick from
the Monroe et al. paper.
What we found in
that work is that it
helped to remind the
model, during decoding,
of which of the three
colors was its target.
And the way we did
that, essentially,
was by taking the color
embedding for the target.
And appending it
to the embedding
of each one of the tokens
that it was producing,
as a kind of reminder.
In terms of how that works
at the level of code,
there is a decoder class,
and you should modify it
so that the input vector to
the model at each timestep
is not just the token embedding.
But the concatenation
of that embedding
with the representation
of the target code.
Then you need to modify
the Encoder/Decoder
class to extract
the target colors,
and feed them to
that decoder class.
And then finally here, this
is the interface that you use.
Modify that interface so that it
uses your decoder and encoder,
and that's a pretty
mechanical step.
When you're developing on
this problem use toy datasets.
Because you don't want
to wait around as you
process the entire
colors corpus, only
to find out that you
have a low level bug.
And I also encourage
you to lean on the tests
that we have included
in the notebook
as a way of ensuring that you
have exactly the right data
structures.
And assuming all those
pieces fall into place,
I think you'll find
that the resulting
models are substantially
better for our task.
That brings us to
the original system.
And here's just
some expectations
about how we think you
might work on this problem.
You could iteratively
improve your answers
to the assignment questions as
part of the original system.
Modify the tokenizer, think
about your GloVe embeddings,
think about how
you're representing
colors, and kind of how all
those pieces are interacting.
You might want to extend
the modified Encoder/Decoder
classes to do new and
interesting things.
And I have provided
guidance on how
to do that at a
mechanical level,
in the colors overview notebook.
Any data that you can
find is fine to bring in
for development, and for
training your original system.
The bake-off involves
a new test set,
that's never been
released anywhere before,
it's just used in this context.
It's got the same
kinds of color context
as in the released corpus.
But it was one-off games
rather than iterated games.
And I do think that makes this
test set a little bit easier
than the training set.
And all the items have
been listener-validated.
So I think all the
descriptions are
in principle good
descriptions at a human level.
And so it should be a
good basis for evaluation.