CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is part 1 in our
series on grounded language
understanding.
I'm just going to
give an overview.
With grounding, I
feel like we're really
getting at the heart of what
makes NLU so special for NLP
and also for artificial
intelligence more broadly.
So this is exciting.
Let's dive in.
Now, grounding is
a very large topic.
And so to ground it
so to speak we're
going to be focused on
a particular task, which
is color reference in context.
I'll be saying much more
about that later on.
This notebook, Colors
Overview, provides an overview
of the data set,
and that data set
is the centerpiece for the
homework and associated
bake-off.
The Core Reading
is the paper that
introduced that dataset,
Monroe et al., 2017.
And I think that paper
is noteworthy also
for introducing some
interesting modeling ideas that
are worthy of
further exploration,
possibly in final projects.
And then I also just want
to recommend a whole bunch
of auxiliary readings.
Not required but exciting
extensions that you might make.
I think grounding is
a wonderful chance
to do interdisciplinary work.
You can connect NLP with
robotics, and computer vision,
and human language
acquisition, and probably lots
of other topics.
So I'm going to
be pushing papers,
and dataset throughout
this series of screencasts
in the hopes that you
can pick up those ideas,
and run with them for
your own projects.
Now to start, I thought we
could just reflect a little bit
on the heart of this, which is
why grounding is so important
and why natural language
understanding is so hard.
And sort of to
kick that off, I've
taken a slide idea
from Andrew McCallum.
Andrew just asks us to
reflect a little bit
on the 1967 Stanley Kubrick
movie, 2001, A Space Odyssey.
In that movie, the spaceship's
computer, which is called HAL,
can do three things
that are noteworthy.
It can display
computer graphics.
It can play chess,
and it can conduct
natural open-domain
conversations with humans.
So this is a chance to ask,
how well did the filmmakers do
at predicting what
computers would
be capable of in the
actual year 2001?
Which is, of course, ancient
history for us at this point.
So let's start
with the graphics.
On the left, you have
some of the graphics that
HAL able to display
in the movie,
and you can see that they
are extremely primitive.
The filmmakers seem to
have wildly underestimated
just how much progress would
happen in computer graphics.
By 1993, which is much
earlier than 2001, of course,
we had the movie
Jurassic Park, which
had these incredible graphics
for lifelike moving dinosaurs.
So let's say that this is a kind
of failure to imagine a future.
For chess, it seems like
they've got the prediction just
about right.
So in the movie, HAL is
an excellent chess player.
And just a few years before
the actual 2001 in 1997,
Deep Blue was the
first supercomputer
to beat world champion
chess players.
What about dialogue and
natural language use?
So on the left here, you have a
sample dialogue from the movie.
Dave Bowman is the human.
He says, "Open the
pod bay doors, HAL."
And HAL replies,
"I'm sorry, Dave.
I'm afraid I can't do that."
"What are you
talking about, HAL?"
Then HAL replies, "I know that
you and Frank were planning
to disconnect me, and I'm afraid
that's something I cannot allow
to happen."
Very interesting.
Not only is it fluent
English, of course,
but it's also displaying
really rich reasoning
about plans and goals.
And it's fully grounded in
what's happening in the ship.
Just incredibly realistic.
To give the filmmakers even
a fighting chance here,
let's move forward
to the year 2014,
which is about when
Siri hit the market.
And we talked
about Siri earlier.
Here, you can see Siri doing
a much more mundane version
of what we just saw
HAL doing, which
is kind of proactively
recognizing plans and goals,
and helping a human user solve
a problem using fluent English.
In this case, it's just
about where to buy food,
but the vision is very similar.
What was life actually like
in 2014 or for that matter,
in the present day?
Well, I also showed
you this dialogue
from Stephen Colbert
from his show
that pretenses that
he has been playing
with this phone all
day, and therefore,
has failed to produce
material for the show.
The cameras are on him,
and he's desperate.
And he asks Siri for help.
And you can see here
that Siri does not
have a deep understanding of
what he's trying to achieve.
I've bolded God and cameras
in Stephen's utterance
because you can see
Siri just picks up
on those as kind of keywords,
and says churches, and camera
stores.
It's not even
topically relevant.
It's just a complete
failure to recognize
what he's trying to do.
And then later things
get even worse,
Siri really doesn't understand
what Stephen is saying.
And so it does that standard
escape valve, which is it
searches the web for the
speech to text transcription
of the thing that he
said in hopes that that
will be helpful.
A far cry from anything like
a helpful, useful, human-like
interaction with language.
Now, why is this so difficult?
I think another angle
on that question
is usefully brought to
the fore with this analogy
that Stephen Levinson offers.
So he asks us to look
at this Rembrandt sketch
here, and just
reflect on the fact
that you can make out people and
structures in the background.
But really, it's incredible
that you can do any of that.
So he says, "We interpret
this sketch instantly
and effortlessly as
a gathering of people
before a structure,
probably a gateway;
the people are listening
to a single declaiming
figure in the center."
And then he says,
"But all of this
is a miracle for there is
little detailed information
in the lines or shading,
such as there is.
Every line is a mere suggestion.
So here is the miracle:
from a merest, sketchiest,
squiggle of lines,
you and I converge
to find adumbration
of a coherent scene."
That is indeed a visual miracle
and a cognitive miracle.
And it's also a glimpse
into why computer vision
is so challenging.
To make the connection with
language, Levinson continues.
"The problem of
utterance interpretation
is not dissimilar to
this visual miracle.
An utterance is not as it were
a veridical model or snapshot
of the scene it describes.
Rather an utterance is just
as sketchy as the Rembrandt
drawing."
So much of what we communicate
as speakers is left implicit.
And so much of
what listeners are
able to extract from
our utterances and stuff
that they're able to
extract only by reasoning
in a general way about the
context, plans, and goals,
world knowledge, and so forth.
If our utterances were
actually fully encoding
in their semantics everything
we intended to communicate,
I think we would have
talking robots at this point.
But the truth is that
so much of communication
in natural language is left
up to the context in a very
general sense, and
that's exactly what makes
this problem so challenging.
In a way though, all
of this grounding
into the context and
all this reasoning,
if you break it
into your system,
it can make things easier.
It might make some intractable
problems tractable.
And one glimpse
of that it's just
this topic of what linguists
and philosophers called
indexicality.
Indexicals are phrases like
"I" as in "I am speaking."
That obviously makes
reference to the speaker,
and that reference
is going to vary
depending on who's speaking.
That's a case where
you can't possibly
understand the statement
unless you know something
about who's speaking, which is
a very simple kind of grounding.
"We won" chose this, a
similar kind of grounding,
but it's more complicated.
So now we have this phrase,
we, which probably by default
is expected to
include the speaker.
But it kind of needs
to include others,
and figuring out who else it
includes can be difficult.
And you also get more
challenging uses, where
you say things like
"we" as in, we,
as the sports team, that I
follow or something like that.
So we have grounding
plus a whole bunch
of contextual reasoning
in order to figure out
what "We won" would mean.
"I am here."
Of course, "I" for the speaker,
that's one kind of grounding,
but "here" is an
indexical expression
referring to a
location, and it does
that in a very complicated way.
When I say I am here, I could
be in my office, or Stanford,
and I suppose all the
way up to planet Earth.
Although, that's
unlikely because it's
not so informative in 2021
to say I'm on planet Earth.
"We want to go here"
is another use.
It has "we" for one
kind of grounding.
And in this case here,
if I'm pointing to a map,
would be an even
more complicated kind
of displaced
indexical reference,
but the map is doing
some iconic duty
for some actual place in the
world that we are aiming to go.
So another kind of complicated
reasoning, but again,
grounded in something about
the utterance context.
"We went to a local
bar after work."
Here, the indexical
is the word "local,"
and it just shows that
indexicality can sneak
into other parts of speech.
"Local" here is going to refer
to things that are somehow
in the immediate vicinity of
the location of the utterance
and again, in a very
complicated way.
And then "three days
ago," "tomorrow,"
and "now" are
temporal indexicals.
And they just show that
the meaning of an utterance
can vary depending
on when it's spoken.
And all of these
expressions are kind of
anchored to that
time of utterance.
And there are other kinds
of context dependence
that really require us
to understand utterances
in their full grounded context.
Let's start with
a simple example.
"Where are you from?"
This can be a
vexing question when
people ask because
it can often be
difficult to know what their
true goals and intentions are
with the question.
They could mean your birthplace.
I would say Connecticut.
It could mean your nationality.
I might say the US.
Affiliation.
For me, that would be Stanford,
and again, maybe one day
it will be informative to
say planet Earth if there
are intergalactic meetings.
That one is typically
ruled out because it's not
so helpful in 2021.
But for the rest
of them, we kind of
have to guess often
about what the speaker is
asking of us in order to
figure out how to answer.
Here are some other examples.
"I didn't see any."
That's one particular sentence.
Its meaning is underspecified.
In the context of the question,
"Are there typos in my slides,"
"I didn't see any"
will take on one sense.
In the context, "Are there
bookstores downtown,"
"I didn't see any" will take
on a very different sense.
"Are there cookies
in the cupboard,"
"I didn't see any" yet
again, another kind of sense.
And of course, there
is no end to the number
of different contexts we
can place the sentence in.
And each one is
likely to modulate
the meaning of "I didn't
see any" in some complicated
and subtle way.
We hardly reflect on this, but
it's an incredible process.
So just to round this
out, here's an example.
Routine pragmatic enrichment.
I've got this simple
sentence in the middle here,
"Many students met
with me yesterday."
It's not a very
complicated sentence
cognitively or linguistically.
I think we can
easily understand it,
but reflect for a second
on just how many hooks
this utterance has
into the context.
We need to know what
the time of utterance
is to understand yesterday
and in turn, to understand
the whole sentence.
We need to ask, how big is the
contextually restricted domain
of students here, in order to
figure out whether how many,
many is.
Is it false for most students?
Did I avoid saying most or all
because that would be false
and instead, chose
a weaker form, many?
That would be a
kind of reasoning
that many listeners
will undergo.
What's the additional contextual
restriction to students,
just students in our course?
Students I advise,
students at Stanford,
students in the world.
Again, the context will tell us.
Who is the speaker?
Of course, that's a
straightforward indexical.
And then there are other
kinds of inferences
that we might make based on
the restrictive modifiers
that the speaker chose.
Again, we don't reflect on
it, but all of this stuff
is happening kind of
effortlessly and automatically.
This, in Levinson's terms, is
the merest, sketchiest squiggle
of what actually
gets communicated.
And that is what's so hard
about so many aspects of NLU.
Now, I want to go
back into history
at least, once more to Terry
Winograd's system SHRDLU
because this just shows that
at the start of the field of AI
and Natural Language Processing,
the focus was entirely
on these grounded
understanding problems.
So SHRDLU was a
fully grounded system
that parses the user's input,
mapped it to a logical form,
and interpreted
that logical form
in a very particular world.
And then it would try
to take some action
and generate responses.
It's incredible, and I
love this characterization
from this YouTube clip.
"One project did succeed.
Terry Winograd's program
SHRDLU could use English
intelligently, but
there was a catch.
The only subject
you could discuss
was a micro-world of
simulated blocks."
This is wonderful in the
sense that it achieves
the goal of grounding,
but it was very far
from being scalable in any sense
that would make it practical.
But here's a kind of simple
dialogue from SHRDLU.
And the thing I just
want to point out
is that there is
so much implicit
grounding into the context.
"The box" is restricted
to the domain
and therefore, has reference.
Of course, there isn't a
unique box in the universe.
So "the box" in
the general context
might be very confusing, but in
the blocks world it made sense,
and you can see that
person leveraging that.
And the computer can
understand it because it too
is grounded in this
particular context,
and therefore, can
make use of all
of that implicit information
in forming its utterances,
and interpreting the
human's utterances.
And you see that pervasively
throughout sample dialogues
in the SHRDLU.
It's a compelling vision
about the kinds of things
that we need to
have, and all of it
turns on this very rich notion
of grounding in the blocks
world.
Finally, another
connection I want to make.
Let's just think the very
best devices in the universe,
as far as we know, for acquiring
natural languages are humans.
What do humans do?
Well, first language
acquirers children
learn language with
incredible speed.
That's noteworthy.
Just a few years.
Despite relatively few inputs--
I mean, they get
a lot of language
data in the ideal
situation, but it's
nothing compared to what
currently language models get
to see.
And they use cues from
contrast inherent in the forms
they hear.
That's a distributional idea
that we're familiar with
but also social
cues and assumptions
about the speaker's goals.
It just feel like
the very richness
of this picture and
its multi-modal aspects
are really important
guiding clues for us.
So what are the consequences
of all this for NLU?
Well, as I said, since
human children are the best
agents in the universe
at learning language
and they depend on grounding,
it seems like our systems
ought to be grounded as well.
Problems that are
intractable without grounding
are solvable with the
right kinds of grounding.
That's important
to keep in mind.
Grounded problems can seem hard,
but the other aspect of that
is that some problems might
be completely intractable
unless you have some
notion of grounding.
Indexicals come to mind.
Thinking about current modeling.
Deep learning is
a flexible toolkit
for reasoning about different
kinds of information
in a single model.
You can bring in language
data, image data, video data,
audio data, and so forth.
And therefore, it has led
to conceptual improvements.
The ungrounded language
models of today
get a lot of publicity,
but there are also
many exciting systems that
are fluently reasoning
about images, and video,
and language together.
And I think that's a really
nice step forward into the world
of true grounding.
So we should seek
out and develop
dataset that include the
right kind of grounding
because the central
thesis here is
that that can lead to
progress by leaps and bounds.
So again, to round
this out, let me
encourage you to think about
this for final projects.
We're going to be working
with the Stanford English
Colors in Context Corpus.
There is also a Chinese
version, and we've
explored exciting
ideas involving
monolingual Chinese,
and English speakers,
as well as bilingual
models for this dataset.
If you want to do
a little bit more
in terms of grounding, slightly
more complicated context,
I would recommend the
OneCommon dataset.
The Edinburgh Map Corpus is an
early task-oriented grounded
corpus that could be
exciting, especially if you
want to do some interesting
initial steps involving
language and
reinforcement learning.
The Cards Corpus would
be much more ambitious
along those same lines.
It's a very
open-ended, difficult,
task-oriented dialogue corpus.
Deal or No Deal is a forward
thinking negotiation corpus.
Negotiation is a
very interesting kind
of slightly adversarial,
social grounding.
CraigsListBargain
is another dataset
that you might use in the
context of negotiation agents.
And then ALFRED,
CrossTalk, and Room-to-Room
are all data sets
that would allow
you to combine grounded language
understanding with problems
relating to computer
vision in various ways.
And again, that kind of
interdisciplinary connection
could be crucial
to making progress
on truly grounded systems.