CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome back, everyone.
This is part six in our
series on Grounded Language
Understanding.
We're going to be talking
about neural RSA, which
is our combination of
the Rational Speech Acts
model with the kind of
machine learning models
that we've been focused
on for this unit.
And I'm hoping that
this draws together
a bunch of themes from
our earlier screencasts,
and also sets you
up, if you choose
to, to apply these ideas in the
context of an original system
or a final project.
I'm going to be talking in a
general way about these ideas.
They really emerge
from the papers that
are listed on this slide,
and the full references
are given at the end
of the slide show.
Now, what's our motivation here?
Recall that in screencast four,
I presented a bunch of tasks
that I claimed would benefit
from the back and forth
reasoning that RSA offers
grounded in specific contexts.
And those tasks included
discriminative image labeling,
image captioning,
machine translation,
collaborative problem
solving, interpreting complex
descriptions, especially
navigational instructions,
and maybe even optical
character recognition.
And I think we can
think of other tasks
that we could put into the
mold, like the colors in context
task, and really benefit from
the mechanisms that RSA offers.
However, as we saw at the
end of the RSA screencast,
there are some
obstacles to doing this.
RSA is standardly presented
as not especially scalable.
It's also not especially
sensitive to the kind
of variation that we're likely
to see in actual usage data
in the large-scale corpora
that would support these tasks.
And relatedly, it just
doesn't have any notion
of bounded rationality, even
though, of course, once humans
interact, they're not
perfectly rational, even
in the pragmatic
sense that RSA offers.
And there's another dimension
to this problem for motivation
here, which is that RSA harbors
a really powerful insight.
And we might hope that we
can achieve more impact
for that model by bringing in
new kinds of assessment for it.
You know, taking it out of the
psychology and linguistics lab
and into the world of AI.
And in turn, achieve
more impact for RSA.
And maybe show more of
the scientific world
that RSA has a really
powerful insight behind it.
But, of course, to realize
all of this potential,
we're going to have to overcome
some of those core issues
and scalability.
And that's what
I'll show you here.
I think I can offer
a simple recipe
for doing that and testing
out a lot of these ideas.
To make this concrete,
let's continue
to ground our discussion
in our core task, which
is this colors in context task.
Just recall that, if you're
playing the speaker role,
you're presented with three
color patches, one of them
privately designated
as your target.
And your task is to
describe that target
in that context for a listener.
And then, in turn,
the listener task
is given the three
patches, and no idea
which one is the target,
and a speaker utterance.
Use that utterance to figure out
which was the speaker's target.
And so you can hear
in that description
that this is potentially a
kind of communication game,
and would support the
back and forth reasoning
that is the hallmark of the
Rational Speech Acts model.
So how are we going to take this
task and RSA and combine them?
Well, the first step
is straightforward.
We're going to start with
a literal neural speaker.
I've given that as S
theta up here with literal
indicating that
it's a base agent.
And for this, it's just going to
be exactly the natural language
generation system that we
explored in the earliest
parts of the screencast, right?
Except now, we're going to
consume three color patches
with the target always
given in the final position.
And then the decoding task
is to offer a description.
And we can make a lot of
different model choices here,
but the fundamental
insight is that we can now
treat this agent as a kind
of black box base listener.
Instead of having
to hand specify
a semantic grammar, which would
be impossible even for the task
the size of the colors
in context dataset,
we now just train
an agent, and use it
to play the role
of the base agent.
And we can, of course,
do the same thing
for the neural literal
listener, who will, again,
have some parameters
theta, which
will represent this entire
encoder/decoder architecture.
This neural literal listener
will process incoming messages
as a sequence.
And then given some context of
colors and a scoring function,
make a guess about which
one of those three colors
the message that it had as
input was being referred to.
And again, instead of hand
specifying the lexicon,
we just treat this
agent as a black box.
It serves the role of
the literal listener.
And from there, the RSA
recursion, so to speak,
is very easy to apply.
Let's consider the base
case of a pragmatic speaker.
So you can see over
here, we're going
to use our trained
literal listener.
And this is the most basic
form that the speaker can have.
And we've just gotten
now a pragmatic agent
that is reasoning about
states of the world as inputs
and making message
choices on that basis.
And it's doing that not
in terms of the raw data,
but rather in terms of how
the literal listener would
reason about the raw data,
so that core RSA insight.
But we're just essentially
using L0 here as the mechanism
to derive the
speaker distribution.
Now, there is one catch
here as we discussed.
In principle for RSA,
this would be a summation
over all messages,
which would be
completely intractable for any
realistically-sized language
model.
What we can do to overcome
that obstacle is simply
use our trained literal speaker,
which I presented before,
and sample utterances from it.
And that small sample
will serve as the basis
for this normalization
down here.
So it's an approximation,
but it's an easy one,
given that we have this
trained agent down here.
And in practice, we've seen that
it does quite well in serving
as the normalization constant.
And then the neural
pragmatic listeners
are even more
straightforward, having
defined that pragmatic speaker.
To put a listener on top
of that is really easy.
Again, you essentially
just apply Bayes' rule,
and you get a listener out.
And in the Monroe et al
paper as you've seen,
we actually found that
weighted combinations
of the literal listener
and the pragmatic listener
were the best at the
colors in context task.
But let me just close
up by mentioning
a few other related
strands of work
that you might think
about bringing in.
And what I just showed you is
the most basic form of this,
but many extensions
have been explored.
So Golland et al 2010
is a really early paper
in the history of these ideas
that is quite forward-thinking.
They explore recursive
speaker listener reasoning
as part of interpreting complex
utterances compositionally,
with grounding in a
simple visual world.
And I love the connection
with semantic composition.
This Wang et al 2016 paper
does even more of that.
Pragmatic reasoning
helps in online learning
of semantic parsers.
I mentioned before, work by
Stefanie Tellex and colleagues
on what they call
inverse semantics, which
is a simple RSA
mechanism applied
in the context of
human-robot interaction
to help humans and robots
collaborate more efficiently.
Khani et al extend this to more
free form social interaction
by showing that RSA has a role
to play in collaborative games.
I mentioned before this work
by Reuben Cohn-Gordon and Noah
Goodman on RSA for translation.
Reuben Cohn-Gordon did
a lot of innovative work
as part of his PhD in
the context of RSA.
He also explored applying RSA
at the word and character level,
so removing the approximation
that we sample from S0 speaker
to create the denominator.
Rather, instead, he applies
RSA at every single timestep
in a left-to-right
sequential decoding step.
And that timestep could
be either the word level
or surprisingly, it
was very effective
at the character level.
And then these final
two papers here
just show that we could
move out of the mode
of pre-training the base
agents and applying RSA on top.
And instead, have a mechanism
of end-to-end RSA learning,
which is more ambitious in terms
of learning and model set up.
But provides more
chances for us to be
responsive to the nature
of actual usage data,
while still making good on
the central insights of RSA,
and with luck, seeing some
empirical benefits from doing
that.