CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome back, everyone.
This is part three
in our series on NLI.
This is our chance to start
getting a little introspective,
and think more about developing
truly robust systems.
So our topic is going
to be Dataset Artifacts
And Adversarial Testing.
I'm pleased to report that a lot
of the discussion in this area
actually traces,
in the NLI context
to a course project
for this class.
In 2016, Leonid
Keselman observed
that for NLI,
hypothesis-only models
were surprisingly strong.
What I mean by
hypothesis-only model
is that these are models
that literally throw away
the premise text,
and reason entirely
in terms of the hypothesis.
So to the extent the
models can succeed,
despite having no information
about the premise.
We might really worry
about whether we're
solving the task we
think we're solving.
Because after all
NLI is supposed
to be about the reasoning
relationship between premise
and hypothesis.
And you would not expect
it to be successful if you
were given only the hypothesis.
But what Leonid observed,
is that these models
were surprisingly strong.
Subsequently, and I think
partly independently,
a number of other groups made
the same sort of observation
about a variety
of NLI benchmarks.
And that leads us to the
conclusion that at least
for SNLI, averaging across a
whole lot of different systems.
Hypothesis-only
baselines are typically
operating in the range of
about 65% to 70% accuracy.
Again, that's eye opening
because chance performance
would be 33%.
And this is showing
us that there
is some unusual bias
in the hypothesis that
is allowing us to
neglect the premise,
and still have a lot
of predictive capacity.
The reason for this
is likely due to what
we're going to call
artifacts in these datasets.
And just for a
few examples here,
we can observe that
specific claims
are likely to be premises
in entailment cases.
And correspondingly
general claims
are likely to be hypotheses
in entailment cases.
Just think of the
lexical level if you have
a pair like turtle and animal.
Where you have a very
specific term in the premise,
and a very general
term in the hypothesis.
That's an entailment
relation, and if you
did just drop off the
premise and looked only
at the hypothesis
"animal" you might still
have a pretty good
guess that that's
going to be an
entailment case in virtue
of the generality
of the second term.
And relatedly
specific claims are
likely to lead to contradiction.
The common strategy for
creating a contradiction pair,
is to just make sure you
have two sentences that
exclude each other, in virtue
of being very specific.
So it's in virtue of patterns
like this, that a system denied
the premise, can
nonetheless succeed
at about 65% to 70% accuracy.
Let's get a little
more precise about what
we mean by an
artifact, because I
think we need to think
about this in a nuanced way.
So my definition is
that a dataset artifact
is a bias that
would make a system
susceptible to
adversarial attack.
Even if the bias is
linguistically motivated.
And let me give
you an example that
brings out the nuance there.
Consider negated
hypotheses tending
to signal contradiction.
This is a very natural
thing linguistically
if you give me a sentence
like; the dog barked.
And you asked me to construct
a contradictory sentence,
it's very natural for me
to say the dog didn't bark,
by simply inserting a negation.
So it's not a surprise
that this happens,
it's linguistically motivated.
Negation is our best way of
establishing the relevant kind
of connection.
However, here's the reason
that this is an artifact.
We could easily curate a
data set, in which negation
correlated with
the other labels,
but nonetheless, this led
to no human confusion.
Because humans are not really
operating at this general level
of a dataset bias.
They are thinking about
individual examples,
and what they mean.
But we know that our
systems are going
to be very sensitive to
the distributions of things
in their training data.
And that's the sense in which we
can be adversarial in this way.
And expose that a system has
overfit to a certain kind
of regularity.
Here are some known artifacts.
This is by no means
exhaustive, but I
think this will give you a sense
for the kind of things that you
want to look out for
in an NLI context
but also generally in
dealing with problems in NLU.
So it's been observed that
these datasets contain
words whose appearance
nearly perfectly
correlates with specific labels.
And what I mean here is
just randomly chosen words
like cat and dog.
The reason for this is probably
that crowd workers were
producing a lot of examples.
And they fell into
a pattern of making
specific lexical choices.
And that created a spurious
bias for one label or another.
Entailment hypotheses
overrepresent
general and approximating words.
We've seen that that's
systematic in terms
of the linguistic patterns.
But it's an artifact
because the world
needn't be this way
for humans to succeed,
in making their predictions.
Neutral hypotheses often
introduce modifiers.
This was a way
that workers found
to create statements
that excluded each other
with simple modifications.
Contradiction hypotheses
overrepresent negation,
we've seen that and
that makes sense.
And neutral hypotheses
tend to be longer.
And that last one is
yet again another case
where that's the
sort of regularity
that our systems are going to
be very good at picking up on.
But that humans
will probably not
make direct use of in making
predictions of their own.
And in that way we can easily
leverage this observation
to create an adversarial
setting for one of our models
where humans succeed at the
task but our models suffer.
Because they're cued into the
wrong aspects of the underlying
problem.
To close this out, I
just want to emphasize
that artifacts are discussed
a lot in the context of NLI.
I think that's because a bunch
of big benchmarks appeared.
And people did a lot of probing
work to understand them.
But it does not follow that
NLI is the only task where
the datasets have artifacts.
In fact, I would venture that
every task that we work on,
has associated datasets
that suffer from artifacts.
Here, I've given you a sample
from prominent NLU problems
where people have
found artifacts
that are similar to the ones
that I just covered for NLI.
And the overall lesson is
clear, whatever problem
you're working on, you
should think critically
about your data, and how
idiosyncrasies in that data
might be affecting
system performance.
And creating a distance
between what you think you're
doing, in terms of
problem solving.
And what your system
is actually doing.
And one way we can expose
this is via efforts
involving adversarial testing.
We're going to have a
whole discussion of this
later in the quarter.
But I do want to
plant the idea here.
In adversarial
testing we're going
to take standard NLI
examples like this
and modify them in ways
that expose that systems
have surprising gaps.
So a prominent early
example of this,
is this wonderful paper
by Glockner et al.
called Breaking NLI.
What they did is
very simple, we're
going to operate with
actual SNLI examples.
Here we would start
with the premise;
A little girl is kneeling
in the dirt crying.
And: A little girl
is very sad, which
is an actual SNLI example
with the entailment relation.
We'll fix the
premise, what they did
to create their adversarial
dataset is simply swap
out "sad" for "Unhappy".
That is to create pairs
that differ only according
to the synonyms that they use.
This is only mildly
adversarial, but you can see
why this might be difficult.
Unhappy contains a negation,
and we might have a hypothesis
that systems will then
predict contradiction
because they've overfit to
the association of negation
with contradiction.
And that's exactly
the kind of pattern
that Glockner et al. found.
And the overall takeaway here
is that these systems that we've
developed are not
behaving systematically
in the sense of
cognitive science,
they're not behaving according
to the kinds of underlying
intuitions that human
language users have.
Their patterns of
errors are more
surprising and
idiosyncratic, leading
us to worry about their
true capacity to generalize.
Let me show you
one other example.
This is from Nie et al. and it
involves syntactic variation.
So in this case, we'll
take actual examples
and fix the hypothesis,
but now vary the premise.
So this is one of
their manipulations
where they simply swap
the subject and object.
Our original premise is;
A woman is pulling a child
on a sled in the snow.
That entails a child is sitting
on a sled in the snow, that's
good.
We would expect that if
we modify the premise so
that the subject is a child,
and the object is a woman.
This would create the
neutral label with respect
to our fixed hypothesis.
But perhaps
unsurprisingly, Nie et al.
found that many systems were
not sensitive to this change
in the premise.
Revealing that they were mainly
making use of the bag of words,
so to speak.
And not truly attuned to
the syntactic structure.
And that's still productive
because that specific lesson
might lead us to go
looking for systems that
are more sensitive to syntax.
And therefore, would be not
susceptible to this kind
of adversary.
And in that kind of
productive back and forth,
I think we can triangulate
on even better systems
for the next generation.