BILL MACCARTNEY: It's good
methodological practice
whenever you're starting to
build new models to start
by evaluating very simple
models, which establish
baselines to which
you can then compare
the more sophisticated
models that you're
going to build later on.
So to do that, we're
going to start by looking
at three simple models.
A random guesser, a very simple
phrase matching strategy,
and then, our first
machine learning
based approach, which will be a
simple bag-of-words classifier.
Just about the
simplest possible model
is one that doesn't
even look at the input,
but just flips a coin.
And I strongly
encourage you, whenever
you're embarking
on a model building
adventure in your final
project, wherever, you start
by evaluating a random guesser.
It's a snap to implement.
It can help to work out the
kinks in your test harness.
And it's often very informative
to put a floor under what
good scores look like.
Now, we've written an
evaluation method for you.
It's in the RelExt module and
it's just called evaluate.
You invoke it with your
splits, your classifier,
and the name of the split
that you want to evaluate on,
which defaults to dev.
When we evaluate
our random guesser,
we have some
interesting results,
so we have results separated
for each of the relations.
And for each one, we have
precision recall, F-score.
Remember, that's F0.5, which
gives more weight to precision
than to recall.
We have the support, which
is the number of instances
whose actual label is true.
And we have size, which is just
the total number of instances.
We find that recall is
generally right around 0.5.
And this makes
sense, because recall
says of the instances
which are actually true,
what proportion do
we predict true?
Well, we predict true
about half the time
because we're just
flipping a coin.
Precision on the other hand,
is generally quite poor,
because precision
says of the instances
where we predict true
which are basically
a random sample, because
we're just flipping a coin.
How many are actually true?
Well, relatively few.
And actually, you can
tell that by looking
at the ratio between
support and size.
The ratio between
support and size
is how many of the
instances are actually true.
So when we're tossing
a coin, the precision
should be right around the
ratio between support and size.
Our F-score is also
generally poor,
it stays close to
precision, for two reasons.
Number one, because
the harmonics--
the harmonic mean stays
closer to the lower number,
and number 2, because
we're using F0.5,
which gives more weight to
precision than to recall.
And the bottom line our
macro-average F-score is 9.7%,
so that's the number to beat.
It's a pretty low bar, but this
is a random guesser, after all.
OK.
So let's look at
another approach, which
is very simple, but smarter
than random guessing.
And it's a simple pattern
matching strategy.
And the idea is
for each relation,
let's go through the
corpus and find the most
common phrases that
connect to entities
that stand in that relation.
The most common middles,
in our terminology.
So here's some code
that does that.
I won't go through it in
detail, but one thing to note
is that it counts separately
the middles that connect subject
with object.
So here, it gets
all the examples
and counts the middles.
It tallies up the middles.
And it does that separately
from the examples that
connect object with subject.
And it stores them in separate
dictionaries under the keys
forward and reverse.
So we're going to
have forward middles
and reverse middles
stored separately, stored
and counted separately.
If we run that code,
here's what we get.
I'm showing results.
I'm only going to show
results for 3 of the relations
here, not all 16.
All 16 are in the
Python notebook
if you want to take a look.
But even from this
sample, there's
a few things that jump out.
First, some of the
most frequent middles
are really natural
and intuitive.
For example, comma, "starring"
indicates a reverse film
performance relation.
So that would be one
where the film comes first
and the actor comes second.
And I think that
makes perfect sense.
Star Wars, comma,
"starring" Mark Hamill.
Similarly, comma, "son of"
indicates a forward parents
relation.
So this would be one
where the son comes first.
The child comes first and
the parent comes second.
So those are extremely
intuitive and it's reassuring
to see them near the top of the
list of most common middles.
Another observation is
that punctuation and stop
words, like comma and
"and" are extremely common.
Unlike some other
NLP applications,
it's probably a bad idea
to throw these away.
They carry lots of
useful information.
On the other hand,
punctuation and stop words
tend to be highly ambiguous.
For example, if you look
across the full range of all 16
relations, you'll
see that a bare comma
is a likely middle for almost
every relation in at least
one direction.
So that comma does very
often indicate a relation,
but it's a really
ambiguous indicator.
OK.
Now that we've identified
the most common middles
for each relation, it's
straightforward to build
a classifier based on that
information, a classifier that
predicts true for a candidate
KB triple, just in case
the two entities in the triple
appear in the corpus connected
by one of the phrases
that we just discovered.
I don't show the
code for that here,
but it's in the Python
notebook for this unit.
And when we evaluate
this approach,
we see some really
interesting results.
First, recall is much
worse across the board.
And that makes sense
because we're no longer just
guessing randomly.
Before, we were saying
true half the time.
Now, we're going to be a lot
more selective about what
we say true to.
But precision and F-score
have improved dramatically
for several
relations, especially
for adjoins and author and
has_sibling and has_spouse.
Then again, there are
many other relations
where precision and F-score
are still quite poor, including
this one genre where
we get straight zeros
across the board.
I'm not quite sure
what happened there.
But it indicates
that although things
have improved a
lot in some places,
they're still rather
poor in others.
And our macro-average F-score
has improved only modestly,
so it improved
from 9.7% to 11.1%.
We're heading in
the right direction,
but you'd have to say that's
still pretty unimpressive.
To make significant
gains, we're going
to need to apply
machine learning.
So let's get started on that.
We're going to build a very
simple classifier using
an approach that should
be familiar from our look
at sentiment analysis last week.
And we're going to start that
by defining a very simple
bag-of-words feature function.
So here's the code
for that, and let
me briefly walk you through it.
What we're going to do is to get
the features for a KB triple.
That's the kbt here.
We're going to find all of
the corpus examples containing
the two entities in the
KB triple, the subject
and the object.
And note that we do that in both
directions, subject and object,
and then, also
object and subject.
For each example, we
look at the middle.
We break it into words.
And then, we count
up all the words.
So a couple of
things to note here.
One is that the feature
representation for one KB
triple can be derived
from many corpus examples.
And this is the point that I
was trying to make last time,
that we're using the
corpus to generate features
for a candidate KB triple.
And the role of the corpus
is to provide the feature
representation.
And the feature
representation for a KB
triple will be based
on all of the examples
in the corpus that contain
those two entities.
The other observation
to make here
is that we make no
distinction between what
you might call forward examples,
which have subject first
and then object, and reverse
examples, which have object
and then subject.
We're lumping them all together.
The words that come from
the middles of examples
in either direction
all get lumped together
into one feature counter.
And you might have qualms
about whether that's really
the smartest thing to do.
So let's get a sense of what
this looks like in action.
First, let's print out the
very first KB triple in our KB.
We actually looked
at this last time.
It's a KB triple that says--
that contains relation, holds
between Brickfields and Kuala
Lumpur Sentral railway station.
And now, let's look
up the first example
containing these two entities.
I'm just going to look them
up in the forward direction,
subject and object, and
get all the examples.
I look at the first one, and let
me just point out the middle.
The middle says, "It was just
a quick 10-minute walk to."
So I guess the full example
probably said something
like, "From
Brickfields, it was just
a quick 10-minute walk to
Kuala Lumpur Sentral railway
station."
And maybe there was more.
Now, let's run our
featurizer on this KB triple
and see what features we get.
So we get a counter that
contains "It was just
a quick 10-minute
walk to the--" So it
looks like it's counted up the
words in that middle, which
is just what we expected.
But if you look closely, there's
something unexpected here
because the word "two"
has a count of 2,
even though it appears
only once in that middle.
And also, the word
"the" has a count of 1,
even though it didn't appear
in that middle at all.
So where did those come from?
Well, remember that the
featurizer counts words
from the middles of all examples
containing those entities
in either direction.
And it turns out that
the corpus contains
another example containing
those two entities
and that other example has--
there's just one other
example, but that other example
has middle "to the."
And so, that's where
these counts come from.
So all is well.
We did the right thing.
OK.
We have our simple
bag-of-words featurizer.
Now, we need a way to train
models to make predictions
and to evaluate the results.
The RelExt module contains
functions for each of those.
And so, I just want to
give you a quick tour
of what those functions are.
But you'll definitely want
to go read the code for this,
so that you're more familiar
with how it can be used.
And a lot of this code appears
in a file called RelExt,
rel_ext.py.
So we'll start with a
function called train models.
This takes as arguments
the dictionary of data
splits, a list of featurizers.
And here, we have
a list consisting
of just our simple
bag-of-words featurizer.
The name of the split
on which to train,
which defaults to train.
And a model factory, which
is a function that returns
a classifier and it's--
sorry, a function which
initializes an Sk classifier.
And by default, it's a
logistic regression classifier,
as shown here.
But you could easily substitute
this with some other Sklearn
classifier.
It returns this thing
called train_result
which is a dictionary holding
the featurizers, the vectorizer
that was used to generate
the training matrix,
and most importantly, a
dictionary holding the trained
models, one per relation.
So it's a dictionary which maps
from relation names to models.
So that's train models.
Next comes predict,
this is a function
that takes his arguments a
dictionary of data splits.
The output of train models,
that train results thing,
and the name of the split on
which to make predictions.
And by default that's dev.
And it returns two
parallel dictionaries,
one holds the predictions
grouped by relation
and the other holds the true
labels grouped by relation.
And our third building block
is evaluate predictions.
So this is a function that
takes as arguments the two
parallel dictionaries
of predictions
and true labels
produced by predict,
and it prints evaluation
metrics for each relation,
like we saw earlier.
Now, before we dwell
on these results,
I want to show one
more function, which is
a function called experiment.
And experiment simply chains
together the three functions
that I just showed you.
It chains together training,
prediction, and evaluation.
So that's very convenient for
running end to end experiments.
I haven't shown all
the parameters here,
but if you go look
at the source code,
you'll see that
it actually takes
a lot of optional parameters.
And those parameters let you
specify everything about how
to run the experiment.
It lets you specify your
featurizers, your model
factory, which splits to
train and test on, and more.
So for example, earlier, I
mentioned that the tiny split
is really useful for running
fast experiments to work out
the kinks.
If you wanted to do
that, it's very easy
using the experiment
function just
to set the training
split and the test split
to tiny to run a very
quick experiment.
Now, here are the
results of evaluating
our simple bag-of-words
logistic regression classifier.
And let's take a closer look,
because this is quite stunning.
Even though this is
just about the simplest
possible classifier,
we've achieved huge gains
over the phrase
matching approach.
The first thing
that jumps out is
that our macro-averaged F-score
has jumped from 11.1 to 56.7.
And we see big
gains in precision
for almost every single
relation and correspondingly,
big gains in F-score.
On the other hand, there's still
plenty of room for improvement.
I mean this is much, much
more impressive than where
we were before, but we're
very far from perfection.
There's abundant
headroom and opportunity
to continue to improve.