BILL MACCARTNEY: OK.
We're underway.
We have a simple model with
reasonable performance.
Where do we go from here?
Well, to make
further gains we need
to stop treating the
model as a black box.
We need to open it
up and get visibility
into what it's learned
and more importantly,
where it still falls down.
And then we can begin to
look at some ideas for how
to improve it.
One important way to gain
understanding of our trained
models is to inspect
the model weights.
Which features are strong
positive indicators
for each relation,
and what features
are strong negative indicators?
The rel_ext model
contains a function
called examine_model_weights
that makes it easy to inspect.
So here, I show results for
just 4 of our 16 relations.
And in general, I
think the features
with large positive weight
are pretty intuitive.
So for the author relation,
the biggest weights
are author, books, and by.
For film performance, we
have starring, alongside,
and opposite.
By the way, I was a
little bit puzzled
when I first saw alongside and
opposite, because I thought
that those are words
that would naturally
appear between the
names of two actors,
not between the name of a
film and the name of an actor.
What I did was I wrote
a little bit of code
to pull up the actual examples
that caused these weights
to wind up being large.
And what I realized was
there's a very common pattern
which is like X appeared
in Y alongside Z.
So X and Z are actors.
Y is a film.
X appeared in Y
alongside Z. So you
have Y alongside
Z. That indicates
that Z is an actor that
appeared in film Y.
And I think something
similar happens for opposite.
So it does make
sense that these are
strong indicators of the
film performance relation.
For has spouse, we have
wife, married, and husband.
I think this makes
perfect sense.
The one that's a bit
surprising is adjoins.
So for adjoins we have
Cordoba, Taluks and Valais.
It's odd to see specific
place names here.
They certainly don't seem to
express the adjoins relation.
I wonder if anyone has
a guess what's going on.
I was really puzzled by this.
And so again, I
wrote a bit of code
to find the specific
examples that contributed
to this result. I
looked for examples
where the two entity mentions,
stand in the adjoins relation.
And these terms, these specific
terms, appear in the middle.
And when I looked
at the examples,
I realized that
what's going on is
that it's very common to have
lists of geographic locations.
So A, B, C, D.
And in such lists,
it's not uncommon that just
by chance A and C or A and D
stand in the adjoins relation.
Maybe it's a list of
provinces in a country.
And of course, some
of those provinces
are adjacent to each other.
So if A adjoins
C or A adjoins D,
that will tend to make B
appear as a positive indicator
for the adjoins
relation and especially
if the corpus just happens to
contain several such examples.
So I think that's
what contributed
to this puzzling result.
The features with
large negative weights
look a bit more haphazard.
But I think that's
not surprising.
It's kind of what you expect
for this kind of linear model.
By the way, you can fiddle with
the code that prints this out.
And here it just
prints the top three.
But you can fiddle
with the code,
there's actually
a parameter that
tells you-- it tells it how
many of the top of the list
to print.
And so you can print
much longer lists.
And for many of the relations,
the top 20, even the top 50,
features all look very
plausible and intuitive.
And it's quite satisfying to
see those results come out.
Another way to gain
insight into our model
is to use it to discover new
relation instances that don't
currently appear in the KB.
In fact, as we
discussed last time,
this is the whole point of
building a relation extraction
system, to augment
a KB with knowledge
extracted from natural
language text at scale.
So the decisive question is, can
our model do this effectively?
We can't really evaluate this
capability automatically,
because we have no other source
of ground truth than the KB
itself.
But we can evaluate it
manually by examining
KB triples that aren't
in the KB but which
our model really, really
thinks should be in the KB.
So we wrote a
function to do this.
It's called
find_new_relation_instances.
And you can go look at the code.
Here's how it works.
It starts from corpus
examples containing
pairs of entities
that don't belong
to any relation in the KB.
So these are what we described
last time as negative examples.
We'll consider each
such pair of entities
as a candidate to
join each relation.
So we'll take the cross product
of all of those entity pairs
and relations.
We'll apply our model to all
of those candidate KB triples.
And we'll just sort the results
by the probability assigned
by the model in order to find
the most likely new instances
of each relation.
So we'll find the candidate KB
triples that aren't currently
in the KB, but which
the model believes
have really high
probability of being valid.
So let's see what we
get when we run it.
Here are the results for
the adjoins relation.
Notice that the model
assigned a probability of 1.0
to each of these pairs.
It is totally convinced
that these pairs
belong to the adjoins relation.
But the results are,
well let's be honest,
the results are terrible.
Almost all of these pairs
belong to the contains relation,
which by the way isn't actually
one of our 16 relations.
But intuitively, they should
belong to a contains relation
not the adjoins relation.
You could make a case maybe
for Mexico and Atlantic
Ocean belonging to
the adjoins relation.
But I mean, to be honest,
even that one is a stretch.
One other thing worth
noting, whenever the model
predicts that X
adjoins Y, it also
predicts that Y adjoins
X. You might for a moment
think that this shows that
the model has understood
that adjoins is a
symmetric relation.
Unfortunately no, that's
not what's going on.
It's just an artifact of how we
wrote the simple bag of words
featurizer.
That simple bag of
words featurizer
makes no distinction between
forward and reverse examples.
So it has no idea
which one comes first
and which one comes second.
And that will be true
for asymmetric relations
just like for
symmetric relations.
So this is not a
very promising start.
It's-- I mean, we saw a pretty
good quantitative evaluation
for this model.
So this is a little
bit surprising.
Let's see what we get
for some other relations.
So here are the results
for the author relation.
And these look a lot better.
Once again, all of the
probabilities are 1.
But this time, every single
one of these predictions
is correct.
Well not quite actually,
because the book
is supposed to appear
first, like "Oliver
Twist" and the author
second, Charles Dickens.
So this first one
actually is correct.
The second one is backwards.
It has the author first
and the book second.
Our model is completely
ignorant of order.
So it's just as likely
to put things in reverse.
But if you ignore
that, if you're
willing to imagine that
we could easily fix that,
then the results look great.
We could put all of these
triples right into our KB
and we'd have a bigger and
better KB because of it.
This is relation
extraction at its finest.
This is what we wanted.
Here are the results
for the capital relation
and it's a similar picture.
All of the
probabilities are 1.0.
The ordering is
frequently reversed.
It's very haphazard.
But if you put that aside,
the results look very good.
You could quibble
perhaps with Delhi here.
I mean, the capital of
India is really New Delhi.
But New Delhi is part of
Delhi, so you know, it's close.
Still overall, I think
this looks really good.
Let me show you one more.
This is the last one I'll show.
These are results for
the worked_at relation.
And here, the results
are more mixed.
So we have Stan Lee
and Marvel Comics.
Sure, if you can say that Elon
Musk worked at Tesla Motors,
then you can say that Stan
Lee worked at Marvel Comics.
And while we're at
it, Genghis Khan
worked at the Mongol Empire.
Sure, why not?
But the rest are nonsense.
So why?
What happened here?
Well, when you encounter
surprising and mysterious
results in your
model output, it's
really good practice to go dig
into the data and investigate.
And this is called
error analysis.
And I want to show you a
couple of examples of that now.
So first let's see
if we can figure out
what happened with Lewis
Chevrolet and William C Durant.
First, let's look up
the corpus examples
containing these two entities.
I'm only going to look
up the examples that
have them in this order.
I should look them up in
the other order as well.
And as a matter of fact, I did.
I'm just not going to
put that on the slide.
I'm just going to focus on
what happens in this order.
So I'm going to look
up these examples
and print out what
they look like.
And here's what we get.
There are 12 examples.
And they all look identical.
Actually, I didn't print
the full context here.
If you look at the
code closely, you'll
see that I'm printing
the suffix of the left
and the prefix of the right.
So there's more context
further out on left and right.
And if you did see
the full context,
you would realize that the
examples do differ slightly.
But they're very, very similar.
They're near duplicates.
I mentioned this last
time that this is one
of the warts of this dataset.
It contains a lot of
near duplicate examples.
And I think this is an
unfortunate consequence
of the way the sample was
constructed, the way the web
documents that this
corpus was based on
were sampled from the web.
And it seems like
that's bitten us here.
But it still leaves
the question, why?
Why did that repetition
leave the model
to predict that
this pair belongs
to the worked_at relation?
Because it doesn't look
obvious that that's
the right relation here.
I suspect that it's because of
the word "founder", because X
being a founder of Y strongly
implies that X worked at Y.
And actually, we can check this.
It's not that hard
to write some code
to inspect the weight
that was assigned
to the word "founder"
in the model
for the worked_at relation.
So here's a little bit
of code that does that.
And sure enough, in the
model for worked at,
the word "founder" gets a weight
of 2.05, which is pretty large.
If you look at the
distribution of weights,
it's a relatively large one.
I forget exactly, but I
think it's in the top 10.
It's a relatively significant,
quite significant,
feature for this model.
So that's what happened.
We've got 12 examples.
Each of them is contributing
a sizable weight.
And the result is that the
model is completely convinced
that this is the right-- that
the worked_at relation holds
here.
By the way, I didn't check.
But I'm confident that
the founder, the model
for the founders relation, will
also predict that the founder
relation holds here.
An understanding
of what went wrong
here could help to stimulate
some ideas for how to fix it.
I don't think I'll--
I think I won't.
I mean, I have some ideas.
I think I won't give them away.
But I hope this underscores
the value of error analysis.
If you really want
to understand--
when you see weird
results, you really
want to understand what's
going on in your data that
led to these weird results.
Let me show you one
more example that has
a bit of a different flavor.
Let's look at what's going
on with Homer and the Iliad.
I wrote a little bit of code
to investigate this one too.
And I'm not going to show
the whole investigation
but I'm just going
to cherry pick
the most informative results.
So one thing that I
notice is that there
are a lot of examples
for Homer and Iliad.
In fact, there are 118 of
them just in that direction.
There's more in the
reverse direction.
That's impressive.
But again, by itself, it
doesn't explain why worked_at
looked like a good prediction.
By the way, I did
check to see if it
was the same explanation as last
time, a lot of near duplicates.
It's not.
That's not what's going on here.
But the next thing I did
was to write some code
to count up the most
common middles that
join Homer and Iliad
across these 118 examples.
And so that code
looks like this.
And here are the results.
And there was one middle
that strongly dominated.
And it's apostrophe s,
so as in "Homer's Iliad."
So that makes sense because
clearly the possessive can
indicate the author relation.
You expect to see Homer's
Iliad and Jane Austen's Pride
and Prejudice and many
other similar formulations.
But the apostrophe
s can equally well
indicate the worked_at relation,
as in Tesla's Elon Musk
or Microsoft's Bill Gates.
So this apostrophe s is
really highly ambiguous.
Just to confirm that
this is actually
significant to the
result that we saw let's
check what weight was
assigned to apostrophe s
in the model for worked_at.
So this code is similar to the
code on the previous slide.
But this time we're looking for
the weight for apostrophe s.
And it turns out that
the weight was 0.58.
OK.
It's not a huge weight.
But it's not small either.
And this feature occurred
51 times across the corpus.
So I think that's what happened.
We had a non-trivial
amount of weight
that got added up 51 times.
And we wound up with a
really big contribution
and the model feeling really
confident about this relation.
So again, thinking
about this problem
might suggest some
strategies for how
to reduce that ambiguity.
The fundamental problem
here is that apostrophe s
is highly ambiguous.
But a good question
to ask yourself
is, is there other information
in the sentence that
could help to distinguish
the author relation
from the worked_at relation?
And I think there is.
Again, I don't want
to give too much away.
But I think there
is other evidence
in these sentences that could
help to tease apart these two
relations.
And this kind of
error analysis is
really indispensable to the
model development process.
Now for the homework
and the bake off.
We're going to turn
you loose to find ways
to improve this baseline model.
And there are a lot
of possibilities.
One area for innovation is in
the feature representation we
pass to the learning algorithm.
So far, we've just used a simple
bag of words representation.
But you can imagine lots
of ways to enhance this.
So you could use
word embeddings,
like the glove embeddings.
You could use a bag of
words representation
that distinguishes between
forward and reverse contexts.
You could use bigrams
or longer n-grams.
You could leverage the
part of speech tags
that we have in the corpus
or information from WordNet.
Much of the early work
on relation extraction
relied heavily on
syntactic features.
So maybe try that.
And so far, we've
used features based
only on the middle phrase, the
phrase between the two entity
mentions.
You could also try using
information about the entity
mentions themselves, for
example, the entity types.
Or you could try
deriving features
from the left and right context.
There are a lot of
possibilities for richer feature
representations.
There's also a lot of room for
innovation with the model type.
Our baseline model is a
simple linear model optimized
with logistic regression.
That's a good place to start.
But there are many
other possibilities.
If you want to stick with linear
models, you could use an SVM.
And sklearn makes that easy.
Or you could experiment
with neural networks.
You could use a simple
feed-forward neural network
as a drop in replacement
for our linear model.
Or since examples can
be a variable length,
you might consider a recurrent
neural network, like an LSTM.
If you go this way you'll
have to think carefully
about how to encode the input.
If the input is just
the middle phrase,
things are probably
relatively straightforward.
But if you want to include
the entity mentions
or the left and
right context, you
might need to think
carefully about how
to demarcate the segments.
Or you could use a
transformer-based architecture
like BERTs, although
the quantity
of training data that
we have available
here might be a bit small.
I think all of these
are potentially
interesting and fruitful
directions for exploration.
And I think you can have
a lot of fun with this.