CHRIS POTTS: Welcome, everyone.
This is the first
screencast in our series
on methods and metrics.
Fundamentally, what we're
trying to do with this unit
is give you help
with your projects,
and specifically give you help
with the experimental aspects
of your projects.
And so the kind of
highlight topics for us
will be around things
like managing your dataset
for the purposes of conducting
experiments; establishing
baseline systems;
and in turn, doing
model comparisons
between baselines
and an original system, or
between an original system
and published results in the
literature, and so forth.
And relatedly, we're
going to give you
some advice on how to optimize
your models effectively.
Those are kind of the
highlight topics there.
And I would say
that all of this is
kind of oriented toward the more
abstract topic of helping you
navigate tricky situations
that arise as you conduct
experiments in NLP.
And as you'll see very often,
these tricky situations
arise because we encounter
limitations in the data that's
available to us, or we're
just fundamentally constrained
in terms of computing resources.
And that leads us to have
to make some compromises
in the ideal experimental
protocol that we would use.
These things are inevitable,
and the idea here
is that we're going to equip you
with some tools and techniques
for thinking about
the trade-offs
in making your way through all
of these tricky situations.
There are a bunch of
associated materials
for these screencasts.
We have a whole notebook
that's on metrics.
I'm going to offer some
screencasts that just highlight
a few of the metrics that are
discussed in that notebook.
But it's meant as a
resource, the notebook
itself, so that you could
pursue other avenues.
And overall, what
I'm trying to do
is give you a framework for
thinking about what metrics
encode in terms of their
values, what bounds they have,
and where they can be
applied and misapplied.
Scikit-learn implements
essentially all of the metrics
that we'll be discussing.
And to their
credit, they've done
a wonderful job of offering
rich documentation that
will again, help you not only
understand what the metrics do,
but also where and how they
can be effectively applied.
And then there is
an entire notebook
that's on methods, especially
experimental methods,
and that covers a lot
of the tricky situations
that I just described
in terms of setting up
experiments and thinking
about trade-offs,
and then following through on
model evaluation and so forth.
And that notebook is
nice as a supplement
to these screencasts, because
it embeds a bunch of code that
can help you run hands-on
experiments to get
a feel for the core concepts.
And we have two readings.
Resnik and Lin 2010 is
a wonderful overview
of experimental evaluations
in the context of NLP.
And Smith 2011, Appendix
B is a compendium
of different metrics, so another
good resource for you if you're
unsure about how a metric
works, or what its bounds are,
or how it's calculated,
and things like that.
The final thing I want
to say for this overview
relates specifically
to the projects
that you'll be pursuing.
And the bottom line for
us is that we will never
evaluate a project based on
how good the results are.
Now, we acknowledge that in the
field and throughout science,
publication venues
do this because they
have additional constraints
on space nominally,
and that leads them-- as a
cultural fact about the way
science works-- to
favor positive evidence
for new developments
over negative results.
I frankly think this is
unfortunate and exerts
a kind of distorting influence
on the set of publications
that we all get to study,
but nonetheless, that's
the way the world
works at present.
In the context of this
course, we are not
subject to that constraint.
So we can do the right and
good thing scientifically,
evaluating positive
results, negative results,
and everything in between.
So I repeat our core value here.
We will never evaluate
a project based
on how good the results are.
Instead, we're going to
evaluate your project
on the appropriateness of
the metrics that you choose;
the strength of your methods;
and really fundamentally here,
the extent to
which your paper is
open and clear-sighted about
the limits of its findings.
So you'll notice that,
given this framework here,
you could report
state-of-the-art results,
world record-breaking results
on a task, but nonetheless,
not succeed with a project if
it fails on all of these things
that we've listed
under our true values.
And conversely, you
might have a hypothesis
that turns out to be a
miserable failure in terms
of the performance metrics
that you're able to report.
But that could lead to
an outstanding grade
in the context of this
course, provided that you
do all of these things.
And that would be under the
heading of a negative result
but nonetheless, teaches us
something really fundamental
and important about NLP, and
therefore pushes the field
forward.