CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is part 4 in our series
on methods and metrics.
We're going to be
talking about how
we organize datasets for
the purposes of conducting
evaluations in NLP.
Let's begin with the classic
train/dev/test split.
This is a very common
format for datasets
in our field, especially
for the very large
publicly available ones.
And it's really
good in the sense
that in releasing datasets
with these splits predefined,
we do ensure some consistency
across the different
evaluations that people run.
It does presuppose that you
have a fairly large datasets
because after all,
right from the get go,
you are setting aside a whole
lot of examples in the dev
and test splits
that you can't use
at all to train your systems.
So even though your system might
benefit from those examples,
you can't use them
in that context.
They can be used
only for evaluations.
You're just giving up a lot of
potentially useful examples.
As we've discussed many times,
we're all on the honor system
when it comes to that test set.
It's distributed as
part of the data set,
but it has a privileged status.
The test set can be used only
once all of system development
is complete, and then you do a
single evaluation on the test
set and report that number
completely hands off.
This is vital for our field
because it's the only way
that we can even hope to
get a true picture of how
our systems are truly
generalizing to new examples.
That said, the downside
of having predefined
train/dev/test splits is
that inevitably everyone
is using those same
dev and test sets.
And what that means
is that over time
as we see consistent
progress on a benchmark test,
we're taking that
same measurement
on that same test set.
And it can be hard to
be sure whether we're
seeing true progress
on the underlying
task or the result of a
lot of implicit lessons
that people have
learned about what works
and what doesn't for
that particular test set.
And that's true even if everyone
is obeying that honor code
and using the test set only
for truly final evaluations.
Nonetheless, information
can leak out,
and we might start to
mistake true progress when
we're actually just
seeing progress
on that particular test set.
And I think the only
way that we can really
combat this is by
continually setting
new benchmark tests for
ourselves with new test sets
so that we see how
systems perform
in truly unseen environments.
As you leave NLP, it's
common to find datasets
that don't come with that
predefined train/dev/test
split, and that poses some
methodological questions
for you.
This is especially true
for small public data
sets that you see out there.
And this poses a
challenge for assessment.
For robust
comparisons, you really
have to run all your models
using your same assessment
regime.
That is, the same splits.
And that's especially important
if the dataset is small
because, of course,
in a small dataset,
you're probably
going to get more
variance across different runs.
And this can make it
really hard to compare
outside of the experimental
work that you're doing.
If someone has published the
results of some random 70/30
train-test split, unless you can
reconstruct exactly the splits
that they used, it
might be unclear
whether you're doing a true
apples-to-apples comparison.
So that's something
to keep in mind.
And it does mean that if you
can for your own experiments,
you might impose a split right
at the start of your project.
This is probably feasible
if the data set is large.
And what it will mean is
that you have a simplified
experimental setup, and you
have to do less hyperparameter
optimization just
because there are
fewer moving parts in your
underlying experimental setup.
It does presuppose that you
have a pretty large data set
because, as I said
before, you have
to give up a whole bunch of
examples to dev and test.
But it will simplify other
aspects of your project
if it's feasible.
For small datasets
though, imposing a split
might leave too
little data, leading
to highly variable performance.
And in that context, if
that's the kind of behavior
that you observe, you
might want to move
into the mode of
cross-validation.
So cross-validation,
in this context
we take a set of examples,
say our entire data set,
and we partition them into
two or more train-test splits.
And you might do that
repeatedly and then
average over the results
of evaluations on those
splits in some way to give
a holistic summary of system
performance.
And in that way, even
as those numbers vary--
they might have a
lot of variance--
we're still getting
in the average,
we hope, a pretty
reliable measure
of how the system performs in
general on the available data.
And I'm going to
talk about two ways
to do cross-validation,
each with its own strengths
and weaknesses.
Let's begin with what I
call random splits here.
So under the random splits
regime, you take your dataset.
And let's say k times, you
shuffle it, and you split it.
And you have t% for train
then probably the rest
left out for test.
And on each one of
those splits, you
conduct some kind of evaluation,
get back your metrics.
And then at the end of
all these k evaluations,
you probably average
those metrics
in some way to give a
single summary number
for system performance.
In general, but not always,
when we do these splits,
we want them to be
stratified in the sense
that the train and test splits
should have approximately
the same distribution over the
classes in the underlying data.
But I have been careful to say
that this is not always true.
There could, for
example, be contexts
in which you would like
your test set to stress test
your system by having a very
different distribution, maybe
an even distribution, or
one that's heavily skewed
towards some of the smaller
but more important classes.
And that will pose a challenge
for train-test regimes
because the system's
experiences at train time
will be different in this high
level distributional sense
from what it sees at test time.
But that, of course,
might be part
of what you're trying
to pursue as part
of your overall hypothesis.
The trade-offs for this kind
of cross-validation-- the good
is that you can
create as many splits
as you want without having this
impact the ratio of training
to testing examples, right,
because k times-- we're just
going to do a random split.
And it can be consistent
that we do independent
of k 70% train,
30% test or 50-50,
or whatever we
decide we want that's
independent of the number
of splits that we set.
The bad of this, of course,
is that there's no guarantee
that every example will be
used the same number of times
for training and for testing.
And for small data sets,
this could, of course,
be a concern because
you might be introducing
unwanted correlations across
the splits in, for example,
never having certain
hard examples be
part of your test set just
as a matter of chance.
So that's something
to keep in mind.
But of course, for
very large data sets,
it's very unlikely
that you'll be
susceptible to the
bad part of this,
and then you do get
a lot of the benefits
of the freedom of being able
to run lots of experiments
with a fixed train-test ratio.
And of course, as
usual, scikit has a lot
of tools to help you with this.
So I've just given some
classic examples down
here from the
model_selection package.
You might import ShuffleSplit,
StratifiedShuffleSplit.
And of course, train_test_split
is a useful utility
for very quickly and flexibly
creating splits of your data.
And I make heavy use of
these throughout my own code.
The second reason
for cross-validation
that I'd like to discuss is
K-folds cross-validation.
Here, the method is
slightly different.
We're going to take our dataset
and split it into three folds,
in this case for three-fold
cross-validation.
You could, of course, pick any
fold number that you wanted.
And then, given that it's
three-fold cross-validation,
we're going to conduct three
experiments-- one where fold 1
is used for testing and 2
and 3 are merged together
for training, the second
experiment where we hold out
fold 2 for testing and
the union of 1 and 3
is used for training, and then
finally a third experiment
where fold 3 is used for
testing and folds 1 and 2
are concatenated
for the train set.
The trade-offs here are slightly
different from the trade-offs
for random splits.
So the good of this
is that every example
appears in a train set
exactly k minus 1 times
and in a test set exactly once.
We have that guarantee
in virtue of the fact
that we use a single
split over here
to conduct our three
experimental paradigms.
The bad of this, of course,
can be really difficult.
The size of K is determining
the size of the training test
split.
But just consider that for
three-fold cross-validation,
we're going to use 67%
of the data for training
and 33 for testing.
But if three experiments is not
enough, if we want 10 folds,
the result of that
will be that we
use 90% of our data for
training and 10% for testing.
And the bottom
line is that those
are very different
experimental scenarios
from the point of view of
the amount of training data
that your system has and
probably the variance that you
see in testing
because of the way
you're changing the
size of the test set.
Whereas for the random splits
that we just discussed,
we have an independence
of the number of folds
and the percentage of
train and test examples
that we're going to have.
And that can be very freeing,
especially for large data
sets where the value
up here in the good
is really less pressing.
And, again, scikit-learn
has lots of tools for this.
And I've actually just
given a sample of them here.
You have KFold, StratifiedKFold,
and then cross_val_score
is a nice wrapper utility
that will, again, give you
flexible access to
lots of different ways
of conceptualizing
K-folds cross-validation.