CHRIS POTTS: Welcome, everyone.
This is part three in our series
on presenting your research.
We're going to be talking
about the sometimes
thrilling and
sometimes agonizing
process of submitting your
work for publication at an NLP
conference.
To start, I want
to review what's
known as the anonymity
period for ACL conferences.
All of the ACL conferences that
have adopted a uniform policy
that submitted papers cannot be
uploaded to repositories like
arXiv or made public in other
ways starting one month from
the submission deadline and
extending through the time when
decisions go out.
So you should be aware of this,
and for specific conferences,
check their sites
for the precise date
when the embargo
goes into effect
so that you're sure you're
playing by the rules.
The rationale of the
policy is an attempt
to balance the benefits of
free and fast distribution
of new ideas against the
benefits of double blind peer
review.
The idea is that we want to
avoid corrupting reviewers just
at the moment that
they sit down to begin
their work of reviewing
by having them see
on arXiv or via Twitter an
announcement about the paper
they're reviewing that reveals
the authors, and the origins,
and so forth, because we know
that that public announcement
would influence their
decision-making process.
So to preserve that balance
against free dissemination
of ideas, we have
this embargo period
around the period where we
know reviewing will happen.
For more on the policy
and its rationale,
you can follow this link here.
But I would say that,
fundamentally, it's
an attempt to balance
these two pressures,
the kind of pragmatic
approach to balancing them.
OK, now let's dive into the
actual process of submitting
work for publication and having
it go through review at one
of these conferences.
So to start, let's suppose
you've submitted your paper.
When you do that, you'll
select some area keywords
that will help determine which
committee gets your paper.
This is already a
really important step.
You'll be choosing from
a bunch of keywords that
signal different areas of NLP.
And what you're
doing at that point
is probably routing your
paper to certain sets
of reviewers and certain
area chairs and so forth.
And in doing that,
you're creating
expectations about the
kind of contribution
that you're making.
So if you're unsure
about this process,
I would encourage you to
recruit an expert in the NLP
reviewing process to help you
make these keyword selections.
Here's an example of how
this could be important.
Suppose that your
paper is fundamentally
a new machine
learning contribution
but it reports some
experiments that
involve kind of topics in
computational social science,
it might be really
a mistake to choose
the computational social
science keyword at this point,
because if your paper
ends up with reviewers who
have expectations
that you'll be making
some new and fundamental
contribution to that area
and what they're looking at is
a machine learning contribution,
that mismatch in
their expectations
might lead them to have
a negative perception
of the work.
And the reverse of
course, holds as well.
If you have a fundamentally new
computational social sciences
contribution but it
incidentally makes
use of some machine
learning apparatus,
I think it would be a mistake
to choose machine learning
as a keyword, precisely
because of that mismatch
in expectations that would
result in reviewers' minds
when they sat down and
started reviewing your paper.
So think strategically
about this stage.
You can see why it's important
at this next stage here.
Reviewers when they
begin their work,
they're going to first
scan a long list of titles
and abstracts, and they'll
make bids on which ones
they want to do.
At this point they signal
yes or maybe or no,
or maybe they indicate
a conflict of interest,
indicating that they can't
review the paper at all.
When they do this, the title
is probably the primary factor
in bidding decisions.
They probably have access to
the abstract at this stage,
but they might be
looking at a list
of over 200 different
contributions,
and it's probably
just too much to ask,
that they would read all of
these abstracts at this stage.
So they're probably
scanning the title
and using that as an indication
about what kind of bids
they want to make.
So again, you might
think strategically
about your title
and the role it will
play at this early
stage in the process.
After that, the program chairs
assign reviewers their papers
partly based on the
bidding or maybe
partly based on other
considerations of workloads
and so forth.
We don't know precisely how
that process will happen,
but by some mechanism your
paper will be assigned probably
three different reviewers.
Reviewers read the papers, write
comments and supply ratings
over the course of a few months.
At the very end of that
process, authors are typically
allowed to respond
briefly to the reviews,
and then the program
chair or the area chair
might seek to stimulate
some discussion
among the reviewers about
conflicts between their reviews
or maybe places where
the author responds,
and says the reviewers
are incorrect
or misguided or something.
We hope that that's a lively and
rich discussion about the paper
that's led by open-minded
people who are just
trying to arrive at the
best possible recommendation
for your paper.
That's what we hope at
this stage in the process.
And finally, at the very
end, the program committee
is going to do some magic to
arrive at the final program
based on all of this input.
Of course, their reviews and
ratings will be a major factor,
but there might be
other considerations
that they bring in at
this stage in terms
of constructing a diverse
and interesting program
for their conference.
At this stage, you
might get a meta review
that provides some insight
into the final decision making
process, although those
vary in the amount
that they actually illuminate
the behind-the-scenes process
that led to the particular
recommendation that
was made by the
reviewers and area chair.
In terms of the work that the
actual reviewers are doing,
I would say that the
current ACL set up
is oriented around structured
text for the reviews as opposed
to providing a lot of
metadata via ratings.
So first, they'll probably
be asked to just indicate
what the paper is about,
what contributions it makes,
and what its main strengths
and weaknesses are.
This is a kind of check
that they actually
understand what's in the paper
and can articulate what's
in the paper, and it
gives the first indication
of their assessment.
Next you have reasons to
accept and reasons to reject.
Then there could be a section
for additional questions
and feedback for the authors.
Maybe the reviewers can indicate
missing references and maybe
also a catchall
section for typos,
grammar, style, and presentation
improvements and so forth.
But of course, you get two
really important ratings--
the overall recommendation
and maybe an assessment
of the reviewer's confidence
in their overall evaluation.
And then finally, there
could be a section
for confidential information
that the reviewers want
to communicate directly
to the program committee.
That would be hidden
from the authors as well
as the other reviewers.
So stepping back, the
most important pieces
of this reviewing
form are obviously
the overall recommendation
must be balanced
against reviewer confidence
and the reasons to accept
and reasons to reject.
You can count on the two texts
that they supply under 2 and 3
here as being really important
to shaping the discussion that
happens and the overall
recommendation that gets made.
There's an author
response period
for at least the
major ACL conferences.
This is a chance for
authors to submit
short responses to the reviews.
This is a rather uncertain
business along many dimensions,
so let me just
offer some thoughts.
First, many people are
cynical about author responses
since they've observed
that reviewers rarely
change their scores
afterwards, and I
think that is an
important consideration.
However, it might just
be bad signaling not
to submit a response at all.
It could incidentally indicate
to the program committee
that you've kind of silently
opted out of the process,
so its mere absence
could reduce your chances
of getting accepted I believe.
More positively, for conferences
that have area chairs,
and I believe all of the current
major ACL conferences do,
the author response could
be really important.
An area chair is
someone who's tasked
with stimulating
discussion and writing
meta reviews for a small number
of papers-- maybe 5 to 20
depending on the
conference volume.
And for those people,
the author response
might have a major impact.
I played the role of
area chair many times,
and the author responses
are always valuable to me.
It's another text
alongside the reviews
that the reviewers
provided, and it
helps me understand places
of conflict, places where
the authors differ in their
perspective from the reviewers
and so forth.
It is always extremely
valuable evidence to me,
and I think that holds
for many area chairs.
And for this reason
alone, you might
think about submitting
a detailed author
response with these
area chairs in mind
as your primary readers.
NLP conferences,
for better or worse,
have very complex rules
about what you can and can't
say in these author responses.
Sometimes you can't
report any new results.
Sometimes you have to be very
circumspect about what kind
of results you
have and so forth.
If you have questions
about what you
can do in a particular
case, seek out
an expert at Stanford
for advice on how
to interpret the precise
rules and what kind of leeway
you actually have in saying what
you think is important to say.
I think all of
these restrictions
are kind of unfortunate.
When I play the
role of area chair
and as reviewer, I would
simply like to have access
to all the information
that I can possibly obtain,
and so I would like these
author responses to be offering
as much information as
they feel is important,
and then I can use that to
balance all the evidence
to make a final recommendation.
So it's unfortunate
from my perspective
that these have restrictions at
all, but they're often there,
and it's important to figure
out how to navigate them.
When you construct an author
response, always be polite.
You can be firm and
direct, but you'll
want to do that
strategically to signal
what you feel most strongly
about, but fundamentally,
you should never say
things like this--
"Your inattentiveness
is embarrassing.
Section 6 does what
you say we didn't do."
You might privately say
that to your co-authors
as a kind of cathartic
act of venting
about how bad your reviews
were, but you should never
put it in an author response.
Rather, you should do things
that are more like, "Thank you.
The information you're
requesting is in section 6.
We will make this more
prominent in our revision."
Fundamentally here,
I think it's just
important to be polite in
these professional contexts,
and it's a way to
remind yourself
that these reviewers did make
an investment of their own time
and intellectual
energy into your work,
and we want to be respectful
and aware of that investment
that they made.
Presentation types and venues.
There are lots of them.
So first, there's the
fundamental distinction.
You might have either oral
presentations or poster
presentations and
crosscutting that, you
might think about
submitting to a workshop
or to a main conference.
And here's a whole bunch of
venues, and what I've done here
is kind of organized
this in a soft way.
So on the left here, I have
NLP conferences and workshops.
I've put what we consider
the most prestigious three
at the top here--
ACL, NAACL, and EMNLP, and
then some other large ones
just below that.
Of course, the prestige
order could really
change here, so who knows what
the next year's will bring.
For example, the Asia
ACL is brand new,
and of course, the
number of people
doing outstanding work in
our area throughout Asia
is enormous, and so
it's very easy for me
to imagine that AACL becomes
at least as prominent,
maybe even more prominent,
than some of these other ones
up here over the next few years.
Then we have some smaller and
older conferences down here,
and then of course, at the
bottom, I've put workshops.
All of these major conferences
have workshop series attached
to them, and workshops can be
a great initial outlet for work
you do, especially for
a course like this.
So I would encourage you
for the major conferences
to scan their
program of workshops,
and if you find one
that's topically
aligned with what
you're working on,
consider submitting
to the workshop.
It will probably be
less competitive,
so you have better
chances of getting in,
but I would say the
more important thing
is that it's a chance for
you to actually connect
with a community of people
who are working on precisely
the topic that
you're working on,
and that can be intellectually
really exciting.
In the middle here, I have
some conferences that kind of
run the spectrum from
linguistics through the world
wide web, through knowledge
graphs and kind of more core
topics in the artificial
intelligence generally,
and those can be really
good outlets for work
that has an NLP aspect to it.
And then over here
on the right, these
are very prestigious machine
learning conferences,
and it's kind of the same story.
All of these
conferences here are
welcoming a work that involves
natural language processing,
but you might just have
to think about how you're
going to precisely connect
with these specific audiences
and their specific concerns.
Here's my personal assessment
of NLP reviewing at present.
First, I think the focus
on conference papers
as opposed to journals has
been really good for NLP.
It fits with and encourages the
very rapid pace of our field,
and I think we all benefit
from that rapid pace overall.
Before about 2010, the
reviewing in the field
was admirably good and
rigorous in comparison
with other fields.
It really was impressive
how many deep and insightful
reviews you would get
when you submitted
to one of the main
conferences in the field.
Lately though, the explosive
growth of the field
has, I think by consensus,
reduced the general quality
of reviewing, and the field
is still grappling with this.
Of course, there
was always a kind
of lottery aspect to whether
your paper would be accepted,
and you should keep
in mind that luck
is a real element in publication
and throughout science.
But that lottery aspect
has gotten more amplified
as the field has
grown, and that's
affecting the main
conferences in ways
that we all have to figure out.
But again, this
is kind of useful.
Keep in mind that a rejection
does not necessarily
mean that your work
was of low quality.
It could mean that you
just had really bad luck
throughout a kind of
chaotic reviewing process.
I also want to say
that I think it's
unhealthy to force every paper
to be four or eight pages.
The reason that
happens is that there
are two kinds of submissions
typically-- a short paper which
has max length four, and a
long paper which has max length
eight, and we all,
as submitters to one
or another of those
tracks, feel a kind
of signaling pressure to
maximize the available space.
So there are no six page
papers in the field,
and there is really no
room to have papers that
are longer than eight pages.
And that's unfortunate,
because sometimes you
just need a different
length than one of these
to express your ideas in
the best possible way.
So that's been unhealthy.
I will say, though, that
this is alleviated somewhat
by the increased use of
appendices and supplementary
materials to express a lot
of details that don't need
to be part of the
main narrative,
and that is in effect
here a back door
allowing papers to be
of more variable length.
The biggest failing to
my mind of the conference
reviewing process is that
there's no revise and resubmit.
That's the standard
we get from journals.
There's no chance for authors
to appeal to an editor
and interact with
an editor in a way
that you get from really
top quality journals.
And that just introduces
inefficiency into the system,
and it's a missed opportunity
for intellectual engagement
that could really
benefit the world.
I do want to say,
though, there's hope.
The Transactions
of the ACL or TACL
is a journal that follows
the standard ACL conference
model fairly closely but allows
for journal-style interaction
with an editor.
I'm conflicted here, because
I've been a TACL action
editor for a very
long time, but I
do that work because I
think TACL is wonderful.
It's allowing for the
best aspects of our field
in terms of fast pace,
while also introducing
some healthy aspects of the
journal reviewing process.
TACL papers are a little
bit longer at ten pages,
so there's still some of
this problematic influence
under four here, but at
least they are a bit longer.
And overall, I think it's just
a healthier rhythm for thinking
about evaluating work in
these scientific contexts,
so think about TACL as an
outlet for your work as well.
Let's focus on two
more specific topics
here and starting with titles.
And as I said before, a title
is an important ingredient
in the fate of your paper
in conference reviewing.
Jokey titles can
be risky, and I've
linked to some evidence for
that down here at this paper.
More importantly,
you might think
that it's important-- calibrate
the scope of your contribution
in your title.
It's a very common
complaint from reviewers
that the title is an overreach--
that it claims a broader
spectrum of the scientific
space than the paper actually
delivers on, and you
want to avoid that
by getting a tight alignment
between title and paper.
And then also consider
the kinds of reviewers
you're likely to attract
during that bidding process.
The choices you
make in your title
will definitely
influence that process,
and so you can again
think strategically
about who you want to pull
in as a reviewer because
of their interest and
expertise and so forth.
I would also say
that it's worthwhile
avoiding special fonts and
formatting if possible,
just because it makes it harder
to consistently reproduce
your title.
That said, I am kind
of charmed by the move
to have emoji in
titles recently.
Jokey is risky,
but this can be fun
and make your paper
a bit memorable,
even if it is harder
to copy and paste
the title in various contexts.
Abstracts-- abstracts are
also incredibly important,
because after the
title, they will
create this first and
lasting impression.
So here's a suggestion about
how to think about writing
abstracts-- the difficult form.
First, have your opening
be a broad overview--
a glimpse of the central
problem in its context.
Next, the middle takes
concepts mentioned
in the opening and
elaborates upon them,
probably by connecting
with specific experiments
and results from your paper.
And then finally,
at the very end,
establish links between
your proposal and broader
theoretical concerns so that
the reviewer on finishing
this abstract has an
answer to the question,
"Does the abstract offer
a substantial and original
proposal?"
So in a little more detail,
here's a kind of meta abstract.
"This opening sentence
situates you, dear reader.
Our approach seeks to address
the following central issue."
You spell it out.
"The techniques we
use are as follows."
And you spell it out.
"Our experiments are
these--" Details.
And then finally,
"Overall, we find
that our approach has
the following properties,
and the significance
of this is--"
And if you just fill in
all those ellipsis dots,
I think you're pretty close
to an effective abstract,
and that's at least a
starting point for you
when you think about maybe
being more creative and fitting
this better to the
specifics of your ideas.
Style sheets-- this is
small but important.
This is the way that you could
avoid the dreaded desk reject.
Pay close attention
to the details
of the style sheet
for your conference
and any other requirements
included in the call
for papers.
It is worth your while to
read those documents carefully
and make sure you've
checked all the boxes.
In NLP, infractions are the
most likely cause of the dreaded
desk reject-- that is
rejection without review, which
is of course so disheartening,
because you made
a big push to get
your paper submitted,
and then shortly
thereafter you get
this desk reject in the mail,
and there's no recourse.
That's pretty much the end
of the process for you,
and you can avoid
it by just attending
to what they've
said in their style
sheets and other guidelines.
And then finally, we
have this charming notion
of a camera-ready version.
This refers to
old-fashioned technology
for publishing papers
where you actually
needed to take
pictures of documents
in order to publish them.
Those days are long gone,
but the terminology remains.
For most NLP conferences,
as part of this
you get an additional
page upon acceptance.
This is presumably to respond
to requests made by reviewers.
Although in practice, you're
free to use the space however
you like.
In general, we find that
the extra page is mainly
used for fixing passages that we
made overly terse at reviewing
time in order to get
into the page limits,
and now, we're kind
of unpacking them
to make them more readable.
And this is obviously
an inefficient process,
but it's the reality at present.
You could, of course,
use your additional page
to improve your results
in all sorts of ways.
It's entirely up to you.
But a word of caution here, if
you have very substantially new
ideas and results,
it might be better
for you to save those for a
follow up paper as opposed
to trying to pack them into work
that's already been accepted,
right?
Instead of just making
more work for yourself
as part of this
first contribution,
it might be that you're
on the exciting path
toward a follow-up
contribution that's
going to be its
entirely own new paper.
So think about that and
balance these pressures.
And then good luck with your
camera-ready submissions.