SPEAKER 1 : Hello everyone.
This video is an
overview of homework 2,
which is on supervised
sentiment analysis.
And I would actually think
of it as an experiment
in cross domain
sentiment analysis.
Let's just walk
through this notebook,
and I'll try to give you
a feel for the problem
and our thinking behind it.
So the plot is the
usual one, we're
going to introduce a
task and associated data.
And help you with
setting up some baselines
and doing error analysis.
And that's all will lead into
these homework questions, which
are meant to help you explore
the data in meaningful ways.
And also set up some
additional baselines
that might inform ultimately
your original system,
which you then enter
into the bakeoff Best
overview we're doing ternary.
That is positive, negative,
neutral sentiment analysis,
and we're going to be
dealing with two data sets.
The Stanford sentiment treebank,
and a brand new assessment data
set that is a dev test
split of sentences
drawn from restaurant reviews.
We're giving you for
training the SST train set,
and asking you to evaluate
on the SST data test.
And also on this new data test
with the restaurant reviews.
And that's the cross
domain aspect of this.
You're completely
unconstrained about what
you do, in terms of bringing
in new data for training
and doing things in development.
The one constraint
that we really
need to firmly impose
here is that, of course,
the SST3 test set is
a public test set.
It's actually included in
your data distribution.
So that other notebooks can
run some baseline systems
and compare against
the literature.
But that test that is completely
off limits during development.
It's really important that you
do all your development just
on the dev splits.
And completely ignore the fact
that you have a label version
to the SST3 test set.
And as I say here, much of
the scientific integrity
of our field depends
on people adhering
to this honor code that is
doing no development on what
is test data.
Because test data is
our own only chance
to get a really
clear look at how
our systems are
generalizing to new examples
and new experiences.
So please keep that in mind
The rationale behind this
assignment of course,
is to help you get familiar
or re familiarize yourself
with core concepts and
supervise sentiment analysis.
And the associated life
cycle of developing systems
in this space.
Which involves writing
feature functions,
trying out model architectures,
hyper parameter tuning.
And also possibly
doing some comparisons
of models using
statistical tests
to try to get a sense for
how much meaningful progress
you're making as you iterate
on your system design.
And we're also trying to
push here in this notebook,
that error analysis
can be a powerful way
to help you find
problems in your system
and then address them.
One more methodological note,
as you'll see from this notebook
I'm encouraging you
to use functionality
in this sst.py module, which
is part of our course code
distribution.
You're not required to use it.
Really, only contract
we need to have with you
is that your original
system have a predict one
method that maps strings to
predictions very directly.
But other than that,
you're unconstrained.
I do want to say, though,
that I think SST. experiment
is a flexible framework for
doing lots of experiments
without writing a lot
of boilerplate code.
So it should, if
you get used to it,
be a powerful basis
for you for doing
a lot of experiments, which
I think is crucial to success
here.
We do some set up by loading
a bunch of libraries,
and get a pointer to the data.
And that brings us to
the training set here.
So this is going to load
independent data frame.
You can see that we've
got about 8,500 examples.
Do review the notebook
covering this data set here.
There are a bunch of other
options for this train reader.
In particular, you can decide
whether to keep or remove
duplicates, and
you can also decide
whether you want to train
on the label subtree
that the SST contains.
Which vastly increases the
amount of training data
you have.
Which will be very
compute intensive,
but it could be very productive.
It is also a point
to say again, that
are free to bring in
other training sets.
And in fact, it might be
very productive to bring
in the dinaset data set which
is covered in our screen test
through this unit.
That data set has
a lot of sentences
from restaurant reviews.
And it was also labeled in
exactly the same way, using
the same protocols as we're used
for creating the development
set of restaurant
reviews for this unit.
Which is importantly
different, I
think, from the protocols
that were used for the SST.
So, bringing in
more training data
could help you not only with
the cross domain problem,
but also with the
kind of label shift
that has probably
happened between SST
and these new development data
sets that we're introducing.
That does bring me
to the dev sets here.
So we have SST dev, that's
also PEMDAS data frame
as well as this new bakeoff
data of restaurant reviews.
Also PEMDAS data
frame and here you
can see just three
randomly chosen examples.
Example ID, the text
of the sentence,
a label which is either
positive, negative, or neutral.
And that is subtree
is always zero
because these assessment data
sets have only four examples.
No labeled subtrees the
way the SST train set does.
We can get a look at
the label distribution.
And I'll just mention that the
label distribution for the test
set is very similar.
It has one noteworthy
property, which
is that it's highly skewed.
A lot of neutral
examples which I think
is realistic for actual
data even review data,
and then there is a skewed
toward positivity with negative
the smallest.
And this kind of label
imbalance, I think
is severe enough, that it might
impact optimization choices
that you make.
This next section here just
sets up a softmax baseline.
We use a undergrounds
feature function.
This couldn't be simpler we're
just splitting on whitespace
and counting the
resulting tokens.
And then we have this
very thin wrapper
around logistic regression.
And those are the two pieces
that come together to run here
and that's SST Experiment.
A lot of information about
your experiment is stored
in this variable and
what's being printed out
is just a summary
classification report.
We have SST dev and bakeoff
dev as our two assessment
data frames.
The results for
each one of those
are printed separately here.
And then our bakeoff
metric is this mean
of the macro average F1 scores
across the two data sets.
Exactly these two but of
course, at the bake off time
we'll be using the test sets.
So you might be guided in sort
of hill climb on this number
here while also attending
to these two numbers, which
are contributing to it.
So for example, you can
see here that as expected
since we trained on the SST.
We're doing better
on the SST dev
by far than we are on
the new bakeoff data.
The next section here just shows
you another kind of baseline
and this is a deep learning
baseline in RNNClassifier.
Our future function
is very simple here
because we just
put on whitespace
and we rely on the RNN itself
to do all the featurization,
which is like an embedding
look up and then processing
the example.
So that's very simple.
And then the wrapper is
also very simple here.
We're going to
set the vocabulary
for the model, the main counter
two, that seems productive.
And then finally
run the experiment.
And the one thing that's
important here the one change,
is that you set vectorized
equals false here.
Unlike in the
previous baseline, we
are not using cycler
dict vectorized
to process count dictionaries to
get us from features to feature
matrices.
Here we are feeding
our examples directly
through into the model.
Our model expects token streams
with no messing about and so
vectorized false would give
them a pass through all
the way to the model.
So remember that otherwise
this will all fall apart.
But other than that, it's
exactly the same setup.
Let's run it here.
I've got some timing
information we're
going to fast forward
to this because this
takes a little bit of time.
But you'll see a report
and I'm currently
on just a very
old CPU based Mac.
So, this will give you a sense
for the cost of development
for deep learning.
In this space.
All right, our models at
least stopping criterion
was met after 49 epochs, and
here's our look at the results.
Which are kind of
comparable to what we
saw with the softmax baseline.
All right, and that
brings us to RNN
analysis, which can be an
important step in improving
your system.
I've written a
few functions that
make use of all the information
that is encoded in the return
values for SST experiment.
Which I hope package
together everything
you need to do RNN analysis,
reproduce your results,
and make use of your model
and downstream experiments.
Here we're going to use
this function find errors.
I've done a little bit of
pre-processing of the errors
that were found and
packaged them together.
And then this cell
here is just an example
of the kind of things
that you might do.
Here we're looking at cases
where the softmax model is
correct, the RNN was incorrect
and the correct label
is positive.
You could of course fiddle
with those parameters here.
We've got 168 examples
going into that class
and then we can look at a
sample of the actual text that
fall into that group,
as a way of figuring out
how these models differ
and maybe improving one
or both of them.
And that brings us to
the homework questions.
And again, these are meant
to help you explore the data
and set up some additional
baselines that inform
original system development.
We're going to start with
one that's data oriented.
I've called this token
level differences.
What I'm trying to do is
raise to your awareness
the fact that the SST data and
the new restaurant review data
are just encoded
in different ways
at the level of tokenization.
This is mainly the results
of the SST being kind
of the result of a
historical process,
beginning with pengelley
2005 and going on
through the SST project itself.
So there are some
funny things about it
that I think could certainly
affect any kind of transfer
from one domain to the other.
And since you are
training on SST data,
it's important to be aware of
how it might be idiosyncratic.
So that happens here, you write
this function get token counts
and as usual you have a
test, you pass the test,
you're in good shape.
Next question relates
to the cross domain
nature of our problem training
on some of the bakeoff data.
In the standard paradigm,
you are training on SST,
evaluating on SST and also
this new bakeoff data center
restaurant review sentences.
What would happen if you
augmented your training
set with a little bit of
data from the development
of restaurant review sentences?
You might have a hunch
that that's going
to improve system performance.
And this question
here simply asks
you to run such an experiment
as usually you have a test.
I think you will
find that this is
very productive in helping
your system get traction
on the new data.
And that should be
a clue as how to do
a really good job in the bakeoff
with your original system.
This next question here is
about, future representation.
A more powerful vector
averaging baseline.
This is a step
toward deep learning.
It builds on this section
of a notebook here,
where essentially
we average together
vector representations of words
to represent each example.
And those are the input to
a simple logistic regression
classifier.
So those are nice low
dimensional models
that tend to be quite powerful.
This question is asking you to
replace the logistic regression
with a shallow
neural classifier.
So maybe the more
powerful part here.
And also to explore a wide
range of hyper parameters
to that model to get a
sense for which settings
are best for our problem.
And that brings us
to BERT encoding.
And this is like
one step further
down the line toward deep
learning and fine tuning.
This question is simply asking
you to encode your examples
using BERT.
In particular, taking the
summary representation
above the class token,
the. final output there
as your summary representation
of the entire example.
And those become
presumably the inputs
to some downstream classifier
or potentially a fine tuning
process.
The idea that this is
like one step better
than the vector averaging
that we just looked at.
You do not need to conduct
an experiment with SST,
you're simply implementing
this feature function here.
But since SST experiment
does make it really easy
to run experiments once
you've implemented the feature
function, I would encourage
you to choose some classifier
model, and see how
well this does.
But as usual, you have a
test and the test is just
about the feature function.
And it will make sure you're
using all of these values
correctly.
And that brings us to
the original system.
And I just want to remind you
that you are unconstrained
except for the fact that you
cannot make any use of the SST
test set during development.
The labels for that
are off limits.
But everything
else is fair game.
Bringing new training data,
try new model architectures.
And so forth and so on.
We've given a few
ideas here but this
is by no means meant
to be restrictive.
It's just meant to get the
creative juices flowing.
Other than that, this is the
same procedure as homework 1,
we want a description of your
system to inform the teaching
team about what worked
and what didn't.
And it would be great if you
reported your pick score, which
is the macro average
of the two F1 macros
F1 scores for our two
data sets but it's
on the development set there.
And that brings
us to the bakeoff.
And again, the bakeoff
procedure is familiar.
The one piece here,
the crucial piece
is that you write up a function,
of predict one function that
maps the text directly
to a prediction using
your original system.
I've given two
examples here, yours
might be simpler depending on
whether or not you use the SST
experiment framework or not.
But that all comes together here
with great bakeoff submission
where you input that function.
won't need to change
this output file.
And you can see that this
function here loads in our two
test sets which are unlabeled.
And uses your
predict one function
on all of those examples here.
And then writes a file which you
then upload to the auto grader
to Gradescope.
That happens here.
So I just want to reiterate
that in all senses,
the test data labels are
completely off limits to us.
All the development conceptual
and otherwise should
happen on the development data.