CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Hello, everyone,
welcome to part 2 in our
series on supervised sentiment
analysis.
The screencast is going to focus
on some general practical tips
for doing work in this
space, especially focused
on setting up a
project and doing kind
of pre-processing of your data.
So first I just wanted
to give you links
to a whole bunch of benchmark
data sets in the space.
We're going to concentrate
on the SST and DynaSent,
but there are a lot
of other choices
you could make both for
developing original systems
and also supplementing
training data
that you've got for a
particular application.
Some of these data sets
are really, really large,
and they cover a
diversity of domains.
So these could be
important assets for you.
In a similar spirit, there
are lots of sentiment lexicons
out there.
They cover different
emotional dimensions
and different aspects
of the problem.
And they too could
be used to help you
with powerful featurization.
They could supplement
features that you've created
or help you group
your vocabulary
into interesting
subcategories that
would be powerful for making
sentiment predictions.
And these range from
simple word lists up
to highly structured
multi-dimensional lexicons.
Now for a first
pre-processing step,
I thought we would just talk a
little bit about tokenization
because I think that this can
be a definitional choice that
really affects
downstream success.
So just as a running
example here,
let's imagine we start
with this raw text, which
is a kind of imagined tweet.
We have an @ mention here.
And then you can see
that some of the markup
has gotten a little bit garbled.
We have an emoticon that
looks sort of obscured
and a link at the end.
I think as a very
preliminary step,
even before we
tokenize it, we might
want to isolate
some of that markup
and replace the HTML entities.
It's a pretty easy
thing that you
can do that could really
make a difference.
Now we've got an apostrophe.
We've got our emoticon intact.
And we still have the link
and other things in here.
So even before you
do that, you might
check to see whether a simple
replacement of the HTML
entities would make a
difference in your data.
Now we begin the
tokenization question.
And I think a good
baseline choice here
would be simply
whitespace tokenizing.
I think we're going
to split on whitespace
and treat all the resulting
strings as tokens.
So that would take our raw
text up here and split it up.
As you can see on these
independent lines,
this looks OK to me.
So we're going to have a
problem with our @ mention,
because it has this
colon on the end.
So we might miss the fact that
this is the actual @ mention.
The unigrams look OK, although
the date has been split apart.
We've preserved our hashtag.
We've got this token that
might appear only once even
though there's a clear
consistent signal there.
We do have our emoticon.
And our link is mostly
intact although this period
could be disruptive
if we actually
want to follow the link,
because it could still
go on onto the end of the URL.
Treebank tokenizing is another
very common scheme in NLP
I would say at this point
largely for historical reasons.
The way treebank tokenizing
works is it takes this raw text
and splits it up into a
whole lot of tokens, right?
In comparison with
whitespace, we
have a lot of
distinct pieces here.
And this really looks kind
of problematic, right?
So we have destroyed
our @ mention,
we don't have that
username anymore.
It does this interesting
thing with words like "can"
that they get split
apart into two tokens.
We've lost our date.
We have lost our hashtag.
This is possibly good.
So YAAAAAAY has been split up
according to its punctuation.
So we have now four
exclamation marks
separated out from
this word here.
But our emoticon
is completely lost
and our link has been
really destroyed.
So this looks problematic
from the point of view
of accurate featurization
and also doing things
with social media.
So that kind of
brings me to what
we might want from
what I've called
the sentiment-aware tokenizer.
We would like to isolate
emoticons clearly because they
can be really sentimentally--
We want to probably respect
Twitter and other domain
specific markup because that's
often the space in which--
our data come from,
the kind of place
we want to make predictions in.
In a similar spirit,
you might take
advantage of underlying markup.
Maybe don't filter off the
HTML, because there could
be an important signal there.
You might be aware that the
website or data producer might
have done some
pre-processing of their own
that might disrupt
things like curses which
could of course carry a
lot of important sentiment
information.
You might want to
preserve capitalization
because of course that
could be used for emphasis.
In a similar spirit,
you might want
to regularize emotive
lengthening like YAAAAAY down
to just three characters
here to capture
that it is an
emotive lengthening
but also regularize all
those distinct tokens.
And then there's a stretch goal.
Although this might be
less important in the era
of contextual models,
you might think
about capturing multiword
expressions that
carry sentiment.
Just think of an example
like "out of this world,"
which is positive.
But none of its component
pieces are positive.
So many models
will miss that that
is conveying clear
sentiment, whereas
with a clever
tokenization scheme,
you might capture that
as one single token.
So here's a simple example
that meets a lot of those goals
here for a
sentiment-aware tokenizer.
We begin from our
usual raw text.
We normalize and
preserve the @ mention.
We keep most of these words
intact and we kind of capture
that June 9 thing was a date.
Preserve the hashtag, of course.
We're treating all these
potentially emotion-laden
punctuation marks as
separate unigrams.
I think that could be good.
Of course capture the emoticon
and capture the link, right?
And if you want something
that meets more or less all
these criteria, except I
think the date normalization,
you could just use the
nltk TweetTokenizer.
It's a good simple
choice that you
could make that I think will be
useful for sentiment analysis.
And to quantify that
a little bit, here's
some experimental
evidence that I think
is going to be relevant
to the kind of work
that you all are doing.
So my data is OpenTable.
That's restaurant
review, short ones.
I've got 6,000 reviews
in my test set.
And what I'm doing
along the x-axis
here is varying the
amount of training data
that these systems can see.
It's simply a Softmax classifier
and my primary manipulation
is I have the sentiment-aware
tokenizer in orange,
treebank in green, and
whitespace in gray.
And the picture is pretty clear.
Right along the x-axis,
we have accuracy.
It's a balanced problem.
And what you can see is that
the sentiment-aware tokenizer
is the clear winner
here, especially where
training data are sparse.
In the limit of adding
lots of training data,
I think we can make up for a lot
of shortcomings of tokenizers
because we see a lot of
redundancy in the training
data.
But where data are sparse,
the sentiment-aware tokenizer
is clearly a good choice.
And another thing I would add
is that because it produces
more intuitive tokens,
the sentiment-aware models
might be more interpretable
in some sense.
And to really connect
with the homework
that you all are
doing in the bakeoff,
this is what happens when
we go across domains.
So here I'm training on
OpenTable restaurant reviews,
but I'm going to test on
movie review sentences here.
Otherwise, this is the
same experimental paradigm.
Because of the
cross domain thing,
the results are a
little bit more chaotic.
But I think, again, the
sentiment-aware tokenizer
is a clear winner with the
largest gains where training
data are a little bit sparse.
And that's the expected picture.
So be thoughtful
about tokenizing.
As a counterpoint to that,
I've called the section
on stemming the
dangers of stemming
because what I want to try
to do is convince you not
to stem your data, the
first word is stemming.
So stemming is a kind of
pre-processing technique
that would collapse
distinct word forms.
There are three common
algorithms for this.
Easy to use, the Porter stemmer.
The Lancaster stemmer,
and the WordNet stemmer.
And my criticisms
are largely leveled
at Porter and Lancaster.
Here is the bottom line.
In doing this kind
of stemming, you
are apt to destroy many
important sentiment
distinctions, making
this a counterproductive
pre-processing step.
On the other hand,
the WordNet stemmer
does not have this problem.
It's much more conservative,
but it also doesn't really
do enough to make it worthwhile.
It's costly to run and has some
requirements that might make it
simply not worth it.
And I would say that the
bottom line here for stemming
is that in an era where we have
very large sentiment data sets,
the function of
stemming would be
to collapse the size
of your vocabulary
and make learning more
easier in small domains,
but we mostly don't confront
that problem anymore.
But just to drive
home this point here,
here are some examples
focused on the Porter stemmer,
of cases where running
the Porter stemmer
actually collapses clear
sentiment distinctions
according to the
Harvard Inquirer, which
is one of those lexicons
I mentioned before.
I got defense and defensive.
They get collapsed down into
this funny, non-word defens.
Extravagance and extravagant,
different sentiment
collapsed down into this
word fragment, and so forth
for these other examples.
I think this is showing that
in pre-processing your data,
you might be removing some
important sentiment signals.
The Lancaster stemmer uses
a very similar strategy
and has arguably even more
problems in this space.
Here we've got the positive
word complement and complicate.
According to the
Harvard Inquirer again,
they could both
get collapsed down
into what is a completely
distinct word, comply.
That should be concerning
for many reasons.
And the other examples
make a very similar point.
The WordNet stemmer I mentioned
before, I think this actually
has something going for it.
There might be cases where
you'd want to use it.
It's high precision.
It requires word,
part of speech pairs.
And the general issue
is just that it removes
some comparative morphology.
That's the only thing you might
worry about for sentiment.
But otherwise it's going to
take like exclaims, explained,
and exclaiming, and
collapse them down.
That could be a
useful compression
of your feature space.
It will leave exclamation
alone, which I think is good.
Similarly for these
things, they all
get preserved across
the two verb forms
but we preserve the
adjective is different.
I think that could be good.
And as I said, the only concern
would be that happy, happier,
and happiest all go down
into their base form
whereas I think
these could encode
different gradations
of sentiment
that you might want to preserve.
That's worth some
thought, but overall I
think you probably want
to avoid doing stemming.
And to bring that
home, let's return
to my experimental
paradigm using
a Softmax classifier, OpenTable
reviews, 6,000 of them
in my test set, and
here along the x-axis,
I'm varying the amount
of training data I have.
And I think what you see is
that the Porter and Lancaster
stemmer in purple and
black respectively
are kind of forever behind,
right, versus just simply
sentiment-aware tokenizing.
It gives you a lead.
The lead is especially
clear as you
get out of this very
sparse domain here
with very few
training instances.
To close, just a few
other pre-processing
techniques that you
might think about.
So you could part-of-speech
tag your data
in the spirit of trying
to capture more sentiment
distinctions that you
might capture otherwise.
So just for example,
arrest, like
arresting as an adjective is
positive, but arrest as a verb
is typically negative.
Fine as an adjective
is positive,
but to incur a fine as a noun
is negative, and so forth.
You can see that some
sentiment distinctions actually
do turn on the part
of speech of the word.
So treating all of your unigram
features as based in word
part-of-speech tag pairs
could be useful for preserving
some of these distinctions.
Again as a pre-processing
step to help your model
be more attuned to these points
of variation in comparison.
But there are limits
even to this, right?
So there is just some
cases on the slides
where even within the
same part of speech,
we have an adjective that
in one sense is positive
and another negative.
For example, the adjective
mean can mean hateful,
but it can also mean excellent
as in they make a mean apple
pie.
Smart as an adjective could be
both painful and also bright
and brilliant, and
so forth like that.
And similarly for serious
and fantastic and sneer,
depending on the context and
the intention of the speaker,
they can kind of cut in
different directions.
So even part-of-speech
tagging is
going to be limiting when it
comes to really recovering
the underlying word
sense, even for something
as low dimensional as a
sentiment distinction.
Finally, this is another
powerful technique
that you might use
and think about
as you select and
evaluate different models.
This is what I've called
simple negation mark.
And the phenomenon
is just that if I
have a verb like enjoy, which
sounds positive in isolation,
of course its contribution
to the overall sentiment
will change depending
on whether it's
in the scope of a negation.
"I didn't enjoy" is negative.
A negation can be
expressed in many ways
as this modifier of
auxiliaries, like not.
But as an adverb like never,
it could be in the subject
like "No one."
And it could even be
really encoded for things
like "I have yet to enjoy it,"
which is a kind of negation.
And then of course the
negation in 5 here is very far.
"I don't think I will enjoy
it," is probably negative,
but the negation is way far away
from the verb that we want to--
with sentiment we want to
modulate with a negation.
So here's a very simple
method that I think was first
explored by Das and Chen.
It's also used in Pang et al.
These are classic early
sentiment analysis papers.
And the idea is simply to append
a _NEG suffix to every word
in the sequence that appears
between the negation and some
clause level mark
of punctuation,
to sort of roughly indicate the
semantic scope of the negation.
This is a simple pre-processing
step, highly heuristic.
It would take a sentence
like "No one enjoys it,"
and literally turn the
unigrams one, enjoys,
and it into variant
forms of them
where one has a NEG
appended to it, and so does
enjoys, and so does it.
And the idea is
that in doing this,
we're giving our
model the opportunity
to discover that enjoys in
this context is actually
a different token in some
sense than enjoys when it's not
in the scope of negation.
And for many of the
linear models with handout
features that we explore, simply
making that initial distinction
might create some
space for your model
to learn the
interaction of negation
with these other features.
And just to quantify it a little
bit by way of rounding this
out, I think this slide shows
the impact that this can
have despite its simplicity.
So similar, we have
OpenTable as our test set.
We're using a
Softmax classifier.
And the x-axis is again varying
the amount of training data
that we have.
The whitespace
tokenizer is in gray.
It's the worst, followed
by Treebank in green.
Then we have that
sentiment-aware tokenizer
in orange.
And then way above
them, consistently
for all parts of the data
here are sentiment-aware
plus that negation marking.
That is obviously
the superior model
for all kinds of amounts
of training data.
And I think what
that's showing is
that the influence of
negation is actually
really real and severe in a
lot of sentiment datasets.
It's just very common to
combine sentiment words,
positive or negative,
with negation
and it has this
predictable effect
of kind of flipping the value.
So in doing this sentiment, and
doing this negation marking,
we're giving our
model a better chance
at discovering exactly
those distinctions.
And here's a similar set
of results for cross-domain
where I'm starting on
OpenTable and testing on IMDB.
Again the results are a
little bit more chaotic,
but I think it's a clear win
for the sentiment-aware plus
negation marking model.