CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to part 5 in our
series on supervised sentiment
analysis.
The focus of this screencast
is on the module sst.py,
which is included in the
course code distribution.
It contains a
bunch of tools that
will let you work
fluidly, I hope,
with the Stanford
Sentiment Treebank
and conduct a lot of
experiments in service
of completing the homework and
also doing an original system
entry for the bake off.
Let's say that my goals for
the screencast are two-fold.
First, I do just want to get
you acquainted with this code
so that you can work with it on
the assignment in the bake off.
And in addition, I'd guess I'd
like to convey to you some best
practices around
setting up a code
infrastructure for
a project, say,
that will let you run
a lot of experiments
and really explore
the space of ideas
that you have without
introducing a lot of bugs
or writing a lot of extra code.
So let's begin.
We'll start with these
reader functions.
At the top in the
first cell here,
I just load in not
only OS so that we
can find our files,
but also sst which
is the module of interest.
We set up this variable here
that's a pointer to where
the data set itself lives.
And then this function,
sst.train_reader,
will let you load in a Pandas
data frame that contains
the train set for the sst.
You'll notice that there
are two optional keywords,
include_subtrees and dedup.
Dedup will remove
repeated examples,
and include_subtrees
is a flag that
will let you include
or exclude all
of the subtrees that
the sst contains.
By default, we'll include
just the full examples.
But if you said, include
subtrees equals true,
you get a much
larger data set as we
discussed in the screencast
on the sst itself.
In cell 4 here, I'm just giving
you a look at one random record
from this.
So remember, it is
a PANDAS data frame.
But we can get it as a
dictionary for a little bit
of an easier look.
We've got an example ID.
We have the text of the
sentence, the label,
which is either negative,
positive, or neutral.
And then is_subtree is
a flag on whether or not
it's a full root level example
or a subconstituent of such
an example.
Since we have loaded
this in with include
subtrees equals false, we get
this distribution of labels
here.
This is just a distribution of
labels on the full examples.
But of course, as we
change these flags,
we get very different
counts down here.
And then something comparable
happens with the dev reader--
dev_df from sst.dev_reader, with
a pointer to the home directory
for the data as before.
And here, the
subtree distinction
and the dedup distinction,
those are much less important
because these data sets consist
just of root level examples.
And there are very few,
if any, duplicate examples
in those data sets.
Now let's turn to
feature functions.
We'll begin to build up
a framework for doing
supervised sentiment analysis.
And the starting point
here is what I've
called the feature function.
It's given in two, unigrams_phi.
It takes in a text
that is a string.
And what it does is return a
dictionary that is essentially
a count dictionary over
the unigrams in that string
as given by this very simple
tokenization scheme, which
just down cases all
of the tokens and then
splits on whitespace.
So as an example text, if I
have "NLU is enlightening,"
space, and then an
exclamation mark,
and I call the feature
function on that string,
I get this count
dictionary here,
which is just giving
the number of times
each token appears
in that string
according to the
feature function.
I'd say it's really
important when you're
working with the standard
version of this framework
doing handbuilt feature
functions, that you just
abide by the contract that
all of these feature functions
take in strings and
return dictionaries,
mappings strings
to their counts.
Or if you want to, they're
Bools or floats or something
that we can make use of when
we're doing featurization.
The next step here is what
I've called a model wrapper.
And this is going to look
a little bit trivial here.
But as you'll see as we move
through more advanced methods
in this unit, especially
the next screencast,
it's really nice to
have these wrappers
around the normal, essentially
the fit function down here.
So I'm going to make use of
a scikit linear model called
LogisticRegression,
a very standard sort
of cross-entropy classifier.
I've called my function
fit_softmax_classifier.
And it takes in a supervised
data set, so a feature matrix
and a list of labels.
And I set up my model down here.
And I've used some of
the keyword parameters.
There are many more
for the scikit model.
And then the crucial thing
is that I call fit and return
the model, which is now
a trained model, trained
on this data set xy.
It might look like all I've
done is called fit on a model
that I set up.
But as you'll see, it's nice
to have a wrapper function so
that we can potentially
do a lot more as part
of this particular step in
our experimental workflow.
So now let's just bring
all those things together
into what is called
sst.experiment,
which is like one-stop shopping
for a complete experiment
in supervised
sentiment analysis.
So we load in these
two libraries.
We get a pointer to our dataset,
and then call sst.experiment.
The first argument
is the dataset
that it will be trained on.
So that's like
train_df from before.
We have a feature function
and a model wrapper.
And then these other
things are optional.
So if I leave
assess_dataframes as none,
then it will do a random
split on this train reader
according to train size.
If you do specify some data
frames here, a list of them,
then each one will be used
as a separate evaluation
against the model that you
train on this original data.
You can set the score
function if you want.
Our default is macro F1.
And then we'll return to
these two options later.
Verbose is just whether you
want to print some information.
And Vectorize is an option
that you can turn on and off.
And you'll probably
turn it off when
you do deep learning
experiments, which we'll
talk about later in the unit.
The result of all that
is a bunch of information
about your experiments
stored in this variable.
And because we had
verbose equals true,
you're going to report here.
And this is just a
first chance to call out
that throughout this
course, essentially, when
we do classifier experiments,
our primary metric is
going to be the macro
average F1 score.
This is useful for us
because it gives equal weight
to all the classes in our data,
regardless of their size, which
is typically reflecting
our value that we care even
about small classes.
We want to do well even on
the rare events in our space.
And it's also perfectly
balancing precision and recall
which is like a
good null hypothesis
if we're not told ahead of
time based on some other goal
whether we should favor
precision or recall.
So that all leads us to
kind of favor as a default
this macro average F1
score as an assessment
of how the model fit.
And here we've gotten 51.3.
The return value of
sst.experiment, as I said,
is a dictionary.
And it should package up for you
all the objects and information
you would need to test the
model, assess the model,
and do all kinds of
deep error analysis.
That is the philosophy here
that you should, if possible,
capture as much information as
you can about the experiment
that you ran in the
service of being
able to do subsequent downstream
analysis of what happened.
And so here I'm just
giving an example
that we've got the model, the
feature function, the train
dataset, whenever our
assess datasets were used.
And if that was a random
split of the train data,
that will be reflected
in these two variables.
The set of predictions
that you made
about each one of
the assess datasets,
the metrics you chose, and
the scores that you got.
And then if you do dive in,
like if you look at train set,
it's a standard data set.
x is your feature space.
y is your labels.
Vectorizer is something
that I'll return to.
That's an important part about
how the internal workings
of sst.experiment function.
And then you have the
raw examples in case
you need to do some really
serious human level error
analysis of the examples as
distinct from how they're
represented in
this feature space.
So here is just a slide that
brings all of those pieces
together.
This is one-stop shopping
for an entire experiment.
We loaded all our libraries.
We have our pointer to the data.
And then the ingredients are
really a feature function
and a model wrapper.
And that's all you need
in our default setting.
Point it to the train data
and it will do its job
and record all you would
want for this experiment,
I hope, in this
experiment variable here.
There's a final piece.
I want to return to
that vectorizer variable
that you saw in the return
values for sst.experiment.
And that is making use of
what in scikit-learn is
called the DictVectorizer.
And this is really nice
convenience function
for translating from human
representations of your data
into representations that
machine learning models like
to consume.
So let me just walk
through this example here.
I've loaded the DictVectorizer,
and I've got my train features
here in the mode that
I just showed you
where here we have two examples
and each one is represented
by our feature function
as a dictionary
that maps like words
into their counts.
It could be more
flexible than that,
but that's like the most
basic case that we consider.
And I set up my vectorizer in
3, and then I call fit_transform
on this list of dictionaries.
And the result here,
x_train, is a matrix,
where each of the
columns corresponds
to the keys in the dictionary
representing a unique feature.
And the values are, of
course, stored in that column.
So this feature
space here has been
turned into a matrix that
has two examples, 0 and 1.
There are a total of
three features represented
across our two
examples, A, B, and C.
And you can see that the
counts are stored here.
So example 0 has 1 for A
and 1 for B and 0 for C.
And example 1 has 0 for
A, 1 for B, and 2 for C.
So that's recorded
in the columns here.
You can, of course,
undertake this step by hand.
But it's a kind of
error-prone step.
And I'm just encouraging
you to use DictVectorizer
to handle it all and
essentially map you
from this, which is pretty
human interpretable, into this,
which is something your
models like to consume.
There's a second
advantage here, which
is that if you use
a DictVectorizer
and you need to now do
something at test time,
you can easily use
your vectorizer
to create feature spaces
that are harmonized
with what you saw in training.
So as an example,
if my test features
are another pair of examples
with a different character,
then I can call transform
on the original trained
vectorizer from up here.
And it will translate that
list of features into a matrix.
Now, the important thing
about what's happening here
is that it's going
to package the test
features into the
original training space
because, of course,
those are the features
that your model recognizes.
Those are the features
that you have weights
for if you've trained a model.
So it's important to call
transform at this space.
And as an indication of
one of the things that's
going to happen here is notice
that in the test features,
my second example has
a brand new feature D.
But D is not represented
in the training space.
We have no weights for it.
It's simply not part of that
original training data set.
And so the result is that
when we call transform,
that feature is
simply elided, which
is the desired behavior
as we're translating
from training into testing.
And notice that the
DictVectorizer has simply
handled that seamlessly
for you, provided
that you remember
at the second stage
not to call fit_transform.
That's the number one
gotcha for this interface
is that if you call
fit_transform a second time,
it will simply
change the feature
space into the one that is
represented in your test
features.
And then everything
will fall apart.
And your model, as
trained from before,
will be unable to consume
these new matrices
that you've created.
But provided you remember that
the rhythm is fit_transform
and then transform, this
should be really a nice set
of interfaces.
And of course, this
is what sst.experiment
is doing by default
under the hood for you.