CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome back, everyone.
This is part 8 in our series
on supervised sentiment
analysis, the final
screencast in the series.
We're going to be talking about
recurrent neural network or RNA
classifiers.
I suppose this is
officially our first step
into the world of deep learning
for sentiment analysis.
This slide gives an
overview of the model.
Let's work through
it in some detail.
So we've got a single
example with three tokens,
"the Rock rules."
These models are prepared for
variable length sequences.
But this example happens
to have like three.
And the first step to
get this model started
is a familiar one.
We're going to look up each
one of those tokens in what
is presumably a fixed
embedding space here.
So for each token, we'll
get a vector representation.
The next step is
that we have some
learned parameters,
a weight matrix, wxh.
And the subscript indicates that
we're going from the inputs x
into the hidden layer h.
So that's a first transformation
and that weight matrix
is used at each one
of these time steps.
There is a second
learned weight matrix
which I've called
whh to indicate
that we are now traveling
through the hidden layer.
And so we start at
some initial state
h0, which could be an all 0 or
a randomly initialized vector,
or a vector coming from some
other component in the model.
And that representation
is combined
with the representation that
we derive going vertically
up from the embedding, usually
in some additive fashion
to create this
hidden state here h1.
And those parameters
whh are used again
at each one of these time steps.
So that we have two learned
weight matrices as part
of the core structure
of this model,
the one that takes
us from embeddings
into the hidden
layer and the one
that travels us across
the hidden layer.
And again, those are
typically combined
in some additive
fashion to create
these internal hidden
representations.
Now we can do anything we want
with those internal hidden
representations.
When we use RNNs
as classifiers, we
do what is arguably the
simplest thing, which
is take the final representation
and use that as the input
to a standard
softmax classifier.
So from the point of view
of h3 going to y here,
we just have a learned weight
matrix for the classifier,
maybe also a bias term.
But from this point here, this
is really just a classifier
of the sort we've
been studying up
until this point in the unit.
But of course, we could
elaborate this model
in all sorts of ways.
It could run bidirectionally.
We could make more full
use of the different hidden
representations here.
But in the simplest
mode, our RNN classifiers
will just derive
hidden representations
at each time step
and use the final one
as the input to a classifier.
Couple of things I would
say about this first,
if you would like.
A further layer of detail on
how these models are structured
and optimized, I encourage
you to look at this pure NumPy
reference implementation
of an RNN classifier
that is included in our
course code distribution.
I think that's a
great way to get
a feel for the recursive
process of computing
through full sequences and then
having the error signals back
propagate through to
update the weight matrix.
But for now, I think
just understanding
the core structure of
this model is sufficient.
I just want to remind you
from the previous screencast,
that we're very close to
the idea of distributed
representations of features
that I introduced before.
Recall that for this
mode, what we do
is look up each token
in an embedding space,
just as we do for the RNN.
But instead of learning
some complicated combination
function with a bunch
of learned parameters,
we simply combine them
via sum or average.
And that's the basis.
That's the input to
the classifier here.
The RNN can be considered an
elaboration of that because
instead of assuming
that these vectors here
will be combined in some
simple way like sum or mean,
we now have really
vast capacity to learn
a much more complicated
way of combining them
that is optimal with
respect to the classifier
that we're trying to fit.
But fundamentally, these
are very similar ideas.
And if it happened that sum
or mean as in this picture
was exactly the right function
to learn for your data,
then the RNN would certainly
have the capacity to do that.
We just tend to favor the
RNN because it can learn,
of course, a much wider range
of complicated custom functions
that are particular to the
problem that you've posed.
Now so far, we've been
operating in a mode which
I've called standard RNN
data set preparation.
Let's linger over that in
a little bit of detail.
Suppose that we have
two examples containing
the tokens a, b, a and b, c.
Those are our two raw inputs.
The first step in
the standard mode
is to look up each one of
those in some list of indices.
And then those indices are
keyed into an embedding space.
And those finally give us
the vector representations
of each examples.
So that really and truly,
the inputs of the RNN
is a list of vectors.
It's just that we typically
obtain those vectors
by looking them up in a
fixed embedding space.
And so for example,
since a occurs twice
in this first example,
it is literally
repeated as the first
and third vectors here.
Now I think you can see
latent in this picture
the possibility
that we might drop
the embedding space and
instead just directly
input lists of vectors.
And that is one way
that we will explore
later on in the quarter of using
contextual models like BERT.
We would simply look
up entire token streams
and get back lists of vectors
and use those as fixed inputs
to a model like an RNN.
And that's a first step toward
fine-tuning models like BERT
on problems like the ones
we've posed in this unit.
So have that idea in
mind as we talk next
about fine-tuning strategies.
Now another practical note.
What I've shown you so
far is what you would
call a simple vanilla RNN.
LSTMs, Long Short
Term Memory networks
are much more powerful models.
And we'll kind of default to
them when we do experiments.
The fundamental issue
is that plain RNNs
tend to perform poorly
with very long sequences.
You get that error signal
from the classifier
there at the final token.
But now information has to
flow all the way back down
through the network.
Could be a very long sequence.
And the result is
that the information
coming from that error signal
is often lost or distorted.
Now LSTM cells are a prominent
response to this problem.
They introduce mechanisms that
control the flow of information
and help you avoid the
problems of optimization
that arise for regular RNNs.
Now I'm not going to
take the time here
to review this
mechanism in detail.
I would instead recommend
these two excellent blog
posts that have great
diagrams and really
detailed discussions.
They can do a much
better job than I
can at really conveying the
intuitions visually and also
with math.
And I think you could
pick one or both
and really pretty quickly gain a
deep understanding of precisely
how LSTM cells are functioning.
The final thing
here is just a code
snippet to show
you how easy it is
to use our course
code repository
to fit models like this.
In the context of
sentiment analysis,
you can again make use
of this sst library.
And what I've done
here is a kind
of complicated
version showing you
a bunch of different features.
So in cell 2, you can
see that I'm going
to have a pointer to GloVe.
And I'm going to create
a GloVe lookup using
the 50 dimensional vectors
just to keep things simple.
The feature function
for this model
is not one that returns
count dictionaries.
It's important for the
structure of the model
we're going to use that you
input raw sequences of tokens.
So all we're doing here is
down casing the sequence
and then splitting
on whitespace.
Of course, you could do
something more sophisticated.
The idea, though, is that you
want to align with the GloVe
vocabulary.
Our model wrapper is
doing a few things.
It's creating a vocabulary
and loading it and embedding
using this GloVe space.
That'll be the initial
embedding for our model.
And if you leave
this step out, you'll
have a randomly
initialized embedding space
which might be fine as well.
But presumably GloVe
will give us a step up.
And then we set up the
Torch RNN classifier.
And what I've done
here is expose
a lot of the different keyword
arguments, not all of them.
There are lots of knobs
that you can fiddle with,
as is typical for
deep learning models.
Maybe the one I
would call out is
that we are using
that fixed embedding
that we got from GloVe.
And I have set
early_stopping equals true,
which might help you efficiently
optimize these models.
Otherwise, you'll
have to figure out
how many iterations you
actually want it to run for.
And you might run it for much
too long or much less time
than is needed to
get an optimal model.
The early stopping
options, and there
are a few other parameters
involved in that,
might help you
optimize these models
efficiently and effectively.
In the end though, having
set up all that stuff,
you call fit as usual and
return the trained model.
And in that context, you can
simply use sst.experiment
with these previous components
to conduct experiments
with RNNs, just as you did
for simpler linear models
as in previous screencasts.
The one change which
will be familiar
from the previous
screencast, is that you need
to set vectorize equals false.
And that is important
because, again, we're
going to let the model
process these examples.
We don't want to pipe
everything through some kind
of DictVectorizer.
That's strictly for
handbuilt feature functions
and sparse linear models.
Here in the land
of deep learning,
vectorize equals false.
And we'll use the
components of the model
to represent each example
as I discussed before.