CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is part three in our
series on contextual word
representations.
We're going to be talking
about the BERT model.
Which is an innovative
and powerful application
of the transformer
architecture which we covered
in the previous screencast.
Let's dive into the core
model structure of BERT.
We'll begin with the inputs.
As usual we'll work with a
simple example; "the Rock
rules" that has three tokens.
But you'll notice
that for BERT, we
begin every sequence with
the designated class token.
And sequences end with
a designated SEP token.
And the SEP token
can also be used
as a boundary marker between
sub-parts of an input sequence.
We'll learn
positional embeddings
for each one of those tokens.
And in addition, as you
can see in maroon here,
we're going to learn a
second notion of position.
It sent A for all
of these tokens,
so it won't contribute
in this particular case.
But if we had a problem like
natural language inference
where examples
consist of a premise
sentence and a
hypothesis sentence,
we could learn
separate embeddings
for the premise
and the hypothesis.
And thereby hope that we can
capture that second notion
of position within our input.
We're going to have
learned embeddings
for each one of these
notions for the word
and the two notions of position.
And as in the transformer,
the actual embeddings
given here in light green
will be additive combinations
of those three learned
embedding representations.
From there we just do a lot
of work with the transformer.
Have we have had repeated
transformer blocks,
it could be 12, it could be
24, it could be even more.
And the output of all of those
transformer blocks in the end
is a sequence of
output representations.
These are vectors, and I've
given that in dark green.
That is the core model
structure for BERT.
And that brings us to how
this model is trained.
The masked language
modeling objective
is the fundamental training
objective for this model.
Fundamentally, what the
model is trying to do
is work as an auto-encoder
and reproduce the entire input
sequences.
To make that problem
non-trivial though,
we're going to employ this
masked language modeling idea.
And what that
means is that we're
going to go through
these input sequences,
and randomly replace some
small percentage, 10% to 15%
of the input tokens, with
this designated mask token.
And then the job of
the model is to learn,
for those masked inputs
to reconstruct what
was the actual input, right?
So in this case, we masked out
rules and the job of the model
is to use this bidirectional
context, that's
flowing in from all those
attention mechanisms
to figure out that
"rules" was actually
the token that belonged
to that initial position.
The BERT team did
a variant of this
as well, which is
masking by a random word.
So in this case, we
might replace "rules"
with a word like "every" picked
randomly from our vocabulary.
But there again, the
fundamental job of the model
is to learn to figure out that
"rules" was the actual token
in that position.
So it's going to make some
prediction in this case.
If it's different from
"rules," then the error signal
will flow back down through all
the parameters of this model.
Affecting, we hope,
all the representations
because of that dense thicket
of attention connections
that exists across
these timesteps.
And in that way the model
will learn to update itself,
effectively learning how
to reconstruct the missing
pieces from these inputs that
we created during training.
So let's dive into that masked
language modeling objective,
a little more deeply.
For transformer
parameters H theta,
and some sequence of tokens x,
with its corresponding masked
version x hat.
This is the objective here.
Well, let's zoom in
on some timestep t.
The fundamental scoring
thing is that we're
going to look up the
vector representation
and the embedding
for that timestep t.
And we'll take the dot product
of that with the output
representation at time t, from
the entire transformer model.
That much there, that
scoring procedure
looks a lot like what you
get from conditional language
models.
You just have to remember that
because of all those attention
mechanisms, connecting every
token to every other token.
This is not just the preceding
context before timestep t,
but rather the
entire surrounding
context for this position.
And then as usual we
normalize that by considering
all the alternative
tokens x prime,
that could be in this position.
Now, you'll notice over here
there's an indicator variable
mt, mt is 1 if token
t was masked, else 0.
So that's like saying we're
going to turn on this loss,
only for the tokens
that we have masked out.
And then the final thing is kind
of not a definitional choice
about this model, but
something worth noting.
You'll see that we're using
the embedding for this token,
effectively as the
softmax parameters.
There could be
separate parameters
here that we learn for the
classifier part, that's
learning to be a language model.
But I think people
have found over time,
that by tying these
parameters, by using
the transpose of
these parameters
to create the output space, we
get some statistical strength
and more efficient learning.
There is a second
objective in the BERT model
and it is the binary next
sentence prediction task.
And I think this was
an attempt to find
some coherence beyond just the
simple sentence or sequence
level.
So this is pretty
straightforward.
For positive instances
for this class,
we're going to take actual
sequences of sentences
in the corpus that we're
using for training.
So here you can see these
actually occur together,
and they are labeled as next.
And for negative examples
we just randomly choose
the second sentence, and
label that as not next.
And I think the
aspiration here was
that this would help the model
learn some notion of discourse
coherence beyond
the local coherence
of individual sequences.
Now what you probably want
to do with the BERT model
is not train it from scratch,
but rather fine tune it
on a particular
task that you have.
There are many modes that you
can think about for doing this.
Kind of default choice, the
standard and simple choice,
would be to use the class token.
More specifically, its
output in the final layer
of the BERT model, as the basis
for setting some task specific
parameters.
And then using that,
whatever labels
you have for
supervision up here.
And that could be effective
because the class token appears
in this position in every
single one of these sequences.
And so you might think of it as
a good summary representation
of the entire sequence.
And then when you
do the fine tuning,
you'll of course be updating
these task parameters.
And then you could,
if you wanted to,
also update some or all
of the actual parameters
from the pre-trained model.
And that would be a true
notion of fine tuning.
Now you might worry
that the class
token is an insufficient
summary of the entire sequence.
And so you could of course think
about pooling all the output
states in the sequence.
Via some function like
sum, or mean, or max,
and using those as
the input to whatever
task-specific parameters
you have up here at the top.
I just want to remind us
that tokenization in BERT
is a little unusual.
We've covered this
a few times before,
but just remember that we're
getting effectively not
full words, but word pieces.
So for cases like
"encode me", you
can see that the word
"encode" has been split apart
into two word pieces.
And we're hoping,
implicitly, that the model
can learn that that is in
some deep sense still a word.
Even though it has been
split apart and that
should draw on the
truly contextual nature
of these models.
The BERT team did two
initial model releases.
BERT base consists of
12 transformer layers
and has representations of
dimension 768 with 12 attention
heads for a total of
110 million parameters.
That's of course,
a very large model,
but this is manageable
for you to do local work.
Especially if you just want
to do some simple fine tuning,
or use this model for inference.
The BERT large release is
much larger, it has 24 layers.
Twice the dimensionality
for its representations,
and 16 attention
heads for a total
of 340 million parameters.
This is large
enough that it might
be difficult to do
local work with.
But of course you might get
much more representational power
from using it.
For both of these models,
we have a limitation
to 512 tokens.
And that is because
that is the size
of the positional embedding
space that they learned.
There are many new
releases of course.
You can find those
at the project site
and Hugging Face has
made it very easy
to access these models, and
that's been very empowering.
To close this let me just
mention a few known limitations
of BERT that we're
going to return
to as we go through
some subsequent models
for this unit.
So first in the
original paper, there
is a large, but still partial
number of ablation studies
and optimization studies.
There's a huge landscape
that's in play here,
and only small parts of it are
explored in the original paper.
So we might worry that there
are better choices we could
be making within this space.
The original paper
also points out
that there's some unnaturalness
about this MASK token.
They say, the first downside
of the MLM objective
is that we are
creating a mismatch
between pre-training
and fine tuning,
because the MASK token is
never seen during fine tuning.
So that's something we
might want to address.
They also point out
that there's a downside
to using the MLM objective
which is to say that it's
kind of data inefficient.
We can only mask out a small
percentage of the tokens.
Because we need the
surrounding context
that would ostensibly
reproduce those tokens.
And that means that it's
kind of data inefficient.
And finally this is
from the XLNet paper,
I think this is
quite perceptive.
BERT assumes that
the predicted tokens
are independent of each other
given the unmasked tokens,
which is oversimplified
as high-order,
long-range dependency is
prevalent in natural language.
What they have in mind
here, is essentially,
if you have an idiom
like "Out of this world"
and it happens that both
the first and the last words
in that idiom are
masked out, then
BERT is going to try to
reproduce them as though they
were independent of each other.
And in fact, we know that there
is a statistical dependency
between them coming
from the fact
that they are participating
in this idiom.
So there's some notion of
representational coherence
that BERT is simply
not capturing
with its MLM objective.