CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome back, everyone.
This is part four in our
series on Contextual Word
Representations.
We are going to be talking
about a robustly optimized BERT
approach a.k.a.
RoBERTa.
So recall that I finished the
BERT screencast by listing out
some known limitations of
the BERT model, most of which
were identified by the original
BERT authors themselves.
And top of the list
was simply that,
although the original
BERT paper does
a good job of exploring
ablations of their system
and different
optimization choices.
There's a very large landscape
of ideas here, and most of it
was left unexplored
in the original paper.
Essentially, what
the RoBERTa team did
is explore more
widely in this space.
That is the robustly
optimized part of RoBERTa.
So what I've done
for this slide here
is list out what I take to
be the central differences
between BERT and RoBERTa.
And I'll follow this up with
some evidence from the RoBERTa
paper in a second.
But first let's go through the
central differences beginning
with this question of static
versus dynamic masking.
So for the original
BERT paper what they did
is create four copies
of their dataset,
each with different masking.
And then those four copies
were used repeatedly
through epochs of training.
The RoBERTa team
had the intuition
that it would be useful
to inject some diversity
into this training process.
So they went to the other
extreme, dynamic masking.
Every single example when
it's presented to the model
is masked a potentially
different way,
via some random function.
There are also differences
in how examples
are presented to the models.
So BERT presented two
concatenated document segments.
This was crucial to its next
sentence prediction task.
Whereas for RoBERTa
we're just going
to have sentence
sequences, that is
pairs, that may even
span document boundaries.
Relatedly whereas BERT had,
as one of its central pieces,
this next sentence
prediction task.
RoBERTa simply drops that as
part of the objective here.
That simplifies the
presentation of examples
and also simplifies
the modeling objective.
Now, RoBERTa is simply using
a masked language modeling
objective.
There are also changes to the
size of the training batches.
So for BERT that batch
size was 256 examples.
RoBERTa cranked out
all the way up to 2000.
There are differences when
it comes to tokenization.
So as we've seen BERT used this
very interesting word piece
tokenization approach which
mixes some sub-word pieces
with some whole words.
RoBERTa simplified that down to
just character-level byte-pair
encoding which I think leads
to many more word pieces
intuitively.
There are also differences
in how the model was trained.
So BERT trained on a substantial
corpus, the BooksCorpus
plus English Wikipedia,
is a lot of data indeed.
RoBERTa again cranked
that up even further,
they trained on the
BooksCorpus, the CC-News corpus,
the OpenWebText
corpus and the Stories
corpus, a substantial increase
in the amount of training data.
There are also differences in
the number of training steps,
and there's a subtlety here.
So for the BERT model,
it was originally
trained on 1 million steps.
The RoBERTa model was
trained on 500,000 steps.
Which sounds like fewer
steps, but overall this
is substantially more
training, in virtue of the fact
that the training batch sizes
are so much larger for RoBERTa
than they are for BERT.
And finally, the
original BERT authors
had an intuition that
would be useful in getting
the optimization process
going, to train just
on short sequences first.
The RoBERTa team
dropped that idea,
and they train on
full length sequences
throughout the life
cycle of optimization.
There are some
additional differences
related to the optimizer
and the data presentation.
I'm going to set
those aside, if you
want the details I refer to
section 3.1 of the RoBERTa
paper.
So let's look at a
little bit of evidence
for these various
choices, starting
with that question of dynamic
versus static masking.
So this is the primary evidence,
they're using three benchmarks.
SQuAD, MNLI and
SST-2, and you can
see that more or less across
the board dynamic masking
is better.
Not by a lot, but
dynamic masking also
has going for this intuition
that BERT is kind of data
inefficient, we can only mask
out a small number of tokens.
And it seems like it ought
to be useful to inject
a lot of diversity into that, so
that a lot of different tokens
get masked, as we go through
the training process.
But the choice is of course,
supported numerically here,
I think pretty substantially.
This slide table here
summarizes the choice
about how to present the
examples to the model.
And this is also a little
bit subtle, so numerically
the DOC-SENTENCES
approach was best.
And this was an approach where
they just took contiguous
sentences from within documents
and treated a document boundary
as a kind of hard boundary.
That's numerically
better, according
to the benchmark results.
But they actually decided to
go with the FULL-SENTENCES
approach.
And the reason for that is,
in not respecting document
boundaries, it is easier
to create lots of batches
of exactly the same size.
Which leads to
all sorts of gains
when you think about optimizing
a large model like this.
So basically, they decided
that those gains offset
the slightly lower performance
of FULL-SENTENCES as
compared to
DOC-SENTENCES, and that's
why this became their
central approach.
Here's the summary of
evidence for choosing 2K
as the batch size.
You can see that they chose 256,
which was the BERT original.
2K and 8K and 2K looks
like the sweet spot
according to MLNI, SST-2.
And this kind of
pseudo perplexity
value that you get out of
bidirectional models like BERT
and RoBERTa.
So that's a clear argument.
And then finally, when we come
to just the amount of training
that we do.
The lesson here apparently
is more is better.
On the top of this table
here we have some comparisons
within the RoBERTa model,
pointing to 500K as the best.
And I would just
remind you that, that
is overall substantially
more training.
Than was done in 1
million steps with BERT,
in virtue of the fact that
our batch sizes for RoBERTa
are so much larger.
In closing, I just want to say
that RoBERTa too only explored
a small part of the
potential design choices
that we could make in
this large landscape.
If you would like to hear
even more about what we know
and what we think we know about
models like BERT and RoBERTa,
I highly recommend this paper
called The Primer in BERTology,
which has lots of
additional wisdom,
and insights, and ideas
about these models.