CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone
to part 3 in our series
on grounded language
understanding.
Recall that in
part 2, we focused
on speakers, speakers
in our sense,
taking on linguistic
representations as inputs
and generate language
on that basis.
Listeners are the
converse of that.
They accept linguistic inputs.
And try to make a
guess about the state
of the world on the basis
of that linguistic input.
For this unit, in
terms of modeling,
our focus is going
to be on speakers.
But I think it's helpful to
have the listener perspective
in mind as you create speakers.
And you might even bring
in the listener perspective
as part of your original system.
And I'll cover some
techniques for doing
that in the context of
the rational SpeechX model
a bit later in this series.
Now to make the speaker
task meaningful,
we need to complicate our
previous task a little bit.
So in part 2, we had for the
speaker, just a single colors
input.
And their task was to produce
a description on that basis.
For listeners,
we're going to move
to a more complicated task.
And this is the task that's
our focus for the entire unit.
It comes from the Stanford
colors in context corpus.
And for that corpus,
the context is not just
a single color representation,
but now three colors.
And the idea is that the
speaker is privately told which
of those three is their target.
And they produce a description
that will hopefully
communicate to a listener, who's
looking at those same three
colors, which one was
the speaker's target.
You can see that gets really
interesting and grounded
very quickly.
So in this first case, the
three colors are very different.
And the speaker
simply said blue.
And that seems to
get the job done.
And I think a listener
receiving blue as input
would know which of
these three colors
was the speaker's
private target.
When we move to
the second context,
we have two competing blues.
They're very similar.
And as a result, the speaker
said the darker blue one.
And the idea is that this
comparative here, darker blue,
is making the
implicit reference,
not only to the target
but to at least one
of the two distractors.
Third example is similar.
Teal, not the two
that are more green.
That's really grounded
in the full context here.
The speaker is not
only identifying
properties of the
target but also
properties of the distractor
in order to draw out contrasts.
And I think the final
two examples here are
interesting in different ways.
So here we have the
target on the left.
In the first example,
the speaker said purple.
And in the second
example, the speaker
said blue even though these
are identical colors here
for the targets.
The reason we saw a variation
is because the distractors
are so different.
And that just shows you
that even though this
is a simple task,
it is meaningfully
grounded in the full context
that we're talking about.
Now what we'll do for our
listeners is essentially
give them these
utterances as inputs
and have them function
as classifiers,
making a guess about
which of the three colors
is the most likely, that the
speaker was trying to refer to.
So in a little more detail.
Here's the neural
listener model.
It's again, an
encoder-decoder architecture.
For the encoder side, we can
imagine some recurrent neural
network or something
that is going
to consume a sequence
of tokens, look them up
in an embedding
space and then have
some sequence of hidden states.
For the decoder, the handoff
happens for the final encoder
state, presumably.
And what we're going to do here
is extract some statistics,
in this case, a mean
and covariance matrix,
and use those for scoring.
So in a little more detail.
We have those three colors
that's given for the listener.
Those are represented down here.
When we embed those
in some color space,
we could use the
Fourier transform,
just like we did
for the speakers
at the end of the
previous screen test.
And then we'll use those extract
statistics from the encoder
to create a scoring function.
And then we just need to
define a softmax classifier
on top of those scores.
And it will be that module
that makes it guess,
based on this encoder
representation, about which
of the three colors the
speaker was referring
to, so fundamentally, a kind
of classification decision
in this continuous space
of colors and encoder
representations.
Now once we start
thinking in this mode,
I think a lot of
other tasks can be
thought of as listener-based
communication tasks.
So even the simplest classifiers
are listeners in our sense.
They consume language.
And they make an
inference about the world,
usually in a very
structured space, right?
So even in the simple case
of our sentiment analysis,
you receive a linguistic
input, and you
make a guess about whether the
state is positive, negative,
or neutral as its
common classifier.
But thinking of it as
a communication task
might bring new
dimensions to the problem.
Semantic parsers are
also complex listeners.
They consume language.
They create a rich,
latent representations
out of logical form.
And then they predict into
some structured prediction
space like a database
or something like that.
Scene generation is clearly
a kind of listener task.
In this task, you
map from language
to structured representations
of visual scenes.
So it's a very complicated
version of our simple color
reference problem.
Young et al explored
the idea that we
might learn visual denotations
for linguistic expressions,
mapping from language into
some highly structured space
similar to same description.
Mei et al, 2015,
developed a sequence
to sequence model that's
very much like the above.
But the idea is that instead
of having simple output spaces,
we have entire
navigational instructions
that we want to get.
So that's going from
a linguistic input
into some kind of
action sequence.
And finally, the
CerealBar data set
is an interesting one to
explore in our context.
That was a task of learning
to execute full instructions.
So that's, again, mapping some
pretty complicated utterances
into some embedded
action that you
want to take in a game world.
And that could be a very
exciting extension of what
we've just been covering.