CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is part 5 in our series
on natural language inference.
We're going to be talking
about attention mechanisms.
Attention was an important
source of innovation in the NLI
literature, and, of
course, it's only
grown in prominence since then.
Let's begin with
some guiding ideas.
In the context of
the NLI problem,
we might have an intuition that
we just need more connections
for a lot of our architectures
between the premise
and hypothesis, right?
Possibly, in processing
the hypothesis,
we just need the model to
have some reminders about what
the premise actually contained.
And whatever summary
representation we have
of that premise
might just not be
enough from the point of view
of processing the hypothesis
and feeding the representation
into the classifier layer.
Relatedly, there's a persistent
intuition in the NLI literature
that it's useful to softly align
the premise and the hypothesis
to find corresponding words
and phrases between those two
texts.
It can be difficult to do
that at a mechanical level,
but attention
mechanisms might allow
us, via our data-driven
learning process,
to find soft connections in
the weights for these attention
layers between the
premise and hypothesis
and achieve some of the
effects that we would get
from a real alignment process.
So let's begin with
global attention.
This is the simplest
attention mechanism
that you see in
the NLI literature,
but it's already quite powerful.
And as you'll see, it has deep
connections with the attention
mechanisms in the transformer.
So to make this concrete, let's
start with a simple example.
We have "every dog
danced" as our premise,
"some poodle danced"
as our hypothesis,
and they're fit together into
this chained RNN model for NLI.
Now, standardly,
what we would do
is take this final
representation, hC,
as the summary representation
for the entire sequence
and feed that directly
into the classifier.
What we're going to do when
we add attention mechanisms is
instead offer some connections
back from this state
into the premise states.
The way that
process gets started
is via a series of dot products.
So we're going to take
our target vector,
hC, and take its dot
product with each one
of the hidden representations
corresponding to tokens
in the premise.
And that gives us this vector
of unnormalized scores,
just the dot products.
And it's common,
then, to softmax
normalize those scores into
our attention weights, alpha.
What we do with alpha is then
create our context vector,
and the way that
happens is that we're
going to get a weighted view
of all those premise states.
Each one-- h1, h2, and h3--
is weighted by its corresponding
attention weight, which
is capturing its kind
of unnormalized notion
of similarity with
our target vector hC.
And then to get a fixed
dimensional version of that,
we take the mean-- or
it could be the sum--
of all of those weighted
views of the premise.
Next, we get our attention
combination layer,
and there are various
ways to do this.
One simple one would be to
simply concatenate our context
vector with our
original context--
target vector hC and feed those
through a kind of dense layer
of learned parameters.
Another perspective,
kind of similar,
is to give the context
vector and our target vector
hC, each one their
own weights, and have
an additive combination
of those two,
and, again, feed it through
some kind of non-linearity.
And you could think of various
other designs for this.
And that gives us this
attention combination, h tilde.
And then, finally,
the classifier layer
is a simple dense layer, just
as before, except instead
of using just hC, we now use
this h tilde representation,
which incorporates both hC and
that kind of weighted mixture
of premise states.
It might be useful
to go through this
with some specific
numerical values here.
So what I've done
is, just imagine
that we have two-dimensional
representations for all
of these vectors.
And you can see, what I've done
here is kind of ensure that,
proportionally, "every" is a lot
like this final representation
here.
And then that kind of
similarity drops off
as we move through
the premise states,
and you'll see what happens when
we take the dot products here.
So the first step gives us
the unnormalized scores,
and you can see that the highest
unnormalized similarity is
with the first token, followed
by the second, and then
the third.
The softmax normalization step
kind of just flattens out those
dot products a
little bit, but we
get the same proportional
ranking with respect to hC.
Here's that context
vector, and you
can see it's just a mean of
the weighted values of all
of these vectors.
That gives us k.
And that k is then fed into this
attention combination layer.
And you can see, in
orange here, this
is the context vector,
two dimensions.
Down here, we have hC,
just faithfully repeated.
And then this
matrix of weights Wk
is going to give us, in the
end, after this non-linearity, h
tilde.
And then the classifier
is as before.
So that's a simple
worked example
of how these attention
mechanisms work.
And the idea is that we are
kind of fundamentally weighting
this target representation
hC by its similarity
with the previous
premise states.
But all of them are mixed
in, and the influence
is kind of proportional to
that unnormalized similarity.
There are other scoring
functions that you could use,
of course.
We've just done a simple
dot product up here,
but you can also imagine having
learned parameters in there
or doing concatenation of
the learned parameters.
This does a kind
of bilinear form,
and this is just a concatenation
of those two states fed
through these learned weights.
And once you see this
kind of design space,
you can imagine there
are a lot of other ways
in which you could
mix in parameters
and have different views of
this global attention mechanism.
We could go one
step further here.
That was global attention.
In word-by-word
attention, we're going
to have a lot more learned
parameters and a lot
more connections between
the hypothesis back
into the premise.
So to make this
kind of tractable,
I've picked one pretty simple
view of how this could work.
And the way we should
track these computations
is focus on this vector
B here, because we're
going to move through time.
But let's imagine that we've
already processed the A state,
and we will subsequently
process the C state.
So we're focused on B.
And the way we establish
these connections
is by taking the
previous context
vector that we've created.
That's kA here.
We're going to multiply that by
repeated copies of the B state,
and that's simply so that we
get the same dimensionality
as we have in the
premise over here,
where I've simply copied
over into a matrix all three
of those states.
And we have a matrix of
learned parameters here
and an additive
combination of the two,
followed by a non-linearity.
That's going to give us this M
here, which kind of corresponds
to the attention weights in
the previous global attention
mechanisms.
We're going to softmax
normalize those,
and that literally
gives us the weights.
And you can see that there
are some additional parameters
in here to create the
right dimensionalities.
And then, finally, we
have the context at B.
So that's going to be a repeated
view of all these premises,
weighted by our context
vector, as before,
and then fed through some
additional parameters Wa here.
And that gives us, as you
can see here, the context
representation for the state B.
When we move to
state C, of course,
that will be used in
the place of A here.
And C will go in for
all these purple values,
and the computation
will proceed as before.
And in that way, because we have
all of these additional learned
parameters, we can
meaningfully move
through the entire sequence,
updating our parameters
and learning connections from
each hypothesis token back
into the premise.
So it's much more powerful
than the previous view, where
we had relatively few learned
parameters in our attention
mechanisms, and, therefore, we
could only really meaningfully
connect that from the
state that we're going
to feed into the classifier.
So this is much more
expressive, right?
And then once we have done the
entire sequence processing,
finally, we get the
representation for C
here, as fed through
these mechanisms,
and that becomes the
input to the classifier
that we ultimately use.
The connection with the
transformer should be apparent.
This is going to return us
back to the global attention
mechanism.
Recall that for
the transformer, we
have these sequences
of tokens with
their positional encodings.
That gives us an embedding here.
And at that point,
we establish a lot
of dot product connections.
And I showed you in the
lecture on the transformer
that the mechanisms here are
identical to the mechanisms
that we used for dot
product attention.
It's just that in the
context of the transformer,
we do it from every state
to every other state.
And then, of course,
the computations
proceed through subsequent
steps in the transformer layer
and on through multiple
transformer layers,
potentially.
And there are some
other variants, right?
This is just the beginning
of a very large design
space for attention mechanisms.
Let me just mention a few.
We could have local attention.
This was actually an
early contribution
in the context of
machine translation.
And this would build connections
between selected points
and the premise and
hypothesis, based
on some possibly a
priori notion we have
of which things are likely to
be important for our problem.
Word-by-word attention,
as I've said,
can be set up in many ways, with
many more learned parameters.
And the classic paper
is the one that I'm
recommending for reading
for this unit, Rocktaschel
et al., where they do a
really pioneering view of this
in using even more complex
attention mechanisms than I
presented under
word-by-word attention
but following a lot of the
same intuitions, I would say.
The attention
representation at a time t
could be appended to the
hidden representation
at time t plus 1.
This would give us another
way of moving sequentially
through the sequence,
having meaningful attention
at each one of those
points, as opposed
to the global attention,
which would just
be for that final state.
And then there are
other connections even
further afield.
For example, memory
networks can be
used to address similar
issues, and they
have similar intuitions behind
them as attention mechanisms
as applied to the NLI problem.
And that's kind of more
explicitly drawing on this idea
that we might, in late
states in processing,
need a bit of a
reminder about what
was in the previous
context that we processed.