OMAR KHATTAB: Hello, everyone.
Welcome to part 2 of our
series on NLU and IR.
The screen cast will be a
crash course in classical IR,
as well as evaluation methods
and information retrieval.
Let us first define the
simplest form of our task,
namely ranked retrieval.
We will be given a large
collection of text documents.
This could be all of the
passages in Wikipedia,
perhaps a crawl of
parts of the web
or maybe all of the
documentation of Hugging Face
or other software libraries.
This corpus will be provided to
us offline, that is before we
interact with any users.
And we will be able to spend a
one time effort at organizing
or otherwise
understanding the content
of these documents in the corpus
before we start searching.
Online though, we
will receive a query
from the users, which
could be a natural language
question written in
English, for example.
The goal of our ranked
retrieval system
will be to output a Top-K
list of documents, sorted
in decreasing order of
relevance to the information
need that the user
expressed in the query.
So this might be the top
10 or the top 100 results.
So how do we conduct this
task of ranked retrieval?
As it turns out, we've
already looked at the way
for doing this before, when
discussing matrix designs.
In particular, we know that
we can build Term-Document
Occurrence Matrices.
And in such a matrix
like the one shown,
each term-document pair
has a corresponding cell
in which the matrix will
store the number of times
that the term appears in
the document, in our corpus.
Of course, we will
probably want to apply
some sort of reweighting
here, because we don't want
to work with these row counts.
But once we've done
that, we can already
answer queries that contain
just a single term pretty well.
And to do that, we would
basically just return
the K-documents with
the largest weight
after normalization or other
processes for the single term.
And again, as it turns
out, this is precisely what
is done in classical IR if
we have just a single query--
just a single term in our query.
When we have multiple
terms in the same query,
classical IR tends to
treat them independently.
So we would basically
add the weights up
across all of the terms
in the query per document.
And then, that's the
score for the document.
This is precisely
the computation
that is shown here, where we
compute the relevance score
between a query and a document.
We would go over all
the terms in the query
and simply add the corresponding
document-term weights
for all of these terms
for that document.
This gives us a score
for the document
and we can then
return the K-documents
with the largest total scores.
Interestingly, this reduces
much of classical IR,
of course, not all
of it, to thinking
about how do we best weigh
each term-document pair, which
has an undeniable
similarity to our first task
this quarter in Homework 1.
Except of course,
that here in IR,
we look at the term to document
relevance, and not word
to word relatedness.
So thinking about
term-document weighting,
here are some intuitions
that might be useful,
as we think about what makes
a strong term weighting
model in IR.
Of course, later, in the next
screencast in particular,
we'll be looking at neural
models that go beyond this.
But for now, perhaps the two
most prominent intuitions
for term-document
weighting are connected
to our first unit's discussion
of frequency and normalization.
In particular, if a
term t occurs frequently
in document d.
The document is
more likely to be
relevant for queries
that include the term t
or so is one of our intuitions.
And in terms of normalization,
if that term t is quite rare,
so if it occurs in only
a few documents overall,
we take that as a stronger
signal that document d
is even more likely to be
relevant for queries including
t.
Lastly, if document
d is rather short,
we take that as also
yet another signal
that might increase our
confidence that the term
t was included in that rather
short document for a reason.
Taking a step back and
thinking more broadly,
we're still functioning
under the same statement
from the first unit.
Our goal is ultimately to
amplify the important signals,
trustworthy and the
unusual and to deemphasize
the mundane and the quirky.
There are so many different
term-weighting functions in IR,
but most of them are
directly inspired by TF-IDF
and take a very similar
computational form.
For TF-IDF, this is a
slightly different version
to the one used in Unit 1.
What I have here is
slightly different.
This is the more popular
version in the context
of IR applications.
But TF-IDF is
overloaded frequently,
and you will see
multiple implementations,
if you go look for them.
So we'll define N to be
the size of the collection.
And DF or document
frequency of a term,
DF of term to be the number
of documents that contain
that term in the collection.
Then TF or term frequency
of a term-document pair
will be defined as the
logarithm of the frequency
of this term in this
document, with 1 just
for mathematical reasons.
IDF or inverse
document frequency
is defined as the logarithm
of N divided by the document
frequency of the term.
TF-IDF is then nothing
but the product
of these two values for each
query term summed up at the end
to assign a single overall
score to each document
by summing up across
all query terms,
as we've discussed before.
Of course, higher
scores are better
and the Top-K
scoring documents are
those that we would
return to the searcher
if we were to use TF-IDF.
Notice how both TF and IDF grow
sub-linearly, in particular,
logarithmically with frequency
and 1 over DF, respectively.
A much stronger term
weighting model in practice
is BM25 or best match number 25.
And as you might imagine,
it took many attempts
until BM25 was developed.
For our purposes, unlike
TF-IDF, term frequency in BM25
saturates towards the
constant value for each term,
and also, it penalizes
longer documents
when counting frequencies,
since a longer
document will naturally contain
more occurrences of its terms.
These are the main
differences, and it really
helps BM25 in practice be a much
stronger term weighting model.
Now that we've decided the
behavior of these weighting
functions or at least
a couple of them,
how would we actually implement
this as an actual system
that we could use for search?
So let's think about this,
whereas the raw collection,
the actual text, supports fast
access from documents to terms,
so basically, [INAUDIBLE] gives
us the terms of each document.
The term-document matrix
that we've studied so far,
allows fast access from
a term to the documents.
So it's a bit of
the reverse process.
Unfortunately, the term-document
matrix is way too sparse
and contains too many
zeros to be useful,
since the average
term does not occur
in the vast majority
of documents,
if you think about it.
For the inverted index,
that's where it comes in.
This is a data structure
that solves this problem.
It's essentially just a sparse
representation of our matrix
here, which maps each unique
term in the collection.
So each unique term
in our vocabulary
is what we call a posting list.
The posting list
of a term t simply
enumerates all of the actual
occurrences of the term t
in the documents, recording
both the ID of each document
in which the term t appears.
And also, its frequency
in each of these documents
So beyond term weighting
models, IR, of course,
contains lots of models
for other things.
So they're models for expanding
queries and documents.
This basically entails
adding new terms
to queries or to
documents, or to both,
to help with the
vocabulary mismatch problem
that we discussed in the first
screencast of the series,
basically, when queries and
documents use different terms
to express the same thing.
There's also plenty of work
on term dependence and phrase
search.
Notice that so far, we've
assumed the terms in each query
and in each document
are independent,
and we function in a
bag-of-words fashion.
But work on term dependence
and phrase search
relaxes these assumptions
that each query
is a bag of independent terms.
Lastly, there is
also lots of work
on learning to rank
with various features,
like how to estimate
relevance when documents have
multiple fields, like maybe a
title, a body, some headings,
a footer and also,
anchor text, which
is a very strong signal when
you have it, like in web search.
So this is basically
the text from links
in other pages to your page.
The text in those links
or around those links
tends to be very useful
as a relevant signal.
And of course, also things like
PageRank with link analysis
and lots of other
features for IR,
like recency and other stuff.
But I think it's worth
mentioning that until recently,
if you just had a collection
that you want to search
and you didn't want
to do a lot of tuning,
BM25 was a very strong
baseline on the best
that you could do ad hoc,
so without lots of tuning
and without lots of
training data, et cetera.
And this only
changed a year or two
ago with the advent of
BERT-based ranking, which we'll
discuss in detail in
the next screencast
of this set of the series.
OK, so we just
built an IR system.
How do we evaluate our work?
What is success like?
Well, a search system,
as you can imagine,
must be both efficient
and effective.
If we had infinite time
and infinite resources,
we would just hire experts to
look through all the documents
one by one to
conduct the search,
but clearly, we don't
have that sort of ability.
So efficiency in
IR is paramount,
after all, we want
our retrieval models
to work with subsecond
latencies for collections that
may have hundreds of
millions of documents,
if not even larger than that.
The most common measure
of efficiency in IR
is latency, which is simply
the time it takes to run
one query through the system.
Say, on average or
perhaps, at the tail,
like the 95th
percentile, for example.
But you can also
measure throughput
in queries per second.
Space, how much, maybe
the inverted index
takes on disk versus say
a term-document matrix.
How well do you scale to
different collection sizes
in terms of the
number of documents
or the size of the documents?
And how do you perform on
the different query loads?
Many queries, few queries,
short queries, long queries.
And lastly, of course, what
sort of hardware do you require?
Is it just one CPU core?
Many cores?
A bunch of GPUs?
But latency tends to
be kind of, once you've
determined the other ones, it's
the go-to metric in most cases.
More central to our discussion
today, and we'll focus on
this for the rest
of the screencast
is IR effectiveness
or the quality,
basically of an IR system.
And here we ask, do our
top-k rankings for a query
satisfy the users'
information need?
Answering this question
tends to be harder
than evaluation for typical
machine learning tasks,
like classification
or regression
because we're not really just
taking an item and assigning it
a class.
We're trying to rank all
of the items in our corpus
with respect to a query.
In practice, if you
have lots of users,
you could run online
experiments where you basically
give different versions of
your system to different users
and compare some metrics of
satisfaction or conversion,
basically in terms of
purchases or otherwise.
But for research
purposes, we're typically
interested in reusable
test collections.
That's collections that allow
us to evaluate IR models offline
and then, compare them
against each other.
Building a test collection
entails three things.
First, we need to
decide on a document
collection for our corpus,
a set of test queries,
and we need to find or get or
produce relevant assessments
for each query.
If resources
permit, a collection
could also include the
train dev split of queries,
but given the high
annotation cost,
it's actually not uncommon
in IR to find or create
only a test set.
The key component
of a test collection
is the relevance assessments.
These are basically
human annotated labels
for each query that
enumerate for us,
whether specific documents are
relevant or not to that query.
These query document
assessments can either be binary
or they could take on a more
fine grained graded nature.
An example of that is
grading a query document pair
as -1, 0, 1 or 2,
with meanings of hey,
this is a junk document, -1.
You should not retrieve it
for any query or this document
is irrelevant, but
it might be useful
for other queries
or this document
is quite relevant
for this query,
but it's not a perfect match.
Or here is a really,
really good match
for our query, which would
be a score of 2 or 3,
depending on the
grades that you're
using for the assessments.
As you might imagine,
because we work
with potentially many
millions of documents,
it's usually infeasible to
judge every single document
for every single query.
So instead, we're often
forced to make the assumption
that unjudged documents
are not relevant
or at least to ignore them
in some metrics of IR.
Though for most purposes, they
are treated as not relevant.
Some test collections take
this further and only label
one or two key documents
per query as relevant
and assume everything
else is not relevant.
So this tends to
be useful when you
work with particular data sets.
And you want to keep it in
mind as you do evaluation.
So many of the test
collections out there in IR
are annotated by TREC or the
Text Retrieval Conference,
which includes annual tracks
for competing and comparing
IR systems.
For instance, the
2021 TREC Conference
has tracks for
search in the context
of conversational assistance,
health misinformation,
fair ranking, and has a
very popular deep learning
track, as well, which we'll
discuss in more detail.
Each TREC campaign
emphasizes careful evaluation
with a very small
set of queries.
So just 50 queries is a
very typical size, actually.
But TREC extensively judges
many, many documents,
possibly hundreds of documents
or even more for each query
here.
So you can imagine
an alternative,
which we'll look at next where
you have lots of queries.
But you only judge
a very small number
of key documents for those
queries with the intention
that the performance
that you get
will average out over a
large enough set of queries.
And this is exactly what
happens in MS MARCO Ranking
Tasks, which is a collection
of really popular IR
benchmarks by Microsoft.
And this MARCO contains more
than half a million Bing search
queries.
And this is the largest
public IR benchmark.
Each query here is assessed with
one or two relevant documents,
and we assume everything
else is not relevant,
and having this
sparse annotation
is often not a problem at all
for training because we have
so many training instances.
And so, MS MARCO provides a
tremendous resource for us
when it comes to building
and training IR models,
especially in the neural domain.
It also turns out that
sparse labels are not
too bad for evaluation, either.
Especially because of the
size of the test queries,
we can use many thousands
of test queries, an average
of results across all of them
to get a pretty reliable signal
about how different
systems compare.
There are multiple test
collections out there
on top of MS MARCO.
And so, there's the
original passage ranking
task and newer
document ranking task
where the documents
are much longer,
but there's fewer of them.
And then, there is also a
track, the deep learning track,
which we've mentioned
before, which
is happening every
year since 2019
and which uses the MS
MARCO data, especially
for training, mostly.
But has far fewer queries
for testing with lots
more labels for evaluation,
a lot more extensive
assessments and
judgments for evaluation,
so these are much denser labels.
There are also plenty of other
rather domain specific IR
benchmarks, many of which
are collected in this table
by Nandan et al.
in a very recent preprint.
As you can see, these
benchmarks vary greatly
in terms of the
training size, if there
is any training at all.
The test set size, the
average query length,
the average document length,
and many other factors.
BEIR, or benchmarking for IR
is a recent effort by Nandan
et al. here to use all
of these different data
sets for zero shot or out of
domain testing of IR models.
Specifically, in BEIR, we
take already trained IR models
that do not have access to any
validation or training data
on these downstream IR tasks
and test them out of the box
to observe their out of
domain retrieval quality,
so that is without training
on these new domains.
OK, so we now have
a test collection
with queries, documents,
and assessments.
How do we compare IR
systems in this collection?
First, we will ask each IR
system to produce its Top-K
ranking, say its top 10 results.
And we'll use an IR metric to
compare all of these systems
at that cutoff K.
The choice of IR
metric and the cutoff K
will depend entirely
on the task,
so I will briefly motivate each
metric as we go through them.
All of the metrics
we will go through
are simply averaged
across all queries.
And so, to keep
things simple, I will
show the computation
of the metric
for just one query
in each case, but you
want to keep in mind that this
is averaged across queries.
Let us start with two of
the simplest IR metrics,
which are Success and MRR.
For a given query, let
rank be the position
of the first relevant
document that we can see
in the Top-K list of results.
Success@K will
just be 1, if there
is a relevant result in the
Top-K list, and 0 otherwise.
This is a very simple
metric, as you can see,
that can be useful
in cases where
we assume that the
user just needs
one relevant result
anywhere in the Top-K.
And in particular,
it can be useful
if our retrieval is spread
to a downstream model that
looks at the Top-K results and
then does something with them.
So you can read all of them,
and it would read all of them
anyway, so we're just interested
in buying the irrelevance here.
Mean reciprocal rank or MRR
also assumes that these only
needs one relevant
query in the Top-K,
but it assumes that
the user does care
about the position of
that relevant document
in the ranking.
So a relevant document at the
second position for example,
is only given half of the
weight of a relevant document
in the top position.
You're probably already familiar
with precision and recall,
but let's define them here
in the context of Top-K
ranked retrieval.
For a given query, let Ret
of K be the Top-K retrieved
documents, that set of
Top-K retrieved documents.
And let Rel be the
set of all documents
that we judged as relevance
as part of our assessments.
In this case,
Precision@K is just
a fraction of the
retrieved items
that are actually relevant.
And recall that
K is the fraction
of all the relevant items
that are actually retrieved.
A pretty popular metric is also
a MAP or mean average precision
or just average precision
for one query, which
essentially brings together
notions from both precision
and recall.
To compute average
precision for one query,
we will add up the Precision@i
for every position i from 1
through K, where the i-th
document is relevant.
We will divide
this whole quantity
by the total number of documents
that we're judged as relevant
for this query.
All of the metrics that we've
considered so far only interact
with binary relevance,
that is they
just care whether each
document that is retrieved
is considered relevant
or not relevant.
DCG or discounted
cumulative gain
works with graded relevance.
So for instance, 0, 1, 2, and 3.
For each position in the
ranking from 1 through K,
we will divide the
graded relevance
of the retrieved
document at that position
by the logarithm of the
position, which essentially
discounts the value
of a relevant document
if it appears late
in the ranking.
Unlike the other
metrics, the maximum DCG
is often not equal to 1.
So we can also compute
normalized DCG or NDCG
by dividing for each
query by the ideal DCG.
This is obtained basically, if
all of the relevant documents
are at the top of
our Top-K ranking,
and they are sorted by
decreasing relevance,
so all of the 2's before all of
the 1's before all of the 0's
in this case that
are not relevant.
All right, having discussed
classical IR and evaluation
in this screencast, we
will focus on Neural IR
and in particular,
state of the art
IR models that use what
we've learned so far in NLU
in the next screencast.