OMAR KHATTAB: Hello, everyone.
Welcome to part 3 of the series.
This screencast will be
the first of two or three
on neural IR.
And in it, we'll be exploring
the inputs, outputs, training
and inference in the
context of neural IR.
Let's quickly start with
a reminder of our setup
from the previous screencast.
Offline, we're given a large
corpus of text documents.
We will pre-process and index
this corpus for fast retrieval.
Online, we're giving a query
that we want to answer.
Our output will be a list of the
Top-K most relevant documents
for this query.
In the classical
IR screencast, we
discussed BM25 as a strong
term-matching retrieval model.
So should we just use BM25?
The short answer
is that we could.
But if our interest is
getting the highest quality
that we can, then we should
probably be using neural IR.
As we will see, neural IR makes
a lot of use of our NLU work
in creative and
interesting ways.
The long answer to whether
we should be using BM25
is that it depends.
Among other factors, it
depends on our budget.
Each IR model poses a different
efficiency-effectiveness
tradeoff.
In many cases, we're interested
in maximizing effectiveness,
maximizing quality, as long
as efficiency is acceptable.
Let's begin to explore this
on the MS MARCO collection
that we introduced in
the previous screencast.
Here we'll be
measuring effectiveness
using the mean reciprocal
rank at cut-off 10.
And we will measure
efficiency, and in particular,
latency using milliseconds.
This figure here shows
BM25 retrieval using
the popular toolkit called
Ansereni as one data
point within a wide
range of MRR values
and latency possibilities.
Just as a reminder,
lower latency is better.
And the latency here is
shown on a logarithmic scale.
And higher MRR is also better.
The higher our MRR is, the
better the model's quality.
So what else could exist in
this large empty space for now?
We're going to see
this space fill up
with many different neural IR
models over the next couple
of screencasts.
And the central
question now and then
will generally be, how
can we improve our MRR@10
or whatever effectiveness
metric we choose
to work with, possibly at the
expense of increasing latency
a bit?
OK, so let's
actually take a look
at how neural IR models
will work, specifically
at their input and
output behavior.
For the purposes of
this short screencast,
we'll treat the neural
ranker as a black box.
We will consider
various implementations
for this black box function
in the next screencast.
We will feed this
neural IR black box
a query and a document.
And the model will do its
thing and return to us
a single score that estimates
the relevance of this query
to that document.
For the same query, we
will repeat this process
for every document
that we want to score.
And we will finally sort
all of these documents
by decreasing relevance score.
And that will give us the
Top-K list of results.
So far, this sounds
simple enough.
But how should we train this
neural model for ranking?
This might not be super obvious,
but one pretty effective choice
is simply two-way
classification,
pair-wise classification.
Here, each training
example will be a triple.
Specifically, each
training instance
will contain a query, a
relevant or positive document,
and an irrelevant
document, or a negative.
In the forward pass
during training,
we'll feed the model the query
and the positive document.
And separately, we'll feed the
query and the negative document
to the neural ranker.
And we optimize the
entire neural network end
to end with gradient descent,
using simple classification
loss--
written in this case,
CrossEntropy Loss with softmax.
The goal here is to maximize the
score of the positive document,
and to minimize
the score assigned
to the negative document.
Recall that we can get
positives for each query
from our relevance assessments.
And that every document that
was not labeled as positive
can often be treated as
an implicit negative.
So we could use this
in generating triples
for 2-way classification
training for our neural ranker.
Once our neural ranker
is trained, inference
or actually conducting
the ranking is very easy.
Given a query, we'll
just pick each document,
pass the query and the document
through the neural network,
get a score, and then we'll
sort all the documents by score.
And this will give us the
Top-K list of documents.
However, there is just a
small yet very major problem.
Collections often have
many millions, if not
billions of documents.
Even if our model is so
fast that it processes
each document in
one microsecond, one
millionth of a
second, it would still
require nine seconds per query
for a dataset like MS MARCO
with nine million
messages, which
is way too slow for most
practical applications.
To deal with this in practice,
neural IR models are often used
as re-rankers--
models that rescore
only the Top-K documents
obtained by another model to
improve the final ranking.
One of the most common
pipeline designs
is to re-rank the top 1,000
documents obtained by BM25.
This can be great because
it cuts down the work
for a collection with 10 million
passages by a factor of 10,000,
because we only need
to rank 1,000 documents
with the neural model.
But it also introduces an
artificial ceiling on recall,
it limits recall in
an artificial way.
Since now, all of the
relevant documents that BM25,
our first stage ranker, fails
to retrieve cannot possibly be
ranked highly by our
shiny new IR ranker.
So, can we do better?
It turns out that
the answer is yes.
We'll discuss the notion of
end to end retrieval later,
where our neural model will
be able to quickly conduct
the search by itself over
the entire collection
without a re-ranking pipeline.
But first, we'll discuss a
number of neural re-rankers
in detail in the
next screencast.