OMAR KHATTAB: Hello, everyone.
Welcome to part five of
our series on NLU and IR.
This screencast will be
the third among three
of our videos on neural IR.
In the previous screencast we
discussed learning term weights
as a paradigm for building
neural IR models that are
both efficient and effective.
We mentioned two such models
from the IR literature, DeepCT
and doc2query.
Both of which, despite
outperforming BM25 in MRR,
still left a very large
margin to the quality
that we see with BERT.
We asked ourselves
can we achieve
high MRR and low computational
cost at the same time.
Can we do better?
To answer this
question, let us begin
exploring more
expressive paradigms
for efficient neural IR.
The next paradigm here is
the representation similarity
paradigm.
In the representation
similarity paradigm
we begin by tokenizing the
query and the document.
And we feed each of
them independently
through an encoder,
like BERT, for example.
This encoder is
then used to produce
a single-vector
representation, for the query
and for the
document, separately.
So for BERT we could take
this through the class token,
for example and take
the output embeddings,
or we could average all
the final layer outputs.
Once we have those, we finally
calculate the relevant score
of this document to our
query as a single dot
product between two vectors.
This paradigm is very
efficient for retrieval.
First each document
can be represented
as a vector offline.
And this precomputed
representation
can be stored on disk before we
even start conducting search.
Moreover, the
similarity computation
between a query
and a document here
is very cheap and
thus very efficient,
as it's just a single
product between two vectors.
A very large number of IR models
are Representations Similarity
models.
Many of those
actually precede BERT.
Like DSSM and SNRM.
But the last year
and a half, we've
seen numerous similarity models
based on BERT for IR tasks,
including SBERT, ORQA, DPR,
DE-BERT and ANCE, among others.
Many of these models were
actually proposed concurrently
with each other, and
their primary differences
lie in the specific
tasks that each one
targets and the supervision
approach each one suggests.
So let us delve deeper
into a representative
in one of the earlier and most
popular models among those.
This is the Dense
Passage Retriever,
or DPR by Karpukhin
et al., which appeared
at EMNLP just a few months ago.
DPR encodes each
passage, or document,
as a 768-dimentional vector,
and similarly for each query.
During training DPR
produces a similarity score
between the query and
the positive passage--
so that's the
relevant passage we
wanted to retrieve-- as
well as between the query
and a few negatives.
Some of them are sampled
from the BM25 top-100
and others are
in-batch negatives,
which are actually positives,
but for other queries
in the same training batch.
Once DPR has all of those
scores during training,
it then optimizes a
classification loss,
Namely N-way classification loss
with softmax-- cross entropy
loss with softmax over the
scores of one positive and all
of these negatives, with
the target of selecting
the positive passage, of course.
DPR was not tested on
the MS MARCO dataset
by the original authors.
But subsequent work
by Xiong et al.
bests a DPR like retriever on
MS MARCO and achieves 31% MRR.
They also then suggest more
sophisticated approaches
for supervision
which can increase
this MRR by a couple of points.
So both of these demonstrate
considerable progress
over the learned
term weight models
that we looked at before,
like DeepCT or doc2query.
But they still substantially
trail behind BERT's much higher
effectiveness.
So why is that?
As it turns out representation
similarity models
suffer from two major downsides
when it comes to IR tasks.
First, are their
single-vector representations,
which involve cramming each
query and each document
into one rather low
dimensional vector.
Second is their lack of
fine grained interactions
during matching.
Representation similarity
models estimate relevance as one
dot product between two vectors.
And as they lose the
term level interactions
between the query terms
and the document terms
that we had in query document
interaction models like BERT--
in fact, even simple
term weighting models
like BM25 or DeepCT
had, by design,
some element of term
level matching there
that we lose here.
So our next natural
question then
becomes can we obtain
these efficiency benefits
of precomputation that we get
from representation similarity
models while still keeping
the fine-grained term level
interactions that
we used to have
before with a model
like BERT or DeepCT?
Toward answering
that question, I
think it helps to
review the neural IR
paradigms we've seen so far.
On the left hand side, we looked
at the learned term weights
paradigm.
These models offered independent
and dependent encoding
of queries and documents,
which was great for efficiency,
but they forced us to work
with a bag of words query
that loses all context.
And thus were not as competitive
as we wanted them to be.
We then explored the
representation similarity
models, which also allowed us to
complete independent encodings
of queries and documents,
which again was
really useful for efficiency.
But this time we were forced
to work with single vector
representations and we lost
our fine-grained term level
interactions, which
we intuitively
believe to be very useful
for matching in IR tasks.
On the right hand side we
looked initially, actually,
at the query document
interaction models
like standard BERT classifiers.
These offered very high
accuracy but were extremely
expensive to use because the
entire computation for one
document depended on both
the query and the document.
We simply couldn't
do any precomputation
in this case offline in advance.
So can we somehow combine the
advantages of all these three
paradigms at once?
Before we answer
that question there's
actually one final feature,
one final capability
of the first two paradigms
that we should discuss.
So query document
interaction models,
which are quite
expensive, they forced us
to use a re-ranking pipeline.
This is a pipeline where
we re-scored the top 1,000
documents that we already
retrieved by BM25.
Sometimes that's OK,
but in many cases
this can be a problem
because it ties our recall
to the recall of BM25, which is
ultimately a model that relies
on finding terms that match
exactly across queries
and documents, and
so it can be quite
restrictive in many cases.
When recall is an
important consideration,
you often want our neural
model that we trained
to do end to end retrieval.
That is, to search quickly
over all the documents
in our collection
directly without
the re-ranking pipeline.
Learning term weights and
representation similarity
models that we've looked
at so far alleviate
this constraint and this is
a big advantage for them.
So, specifically, when
we learn term weights,
we can save these weights
in the inverted index
just like with BM25,
and that allows
us to obtain fast retrieval.
When we learn vector
representations,
it also turns out
that we can index
these vectors using libraries
for fast vector similarity
search, like FAISS,
f-a-i- double s.
This relies on efficient
data structures
that support pruning,
which is basically
finding the top-K matches,
say the top 10 or the top 100
matches, without having
to exhaustively enumerate
all possible candidates.
The details of search with
these pruning data structures
is beyond our scope,
but it's really useful
to be aware of this
important capability for end
to end retrieval.
OK, so let's go back to
our last main question.
Can we obtain the
efficiency benefits
of precomputation while still
having the fine-grained term
level interactions
that we used to have?
The neural IR paradigm that
will allow us to do this
is called Late Interaction,
and this is something
that I've worked on
here at Stanford.
So let's build late
interaction from the ground up.
We'll start, as usual
with tokenization
of the query and the document.
We'll seek to
independently encode
the query and the document
but into fine-grained
representations this time.
So, as you can see on
the left hand side,
this is actually not hard.
As it's shown, we can feed
two copies of BERT, the query,
and the document separately, and
keep all the output embeddings
for responding to
all the tokens as
our fine-grained
representation for the query
and for the document.
OK.
So, we're only going to be
done here once we actually
close this loop.
Right?
We still need to estimate
relevance between this query
and that document.
Essentially we have
two matrices and we
need a notion of similarity
between these two matrices
or these two bags of vectors.
However, not every
approach will suffice.
We insist that we get a
scalable mechanism that
allows us to use vector
similarity search with pruning
to conduct end to end
retrieval in a scalable fashion
across the entire collection.
In doing this, it turns out
that a very simple interaction
mechanism offers both
scaling and high quality.
So here's what we'll do.
For each query embedding,
as I show here,
we compute a maximum
similarity score
across all of the
document embeddings.
So this is just going to be
a cosine similarity giving us
a single partial score
for this query term, which
is the maximum cosine
similarity across all
of the blue embeddings
in this case.
We'll repeat this here for
all the query embeddings
and we'll simply sum all of
these maximum similarity scores
to get our final score
for this document.
So, we will refer to
this general paradigm
here as late interaction, and to
this specific model shown here
on top of BERT as ColBERT.
And the intuition is simple.
For every term in
the query, we're
just trying to softly
and contextually locate
that term in the document,
assigning a score to how
successful this matching was.
Let me illustrate this with a
real example from the MS MARCO
ranking development
set, and I hope
it will be quite
intuitive once you see it.
At the top is a query
and at the bottom
is a portion of
the correct passage
that ColBERT retrieves
at position one.
Because we have the simple
late interaction mechanism,
we can actually
explore the behavior.
And we can see in this
particular example that ColBERT
matches, through maximum
similarity operators, the word
"when" in the question with
the word "on" in the phrase
"on August 8," which is a
date as we might expect.
It matches the
word "transformers"
with the same word
in the document.
It matches "cartoon"
with "animated."
And it matches the individual
words, "come" and "out,"
with the term
"released" in the phrase
"it was released on August
8th" in the document,
as we might intuitively expect.
So, we're basically just
trying to contextually match
these query terms
in the document
and assign some matching
score for each of these terms.
So notice here and remember
that ColBERT represents
each document as a dense
matrix of many vectors
and in particular
one vector per token.
And this differs from
the representation
similarity models
we looked at before,
which try to cram each
document into one vector.
And what makes this possible
is the maximum similarity
operators that we have on top
of these matrix representations.
So how well does ColBERT do?
And how does it do
with this gap that we
have here between
efficient models and highly
effective ones?
Well, by redesigning
the model architecture
and offering a late
interaction paradigm,
ColBERT allows us to achieve
quality comparative with BERT
at a small fraction
of the costs.
Perhaps more
importantly, ColBERT
can scale through the entire
collection due to pruning
with end to end retrieval.
All 9 million passages
here in this case,
while maintaining
subsecond latencies,
And thus it allows
much higher recall
than traditional re-ranking
pipelines permit.
All right.
So far we've looked at in-domain
effectiveness evaluations.
Basically cases where we
had training and evaluation
data for the IR task at hand,
which was MS MARCO, so far.
But we often want
to use retrieval
in new out-of-domain settings.
We just want to throw our search
engine at a difficult problem
without training data,
without validation data,
and see it perform well.
We briefly discussed
BEIR before,
which is a recent
effort to test IR
models in a zero-shot setting
where the models are trained
on one IR task and
then they're fixed,
and then they are tested on
a completely different set
of tasks.
BEIR includes 17 IR data sets
and there are nine different IR
tasks or scenarios, and
the authors, Nandan et al.,
compared a lot of the IR
models that we discussed today
in a zero-shot manner
against each other
across all of these tasks.
So let's take a look.
Here we have BM25 results for
an interaction model, which
is in this case ELECTRA, which
tends to perform slightly
better than BERT for ranking.
We have two representation
similarity models, DPR
and SBERT.
And we have a late interaction
model, which is ColBERT.
The best in each row-- in
each IR task is shown in bold.
And we see that across all tasks
the strongest model at NDCG@10
is always one of
the three models
that involve term level
interactions, which
are ELECTRA, ColBERT, and BM25.
Interestingly, the
single vector approaches,
which seemed quite
promising so far,
failed to generalize robustly
according to these results.
Whereas ColBERT, which
is also a fast model,
almost matches the quality of
the expensive ELECTRA ranker.
The results, so far, were
on the metric NDCG@10,
which is a precision
oriented metric--
looks at the top results.
But here I have the
author's results
after the task level aggregation
considering recall at 100.
And here, although we see
that the results are rather
similar when we consider
recall, one major difference
is that ColBERT's late
interaction mechanism, which
allows it to conduct end to end
retrieval with high quality,
allows it to achieve the
strongest recall in this case.
And so we can
conclude, basically,
that scalable
fine-grained interaction
is key to robustly high recall.
Of course notice that the
BM25 and ELECTRA recall here
is the same since ELECTRA
just re-scores the top 100,
in this case, from BM25.
So this concludes our neural
IR section of the NLU plus IR
series.
In the next screencast,
we will discuss
how scalability with
these retriever models
can actually drive
large gains in quality,
not just speed,
which we haven't seen
so far except on
the recall case,
and how tuning a
neural IR model fits
into a larger downstream
open domain NLU task.