BILL AMCCARTNEY: So
I now want to turn
to the question of how to
formulate our prediction
problem precisely.
I want to be precise about
how we're defining the inputs
and outputs of our
predictions, and that, in turn,
is going to have
consequences for how
we join the corpus and
the KB, how we construct
negative examples for
our learning algorithms,
and how we handle
multi-label classification.
So first what is the input
to our prediction problem?
In the supervised
learning paradigm,
the input is a pair
of entity mentions
in the context of a
specific sentence.
We're trying to
label a sentence just
like we do in part of speech
tagging or sentiment analysis.
But in the distance
supervision paradigm,
we'll do things differently.
The input will be a pair of
entities full stop, independent
of any specific context.
We're trying to determine the
relation between this entity
and that entity, and that's it.
The other question
I want to look at
is, what's the output of
the prediction problem?
Are we trying to assign
a pair of entities
to a single relation?
That's called multi-class
classification.
Or are we trying to
assign a pair of entities
to multiple relations?
That's called multi-label
classification,
and it's a different beast.
So over the next
couple of slides,
I want to explore the
consequences of these choices.
The difference
between these two ways
of thinking about the input
becomes really important
when we talk about
how we're going
to join the corpus and the KB.
In order to leverage the
distance supervision paradigm,
we need to connect those two.
We need to connect information
in the corpus with information
in the KB.
And there's two
different possibilities
depending on how we
formulate the prediction
problem, depending
on how we define
the input to the problem.
If our problem is to classify
a pair of entity mentions
in a specific example in the
corpus, in a specific sentence,
then we can use the KB
to provide the label,
and this is what it looks like.
We have a corpus
example like this.
We're trying to label
this specific example.
And to do it, we can check to
see if these two entities are
related in the KB.
Yep, they are.
And we can use that to generate
a label for this example.
Labeling specific examples
is how the fully supervised
paradigm works.
So it's an obvious way
to think about leveraging
distance supervision as well.
It can be made to work,
but it's not actually
the preferred approach.
If we do it this way,
we'll be doing things
exactly as they're done in
the supervised paradigm.
It does work, but
it's not the best way
to take advantage
of the opportunity
that distance
supervision creates.
There's another way
of doing things,
and the other way is
where, instead, we
define our problem as
classifying a pair of entities.
Not entity mentions in a
specific sentence, but just
entities.
Elon_Musk and Tesla, period,
apart from any sentence.
And if that's how we define
the input to our problem,
then we can use the
corpus to provide
a feature
representation that will
be the input to the prediction.
So if we have an entity pair
like Elon_Musk and SpaceX
that we're considering adding
to a relation in the KB,
we can find all sentences
in the corpus containing
this pair of
entities, and then we
can use all of those sentences
to generate a feature
representation for this pair.
So in this example,
and I'm imagining--
it doesn't have to
be this way, but I'm
imagining that we're using a
simple bag of words feature
representation.
The bag of words has come
from the middle, that
is, the phrase
between the two entity
mentions, the blue phrases here.
And all I've done is
counted up the words
in all of these blue
phrases across all
of the examples in
the corpus where
these two entities co-occur.
Yeah.
Well, you can see here
in the token counts
that they include tokens
from the various examples.
All of these
examples together are
used to generate a single
feature representation.
This is a feature
representation for this pair,
and it's this feature
representation
that my learned model
will use to make
a prediction about this pair.
So this is a very interesting
way of reversing things.
Instead of using the
KB to generate a label
to make a prediction about
a specific pair of entity
mentions in a specific sentence,
I'm turning things around.
I'm using the corpus to generate
a feature representation that I
will use to make a
prediction about an entity
pair in abstraction,
an entity pair
considered just as
a pair of entities.
Just one more thought on this.
This is still kind of
about the topic of joining
the corpus and the KB.
We've created a
data set class which
does that, which combines
a corpus and a KB.
Just kind of staples
them together
and provides a variety
of convenience methods
for the dataset.
And one of those
convenience methods
is this one,
count_examples, which
shows, for each relation,
how many examples we have
in a corpus, how many
triples we have in a KB,
and the ratio, so
the total number
of examples, the average
number of examples per triple.
For most relations, the
total number of examples
is fairly large, so we can
be optimistic about learning
which linguistic patterns
express a given relation.
I mean, even the smallest one
has at least 1,500 examples.
That's not really
industrial grade data,
but it's certainly enough
for the kind of exploration
that we're doing here.
However, for individual entity
pairs, the number of examples
is often quite low.
So some of these
relations are betwee--
some of these ratios
are between 1 and 2.
Of course, more data would
be better, much better,
but more data could
quickly become
unwieldy to work with in a
notebook like this, especially
if you're running on
an ordinary laptop.
And this data is going to be
enough to allow us to have
a fruitful investigation.
First, I want to talk
about negative examples.
So by joining the
corpus to the KB,
we can get lots of positive
examples for each relation,
but we can't train a classifier
on positive examples alone.
We're also going to need
some negative examples,
negative instances.
So that is entity pairs that
don't belong to any relation.
We can find such
pairs by searching
the corpus for
examples which contain
two entities which don't belong
to any relation in the KB.
So we wrote some
code to do this,
and there's a method on
the dataset class called
find_unrelated_pairs.
And when we run it, wow.
It found almost 250,000
unrelated pairs,
so 250,000 negative instances
for our prediction problem.
And that's way more than the
number of positive instances.
If you remember, the
KB has 46,000 triples.
Each of those is basically
a positive instance.
It's something that we know is
definitely a positive example
of the relation.
Here, we have 250,000
negative examples.
It's so many more that
when we train models,
we'll wind up downsampling
the negative instances
substantially so that
we have a somewhat
more balanced distribution.
A reminder, though.
Some of these supposedly
negative instances
may be false negatives.
They may be entity pairs that
don't appear to be related,
but in the real
world, actually are.
Our KB is not complete.
A pair of entities might
be related in real life,
even if they don't
appear together in a KB.
And as I said earlier, after
all, that's the whole point.
That's the whole reason we're
doing relation extraction is
to find things that
are true in real life
and true according to some text
that somebody wrote, but aren't
yet in our KB.
OK, now I'm going to
come to the question that
was asked about pairs that
belong to multiple relations.
And this is related to the
question of the outputs
of our prediction problem.
We wrote some code to check
the KB for entity pairs
that belong to more
than one relation.
So that's this method
count_relation_combinations.
And it turns out, this is
a really common phenomenon
in the KB.
There are lots of pairs that
belong to multiple relations.
For example, I won't even
mention the most common one,
but there are 143 people in
the KB whose place of birth
is the same as their
place of death.
And actually, that's
not that surprising.
That makes perfect sense.
It even turns out that there's
no fewer than seven people who
married a sibling.
Well, since lots of
entity pairs belong
to more than one
relation, we probably
don't want to be forced to
predict a single relation.
So this suggests
formulating our problem
as multi-label classification.
We want our models to be able
to predict multiple relations
for any given entity pair.
There are a number
of ways to approach
multi-label classification,
but the most obvious
is the binary
relevance method, which
just factors multi-label
classification over n labels
into n independent
binary classification
problems, one for each label.
So if you have a pair
like Pericles and Athens,
you want to be able to
predict any combination
of these labels.
You just train a separate model,
a separate binary classifier,
for each of the
labels independently.
Each of them generates a
prediction independently.
And in this example,
we've predicted
that the place of
birth relation applies,
the place of death
relation applies, but not
the has_sibling relation.
A disadvantage of this
approach is that it fails to--
because it treats the binary
classification problems
as independent, it
fails to exploit
correlations between labels.
For example, there may
well be a correlation
between the place of birth label
and the place of death label.
And if you already have evidence
that the place of birth label
applies, that might tilt
you, at least a little bit,
toward saying yes
for place of death.
This approach of factoring
them into independent binary
classification problems
is not able to take
advantage of that information.
But it has the great
virtue of simplicity.
It's incredibly straightforward,
incredibly easy to think about
and to implement.
And it'll suffice
for our purposes.
It's going to make the
investigation move forward
very smoothly.
So I want to sum
up a little bit.
We set out to establish
a precise formulation
of our prediction problem.
And when we put all
the pieces together,
here's the problem
formulation we've arrived at.
The input to the prediction
will be an entity pair
and a candidate relation.
The output will be a Boolean
indicating whether the entity
pair belongs to the relation.
Since a KB triple is precisely
a relation and a pair
of entities, we could
say equivalently
that our prediction
problem amounts to binary
classification of KB triples.
Given a candidate KB
triple like worked_at,
Elon_Musk, SpaceX, do we
predict that it's valid?
This is really nice because
it's a very simple way
of thinking about what
problem we're taking on.
We have a bunch of
positive examples,
which come from our KB.
We have a bunch of negative
examples, which we synthesize
from the corpus using pairs
which co-occur in the corpus
but don't occur in the KB.
Now we have lots of data
consisting of candidate KB
triples, including positive
examples and negative examples.
We can use that data both for
training and for evaluation.
And once we've
trained a model to do
this binary
classification, we can now
consider novel KB triples
which don't appear anywhere
in our data, and ask
whether the model will
predict them to be true.
And by doing that, we may
discover new relations that
are not currently
part of the KB that
could be candidates for adding.