BILL MACCARTNEY: Last
time I introduced
the task of relation
extraction, I
described the corpus and the
KB that we're going to use.
And I proposed a
precise formulation
of our prediction problem.
So now, let's talk about how
we're going to measure success
on this problem.
We need to define a
quantitative evaluation that
can drive a process of
iterative development.
In this section, I'm going
to first make a connection
to the software
engineering principle
of test-driven development.
Then I'm going to
explain how we'll
split our data into training
and evaluation data.
I'll do a brief refresher
on precision, recall,
and F-measure.
And I'll review the distinction
between micro-averaging
and macro-averaging.
And by the end, we'll
know exactly how
we're going to measure success.
When you start working on a
new machine learning problem,
it's very tempting to jump in
and start building models right
away.
Because you're
bursting with ideas,
and you can't wait
to get started.
But whoa, Nelly.
That's like driving
cross-country without a map.
There's going to be lots
of forks in the road,
and you won't know
which way to go.
There's a better way.
In software engineering, we
use test-driven development.
First, write the tests,
and then write code
and iterate until
it passes the tests.
In model engineering, we
can use a similar paradigm.
First, implement a
quantitative evaluation.
Specify your evaluation dataset,
choose your evaluation metric,
build a test harness that takes
a model and generates a score.
Then when you start
building models,
you can hill-climb
on this score.
And at those forks
in the road where
you could do it this
way or that way,
your quantitative evaluation
will tell you which way to go.
Now, whenever we build
a model from data,
it's good practice
to partition the data
into multiple splits, minimally,
a training split and a test
split.
Actually, here we'll
go a bit further,
and we'll define
multiple splits.
First, we'll have a tiny split
with just 1% of the data.
Having a tiny split
is super useful,
and I encourage you to adopt
this practice whenever you
take on our prediction problem.
During the early
stages of development,
you can use the tiny split
as training data or test
data or both, and
your experiments
will run super fast.
Of course, your
quantitative evaluations
will be pretty much
meaningless, but it's
a great way to quickly flush
out any bugs in your setup.
Then we'll have the train
split with 74% of the data.
This is the data that we'll
usually use for model training.
Then the dev split,
with 25% of the data.
We'll use this as test data
for intermediate evaluations
during the development.
And for the bake-off, we're also
going to have a separate test
split, but you won't
have access to it,
so we won't talk about it here.
There's one complication.
We need to split both
the corpus and the KB.
We want each relation to
appear in both the training
data and the test data so that
we can assess how well we've
learned how each relation is
expressed in natural language.
But ideally, we'd like to
have any given entity appear
in only one split.
Otherwise, we might be leaking
information from the training
data into the test data.
In an ideal world,
each split would
have its own hermetically
sealed universe of entities,
and both the corpus and
the KB, for that split,
would refer only
to those entities.
So for example, you might have a
new world corpus whose examples
mention only new world
entities like Elon Musk
and Bill Gates and Steve Jobs,
and a new world KB, which
contains only triples about
the same new world entities,
and then an old world
corpus that talks
about Daniel Ek and
Jack Ma and Pony
Ma and a corresponding
old world KB.
If we had this, then
we could achieve
a really clean separation
between train and test data
with no overlap in entities.
But in practice, the world
is strongly entangled,
and this ideal is
hard to achieve.
So instead, we're going
to approximate the ideal.
I think I won't
dwell on the details,
but we've written
the code for you
to achieve a good enough split.
In particular, the
dataset class provides
a method called
build_splits which
lets you specify split names and
proportions and a random seed.
And it just returns a map from
split names to datasets each
containing a corpus and a KB.
So now that we
have our splits, we
need to choose an
evaluation metric.
We've formulated our problem
as binary classification,
and the standard metrics
for binary classification
are precision and recall.
So here's an example where we
have 100 problem instances.
The rows of this table
represent the actual labels.
88 are labeled false, and
only 12 are labeled true.
So this is a skewed
distribution.
The columns of this table
represent the labels
predicted by our model.
So 95 are predicted to
be false and 5 true.
Now, there are 89 instances
where the predicted label
agrees with the actual label.
So the accuracy of
this model is 89%.
But accuracy is not a
great evaluation metric,
especially when you have a
skewed distribution like this
because even a model
that ignores the data
and always guesses false
can get 88% accuracy
just by always guessing false.
So instead of accuracy,
we look at precision,
which says of the instances
that are predicted to be true,
what proportion
are actually true?
And recall, which says
of the instances which
are actually true,
what proportion
are predicted to be true?
So that's great.
Precision and recall
are really useful.
But having two evaluation
metrics is often inconvenient.
If we're considering a
change to our model which
improves precision but degrades
recall, should we take it?
In order to drive an
iterative development process,
it's useful to have a single
metric on which to hill-climb.
So for binary classification,
the standard answer
is the F1 score,
which is the harmonic
mean of precision and recall.
The harmonic mean is the
reciprocal of the arithmetic
mean, the average
of the reciprocals,
and it's always less
than the arithmetic mean.
It's pessimistic in a
sense that it's always
closer to the lower number.
So the arithmetic mean of
60% and 25% is-- sorry,
the harmonic mean of
60% and 25% is 35.3%.
Now, the F1 score
gives equal weight
to the precision and recall.
But depending on
the application,
they might not be
of equal importance.
In relation
extraction, we probably
care more about
precision than recall,
and that's because adding
an invalid triple to the KB
is more harmful than
failing to add a valid one.
So instead, we could
use the F-measure, which
is a generalization of F1.
It's a weighted harmonic
mean of precision and recall.
And this parameter beta controls
how much more importance
you place on recall
than on precision.
So let's say that in a
particular evaluation,
you have high precision,
80%, and low recall, 20%.
The F1 score gives equal
weight to precision and recall,
so its value is 32%.
If we set beta
equal to 0.5, we're
giving more weight to
precision, so the value is 50%.
If we set beta equal to 2, we're
giving more weight to recall,
so the value is 23.5%.
In relation
extraction, precision
is more important than
recall, so let's go with F 0.5
as our evaluation metric.
OK, another issue that comes
up in evaluation scenarios
like this is whether
to use micro-averaging
or macro-averaging.
We're going to compute
precision, recall, and F score
separately for each relation.
But in order to drive
iterative development,
we'd like to have summary
metrics, which aggregate
across all of the relations.
And there are two
possible ways to do this.
Micro-averaging
gives equal weight
to each problem
instance, which means
that it gives more weight to
relations with more instances.
Macro-averaging just gives
equal weight to each relation.
So let me show you an
illustration of this.
This is an artificial example
where I have just three
relations, and the
contains relation
has 10 times as many instances
as the other two relations.
It also has the highest F score.
When I compute the micro-average
and the macro-average,
well, the micro-average
gives equal weight
to each problem instance,
so it gives a lot
more weight to the
contains relation,
and the result is that
the micro-average F
score is very close to
the F score for contains.
Whereas the macro-average gives
equal weight to each relation,
and so it's just right in
the middle of this range.
The micro-averaged F
score is probably not
what we want because the number
of instances per relation
is kind of an accident of our
data collection methodology.
And it's not like we believe
that the contains relation is
more important than
the other relations.
It just happens to be
more numerous in the data
that we collected.
So we're going to
use macro-averaging
so that we don't
overweight large relations.
So if you put it all
together, the bottom line
is that with every
evaluation, we're
going to report lots of
metrics, but there's one metric
that we're going to focus on.
And this will be
our figure of merit.
It's the one number that we're
going to be hill-climbing on,
and we're choosing, as
our figure of merit,
the macro-averaged F 0.5 score.