CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is part 5 in our series
on analysis methods in NLP.
We're going to be talking about
feature attribution methods.
This is fundamentally
a powerful tool kit
for helping you understand
how the features in your model
contribute to its
output predictions.
Our fundamental question
here is, kind of,
why does your model make the
predictions that it makes?
There are many motivations
for asking this question,
here are just a few.
To start, you might
just want to understand
whether your model is
systematic with regard
to some specific
linguistic phenomenon.
Has it actually captured
that phenomenon?
You might also want
to know whether it's
robust to minor
perturbations in its input.
You might use these techniques
to diagnose unwanted biases
in your model.
And relatedly, you might
use them to find weaknesses
in your model that
an adversary could
exploit to lead your model to
do really problematic things.
Fundamentally, I think that
this is a tool kit that
will help you write
really excellent analysis
sections for your paper.
To that end, I'm going
to try to show you
a bunch of code that
will help you get hands
on with these techniques.
I'll do it at a kind of high
level in the screen cast.
And I've just contributed
this new notebook,
feature attribution, to
the course code repository.
And that should be
flexible and adaptable,
and help you take
these techniques
and apply them to
whatever models and ideas
you're exploring
for your projects.
The star of our show, really the
only reason that I can do this,
is this amazing
Captum.ai library.
It implements a wide range of
feature attribution techniques.
We're going to talk extensively
about the integrated gradients
method and use the
gradient-based method
as a kind of simple
baseline for that method.
But as you can see here,
Captum implements a wide range
of different
algorithms, some very
particular to specific model
designs and others completely
agnostic about what kind
of model you're exploring.
So it's a very
exciting tool kit.
The Sundararajan
et al 2017 paper
introduced the integrated
gradients method.
It's also a lovely contribution
because it gives us
a kind of framework for thinking
about feature attribution
methods in general.
And as part of that,
they offer two axioms
that I'm going to use to
guide this discussion.
The first, and the more
important one, is sensitivity.
If two inputs x and x prime
differ only at dimension i
and lead to different
predictions,
then the feature associated
with that dimension
must have non-zero attribution.
And with my simple
example here, you
can get a sense
for why sensitivity
is such a fundamental axiom.
If for some model m and three
dimensional input 1, 0, 1,
we get a prediction of positive.
And if for that same
model the input 1, 1, 1,
leads to the
prediction negative,
then we really ought to expect
that the feature associated
with the second position must
have non-zero attribution.
Because it must be decisive
in leading the model
to make these two
different predictions.
The second axiom
is going to be less
important to our discussion,
but it's nonetheless worth
having in mind.
It is implementation invariance.
If two models m and m prime
have identical input/output
behavior, then the
attributions for m and m prime
are identical.
This is really just saying
that the attributions we give
should be separate from any
incidental differences in model
implementation that don't
affect the input/output behavior
of that model.
To start our
discussion let's begin
with this simple baseline,
which is simply multiplying
the gradients by the inputs.
This is implemented
in Captum as input
by gradient that I'm
showing with respect
to some particular feature
i, given model M and input x.
And we simply get the
gradients for that feature
and then multiply it by the
actual value of that feature.
It's as simple as that.
Here are two implementations.
The first one in
cell 2 does this kind
of using raw PyTorch
just to show you
how we can use PyTorch's
autograd functionality
to implement this method.
And the second implementation
is from Captum.
And it's probably more flexible.
And it uses this input
by gradient class.
To give you a full
illustration here,
I've just set up a simple
synthetic classification
problem using scikit tools.
My model will be a
TorchShallowNeuralClassifier
which I fit on that data.
And then in cells 9 and 10, I
use those two implementations
of this method.
And you can see in
11 and 12, that they
give identical outputs.
Another thing worth
noting here is
that I have used the
method by taking gradients
with respect to the actual
labels in our data set.
You can often get
a different picture
if you take gradients
with respect
to the predictions
of that model.
And that might give
you a better sense
for why the model is making
the predictions that it makes.
In this case, since
the model is very good,
the attributions are
only slightly different.
That's our kind of baseline.
I want to show you now that
the input by gradients method
fails the sensitivity test.
And this is an example from
the Sundararajan et al paper.
They give this
simple model M here,
which is effectively just ReLU
applied to 1 minus the input.
And then you take 1 minus
that ReLU calculation there.
And that's the model.
It's got one dimensional
inputs and outputs.
If you calculate for input
0, you get an outcome of 0.
And if you give the model input
2, you get an output of 1.
Since we have differing
output predictions,
sensitivity tells
us that we have
to have differing
attributions for these two
cases here, these two
one dimensional inputs.
But unfortunately, when
you calculate through
with this method you get 0
attribution in both cases.
That's a failure of
sensitivity and points
to a weakness of this method.
Let's move now to
integrated gradients.
And let me start by giving
you the intuition for how
this method is going to work.
Imagine we have a simple two
dimensional feature space,
feature x1 and x2.
So here's the actual
point represented here.
The idea behind
integrated gradients
is that we're going to
compare that with respect
to some baseline.
That typical baseline for us
will be the all 0s vector.
And then to do the comparison
what we'll actually do
is interpolate a bunch of
points between that baseline
and our actual input, take
gradients with respect
to each one of them, and average
all of those gradient results.
And that will give us some
measure of future importance.
Here's the calculation of
the method in full detail.
I've taken this presentation
from this really excellent
tutorial from TensorFlow
integrated gradients.
It does all these annotations
that I find quite helpful.
Here's fundamentally
how this works.
The core thing is in purple.
We're going to
interpolate a bunch
of different inputs
between that baseline
of all 0s and our actual input.
That's what's happening here.
And we'll take the
gradients with respect
to each one of
those with respect
to each one of the features.
And we're going to sum
those up and average them.
And that gives us the
core calculation here.
And then in 5, we just kind of
scale that resulting average
with respect to the
original input to put it
back on the same scale.
And as I showed here,
integrated gradients
obeys the sensitivity axiom.
Let's go back to
that original example
of that simple ReLU-based
model presented here.
I showed you that the
input by gradients method
failed sensitivity
for this model.
Integrated gradients
of course is
sensitive in the relevant sense.
And you can kind
of see why that's
happening, because our
core calculation now
is not with respect
to a single input,
in the case of the input
2, but rather with respect
to all of those interpolated
feature representations.
Although some of those
interpolated feature
representations give a gradient
of 0 not all of them do.
And the result in
effect is that you'll
get a feature attribution
of approximately 1
for this case of an input 2.
The desired result
showing sensitivity,
because of course the
input of 0 in this case
would give an attribution of 0.
Now let me walk you through
a few examples that show you
how you can use Captum to get
hands on with the integrated
gradients method.
And I'm going to do that
for two classes of model.
The first one is just a
simple feed-forward network.
And what I'm doing is
reconnecting with the Stanford
Sentiment Treebank that we
used during our sentiment unit.
So on this slide, I've just
set up an SST experiment
using sst.experiment
from that SST module.
My feature
representations are going
to be essentially
a bag of words.
And I've filtered off stop
words to make this a little more
interpretable.
And our classifier is a
TorchShallowNeuralClassifier.
I run the experiment
and a lot of information
about that experiment,
you'll recall,
is stored in this
variable, experiment.
Here I extract the model
from that experiment report.
And here, we get a
bunch of other metadata
that we're going to use to run
the IntegratedGradients method.
The feature representations
of our test examples,
the actual labels, and
the predictive labels,
along with the feature names.
And the one thing to note here
is that for the sake of Captum,
we need to turn the
string class names
into their
corresponding indices.
And that's what's
happening in cell 9 here.
Then we set up the
integrated gradients
using the forward
method for our model.
And we set up the baseline,
which is that all 0s vector.
And then finally use
the attribute method.
And here I'm taking
attributions with respect
to the predictions of the model.
I think this can be a
powerful device for doing
some simple error analysis.
And that's what I've set
up on this slide here.
I've offered two
functions, error analysis
and create attribution
lookup that
will help you understand
how features in this model
are relating to its
output predictions.
You can see in cell
14 here, I'm looking
for cases where the
actual label is neutral
and the model
predicted positive.
We can find those attributions.
And this is actually an
informative picture here.
It looks like the model
has overfit to features
like the period and the comma.
This ought to be indicative
of the neutral category.
But here it's using
them in ways that
lead to a positive prediction.
So that's something that
we might want to address.
And we can go one level
further if we choose and look
at individual examples.
So here I have pulled out
an individual example.
"No one goes
unindicted here, which
is probably for the best."
This is a case where the
correct label is neutral.
And our model
predicted positive.
And I think the
attributions again
help us understand
why because by far
the feature with the highest
attribution is this "best" one.
And this is revealing that
the model just does not
understand the context in
which the word "best" is
used in this example.
That might point to a
fundamental weakness
of the bag of words approach.
For my second
example let's connect
with transformer models, since
I assume that a lot of you
will be working
with these models.
And these present
exciting new opportunities
for feature attribution.
Because in these models, we
have so many representations
that we could think about
doing attributions for.
Here's a kind of general picture
of a BERT-like model, where
I have the outputs up here.
You have many layers of
transformer block outputs.
Those are given in purple and
probably an embedding layer
in green.
And that embedding layer
might be itself composed
of like a word-embedding layer
and a positional embedding
layer, and maybe others.
All of these layers
are potential targets
for integrated gradients.
And Captum again makes
that relatively easy.
So to start this off, I just
downloaded from HuggingFace
a RoBERTa-based
Twitter sentiment model
that seemed really interesting.
And I wrote a
predict_one_proba method
that will help us with the error
analysis that we want to do.
This next step here
does the encodings
of both the actual example,
using the model's tokenizer
as well as the
baseline of all 0s
that we'll use for comparisons.
In cell 7, I've just designed
a small custom forward method
to help Captum out,
because this model
has slightly different output
structure than is expected.
Here in cell 8, we set up the
layer that we want to target.
And as you can see I'm
targeting the embedding layer.
But many other layers
could be targeted.
Captum makes that easy.
For our example, we use,
"This is illuminating!"
which I'll take to have
true class positive.
We do our encodings in cell
11 of both the actual example
and the baseline.
And then that's the
basis for our attribution
of this single example.
Now for BERT, because
we have high dimensional
representations for
each one of the tokens
that we're looking
at, we need to perform
another layer of
compression that we
didn't have to for the
feed-forward example.
As you can see here,
the attributions
have for one example
dimensionality 6 by 768.
This is one vector
per word token.
To summarize those at the level
of individual word tokens,
we'll just sum them
up and then z-score
normalize them to kind of put
them on a consistent scale.
So that will reduce
the attributions down
to one per sub-word token.
And that feeds into our final
kind of cumulative analysis.
So we'll do the
probabilistic predictions,
look at the actual class,
convert the input to something
that Captum can digest, and
then use this visualization data
recorder method to
bring this all together
into a nice tabular
visualization.
And that's what's
happening here.
You can see, for example,
we have the True Label,
the Predicted Label with
the associated probability.
And then the really interesting
part, per word token,
we have a summary
of its attributions.
And you can see that
green is associated
with positive, white with
neutral, and red with negative.
And this is giving us
a reassuring picture
about the systematicity
of these predictions.
It's a positive prediction.
And most of that is the result
of the word "illuminating"
and the exclamation mark.
And that kind of
feeds into a nice kind
of error
analysis/challenge analysis
that you can do with models
like this using Captum.
For this slide here, I've
posed a little challenge
or adversarial test to see how
deeply my model understands
sentences like, "They
said it would be great
and they were right."
You can see it makes the
correct prediction in that case.
And when I change it to,
"They said it would be great
and they were wrong.",
it predicts negative.
That's reassuring, and so
are the future attributions.
It seems to be keying
into exactly the pieces
of information that I would
hope and even doing it
in a context sensitive way.
For the next two
examples, I just
change up the syntax
to see whether it's
kind of overfit to the position
of these words in the string.
And it again looks robust.
"They were right to say
that it would be great."
Prediction of positive.
"They were wrong to say
that it would be great."
Prediction of negative.
Very reassuring.
As is the second
to last example,
"They said it would be stellar
and they were correct."
The only disappointing thing
in this challenge problem
is for this final example
it predicts neutral
for, "They said it
would be stellar
and they were incorrect."
And the attributions are
also a little bit worrisome
about the extent to
which the model has truly
understood this example.
Maybe we can think about
how to address that problem.
But the fundamental
takeaway for now
is simply that you can see how
you can use feature attribution
together with challenge
examples to kind of home
in on exactly how systematic
a model's predictions are
for an interesting
class of cases.