CHRIS POTTS: Welcome, everyone.
This is part three in our
series on methods and metrics.
We're going to be
talking about metrics
for assessing natural
language generation systems.
We previously talked
about classifier metrics,
and the issues seem
relatively straightforward.
As you'll see,
assessment for NLG
systems is considerably
more difficult.
Let's actually begin with
those fundamental challenges.
Maybe the most
fundamental of all
is that in natural
language, there
is more than one effective
way to say most things.
The datasets we
have might have one
or a few good examples of
how something should be said.
But that's just a sample of
the many ways in which we
could communicate effectively.
And that leaves us with
fundamental open questions
about what comparisons
we should make
and how we should assess
so-called mistakes.
Relatedly, there's
just an open question
of what we're actually
trying to measure.
Is it fluency?
Or truthfulness?
Or communicative effectiveness?
Or some blend of the three?
As we think about
different metrics,
we might find that
they capture one
or a few of these and
completely neglect others
and that's sure to
shape the trajectory
of our project and the
actual goals that we achieve.
So we have to be really
thoughtful about what
we're actually trying to
measure in this space.
Let's begin with perplexity.
I would say what
perplexity has going
for it is that it is at
least very tightly knit
to the structure of
many of the models
that we work with in NLG.
So the core calculation
is that given
some sequence x of length n, and
a probability distribution p,
the perplexity of x relative
to that distribution
is the product of the inverse of
all the assigned probabilities.
And then we take
an average here.
There are many ways to express
this calculation and many ways
to connect with information
theoretic measures.
Let me defer those
issues for just a second,
and I'll try to build up an
intuition just after getting
through the core calculation.
So that's perplexity.
And then when we do
token-level perplexity, right,
we want to assign perplexity
to individual examples,
we need to normalize by the
length of those examples.
And we do that in
log space in order
to capture the kind of
geometric mean, which
is arguably more appropriate for
comparing probability values.
And then if we
want the perplexity
for an entire corpus, we
again use a geometric mean
of all the token-level
perplexity predictions.
And that gives us a single
quantity over an entire batch
of examples.
What are the properties
of perplexity?
Well its bounds are 1 to
infinity with 1 the best,
so we would like to
minimize perplexity.
It is equivalent to
the exponentiation
of the cross-entropy loss.
That's the tight
connection with models
that I wanted to call out.
We often work with
language models
that use a cross-entropy loss.
And you can see that
they are directly
optimizing for a quantity that
is proportional to perplexity.
Now that can be useful
as a kind of getting
a direct insight into the nature
of your model's predictions.
What value does it encode?
Well I think it's simple.
Does the model assign
high probability
to the input sequences?
That is, does it
assign low perplexity
to the input sequences?
The weaknesses, there
are many actually.
First, it's heavily dependent
on the underlying vocabulary.
To see that,
imagine an edge case
where we take every
word in the vocabulary
and map it to a
single UNK token.
In that case, we will
absolutely minimize perplexity,
but our system will be useless.
In that edge case, you can see
that I could reduce perplexity
simply by changing the
size of my vocabulary.
That's a way that you
could kind of game
this metric inadvertently.
As a result of that,
we can't really
make comparisons across
datasets because of course they
could have different
vocabularies
and different intrinsic
notions of perplexity.
And it's also even tricky to
make comparisons across models.
You can see that in my
first weakness there.
If we do compare models,
we need to fix the data set
and make sure that the
differences between the models
are not inherently shaping
the range of perplexity values
that we're likely to see.
Let's move on now
into a family of what
you might think of as
n-gram based methods
for assessing NLG
systems, beginning
with the word-error rate.
So the fundamental thing
here will be an edit distance
measure.
And therefore you can
see word-error rate
as a kind of family
of measures depending
on the choice of the edit
distance function, which
we would just plug in.
The word error rate
is the distance
between the actual sequence
x and some predicted
sequence pred normalized by the
length of the actual sequence.
And if we would like
the word-error rate
for an entire corpus,
it's easy to scale it up,
but there's one twist here.
The way that's
standardly calculated
is that the numerator
is the sum of all
the distances between the
actual and predicted sequences.
Not normalized as it was up
here for the word error rate.
The normalization that happens
over the entire corpus,
it's the sum of all the
lengths of the actual strings
in the corpus.
So we have one
average as opposed
to taking an
average of averages.
The properties of
the word error rate.
Its bounds are 0
to infinity, and we
would like to minimize
it, so 0 is the best.
The value encoded is
similar to F scores.
We would like to
answer the question,
how aligned is the
predicted sequence
with the actual sequence.
And I've invoked F scores here
because if our edit distance
measure has notions of
insertion and deletion,
they play roles that are
analogous to precision
and recall.
The weaknesses.
Well first, we have just
one reference text here.
I called out before that
there are often many good ways
to say something,
whereas here we can
make only a single comparison.
And it's also, maybe
this is more fundamental,
word error rate is a
very syntactic notion.
Just consider comparing
text like, it was good,
it was not good,
and it was great.
They're likely to have
the identical word error
rates, even though the first
two differ dramatically
in their meanings and
the first and the third
are actually rather
similar in their meanings.
That semantic
notion of similarity
is unlikely to be reflected
in the word-error rate.
Let's move now to BLEU scores.
This is another
n-gram based metric,
but it's going to try to
address the fact that we want
to make comparisons against
multiple human-created
reference texts.
It has a notion of
precision in it,
but it's called modified
n-gram precision.
Let me walk you
through an example
and hopefully that
will motivate.
Imagine we have
the candidate that
had just seven instances
of the word the" in it.
And we have two reference texts,
presumably written by humans.
The cat is on the mat.
And there is a cat on the mat.
The modified precision
takes for the token "the."
The maximum number
of times that "the"
occurs in any reference text,
and that's 2 with reference 1
here.
And it divides that
by the number of times
that "the" appears in the
candidate, which is 7.
That would give us 2 over 7
as the modified n-gram 1-gram
precision score
for this candidate.
There's also a
brevity penalty, which
will play the role of
something like recall
in the BLEU scoring.
So we have a
quantity r, which is
the sum of all the
minimal absolute length
differences between
candidates and reference.
We have c, which is the total
length of all the candidates.
And then we said that
the brevity penalty is 1
if c is greater than r.
Otherwise, it's an
exponential decay
off of the ratio of r and c.
And again, that will play
kind of the notion of recall.
And then the BLEU
score is simply
the product of that
brevity penalty
with the sum of the weighted
modified n-gram precision
values for each n-gram
value n considered.
So we probably go 1 through 4.
That's a standard set
of n-grams to consider.
We would sum up all of
those notions of modified
n-gram precision for each n.
And possibly weight
them differently
depending on how we want
to value 1-grams, 2-grams,
3-grams, and 4-grams.
So that's the BLEU scoring.
What are its properties?
Its bounds are 0 and 1.
And 1 is the best.
But we have really
no expectation
that any system will
actually achieve 1
because even comparisons
among human translations
or human created text will
not have a BLEU score of 1.
The value encoded is
an appropriate balance
of modified precision and
recall under the guise
of that brevity penalty.
It's very similar to the
word-error rate in that sense,
but it seeks to accommodate the
fact that there are typically
multiple suitable outputs
for a given input.
And that's a real
strength of BLEU score.
The weaknesses.
Well, this team has argued
that BLEU scores just
fail to correlate with human
scores for translations.
And that's kind of worrying,
because BLEU scores
were originally motivated in the
context of machine translation.
And the issues
that they identify
are like it's very sensitive
to n-gram order in a way
that human intuitions
are not and it's
insensitive to the
type of the n-grams.
So again, just
consider comparisons
like that dog, the
dog, and that toaster.
Those will likely have
very similar BLEU scores,
but that dog and the dog are
just inherently much more
similar than that dog and that
toaster in virtue of the fact
that that and the,
it's just a difference
at the level of
functional vocabulary,
versus dog and toasters, a
really contentful change.
And then as we move into topics
that are more closely aligned
with NLU, could possibly have
an even more worrying picture.
So this team argues that BLEU is
just a fundamentally incorrect
measure for assessing
dialogue systems.
And that could be an
indicator that it's not
going to be appropriate for
many kinds of NLG tasks in NLU.
That's just a sample of
two n-gram based metrics.
I thought I'd mention
a few more to give you
a framework for making
some comparisons.
So I mentioned the
word-error rate.
That's fundamentally
edit distance
from a single reference text.
BLEU, as we've seen,
is modified precision
and a brevity penalty.
Kind of recall motion comparing
against many reference texts.
ROUGE is a recall
focused variant of BLEU
that's focused on assessing
summarization systems.
METEOR is interestingly
different,
because it's trying to push
past simple n-gram matching
and capture some
semantic notions.
It's a unit gram
based measure that
does an alignment measure
between not only exact matches
of the unit grams, but also stem
versions and synonyms really
trying to bring in
some semantic aspects.
And CIDEr is similar.
This is going to be even a more
semantic notion, because it's
going to do its comparisons
in vector space.
It's kind of approximately
a weighted cosine
similarity between
TF-IDF vectors created
from the corpus.
Finally, in closing,
I just wanted
to exhort you all to think
about more communication based
metrics in the context of NLU.
For NLU, it's worth asking
whether you can evaluate
your system based on how
well it actually communicates
in the context of a real
world goal as opposed
to just comparing
different strings that
are inputs and reference texts.
And we've actually
seen an example
of that in our assignment and
bake off on color reference.
We didn't really assess
how well your system
could reproduce the utterances
that were in the corpus.
Rather, our fundamental
notion was listener accuracy,
which was keying into
a communication goal.
How well is your system actually
able to take messages and use
them to figure out what the
speaker was referring to
in a simple color context?
And for much more on
that, and a perspective
on a lot of these
issues, I encourage
you to check out this paper
that was led by Ben Newman.
It began as a course
project for this class
and grew into a really
successful paper.