CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to the first
screencast in our series
on presenting your research.
The purpose of this
series is really
to help you do
outstanding scholarship
in the field of NLP.
And I'm also going to try
to demystify publishing
in the field of NLP.
To kick it off, I'd like to
focus on the final papers
that you're writing
specifically for this course.
Here are some practical details.
These links take you
to essential things
about writing final papers,
specifically for CS224U.
The first link is possibly
the most important.
That just enumerates
the requirements
for the final paper.
Please do review it to make sure
that you don't get points off
for something small
that could easily
have been corrected just
because you didn't conform
to our requirements.
The next two links are
much more about helping you
with the substance of this.
So the projects file has lots
of frequently asked questions
and other information
about writing
final papers for this course.
And it also expands out to
publishing in the field of NLP.
So it has a lot of
useful resources
when it comes to
trying to report out
your research to the community.
And then this third
link here links
to some excellent
past final projects.
Many of them became publications
typically after a bunch
of additional work after
the end of the quarter,
but it is exciting that a
lot of these really excellent
published papers
began in this course.
It's very inspiring.
For your projects, I
just want to review
a really important point
for me that concerns
how we'll evaluate your work.
This is from the methods
unit for the course,
but I want to repeat it
here just to emphasize it.
We will never evaluate
a project based
on how good the results are.
We do recognize
that in our field,
as in all scientific
fields, publications
tend to do this because they
have additional constraints
on space.
And that leads them,
as a cultural fact,
to favor positive evidence
for new developments
over negative results.
But we, of course, are not
subject to such constraints.
So we can do the
right and good thing
scientifically of
valuing positive results,
negative results, and
everything in between.
This has real consequences for
how we do evaluation, right?
We're going to evaluate
your project based
on the appropriateness of
the metrics that you chose,
the strength of the
methods that you used,
and maybe most
importantly, the extent
to which your paper
is open and clear
sighted about the
limitations of its findings.
Those are the things that really
matter for us scientifically.
And it is a consequence
of this policy
that you could have
a paper that reported
state of the art results.
But if it's just not a
clear and substantive paper,
it might not get very
good marks from us.
And conversely, if all of
your hypotheses fell apart
and it turned out that all
your evidence pointed away
from them as being true,
but you nonetheless
wrote a paper that was
clear about those findings
and helped push the field
forward by steering us away
from those hypotheses, that, of
course, could earn top marks.
And we'd be very happy to
help you report those results
out to the rest of the field.
Because it is important
for us to know
about these negative
findings so that we
know where to invest
our energy as scholars.
Here's a detail that's
from the requirements
for the final paper.
This is the
authorship statement.
This is just a section
where you explain
how the individual authors
from your team and anyone
else who helped out contributed
to the final project.
You're free to say whatever
you like in these sections.
If you would like
a model, here's
a link to the PNAS guidelines,
which give some details
and kind of typical statements.
The rationale is
really just that we
think this is an
important aspect
of such scholarship in general.
And it's not yet pervasive
in the field of NLP,
whereas it is in other fields.
But we would like it to be more
widespread, because it just
seems like a healthy
form of disclosure.
That's the real rationale.
I want to emphasize that
only in really extreme cases
and after discussion with
all the team members would
we consider giving
separate grades to the team
based on what was
in the statement.
This is really not the intent.
The intent rather
is this rationale
of just disclosing who did
what as part of the project.
It's really not
about evaluation.
I also want to
emphasize that we have
a policy on multiple
submissions for this course.
It's nuanced and subjective.
Here's a link to it.
And here are some notes,
kind of rationale for this.
So first, the policy mirrors the
policy on multiple submissions
to conferences, right?
You can't take the same
paper and submit it
to two different venues
with minor modifications
and expect to get two
publications out of it.
And the same thing
holds for us when
we think about requirements for
final papers for this course.
This is designed to ensure
that your project is
a substantial new effort.
This does mean that
you can't merely
submit an incremental
advancement
over another project
that you did.
We are trying to push
back against the pattern
where people would take final
projects from previous courses,
add a couple of new
models, and submit
those as entirely new papers.
That's just unfair to the people
who are starting from scratch.
And it's really not
the sort of work
that we would say is up to
the level of a final project
for a course like this.
Other courses might have
different policies at Stanford,
but that fact alone
is not going to lead
us to change our policy.
Because we do think
that this is equitable
and also reflecting values
that are pervasive in our field
as you can see from the policies
on submission to conferences.
If any of these policies
seem relevant to your work,
for example, if you are taking
a previous course project
and developing it in lots
of fresh and new ways,
start the discussion
with your mentor
as early as possible
to make sure
that they're in the loop
about what you're doing.
We don't want any surprises
when you submit your final paper
or after that when it
comes to this policy.
So just make sure
everyone is in the know,
and I predict that
things will go fine.
To close, a brief note
about impact statements.
For now, an impact statement
is an optional section
for your final paper.
Absolutely not required.
But this has been on
my mind a lot lately,
and I think it's really
healthy that the field is
moving toward having authors
include impact statements.
And so I thought I
would exhort you all
to consider having that as part
of your final paper as well.
It does not count against
your length limits,
and it's up to you exactly
what you would disclose
as part of the statement.
Here are some examples of
things that might include.
You could try to enumerate
both the benefits and the risks
of your research to individuals,
to society, to the world.
Specifically for the risk, you
could talk about costs, again,
to the participants, to
society, to the planet,
where, for example,
participant costs would
be if you had human
annotators doing
a really difficult or kind of
negative annotation project.
You might mention that
they paid a certain cost
and think about whether
the costs were worthwhile.
You could also think
about costs to society,
and that would
really probably turn
on sort of misapplication
of your ideas
in ways that might have
more harm than good.
And, of course, if you trained
a really large language model
or did really a
lot of experiments,
you could think about the
cost to the planet in terms
of energy expenditures,
and so forth.
Just by way of getting us
all to think about the fact
that our research
does have costs
and that we should all the
time be thinking about the cost
benefit analysis when it
comes to the work that we do.
And these disclosures are
part of helping us all
have that in mind.
And finally, I think it
might be really inspiring
for you to think about
responsible use of your data
models and findings.
Never mind really evil actors.
There are likely to be
people out there who
are well-meaning and would
like to apply your ideas,
but they might be
unsure of the limits.
Unsure of precisely how
to do that responsibly.
So guidance that you could offer
about where your ideas work
and where they don't, or
where your data are relevant
and where they're
irrelevant could really
help someone who is
trying to just make
responsible use of your ideas.
You could think about them as
part of crafting this impact
statement.
For other resources, I
think it's really great
to go through the exercise of
doing a data sheet and a model
card.
A data sheet is a
disclosure about a data
set that you created or used.
And a model card is a
similar unstructured document
for models that you've
developed and released out
into the world.
They're both pretty
long documents.
So it's a lot of work
to do one in full,
but it's very
rewarding in the sense
that it helps you confront
some hard truths about the work
that you did and articulate
the limits of the work
that you did.
All these things are really
helpful for your scholarship.
And, of course, these
things are helpful when
it comes to other people
consuming your ideas.
So that's highly encouraged.
And you could take
bits and pieces
from those structured
documents and have them
in for maybe a shorter impact
statement that you wrote.
And for even more
guidance on this,
you could check out this survey
of NeurlPS impact statements.
It has a lot of information
about the kinds of things
people are disclosing
in these statements.
And that too could
help you kind of figure
out what you want to
say and what might
be relevant to your audience.
So again, this is
entirely optional,
but I hope this is inspiring
and interesting for you
as a new dimension when it
comes to reporting on the work
that you did.