Hello. We hope you found this course to be enjoyable and rewarding.
Now that we're wrapping up,
your thoughts might be turning to how you can build on what
you've learned to conduct original research,
to develop new technologies,
and so much more.
The material should position you really well to do this.
The models for word representations that we discussed are
likely to be valuable components for any task you take on.
Our relation extraction unit focused on powerful techniques for distant supervision,
which is a really common mode for applied problems.
And the natural language inference unit is
representative of the kind of opportunities and
challenges one faces when building deep learning systems with really large data sets.
And of course, the other lectures highlight
more diverse application areas and help reveal
how even complex cutting edge models are actually
usually made up of familiar modular components.
And of course, by now you've done a lot of work with our notebooks,
you've designed three original systems and entered them into bake-offs,
and you've completed an original project.
This is an unusually high level of hands-on work,
and the practical skills you've acquired should serve you well in many domains.
The field of NLU continues to progress rapidly,
and you're now extremely well-positioned to
follow those changes and even help to shape them.
For our part, we'll continue to update and improve
our NLU course materials, and share them widely.
And we hope to see you in a future Stanford class soon.