CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome back, everyone.
This is part 4 on our
series on distributed word
representations.
We're going to be talking about
basical reweighting schemes.
Essentially, I feel
like we've been
faithful to the underlying
counts of our matrices
for too long.
It's time to start
messing with them.
Here are some high-level goals
that we have for reweighting.
And we would like
in these matrices
to amplify the
associations that are
important and trustworthy and
unusual while correspondingly
deemphasizing the things
that are mundane or quirky
or reflect errors or
idiosyncrasies in the data
that we use.
Now, of course, absent the
defined objective function
of the machine-learning sense.
This is going to
remain a fuzzy goal,
but we do have some
quantitative hooks, I think.
We have this guiding
intuition that we
would like to move
away from raw counts
because frequency
alone is generally
a poor proxy for the kind
of semantic information
that we hope to extract.
So we can ask for each of
the reweighting schemes
that we consider,
first, how does
it compare to the
underlying raw count values?
If the scheme is just rescaling
the underlying counts,
it's probably not
worth the effort.
On the other hand,
if it gives us
a very different
distribution, then
at least we know that
we're cooking with fire
when it comes to moving
away from raw frequency.
There's a related
question that I
would like us to
have in mind, what
is the overall
distribution of values
that the reweighting
scheme delivers?
Count distributions are
very skewed in a way that
can make them difficult
to deal with for lots
of analytic and
machine-learning methods.
So we might hope that in
reweighting, in addition
to capturing things
that are important
and deemphasizing
things that are mundane,
would also give us an overall
distribution of values
that was more tractable for
these downstream applications.
And then finally
I personally have
a goal that we would like
to do, no feature selection
based on counts or
outside resources
like stopword dictionaries.
I don't want to be filtering
off parts of the vocabulary
a priori, because
for all I know,
something that's a boring
stopword for one genre is
actually an important
content word for another.
We would like the method to
sort of make that decision.
So let's start with
the most basic scheme.
And this is a scheme that
will pay attention only
to the row context.
This is normalization.
So this is actually a repeat
from the lecture on vector
comparison L2 norming.
We've calculated the
L2 length as a fixed
quantity for each row vector.
And then the length
normalization
of that row vector
is just taking
each value in the
original vector
and dividing it by that fixed
quantity of the L2 lengths.
There's a related, and
perhaps more familiar
notion, which I've called
probability distribution where
we follow the same logic.
We just replace that
normalizing constant,
the L2 length with
the sum of all
the elements in the vectors.
But again we do this
element-wise division
by that fixed
quantity to normalize
the vector into a
probability distribution.
I think both of these
methods can be powerful,
but the shame of them is that
they are paying attention only
to the row context.
For a given cell, IJ,
we're looking just
across the row I. We're not
considering the context that
could come from the
column J. So let's begin
to correct that omission.
Here is kind of the star of
our show in the quiet sense.
This is the first scheme we'll
look at that pays attention
to both row and column context.
This is observed over expected.
Let's just go through
this notation here.
We have the row sum.
I think that's intuitive.
Correspondingly, the
column sum, the sum of all
values along the column.
And then the sum for
some matrix x is just
the sum of all the cell
values in that matrix.
Those are the raw materials
for calculating what's
called the expected value.
The expected value given
a matrix x for cell i, j
is the rowsum
times the columnsum
as the numerator divided
by the sum of all
the values in the matrix.
This is an expected quasi count.
It is giving us the
number we would expect
if the row and column were
independent of each other
in the statistical sense.
And that's the sense in
which this is an expectation.
The observed over expected
value simply compared
the observed value in the
numerator by that expected
value.
So in a bit more detail, here's
how the calculations work.
We've got this tiny
little count matrix here.
Let's look at cell XA.
It's got a count of 34.
That's our observed count
over here in the numerator.
The denominator is the
product of the rowsum
and the columnsum,
45 by 81 divided
by the sum of all the values
in this matrix, which is 99.
We repeat that calculation
for all the other cells,
making the corresponding
adjustments,
and that gives us a
completely reweighted matrix.
Here's the intuition.
That was the calculation.
Let's think about why we
might want to do this.
So I've got here a highly
idealized little count matrix.
And the conceit of this example
is that "keep tabs" in English
is an idiom.
And otherwise, the
word "tabs" alone
doesn't appear with
many other words.
It's kind of constrained
to this idiomatic context.
So we get a really high
count for "keep tabs"
and a relatively low
count for "enjoy tabs"
again because "tabs" doesn't
really associate with the word
"enjoy."
On the right here, I've got
the expected calculation.
And it comes out just
like we would hope.
The expected count for
"keep tabs" is mere 12.48%,
compare that with the
observed count of 20.
"Keep tabs" is overrepresented
relative to our expectations
in virtue of the fact that the
independence assumption built
into the expected calculation
is just not met here because
of the collocational effect.
Similarly, the expected count
for "enjoy tabs" is 8.5.
That's much larger
than our observation,
again because these are
kind of disassociated
with each other in virtue of
the restricted distribution
of tabs.
And that brings us to
really the star of our show,
and in fact the star of a lot
of the remainder of this unit.
This is pointwise mutual
information, or PMI.
PMI is simply observed
over expected in log-space
where we stipulate
that the log of 0 is 0.
In a bit more detail for
matrix x, given cell i, j,
the PMI value is the
log of the observed
count over the expected count.
And that's it.
Many people find it
more intuitive to think
of this in probabilistic terms.
That's what I've done
over here on the right.
It's equivalent numerically, but
for this kind of calculation,
we first form a joint
probability table
by just dividing all the cell
values by the total number
of values in all the cells.
That gives us the
joint probability table
and then the row probability
and the column probability
are just summing across the row
and the column respectively.
And again we multiply them.
And that's kind of
nice, because then you
can see we really are testing
an independence assumption.
It's as though we say we can
multiply these probabilities
because they're independent.
If the distribution
is truly independent,
that ought to match
what we observed.
And of course discrepancies
are the things
that these matrices
will highlight.
Let's look at an example.
And there's one
thing that I want
to track because we work
through this example.
And that's the cell down
here, this lonely little 1.
So this is a count matrix.
I've got this as a word
by document matrix.
This is a very flexible
method, and we apply
to lots of matrix designs.
Over here, I form the
joint probability table.
And I've got here the columnsum
and the rowsum corresponding
to the column and
row probability.
These are the raw ingredients
for the PMI matrix, which
is derived down here by
applying this calculation to all
of these values.
Notice what's
happened, that lonely 1
down here because it's in a very
infrequent row and a relatively
infrequent column.
It has the largest PMI value
in the resulting matrix.
Now that could be
good, because this
could be a very important
event, in which case
we want to amplify it.
On the other hand,
NLP being what it is,
this could be just a mistake
in the data or something.
And then this
exaggerated value here
could turn out to
be problematic.
It's difficult to
strike this balance.
But it's worth keeping in mind
as you work with this method
that it could amplify not
only important things but also
idiosyncratic things.
Positive PMI is an important
variant of PMI, so important,
in fact, that I
would like to think
of it as the kind
of default view
that we take on PMI for
the following reason.
PMI is actually undefined where
the count is 0, because we
need to take the log of 0.
So we had to stipulate
that the log of 0
was 0 for this calculation.
However, that's
arguably not coherent
if you think about what the
underlying matrix represents.
What we're saying with
PMI is that larger
than expected values
get a large PMI.
Smaller than expected
values get a smaller PMI.
That's good.
But when we encounter a 0, we
place it right in the middle.
And that's just strange
because a 0 isn't evidence
of anything larger or smaller.
It doesn't deserve to be
in the middle of this.
If anything, we just don't know
what to do with the 0 values.
So this is arguably
sort of incoherent,
and the standard
response to it is
to simply turn all of the
negative values into 0.
And that's positive PMI
that's defined here.
So we simply lop off
all the negative values
by mapping them to 0.
And that at least restores
the overall coherence
of the claims where
all we're doing
is reflecting the fact that
larger than expected counts
have large positive PMI
and the rest are put in 0.
Let's look briefly at a few
other reweighting schemes,
starting with the t-test.
The t-test is
something that you work
with on the first
assignment to implement it.
It turns out to be a very
good reweighting scheme.
And I like it because
it obviously reflects
many of the same intuitions
that guide the PMI
and observed over
expected calculations.
TF-IDF is quite different.
So this is typically
performed on word
by document matrices in
the context of information
retrieval.
Given some corpus
of documents D,
we're going to say that the
term frequency for a given cell
is that value divided by
the sum of all the values
in the column, giving us
the kind of probability
of the word given the
document that we're in.
And then the IDF value is the
log of this quantity here.
This is the number of
documents in our corpus
that is the column
dimensionality divided
by the number of documents
that contain the target word.
And again we met log of 0 to 0.
The TF-IDF is the product
of those two values.
I think this can be
an outstanding method
for very large sparse matrices,
like the Word Document one.
Conversely it is typically
not well-behaved for very
dense matrices, like
the word-by-word ones
that we were favoring
in this course.
The reason, this is IDF value.
It's very unlikely
that you would
have a word that appeared
literally in every document.
However, in the context of very
dense word by word matrices,
it is possible for
some words to co-occur
with every single other
word, in which case
you'll get an IDF of value
of 0, which is probably not
the intended outcome for
something that's high frequency
but might nonetheless be
important in the context
of individual documents.
So I'd probably steer
away from TF-IDF
unless you're working with
a sparse matrix design.
And then even further
afield from the things
we've discussed, you might
explore using, for example,
pairwise distance matrices where
I calculate the cosine distance
between every pair of
words along the rows
and form a matrix on that basis.
Really different in its approach
and probably in its outcomes,
but it could be
very interesting.
Let's return to our
essential questions.
Remember for each one of
these reweighting schemes
we want to ask, how does
it compare to the raw count
values, and what overall
distribution of values
does it deliver?
So let's do a bit of
an assessment of that.
I'm working with
the giga5 matrix
that you can load as part
of the course materials.
That's Gigaword with a window
of 5 and a scaling of 1 over n.
Up here in the left, I have the
raw counts, and the cell value
along the x-axis and the
number of things that have
that value along the y-axis.
And you can see that
raw counts, it's
a very difficult distribution.
First of all, this goes all the
way up to about 100 million,
and starting from 0.
Most things have quantities
that are close to 0.
And then you have this
very long thin tail
of things that are
very high frequency.
This highly skewed
distribution is
difficult for many
machine-learning methods,
both in terms of the skew
towards 0 and very low values
and also in terms of the
range of these x-axis values.
So we would like to
move away from it.
That's one motivating reason.
When we look at L2 norming
and probability distributions,
they do kind of the same thing.
They're constraining the cell
values to be between 0 and 1,
or roughly about
between 0 and 1.
But they still have a
heavy skew toward things
that are very small in
their adjusted values
and their reweighted values.
Observed over expected is more
extreme in that as is TF-IDF.
So again the observed
over expected values
range quite high, up
to about almost 50,000
which is somewhat better
than the raw counts,
but it's still very large
in terms of its spread.
And we still have that
heavy skew towards 0.
TF-IDF solves the range
problem down here,
because it's highly constrained
in the set of values,
but it still has
a very heavy skew,
looking a lot like the
raw count distribution.
From this perspective, it
looks like PMI and positive PMI
are really steps forward.
First of all, for PMI the
distribution of cell values
has this nice sort of
normal distribution.
And the values themselves
are pretty constrained
to like negative 10 to 10.
And then for positive
PMI, we simply
lop off all the negative
values and make it back to 0.
So it's more skewed towards
0, but not nearly as skewed
as all these other methods
that we're looking at.
So this is looking like PMI,
and PPMI are good choices here,
just from the point of view of
departing from the raw counts
and giving us a
tractable distribution.
There's another perspective
where we directly
compare in these matrices the
co-occurrence count on log
scale, so it's doable, with the
result the new weighted cell
value.
What we're looking
for here presumably
is an overall lack
of correlation.
I think we find that L2
norming and probabilities are
pretty good on this score.
They have kind of
low correlations.
And they make good use of
a large part of the scale
that they operate on.
Observed over expected
has a low correlation
with the cell counts,
which looks initially good,
but it has its biggest problem
that the cell values are
strangely distributed and this
correlation value might not
even be especially
meaningful, given
that we have a few outliers
and then a whole lot of things
that are close to 0.
And TF-IDF is frankly similar
low correlation but maybe not
so trustworthy in terms
of that correlation value.
Fundamentally, again, these look
like difficult distributions
of values to work with.
Again, PMI and positive
PMI look really good.
Relatively low
correlations, so we've
done something meaningful.
And both of these are
making meaningful use
of a substantial part
of the overall space
that they operate.
And we have lots of
different combinations
of cell values and underlying
co-occurrence counts.
Something of a correlation,
but that could be good.
But we're not locked
into that correlation.
So we've done
something meaningful.
To wrap up, let's do
some relationships
and generalizations,
just some reminders here.
So a theme running through
nearly all of these schemes
is that we want to
reweight the cell
value relative to
the values we expect,
given the row and the column.
And we would like
to make use of both
of those notions of context.
The magnitude of the counts
might be important, just
think about how 1, 10
as a bit of evidence
and 1,000, 10,000
might be very different
situations in terms
of the evidence that
you have gathered.
Creating probability
distributions and lengths
normalizing will
obscure that difference.
And that might be something
that you want to dwell on.
PMI and its variants
will amplify the values
of counts that are tiny
relative to their rows
and their columns.
That could be good because that
might be what you want to do,
find the things that are
really important and unusual.
Unfortunately,
with language data,
we have to watch out
that they might be noise.
And finally, TF-IDF
severely punishes words
that appear in many documents.
It behaves oddly
for dense matrices,
which can include the
word by word matrices
that we're working with.
So you might
proceed with caution
with that particular
reweighting scheme
in the context of this course.
Finally, some code snippets.
I'm just showing off that
our VSM module in the course
repository makes it really
easy to do these reweighting
schemes, a lot--
all the ones that we've
talked about and more in fact.
And returning to the end of
our vector comparison method,
you might recall that I
looked at the neighbors
of "bad" in this yelp5 matrix.
And it really didn't look good.
This does not look especially
semantically coherent.
When I take those
underlying counts
and I just adjust
them by positive PMI,
I start to see something
that looks quite semantically
coherent.
And I think we're
starting to see
the promise of these methods.
And this is really
just the beginning
in terms of surfacing
semantically
coherent and
interesting information
from these underlying counts.