CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Hello, everyone.
Welcome back.
This is part 5 in our
series on distributed word
representations.
We're going to be talking
about dimensionality reduction
techniques.
We saw in the
previous screencast
that reweighting
is a powerful tool
for finding latent semantic
information in count matrices.
We're going to push
that even further.
The promise of dimensionality
reduction techniques
is that they can
capture higher order
notions of co-occurrence
corresponding
to even deeper sorts of
semantic relatedness.
There's a wide world of these
dimensionality reduction
techniques.
I've chosen three
that we're going
to focus on as interesting
representatives of a much
larger space.
We'll look at latent
semantic analysis, which
is a classic linear method.
Then we'll talk about
autoencoders and newer,
powerful deep learning mode for
learning reduced dimensional
representations.
And then finally, GloVe, which
is a simple yet very powerful
method that, as you'll
see, has a deep connection
to pointwise mutual information.
And then I'm going to
close by talking briefly
about visualization,
which is another kind
of dimensionality
reduction technique
that we might use for
very different purposes.
So let's begin with
Latent Semantic
Analysis, a classic method.
The paper is due to
Deerwester et al, 1990.
That's a classic paper
that really made a splash.
It's one of the--
LSA is now one of the oldest,
most widely used dimensionality
reduction techniques, not only
in scientific research but also
an industry.
I think it was really
eye opening for people
at the time of the
paper's appearance
to see just how powerful
this technique could be,
especially in contexts
involving information retrieval.
The method is also known
as Truncated Singular Value
Decomposition.
And I'll explain why
that is in a second.
The final thing I want
to say at this high level
is just that LSA remains
a very powerful baseline,
especially when part of a
pipeline of other reweighting
methods.
So it should probably be
in your results table.
And it's often very
difficult to beat.
Now I think we can't, in
the time allotted to us,
cover all of the technical
details surrounding
latent semantic analysis.
In my experience,
this would be kind
of the culmination of a full
course in linear algebra.
But I do think I can convey
the guiding intuitions.
And that will help you with
responsible use of the method.
So let's imagine that we have
this simple two-dimensional
vector space model.
I've got four points,
A, B, C, and D
arrayed out in this
two-dimensional space.
I think we're all familiar with
fitting linear models, which
capture the largest source
of variation in the data.
That's this orange line here.
And the perspective I
would encourage you to take
is that we can think of
that linear regression model
as performing dimensionality
reduction in that it encourages
us to project points like B
and C down onto that line.
And then projecting them
down onto that line,
essentially in abstracting away
from their point of variation
along the y-axis, we can
see the sense in which
they are abstractly similar.
They're close together in this
reduced dimensional space.
Now with a linear
model, we captured
the source of greatest variation
in this little data set.
In the high dimensional space,
we could continue fitting lines
to other sources of
variation in the data,
other axes of variation.
So here's a blue line here that
captures the next dimension.
And we could, again,
project points like A and C
down onto that line.
And that would capture
the abstract sense
in which A and C,
although very spread out
along the x dimension,
are very close together
along the y dimension.
And of course, if we had more
dimensions in this vector space
model, we could
continue to perform
these cuts and
dimensionality reductions,
capturing ever more abstract
notions of similarity
along these different axes.
And that is, in
essence, what LSA
is going to do for us in
our really large matrices.
The fundamental
method, as I said,
is singular value decomposition.
This is a theorem
from linear algebra
that says any matrix
of dimension n by n
can be decomposed into the
product of three matrices, T,
S, and D, with the
dimensions given.
Here's a more concrete example.
Start with this matrix
of dimension 3 by 4.
We learn the term matrix, which
is full of length normalized
orthogonal vectors.
We have this matrix of singular
values along the diagonal.
They are organized from largest
to smallest, corresponding
to the greatest to least source
of variation in the data.
And then we have the document
or columnized matrix,
which is also length normalized
and orthogonal in its space.
And the theorem here is
that we can reconstruct A
from these three matrices.
Of course, we don't want
to precisely reconstruct
A. That probably wouldn't
accomplish very much for us.
But what we can do
is use this to learn
reduced dimensional
representations of A
by being selective
about which term
and singular value dimensions
we include in the model.
Let me walk you through an
example of how that happens.
And first, let me
motivate this a little bit
with an idealized
linguistic case.
So I've got up here a
word by document matrix.
Its vocabulary is gnarly,
wicked, awesome, lame,
and terrible.
And the conceit of my example
is that both gnarly and wicked
are positive terms.
So they tend to co-occur
with awesome and not
co-occur with lame and terrible.
However, gnarly and wicked never
occur in the same doc here.
The idea is that gnarly is a
slang positive term associated
with the West Coast
of the United States.
And wicked is a slang term
associated with the East
Coast of the United States.
In virtue of that
idealized dialect split,
they never occur in
the same document.
But nonetheless, they
have similar neighbors
in this vector space.
And that's the kind of abstract
notion of co-occurrence
that we want to capture.
If we simply use our
standard distance
measures and reweighting
techniques and so forth,
we will not capture that
more abstract notion
of co-occurrence.
Here, distances in
this raw vector space,
gnarly, awesome, terrible,
and wicked, wicked
is farther away from gnarly
even than terrible is.
So we've got a sentiment
confusion and really just
not the result we
were shooting for.
So we perform singular
value decomposition
into these three matrices.
And then the truncated
part is that we're
going to consider just the
first two dimensions of the term
matrix corresponding to these
two singular values capturing
the top two sources of
variation in the data.
So we multiply those
together and we
get this reduced dimensional
matrix down here, 2
by the size of the vocabulary.
And if we do distance
measures in that space,
just as we were hoping, gnarly
and wicked are now neighbors.
The method has captured
that more abstract notion
of having the same
neighbors as the other word.
In the previous
lecture, I encouraged
you to think about what
you're doing to a matrix
when you perform some kind
of reweighting scheme.
Let's extend that to these
dimensionality reduction
techniques.
So here's a picture of what LSA
does starting with a raw count
distribution over here.
If I just run LSA on that
raw count distribution,
I get what looks also like a
very difficult distribution
of values.
The cell values are
very spread out.
And they have a lot of the
mass centered around 0 here,
corresponding to the peak
in the raw counts over here
near 0 as well.
So that doesn't look like
we've done very much in terms
of taming the kind of
untractable skewed distribution
we started with.
However, if instead we take
the raw counts and first feed
them through PMI,
which as we saw
before gives us this nice
distribution of values, highly
constrained along the
x-axis, and then we run LSA,
we retain a lot of
those good properties.
The values are somewhat
more spread out
but still nicely distributed.
This looks like a
much happier input
to downstream analytic methods
than the top version here.
And I think this is
beginning to show
that it can be powerful
to pipeline reweighting
and dimensionality
reduction techniques.
Another note I would
want to make, how do you
choose the dimensionality
for, let's say, it
has this variable k
corresponding to the number
of dimensions that you keep.
If you read the
literature on LSA,
they often imagine this kind
of what I've called the dream
scenario where you plot
the singular values
and you see that a lot
of them are very large.
And then there's
a sudden drop off.
And if you do see
this, then it's
obvious that you should pick
the point of the sudden drop
off as your k.
So here, you would pick k as 20.
And you'd be confident that
you had captured almost all
the variation in your data in
the reduced dimensional space
you were creating.
Unfortunately, for the kinds
of matrices and problems
that we're looking at, I really
never see the dream scenario.
What I see looks
something much more
like this, where you have
kind of a sudden drop
off early and then a long
decline and maybe a sudden drop
off at the end.
And it's basically totally
unclear where in the space
you should pick k.
And the result is
that k is often
chosen kind of empirically
as a hyperparameter to
and against whatever
problem you're actually
trying to solve.
If, in doing this work, you
do see the dream scenario,
please do write to me.
It would be very exciting
to see that happen.
LSA is just one of a large
family of matrix decomposition
methods.
Here's a list of a few of them.
And a lot of them are
implemented in scikit-learn
in its decomposition library.
And I would encourage you
to try them out and just see
how they perform on problems
that you're trying to solve.
And finally, here's
a little bit of code.
vsm.lsa with k set
to 100 gives me back
a reduced dimensional
version of that matrix,
keeping the same
vocabulary, of course,
but now with only 100
column dimensions.
Let's move to autoencoders.
This will be a point
of contast with LSA.
Because this is a much
more powerful method.
So here's the overview.
Autoencoders are
a flexible class
of deep learning architectures
for learning reduced
dimensional representations.
If you want to hear much more
about this class of models,
I would encourage you to read
chapter 14 of the Goodfellow et
al book, Deep Learning.
It has a lot of
details and a lot
of variations on this theme.
Here is the basic
autoencoder model.
The input would be
the, say, that vectors
from the rows in our matrices.
So this could be the
counts or something
that you've done to the counts.
Those are fed through a hidden
layer of representation.
And then the goal
of this model is
to try to literally
reconstruct the input.
Now, that might be
trivial if h had
the same dimensionality as x.
But the whole idea
here is that you're
going to feed the input
through a very narrow pipe
and then try to
reconstruct the input.
Given that you're feeding it
through a potentially very
narrow pipe, it's
unlikely that you'll
be able to fully
reconstruct the inputs.
But the idea is
that the model will
learn to reconstruct the
important sources of variation
in performing this
autoencoding step.
And then when we use these
models for representation
learning in the mode that
we've been in for this unit,
the representation
that we choose
is this hidden unit here.
We typically don't
care about what
was reconstructed on
the output, but rather
only about the hidden reduced
dimensional representation
that the model learned.
This slide has a bunch of
other annotations on it.
And the reason I included them
is that the course repository
includes a reference
implementation
of an autoencoder and all the
other deep learning models
that we cover in pure NumPy.
And so if you want
it to understand
all of the technical details
of how the model is constructed
and optimized, you could use
this as a kind of cheat sheet
to understand how
the code works.
I think the fundamental idea
that you want to have is simply
that the model is trying
to reconstruct its inputs.
The error signal that
we get is the difference
between the reconstructed
and actual input.
And that error signal
is what we use to update
the parameters of the model.
Final thing I would
mention here is
that it could be very
difficult for this model
if you feed in the raw
current vectors down here.
They have very high
dimensionality.
And their distribution is
highly skewed as we've seen.
So it can be very productive to
do a little bit of reweighting
and maybe even dimensionality
reduction with LSA
before you start feeding
inputs into this model.
Of course, it could
still be meaningful,
even if you've done LSA
as a pre-processing step,
to learn a hidden
dimensional representation
because this model is presumably
capable of learning even more
abstract notions than LSA is
in virtue of its non-linearity
at this hidden layer.
And here's a bit of code
just showing how this works,
using both the reference
implementation that I mentioned
as well as a faster
and more flexible
Torch autoencoder which is
also included in the course
repository.
I think the only interface
thing to mention here
is that these models
have a fit method,
like all the other machine
learning models for this.
But the fit method
returns that hidden
dimensional
representation, the target
for our learning
in this context,
which is a bit non-standard.
But it's the
intended application
for this kind of
representation learning.
The other thing I
would mention is,
so let's see how well the
autoencoder is performing.
This is the raw distances in
the giga5 matrix for finance.
This is the count matrix.
It doesn't look great.
If we run the autoencoder
directly on the count matrix,
it looks a little better.
But it's still not excellent.
If we think of this
as part of a pipeline
where we've first done positive
pointwise mutual information,
and then LSA at
dimension 100, and then
dub the autoencoding
step, it starts
to look like a really good and
interesting semantic space.
And I think that's pointing
out the power of including
the autoencoder in a larger
pipeline of preprocessing
on the count matrices.
Let's turn to GloVe
for Global Vectors
for the final major unit
for this screencast.
Here's a brief overview.
GloVe was introduced by Jeffrey
Pennington, Richard Socher,
and Chris Manning, a
Stanford team, in 2014.
Roughly speaking,
the guiding idea here
is that we want to
learn vectors for words
such that the dot
product of those vectors
is proportional to the log
probability of co-occurrence
for those words.
And I'll elaborate
on that in a second.
For doing computational
work, we can
rely on the implementation
torch.glove.py
which is in the course repo.
I'll mention that
there's also a reference
implementation in bsm.py.
It's very slow but it kind
of transparently implements
the core GloVe
algorithm so it could
be interesting to inspect.
And then if you're
doing practical work
with really large corpora and
really large vocabularies,
I would encourage you to use the
GloVe team's C implementation.
It's an outstanding
software artifact
that will allow you to learn
lots of good representations
quickly.
And that kind of brings
me to my last point.
I just want to mention
that the GloVe team was
among the first teams in
NLP to release not just data
and code but pre-trained
model parameters.
Everyone does that these days.
But it was rare at the time.
And I think this team
was kind of really
forward thinking in seeing
the value of releasing
these centralized resources.
And a lot of really
interesting work
happened with GloVe
vectors as a foundation.
All right, so let's think
about the technical aspects
of this model.
This is the GloVe objective.
And you're going to see,
pointwise, mutual information
kind of creep into this
picture in an interesting way.
So this is equation
6 from the paper.
It's kind of an idealized
objective for the GloVe model.
And it says what I said before.
We have a row vector and a
column vector, wi and wk.
We're going to get
their dot product.
And the goal is to learn
to have that dot product be
proportional to the log of the
probability of co-occurrence
of word i and word k.
Where the probability
of co-occurence
is defined in the way that
we defined it before when
we were talking about
row normalization.
It's just done in log space.
This is the co-occurrence count.
This is the sum of all
the counts along that row.
And basically in
log space, we're
just dividing this
value by this value.
So keep that in mind.
Now the reason they have
only the row represented
is that in the paper
they're assuming
that the rows and columns in
the underlying count matrix
are identical.
And so we don't need
to include both.
However, if we did allow that
the row and context could
be different, we
would just elaborate
equation 6 to have a slightly
different denominator, right?
We would have the product of
the row sum and the column sum,
and take the log of that
and subtract that out.
And that would be kind of our
goal for learning these dot
products here.
But aha, this is
where PMI sneaks in.
Because that simply is
the PMI objective, right?
Where we stated that is
the log of the probability
of co-occurrence divided
by the product of the row
and the column
probabilities, here they've
just stated exactly that
calculation in log space.
And these are numerically
equivalent by the equivalence
of log of x over y
being the same as log
of x minus the log of y.
So that's the deep connection
that I was highlighting
between GloVe and PMI.
And I think that's
really interesting
because it shows that
fundamentally we're
testing a very similar
hypothesis using
very similar notions of
row and column context.
Now the GloVe team
doesn't just stop there.
The GloVe objective is
actually much more interesting
as an elaboration of
that core PMI idea.
But it's worth
having PMI in mind
because it's there
throughout this presentation.
In the paper, they state this
is a kind of idealized objective
where we're going to have the
dot product, as I said before,
and two bias terms.
And the goal will be to make
that equivalent to the log
of the co-occurrence count.
That has some
undesirable properties
from the point of view
of machine learning.
So they propose, in the
end, a weighted version
of that objective.
You can see we still have
the product of the row
and the column vectors
and two biased terms.
We're going to subtract out the
log of the co-occurance count
and take the square of that.
And that's going
to be weighted by f
of the co-occurrence count,
where f is a function that you
can define by hand.
And what they do in the paper
is that it was two parameters, x
max and alpha.
For any count that
is above x max,
we're going to set it to 1, kind
of flatten out all the really
large counts.
Everything that's
below x max, we
will take as a
proportion of x max
with some exponential scaling
as specified by alpha.
That's the function there.
And typically, alpha is set
to 0.75 and x max to 100.
But I encourage you to
be critical in thinking
about both those choices and
how they relate to your data.
I'll return to that in a second.
So GloVe really has these
three hyperparameters,
the dimensionality of the
learned representations, x max
which is going to have
this flattening effect,
and alpha which is going
to scale the values, right?
And so here's an example of
how those are interacting,
x max and alpha.
If I start with
this vector, 100 99,
75, 10, and 1, the function
f, as we specified it,
is going to flatten that out
into 1, 99, 81, 18, and 0.3.
You should just be aware
that kind of flattening
is happening.
So GloVe learning, so it's kind
of interesting to think about
it analytically about how
GloVe manages to learn
interesting representations.
And one thing that might be
on your mind is the question,
can it actually learn higher
order notions of co-occurrence?
That's been the major selling
point of this lecture.
I gave that example involving
"gnarly" and "wicked" with LSA.
Is GloVe going to be
able to do that, right?
We could just pose
that as a question.
So let's start that and see what
happens, see how this works.
The loss calculations
for GloVe, this
is a kind of simplified version
of the derivative of the model.
And we're going to
show how GloVe manages
to pull "gnarly" and
"wicked" toward off center,
that little idealized
space that I used before.
I'm going to leave out the
bias terms for simplicity.
But we could bring those in.
And so here's how this
is going to proceed.
What I've done, just from
this idealized example,
is begin in a GloVe space where
wicked and gnarly are as far
apart as I could make
them, so as different
as I could possibly make them.
But I've got awesome
and terrible.
And awesome is kind of
close to gnarly already.
What you'll see is that
after just one iteration
of the model, what has happened
is that wicked and gnarly
have been pulled toward awesome.
And that's just the kind
of effect that we wanted.
That's the sense in which GloVe
can capture these higher order
notions of co-occurrence.
Just in a little
more detail, you
might want to study
this on your own.
But the high level overview
of exactly how that learning
happens proceeds as follows.
We start from these
counts up here.
And the crucial
assumption I'm making
is that wicked and
gnarly never co-occur.
But they occur a
lot with awesome.
And awesome will be kind of the
gravitational pull that makes
gnarly and wicked look similar.
Keep in mind that because
of that function f, by
and large with GloVe we're
dealing not with the raw counts
but rather with the
reweighted matrix.
And that preserves this property
that may never co-occur.
It gives differently
scaled values
for the rest of the
co-occurrence or pseudo
co-occurrence probabilities.
Right, and here's what
we're going to track.
This is the "gnarly"
vector in 0.
And you can see I've made
them as far apart as I could.
They're kind of
opposed to each other.
But we're going to see how they
get pulled toward "awesome"
in the context vector.
So this is that
loss calculation.
I have just plugged in
all the values here.
And you can see that we get
this initial set of losses.
That's after one iteration, and
we update the weight matrices.
And we perform one
more round of learning.
And you can see that
both of these models,
the values here are getting
larger corresponding to getting
pulled closer and
closer toward awesome.
And you can see that
graphically happening over here
in these plots on the left.
And as I do more iterations
of the GloVe model,
this effect is just going
to strengthen corresponding
to wicked and gnarly getting
pulled toward awesome
and away from terrible as a
result of these underlying
counts.
And I take this as good
evidence that GloVe,
like the other methods
we've discussed,
is capable of capturing
those higher order
notions of co-occurrence that
we're so interested in pursuing
with these methods.
Let's close the loop also.
We have those central questions.
What is GloVe doing to
our underlying spaces?
With GloVe, because of
the design of the matrix,
we have to begin from word by
word co-occurrence matrices
accounts.
So we begin with these
raw count values.
And GloVe is one-stop shopping.
It's going to take
us all the way
to these reduced
dimensional representations.
And boy, by the
criteria we've set up,
does GloVe do an
outstanding job.
This is the result of running
GloVe at dimension 50.
And you can see that the values
are extremely well scaled
between negative 2 and 2 and
nicely, normally distributed.
This is an outstanding input to
modern machine learning models.
And I think this is probably a
non-trivial aspect of why GloVe
has been so successful as
a kind of pre-trained basis
for a lot of subsequent
machine learning architectures.
And then here's a
little bit of code,
just showing you how you can
work with these interfaces
using our code base.
The one thing I
wanted to call out
is that I'm trying
to be careful.
I have defined this
function percentage
non-zero values above.
And you can set x max
here and just feed
in a matrix and
study what percentage
of the values in
that matrix are going
to get flattened out to 1
as a result of the x max
that you've chosen.
And this value really varies
by the design of the matrix.
If I feed in yelp5, only
about 5% of the values
are getting flattened out.
But if I feed in yelp20,
which is much denser
and has much higher
counts, 20% of the values
are getting flattened out to 1.
If this number gets
too high, the matrix
might become
completely homogeneous.
And so we should really be aware
of how the setting of x max
is affecting the kind of
learning that we could even
be performing with GloVe.
And it might turn out that
this is even more important
than the number of iterations
or the dimensionality
of the representations
that you learn.
Once you've made those
choices, though, the interface
is pretty clear.
And the fit method, as
with the autoencoder,
returns the matrix of
learned representations
that we want to use for
the current purposes.
And then finally, I've
included a score method.
And the score method
is literally just
testing to see how well the
vectors that you've learned
correspond to the GloVe
objective of having the dot
products be
proportional to the log
of the co-occurrence
probabilities.
Since you can get
a score for that,
we're doing pretty
well here, let's say
for a large empirical matrix.
Final section, let's just say
a bit about visualization.
And this is a dimensionality
reduction technique
in the sense that
the whole point
is to try to flatten out a
very high dimensional space
into possibly two
or three dimensions.
You have to recognize
that inevitably this will
involve a lot of compromises.
It's just impossible to capture
all the sources of variation
in your underlying matrix
in just a few dimensions.
But nonetheless, this
can be productive.
I think it's especially
valuable if you pair it
with some kind of hands-on
qualitative exploration using
something like BSN neighbors
to understand at a low level
what your matrix encodes.
And then the high
level visualizations
can be a kind of
counterpart to that.
There are many visualization
techniques and a lot of them
are implemented in the
scikit manifold package.
So I encourage you to use them.
I'm going to show you some
results from t-SNE which
stands for t-distributed
stochastic neighbor embedding.
There are lots of user
guides there that you
can study for more details.
Let me just give
you the high level.
This is t-SNE run on
our giga20 matrix.
I think this is typical of
pretty good output from t-SNE.
So what we're seeing here is
some pockets of high density.
Those are areas of
local coherence.
Globally, we should be
careful not to over interpret
this entire diagram
because as you rerun
the model with
different random seeds,
you'll see that it gets kind of
reoriented in different parts
or correspondingly close
to different other parts.
But what you can count
on pretty reliably
is that these local
pockets of coherence
correspond to coherence parts of
the space that you've defined.
And if you zoom in on
them, you can assess
what the model has uncovered.
So for this giga21,
for example, I
think we see prominent clusters
corresponding to things
like cooking and conflict.
If we do the same thing
for our Yelp matrix,
again, this looks
pretty good in terms
of having some substructure
that we can analyze.
And if we zoom in, we do see
clusters like positive terms
and negative terms corresponding
to the evaluative setting
of these Yelp reviews.
So this is all very
encouraging and suggests
that the underlying spaces
have some really interesting
structure that might be useful
for subsequent analysis.
And here are some code snippets.
We have this simple
wrapper around
the scikit t-SNE
implementation that
will allow you to flexibly
work with this stuff using
the account matrices
from our unit.
And I'm just mentioning
here that it's pretty easy
if you want it to color code
the words in your vocabulary,
say, according to a sentiment
lexicon or some other kind
of lexicon.
That could be a way for
you to reveal exactly what
structure your model has been
able to uncover with respect
to those underlying labels.
And that can be useful.