BILL MACCARTNEY: So that's
the end of the introduction.
Let's now begin to drill
down on the data resources
that we'll need to
launch our investigation.
And there are two
different kinds
of data we need to talk
about, the corpus and the KB.
Just like any other
NLP problem, we
need to start with a
corpus, a large collection
of natural language text.
And for relation extraction,
we need sentences containing
two or more entities.
And because our goal is
to do relation extraction
with distant
supervision, we need
to be able to connect
the entities to a KB.
So we need a corpus in
which the entity mentions
are annotated with
entity resolutions, which
map them to unique
unambiguous identifiers.
The same identifiers
that are used in the KB.
So in this representation,
I've got the string Elon
Musk, which is just an
English language string.
That's what we call
an entity mention.
And then I've got Elon_Musk,
which is an entity ID.
It's a unique
unambiguous identifier
for this entity in some
predefined dictionary of entity
IDs.
And it's very common
for this purpose
to use something
like Wikipedia, which
has one Wikipedia page
for almost any entity
that you can think of.
For our investigation,
we're going
to use an adaptation of
the Wikilinks corpus, which
was produced by Google
and UMass in 2013.
The full corpus contains
40 million entity mentions
from 10 million web pages.
And each entity mentioned is
annotated with a Wikipedia URL.
But we're going to use just
a subset of the full corpus
in order to make
things manageable.
So let's start to look
at some of the code we'll
use in the Python
notebooks for this topic.
The data assets
that we'll use live
in a subdirectory of our data
directory called rel_ext_data
and we've defined a class
called corpus, which
holds the examples and which
lets you quickly look up
examples containing
specific entities.
So if we load our
corpus, we find
that it contains more
than 330,000 examples.
Pretty good size.
It's small enough that we
can work with it easily
on an ordinary laptop,
but it's big enough
to support effective
machine learning.
And we can print out a
representative example
from the corpus.
Actually, this is
a bit hard to read.
So let me give you a different
view of the same example.
We represent examples
using the example
class, which is a namedtuple
with 12 fields listed here.
The first two fields
entity_1 and entity_2
contain unique identifiers for
the two entities mentioned.
We name identities
using Wiki IDs,
which you can think of as the
last portion of a Wikipedia
URL.
The next five fields
represent the text
surrounding the two mentions,
divided into five chunks.
So left contains the text
before the first mention.
mention_1 is the
first mention itself.
middle contains the text
between the two mentions.
mention_2 is the second mention
and right contains the text
after the second mention.
And the last five fields contain
the same five chunks of text,
but this time,
annotated with part
of speech tags,
which may turn out
to be useful when we start
building models for relation
extraction.
Now, whenever you start
to work with a new dataset
it's good practice to
do some data exploration
to get familiar with the data.
A big part of this is getting
a sense of the high level
characteristics of the
data, summary statistics,
distributions and so on.
For example, how many
entities are there
and what are the
most common ones?
Here's some code that computes
that and here are the results.
So there are more than
95,000 unique entities,
and it looks like the most
common entities are dominated
by geographic locations.
Now the main benefit we
get from the corpus class
is the ability to retrieve
the examples containing
specific entities.
So let's find
examples containing
Elon Musk and Tesla Motors.
There are five such examples,
and here's the first one.
Actually, this might not be
all of the examples containing
Elon Musk and Tesla Motors.
It's only the examples where
Elon Musk was mentioned first
and Tesla Motors was
mentioned second.
There may be additional
examples that
have them in the reverse order.
So let's check, look for
Tesla Motors, Elon Musk.
Sure enough, two more
examples in reverse order.
So going forward,
we'll have to remember
to check both
directions when we're
looking for examples containing
a specific pair of entities.
OK, a few last
observations on the corpus.
First, this corpus
is not without flaws.
As you get more
familiar with it,
you'll probably discover
that it contains
many examples that are nearly,
but not exactly duplicates.
This seems to be an artifact
of the web document sampling
methodology that was used in the
construction of the Wikilinks
data set.
And it winds up creating
a few distortions
and we may see some
examples of this later.
But even though the
corpus has a few warts,
it will serve our
purposes just fine.
One thing that this
corpus does not include
is any annotation
about relations.
So it could not be used for
the fully supervised approach
to relation extraction,
because that
requires a relation label on
each pair of entity mentions.
And we don't have any
such annotation here.
The only annotations that
we have in this corpus
are entity resolutions.
Mapping an entity
mention to an entity ID.
That means that in
order to make headway,
we'll need to connect the
corpus with an external source
of knowledge about relations.
We need a KB.
Happily our data distribution
does include a KB,
which is derived from Freebase.
Freebase has an
interesting history.
It was created in the
late 2000s by a company
called Metaweb led by
John Giannandrea, who
later became my boss.
Google acquired Metaweb
in 2010, and Freebase
became the foundation of
Google's knowledge graph.
Unfortunately,
Google shut Freebase
down in 2016, which was tragic.
But the Freebase data is still
available from various sources.
So our KB is a collection
of relational triples each
consisting of a relation,
a subject, and an object.
So for example, place_of_birth,
Barack_Obama, Honolulu.
has_spouse, Barack_Obama,
Michelle_Obama.
Author, The Audacity
of Hope, Barack_Obama.
So as you might
guess, the relation
is one of a handful of
predefined constants
like place_of_birth
birth or has_spouse.
The subject and the
object are entities
represented by Wiki IDs.
It's the same ID space
used in the corpus.
Wiki IDs are basically the
last part of a Wikipedia URL.
Now just like we
did for the corpus,
we've created a KB class
to store the KB triples
and some associated indexes.
This class makes it
easy and efficient
to look up KB triples both
by relation and by entities.
So here, we're just
loading the data
and printing a count
of the KB triples.
There are 45,000 KB
triples, so this is quite
a bit smaller than the corpus.
If you remember the
corpus has 330 examples
and we can print out
the first KB triple.
So this is a KB triple that
says that the contains relation
holds between Brickfields and
Kuala Lumpur Sentral railway
station which I did not know.
Just like we do with the corpus,
let's do some data exploration
to get a sense of the high
level characteristics of the KB.
So first, how many
relations are there?
The all_relations
attribute of the KB
contains a list
of its relations.
And it seems that
there are 16 of them.
Well, what are the relations
and how big are they?
This code prints out
a list with sizes.
Note the
get_triples_for_relation
method, which returns a
list of the KB triples
for a given relation.
You begin to get a sense of what
kind of stuff is in this KB.
It looks like the
contains relation
is really big with more
than 18,000 triples.
And there are a
few relations that
are pretty small with
fewer than 1,000 triples.
Here's some code, that prints
one example from each relations
so that we can form a better
sense of what they mean.
Some of these are familiar facts
like adjoins, France, Spain.
Others might refer to
unfamiliar entities.
So for example, I've never
heard of Sheridan Le Fanu.
But I think you can quickly
form an intuitive sense of what
each relation is about.
Now one of the most important
message in a KB class
is get_triples_for_entities
which lets us look up triples
by the entities they contain.
So let's use it to
see what triples
contain France and Germany.
OK, sure, they belong
to the adjoins relation.
That makes sense.
Now relations like adjoins
are intuitively symmetric.
So we'd expect to find the
inverse triple in the KB
as well, and yep, it's there.
But note that
there's no guarantee
that such inverse triples
actually appear in the KB.
There's no guarantee
that the KB is complete.
And you could easily write some
code to find missing inverses.
Now, that relation
adjoins is symmetric,
but most relations are
intuitively asymmetric.
So let's see what
triples we have
for Tesla_Motors and Elon_Musk.
OK, they belong to
the founders relation.
Good.
That's expected.
That's an asymmetric relation.
What about the inverse,
Elon Musk and Tesla Motors?
OK, they belong to the
worked_at relation.
Seems like a funny way to
describe Elon's role at Tesla,
but OK.
So this shows that you
can have one relation
between x and y and a
different relation that
holds between y and x.
One more observation.
There may be more
than one relation
that holds between a
given pair of entities,
even in one direction.
So for example, let's
see what triples hold--
what triples contain
Cleopatra and
Ptolemy_XIII_Theos_Philopator.
Oh, my goodness.
This pair belongs to
both the has_sibling
relation and the has_spouse
relation to which I can only
say, oh.
Moving right along, let's
look at the distribution
of entities in a KB.
How many entities are there and
what are the most common ones?
Well, here's some code
that computes that.
There are 40,000
entities in the KB.
So that's fewer than half as
many entities as in the corpus.
If you remember, the corpus
has 95,000 unique entities.
So there are lots of
entities in the corpus that
don't appear in the KB at all.
But just like the corpus,
the most common entities
are dominated by geographic
locations, England, India,
Italy and so on.
Note that there's no
promise or expectation
that this KB is complete.
For one thing, the
KB doesn't even
contain many of the
entities from the corpus.
And even for the
entities it does include,
there may be possible triples
which are true in the world
but are missing from the KB.
So as an example,
these triples are
in the KB, founders,
Tesla_Motors, Elon_Musk,
worked_at, Elon_Musk,
Tesla_Motors, Founders, SpaceX,
Elon_Musk.
You might expect to find
worked_at, at, Elon_Musk,
SpaceX.
But nope, that triple
is not in the KB.
That's weird.
Well, in fact, the whole
point of relation extraction
is to identify new relational
triples from natural language
text so that we can
add them to a KB.
If our KB's were complete, we
wouldn't have anything to do.
Now actually, in
this case, you might
object that we don't need to
do relation extraction to make
that completion.
We could write some
logic that recognizes
that founders, xy
entails worked at yx
and apply that
rule systematically
across the KB and use that
to fill in the missing
triple in this case.
But the general
point still stands
that there may be
lots of triples
that are true in the world
but missing from the KB
where that strategy is not going
to allow us to add the missing
information.