CHRIS POTTS: Hello, everyone.
Welcome to part 4 of our
series on supervised sentiment
analysis.
This is the second screencast
in the series that is focused
on a dataset for sentiment.
And that dataset is DynaSent.
This video could be
considered an optional element
in the series.
I'm offering it for
two reasons really.
First, this is a new data
set that I helped produce.
And I would love it if
people worked on it.
It would be great to see some
new models, new insights.
All of that would help
push this project forward
in interesting ways.
The second reason
is more practical.
I think that this data
set could be useful to you
as you work on the assignment
and the associated bake-off.
You could use the
data set itself
for supplementary training data.
You could use it to
evaluate your system.
And as you'll see,
there are a few points
of conceptual connection
between this data set
and the brand new dev and test
sets of restaurant sentences
that are part of the
bake-off this year.
So let's dive in.
Here's a project overview.
First, all the data, code, and
models are available on GitHub
at this link.
This dataset itself consists
of about 122,000 sentences.
They are across two rounds.
And I'm going to cover
what each round means.
And each of the sentences has
five gold labels in addition
to an inferred majority
label where there is one.
And I'll return to that as well.
I think that's an interesting
aspect to this kind of data
collection.
The associated paper
is Potts et al.
2020, which I
encourage you to read
if you want to learn even more
about this dataset and how,
in particular, it relates to
the Stanford Sentiment Treebank,
our other core dataset.
And another ingredient
here, as you'll
see when we get to round
two, is that this is partly
an effort in model in the loop
adversarial data set creation.
For round two, crowd
workers interacted
with the model
attempting to fool it
and, thereby, creating sentences
that are really difficult
and are going to challenge
our models in what we hope
are exciting and
productive ways.
So here's a complete
project overview.
Let me walk through it quickly.
And then we'll dive
into the details.
We begin with what we've
called Model 0, which
is a RoBERTa model that's
fine-tuned on a bunch of very
large, sentiment
benchmark data sets.
The primary utility
of Model 0 is
that we're going to use it as
a device to find challenging,
naturally occurring sentences
out in a large corpus.
And then we human validate those
to get actual labels for them.
The result of that
process is what
we hope is a really challenging
round 1 dataset of naturally
occurring sentences that are
hard for a very good sentiment
model like Model 0.
On that basis, we
then train a Model 1,
which is similar to Model 0 but
now extended with that round 1
training data.
So we hope that, in
bringing in that new data
and combining it with
the sentiment benchmarks,
we get an even stronger model.
That is the model that
crowd workers interacted
with on the Dynabench
platform to try
to create examples
that are adversarial
with respect to Model 1.
So they ought to be
really difficult.
We feed those through exactly
the same human validation
pipeline.
And that gives us our
second round of data.
So two rounds of data
that can be thought
of as separate problems
are merged together
into a larger data set.
I think we're kind
of still deciding
how best to conceptualize
these various data aspects.
So let's look at round 1
in a little more detail.
This is where we
begin with Model 0,
and try to harvest interesting
naturally occurring sentences.
We sort of run Model 0 as
a RoBERTa-based classifier.
And its training data are
from customer reviews,
which is small, the IMDB
dataset, which I linked to
in an earlier
screencast, SST-3, which
you saw in the previous
screencast, and then these two
very large external benchmarks
of product and service reviews
from Yelp and Amazon.
You can see that
they're very big indeed.
And the performance of
Model 0 on the datasets,
these are our three
external data sets.
It's pretty good.
They range from the
low 70s, for SST-3,
to the high 70s for
Yelp and Amazon.
So this is a solid model.
And I will say,
impressionistically,
if you download Model 0
and play around with it,
you will find that it is a very
good sentiment model indeed.
So we used Model 0 to
harvest what we hope
are challenging sentences.
And for this, we used
the Yelp academic dataset
which is a very large collection
of about 8 million reviews.
And our heuristic
is that we're going
to favor in our sampling
process harvesting sentences
where the review was one
star, so it's very low,
and Model 0 predicted
positive for a given sentence
and, conversely, where
the review is five stars,
and Model 0 predicted negative.
We are hoping that that at least
creates a bias for sentences
that are very
challenging for Model 0,
where it's actually
making a wrong prediction.
We're not going to depend
on that assumption.
Because we'll have
a validation step.
But we're hoping that this
is as kind of as adversarial
as we can be without actually
having labels to begin with.
This is a picture of the
validation interface.
You can see that there were some
examples given and a little bit
of training about how
to use the labels.
And then, fundamentally,
what crowd workers did is
they were prompted
for a sentence,
and they made one of four
choices, positive, negative,
no sentiment, which is our
notion of neutral, and mixed
sentiment, which is
indicating a sentence that
has a balance of positive and
negative sentiments expressed
in it.
I think that's an important
category to single out.
We're not going to try
to model those sentences.
But we certainly
want crowd workers
to register that kind of mixing
of emotions where it appears.
So here's the resulting dataset.
And because we got five gold
labels for every sentence,
there are two perspectives
that you can take.
The first one I've called
distributional train.
And this is where,
essentially, we
take each one of the
examples and reproduce it
five times for each of
the labels that it got.
So if an individual sentence
got three positive labels, two
negative, then we would have
five examples, three labeled
positive and three
labeled negative,
with the actual text of the
example repeated five times.
What that is doing
is essentially
simulating having a
distribution over the labels.
And for many
classifier models, that
is literally the
same as training
on a distribution of the labels
as given by our crowd workers.
I think this is an exciting
way to bring in uncertainty
and capture the fact
that there might
be kind of inherent disagreement
among the crowd workers
that we want our model
to at least grapple with.
And in the paper,
as we discuss, this
gives better models than
training on just the majority
labels.
But you can take a
more traditional view.
So majority label here
means that at least three
of the five workers
chose that label.
That gives you 94,000 or
95,000 sentences for training.
And then these dev and test
sets have 3,600 samples each.
And presumably, we would
predict just the majority label
for them.
What's more open is how
we train these systems.
And in the end, what we found
is that 47% of these examples
are adversarial with
respect to Model 0.
And as you'll see,
the dev and test set
are designed so that Model 0
performs at chance on them.
Yeah, that's the Model
0 versus the human.
So here's a summary
of the performance.
I showed you these
categories before.
And I'm just signaling that
we have, by design, ensured
that Model 0 performs
at chance on round zero.
We could compare that
to our human baseline.
For this, we kind of
synthesized five annotators
and did pairwise
F1 scoring for them
to get an estimate
of human performance
that is on the same scale
as what we got from Model 0
up here.
And we put that estimate of
88% for the dev and test sets.
I think that's a good
conservative number.
I think if you got close to
it, that would be a signal
that we had kind of
saturated this round.
And we'd like to think about
additional dataset creation.
I do want to signal,
though, that I
think this is a conservative
estimate of how humans do.
And one indicator of
that is that, actually,
614 of the roughly 1,200
people who worked on this task
for validation never disagreed
with the majority label, which
sort of starts to suggest
that there are humans who
are performing
perfectly at this task,
putting the set at
pretty low bound.
And here are some
example sentences.
These are fully randomly
sampled with the only bias
being that I set a length
restriction, so that the slide
would be manageable.
These are the same
examples that appear
in the paper, where
we needed to fit them
all into a pretty small table.
I think this is
illuminating though.
So it's showing all
the different ways
that Model 0 could get
confused with respect
to the majority response.
And I would like to
highlight for you
that there is a real discrepancy
here on the neutral category.
What we find is that,
because Model 0 was trained
on large external benchmarks,
its notion of neutral
actually mixes
together things that
are mixed sentiment
and things that
are highly uncertain about the
sentiment that is expressed,
for whatever reason.
So you get a lot of borderline
cases and a lot of cases
where humans are
kind of inherently
having a hard time agreeing
about what the fixed sentiment
label would be.
I think that DynaSent
is doing a better
job of capturing some
notion of neutral
in these labels over here.
And we should be a little wary
of treating three-star reviews
and things like that as a
true proxy for neutrality.
This is a good point to signal
that the validation and test
sets for the bake off of
the restaurant sentences
were validated in the
same way as DynaSent.
So those sentences will have
the same kind of neutrality
that DynaSent has,
which could be opposed
to the sense of neutrality
that you get from the Stanford
Sentiment Treebank, which
was, of course, underlying we
kind of gathered in
this setting of having
a fixed five-star rating scale.
So that's round 1.
That's all naturally
occurring sentences.
Let's turn to round 2.
So recall that we benefit
from round 1 at this point
by training a brand new model
on all those external datasets
plus the round 1 dataset.
And then we have workers
on Dynabench interact
with this model
to try to fool it.
And we validate the
resulting sentences
to get our round 2 data set.
So Model 1 is, again, a
RoBERTa-based classifier.
What we've done for
our training here is,
more or less, carry over what
we did for the first round.
Except, we have upsampled the
SST to give it more weight.
And we have
dramatically upsampled
the distributional labels
from our round 1 dataset,
effectively, trying to
give it equal weight as all
of these other datasets combined
in the training procedure.
So we're trying to get a
model that, as a priority,
does really well on
our round one dataset.
Here is a look at the
performance of this model.
And first, I would
just note that it's
doing well on round 1.
We're at about 81%, which
is a little below humans
but certainly much better
than the chance performance,
by design, that we
set up for Model 0.
I do want to signal,
though, that we
have a kind of
drop in performance
for a few of these categories.
You can see that especially
for Yelp and Amazon,
where Model 0 was at about,
for example, 80 here.
Model 1 dropped down to 73.
And it's a similar
picture for dev.
And, more or less, that's
repeated for Amazon with a drop
from about 76 to 73 and
77 to 73, similarly.
So we have a trade
off in performance
that I believe
traces to the fact
that we are performing some
changes to the underlying
semantics of the labels.
But that's something
to keep in mind.
And you can see that
there's a tension here
as we try to do well at our
dataset versus continuing
to do well on these fixed
external benchmarks.
Here is the Dynabench interface.
And there's one thing that
I want to note about it.
This is the stock interface.
But we've actually
concentrated on a condition
that we call the prompt
condition, where workers,
instead of having to just write
a sentence as a blank slate,
sit down to an empty buffer
and try to fool the model,
they were given an
inspirational prompt, which
was an attested sentence from
the Yelp academic data set,
and invited to modify that
sentence if they chose in order
to achieve their goal of fooling
the model in a particular way.
And this proved to be
vastly more productive.
It led to more diverse
and realistic sentences.
I think we've essentially
freed the crowd workers
from the creative burden of
having each time to come up
with a completely new sentence.
And we're hoping that
this procedure leads
to fewer artifacts,
more diversity, and more
realism for this adversarial
dataset collection procedure.
Our validation pipeline was
exactly the same as round 1.
And here is the
resulting data set.
It's a little bit
smaller because this kind
of adversarial dataset
collection is hard.
And you can see how
good Model 1 is.
It was actually pretty
hard for crowd workers
to fool this model.
They did so only
about 19% of the time.
Here's the dataset for
distributional training.
You have about 93,000 sentences.
And if you go for the
majority-label training,
you have about 19,000.
And the dev and test
sets are smaller.
But again, the reason
they're smaller
is that they are designed to
set Model 1 as having chance
performance on this data set.
And so that's what
I'll flesh out here.
You can see that this
model chance performance,
I showed you before that it's
doing pretty well on round one.
And we had that kind of tension
with the external benchmarks.
In terms of human
performance, we're at about 90
using that procedure
of synthesized,
kind of averaged F1 values.
And I would just note,
again, that that's certainly
conservative.
In that, almost
half of the workers
never disagreed with
the majority label.
So it is certainly within the
capacity of individual humans
to perform essentially
perfectly on this data set.
But 90 is, nonetheless,
a good signpost for us
as we think about hill
climbing and launching
subsequent rounds of DynaSent.
And here are some
short examples.
And I think they
make the same point
that our neutral category is
more aligned with the semantics
of what we mean when we
identify neutral sentences
and less heterogeneous than you
get from naturally occurring,
neutral sentences derived
from star rating metadata
and so forth.
So I'm hopeful
that this is a kind
of positive step toward
getting true ternary sentiment.
But we should be aware
that this label shift has
happened in these data sets.
And the final thing I want to
say is just to reiterate that,
if people do exciting
work with this dataset
and start to make real progress
on the existing rounds, that
would be our cue to
launch new rounds.
The Dyna in DynaSent
is that we would
like to have an evolving
benchmark, not one that's
static but rather
responsive to progress
that's made in the field
and the evolving needs
of people who are trying to
develop practical sentiment
analysis systems.
So do let us know what
kind of progress you make
and what you discover.