CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is part 7 in our series on
supervised sentiment analysis.
The focus of this screencast
is on feature representation
of data.
There are really two
things I'd like to do.
First, just explore some
ideas for effective feature
representation in the context
of sentiment analysis.
And, second, cover some of
the core technical concepts
that surround feature
representation that you'd
do well to have in mind as you
write new feature functions
and optimize models.
Let's begin in a
familiar place which
is N-gram feature functions.
To this point in the
series of screencasts,
I've been just focusing on
unigram feature functions.
That's also called the
"bag-of-words" model,
and we can easily generalize
that idea to bigrams,
and trigrams, and so forth.
All of these schemes
will be heavily
dependent on the
tokenizer that you've
chosen because, of course in
the end, for every example
we represent, we are simply
tokenizing that example
and then counting the
tokens in that example.
This can be combined of course
with preprocessing steps.
In part 2 in this series, I
covered the preprocessing idea
of _NEG marking.
Which is essentially
to mark words
as they appear in
a heuristic way
in the scope of
negative morphemes
as a way of indicating
that, for example, "good"
is positive in normal
context but might
become negative when it is
in the scope of a negation
like "not" or "never."
We would handle that as a
preprocessing step and that
would just create more unigrams
that our tokenizer would turn
into tokens and then would
be counted by these feature
representation schemes.
A hallmark of these
feature approaches
is that they create very
large, very sparse feature
representations.
You are going to have a column
in your feature representation
for every single word
that appears anywhere
in your training data.
And another important
thing to keep
in mind about this approach
is that, by and large, they
will fail to directly model
relationships between features
unless you make some special
effort to effectively interact
these features.
All you'll be doing is studying
their distribution with respect
to the class labels
that you have.
And it's very
unlikely that you'll
recover, in any
deep way, the kind
of underlying synonymy of
words like "couch" and "sofa,"
for example.
And this is a
shortcoming that we
might want to address as
we move into distributed
representations of
examples like deep learn.
So for our first
technical concept,
I would like to just distinguish
between feature functions
and features.
And to do this, I've just got
a fully worked out example
here using tools
from scikit-learn
that I think will make the
importance of this distinction
really clear and concrete.
So in cell 1, I've just
loaded a bunch of libraries.
In cell 2, I've got my
standard, kind of lazy unigrams
feature function, which is
taking in a stringed text,
downcasing it, and then simply
splitting on whitespace.
And then the counter
here is just turning that
into a count dictionary
mapping each token
to the number of times that
it appears in this example,
according to our tokenizer.
That would be fine for now.
In cell 3, I have a
tiny little corpus that
has just two words, a and b.
In cell 4, I create a
list of dictionaries
by calling unigrams_phi on each
of the texts in my corpus here.
So that gives me a list
of count dictionaries.
In 5, I use a
DictVectorizer, as covered
in a previous screencast.
And what that's going to do
is when I call fit_transform
on my list of
feature dictionaries,
it will turn it
into a matrix, which
is the input that all of these
scikit machine learning models
expect for their training data.
And in cell 7,
I've just given you
what I hope is a pretty
intuitive view of that design
matrix.
Underlyingly, it's
just an NumPy array.
But if we use pandas, we can
see that the columns here
correspond to the names of
each one of the features.
Because we have just two
word types in our corpus,
there are two columns, a
and b, and each of the rows
corresponds to an
example from our corpus.
And so you can see that our
first example has been reduced
to a representation that has
3 in its first dimension and 0
in its second, corresponding
to the fact that it has three
a's and no b's.
Example 2, a, a, b
is represented as a 2
in the first column and
a 1 in the second column,
and so forth.
So that's a first distinction.
We have this feature function
here, which is like a factory,
and depending on the data
that come in for our corpus,
we're going to get very
different features which
correspond to each one of
the columns in this feature
representation matrix.
Let's continue this a
little bit and think
about how this actually
interacts with the optimization
process.
So in cell 7 here, I've just
repeated that previous matrix
for reference.
In cell 8, I have the class
labels for our four examples,
and you can see there are
three distinct classes--
C1, C2, and C3.
I set up a logistic
regression model,
although that's not
especially important,
it's just a useful illustration.
And I call fit on my pair x, y.
That is my feature
representations and my labels,
and that's the
optimization process.
As part of that, and for
a convention for scikit,
the optimization process
creates this new attribute coef_
and this new attribute classes_.
coef_ here, these are the
weights that we learned as part
of the optimization process, and
of course classes_ corresponds
to the classes that inferred
from the label y that we input.
And here I'm just using
a pandas data frame again
to try to make this intuitive.
It's really just a NumPy
array, this coef_ object here.
And you can see that
the resulting matrix has
a row for each
one of our classes
and a column for each
one of our features.
And that's a useful reminder
that what the optimization
process for models like
this is actually doing
is learning a weight that
associates class feature name
pairs with a weight, right?
So it's not just that we
learn individual weights
for features, but rather
we learn them with respect
to each one of the classes.
And that's a hallmark
of optimization
for multi-class
models like this one.
And then in cell 12, I've just
shown you that you can actually
use the coef_ and this
other bias term, intercept_,
to recreate the
predictions of the model.
All you're doing is multiplying
examples by those coefficients
and adding in the bias term.
And this matrix here
is identical to what
you get in scikit, if you simply
directly call predict_proba
for predict probabilities
on your examples.
Let's turn back to
what we're trying
to do to create good models,
having those ideas in mind.
So let's just cover a few other
ideas for hand-built feature
functions that I think could
be effective for sentiment.
So, of course, we could have
lexicon-derived features.
I earlier showed you a
bunch of different lexicons.
And that could be used
to group our unigrams.
So we could have these feature
functions work in conjunction
with a "bag-of-words" or
"bag-of-acronyms" model,
or we could use them to
replace that model and develop
a sparser feature
representation space.
We could also do
the negation marking
that I mentioned before, and
we could generalize that idea.
So many things in
language take scope
in a way that will affect
the semantics of words
that are in their scope.
So another classical example
behind-- besides negation
is these modal adverbs like
"quite possibly" or "totally".
We might have the idea
that they are modulating
the extent to which
the speaker is
committed to "masterpiece"
or "amazing," in this case.
And keeping track of
that semantic association
with simple underscore
marking of some kind
might be useful for
giving our model a chance
to see that these
unigrams are different
depending on their environment.
We can also have
length based features,
and that's just a useful
reminder that these don't all
have to be count features.
We can have real valued
features of various kinds
and they could signal something
important about the class
label.
For example, I think
neutral reviews,
three star reviews tend to
be longer than one and five
star reviews, so might
as well throw that in.
And we could expand that
idea of float valued
features a little bit more.
I like the idea of
thwarted expectations
which you might keep
track of as the ratio
of positive to negative
words in a sentence.
The idea being that very often
if that ratio is exaggerated,
it's telling you the opposite
story that you might expect
about the overall sentiment.
Many, many positive
words stacked up together
might actually be preparing
you for a negative assessment
and the reverse.
But the important thing
about this feature
is that it wouldn't decide for
you what these ratios mean.
You would just hope that
it was a useful signal
that your model might pick
up on as part of optimization
to figure out how to make
use of the information.
And then, finally, we could
do things, various kinds
of ad-hoc feature
functions to try
to capture the fact that
many uses of language
are non-literal and might
be signaling exactly
the opposite of what they
seem to do on their surface.
Like, "Not exactly
a masterpiece."
is probably a pretty
negative review.
It was "Like 50 hours long." is
not saying that it was actually
50 hours long but rather,
with hyperbole, indicating
that it was much too long
or something like that.
And "The best movie in the
history of the universe."
could be a ringing endorsement,
but it could just as easily
be a bit of sarcasm.
Capturing those kind
of subtle distinctions
is, of course, much
more difficult.
But the hand-built
feature functions
that you write where you
could try to capture it,
and if they have
a positive effect,
then maybe you've made
some real progress.
And that's a good
transition point
to this topic of assessing
individual feature functions.
As you can see, the philosophy
in this mode of work
is that you write lots
of feature functions
and kind of see how well
they can do at improving
your model overall.
You might end up with
a very large model
with many correlated
features and that
might lead you to want to do
some feature selection to weed
out the ones that are not
contributing in a positive way.
Now, scikit-learn
has a whole library
for doing this called
feature selection,
and it offers lots
of functions that
will let you assess how much
information your feature
functions contain with
respect to the labels
for your classification problem.
So this is very powerful.
And I encourage you to use them,
but you should be a little bit
cautious.
Take care when assessing
feature functions individually
because correlations
between those features
will make the assessments
very hard to interpret.
The problem here is that
your model is holistically
thinking about how
all of these features
relate to your class
label and figuring out
how to optimize
weights on that basis,
whereas the feature function
methods, many of them,
just look at individual
features and how
they relate to the class label.
So you're losing all that
correlational context.
And to make that
a little concrete,
I just cooked up an example
here, an idealized one, that
shows how you could be misled.
So I have three
features, x1, x2, and x3
in a simple binary
classification problem.
And I use the chi-square
test from feature selection
to kind of assess how important
each one of these features
is with respect to this
classification problem.
And what I found is
that, intuitively, it
looks like x1 and x2 are
really powerful features.
And that might lead me
to think, well, I'll
drop the third
feature and include
just one and two in my model.
So far, so good.
However, if we thoroughly
explore this space, what
we find is that in truth a
simple linear model performs
best with just feature
x1 and actually
including x2 hurts the
model, despite the fact
that it has this positive
feature importance value.
So what you really
ought to be doing
is using just this
single feature,
but these methods
can't tell us that.
And even a positive
feature selection value
might actually be
something that's
at odds with what we're
trying to do with our model,
as this example shows.
So, ideally, what
you would do is
consider more holistic
assessment methods
which scikit also offers.
This would be things like
systematically removing
or perturbing feature values in
the context of the full model
that you're optimizing
and comparing performance
across those models.
This is much more
expensive because you're
optimizing many, many models.
So it might be prohibitive
for some classes of models
that you're exploring.
But if you can do it, this
will be more reliable.
However, if this
is impossible, it
might still be productive
to do some feature selection
using simpler methods.
You should just
be aware that you
might be doing
something that's not
optimal for the actual
optimization problem
that you've posed.
OK, and the final section
of this screencast
is a kind of transition into
the world of deep learning.
I've called this distributed
representations as features.
This is a very different
mode for thinking
about representing examples.
What we do in this case is
take our token stream as before
but instead of writing a lot of
hand-built feature functions,
we simply look up each one of
those tokens in some embedding
that we have.
For example, it
could be an embedding
that you created in the
first unit of this course.
Or it could be a GloVe
embedding or a static embedding
that you derived from
BERT representations,
and so forth and so on.
The important thing is
that each token is now
represented by a vector and
that could be a powerful idea
because in representing each
of these words as vectors,
we are now capturing
the relationships
between those tokens.
We might now have
a hope of seeing
that "sofa" and
"couch" are actually
similar features
in general and not
just with respect to the
class labels that we have.
So that's the idea why
this might be powerful.
So we take all those
vectors and look them up.
However, for all these
classifier models,
we need a fixed
dimensional representation
to feed into the
actual classifier unit.
So we're going to have
to combine those vectors
in some way, and the
simplest thing you could do
is combine them via some
function like sum or mean,
right?
So take all these
things, for example,
and take their average and that
would give me another fixed
dimensional representation,
no matter how many tokens are
in each one of the examples.
And that average vector would
be the input to the classifier.
So if each one of these vectors
has dimension 300, then so,
too, does the feature
representation
of my entire example.
And I now have a
classifier which
is processing feature
representations that
have 300 columns.
Each dimension in the
underlying embedding space
now corresponds to a feature.
And that's the basis
for optimization.
And I'd say an eye opening
thing about this class of models
is despite them
being very compact--
300 dimensions versus 20,000
that you might have from
a "bag-of-words" model--
they turn out to
be very powerful.
And this final slide
here just shows you
how to implement those using
tools and other utilities
for our course.
So I'm going to
use GloVe, and I'm
going to use the 300 dimensional
GloVe space which is included
in your data distribution.
In 4 and 5 here, we just
write simple feature functions
and the hallmark of these
is that they are simply
looking up words
in the embedding
and then combining them
via whatever function they
use or specifies.
So the output of
this is directly
a vector representation
of each example.
In cell 6, we set up a
logistic regression, as before.
Of course, it could be
a much fancier model
but logistic regression will do.
And then we use sst_experiment
almost exactly as before.
The one change we
need to remember
to make in operating
in this mode is
to set the flag of
vectorized equals false.
We already have each example
represented as a vector,
so we do not need to pass it
through that whole process
of using a DictVectorizer
to turn count
dictionaries into vectors.
And as I said before,
these turn out
to be quite good models
despite their compactness.
And the final thing I'll
say is that this model
is a nice transition into
the recurrent neural networks
that we'll study in the final
screencast for this unit, which
essentially generalize
this idea by learning
an interesting combination
function for all
the vectors for each of
the individual tokens.