CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is part 4 of our series
on presenting your research.
We're going to be talking
about the possibly
thrilling and possibly
nerve-wracking
process of giving a
conference talk in our field.
Let's start with the
basic structure of a talk.
This is pretty easy.
It's probably going to mirror
the structure of papers
in our field.
But the thing to keep in mind
is that the top narrative
has to be dramatically simpler.
The beginning should start
just like a paper does
and just like an abstract does.
You need to answer questions
that involve context.
What problem are you solving?
Why is the problem important?
What's been tried before and
why wasn't it a full solution?
These things will
contextualize your results
and set your audience up to be
prepared for the contribution
that you're about to offer.
That will happen in the middle.
You'll give concrete
details about what
data you used, and then
crucially what approach you
took, and what its details
are up to the level of detail
you can supply in
a talk like this.
And also information
about your metrics.
How do you evaluate success?
These concrete details are
what constitute your proposal,
and they're really crucial.
And then in the final
part of the talk,
you'll offer results in the
form of tables, and graphs,
and so forth.
And you might review some
aspects of the analysis from
your paper-- what
worked and what didn't.
What work still needs to be
done, and things like that.
And then crucially
at the very end,
you should be sure to articulate
what you achieved in the work
and why it's significant.
The idea is to leave the
audience with information
that will compel them to take
the time and energy to read
your actual paper for the full
details on your contribution.
And then that way,
the talk will serve
as an effective advertisement
for the underlying project.
Now you can read lots of
advice on the internet
about how to give effective
talks in various contexts.
And I would encourage you to
seek it out, because some of it
might really align
with your style.
You should keep in mind
though that styles differ
and contexts differ.
And so this will be a process
of figuring out what advice
is really suitable for you.
The one thing that I
can say with confidence
is that Patrick Blackburn's
fundamental insight
will apply no matter what the
context and what the style.
Patrick Blackburn asks, where
do good talks come from?
And his answer is honesty.
He says, a good
talk should never
stray far from simple,
honest communication.
And if you abide
by that, and you're
introspective about
where you've achieved
open, honest
communication and where
you fell short in various
talks that you give,
and you're willing to
learn from that process,
you will definitely
find your style
and become an
effective communicator
about scientific
ideas, according
to what works best for you.
A note about PowerPoint.
You can find lots
of think pieces
about how PowerPoint and
related slide technologies are
inherently kind of evil.
I think they can be used
to confuse and deceive,
but they also have lots
of good aspects to them.
And it's not an
accident that slides
are pretty pervasive when
giving talks in our field.
And it's just a matter,
again, of finding your style
and thinking about how
to use these slides
for open, honest communication.
In that vein, and again, this
is a matter of personal style,
I thought I would mention two
kind of schools of thought
when it comes to slide design.
The minimalist and
the comparative.
So the minimalist
would probably just
have two words on the slide,
the minimalist and comparative.
And the rest would be
delivered via a talk track.
The idea behind the
minimalist approach
is a slide should be
as spare as possible.
The audience should spend most
of their time listening and--
listening to you
and looking at you.
And individual slides
don't stay up for very long
or get used in
more than one way.
They're kind of punctuation
for your narrative talk track.
By contrast, the
comparative approach
would be to have lots of
details on your slides.
Slides should be
as full as possible
without sacrificing clarity.
Your talk should make
it easy for people
to spend time
studying your slides.
You have to think about how
your narrative is going to align
with the very detailed slides.
And individual slides might
stay up for a long time
and get used to make
multiple comparisons
and establish
numerous connections.
I want to emphasize
again that this is really
a personal matter.
The minimalist view seems
right for telling a story.
It's often the best when
time is of the essence,
and the audience is
mainly there to learn
about what your paper contains.
Whereas the comparative view
seems right for teaching,
right?
It's the closest
that the slides can
come to full, well-organized
chalkboards and things
like that, where a
lot of information
might stay up for
a very long time.
Fundamentally, though,
this is a matter of style.
Find the version that works for
you for the context you're in.
And I'll just say again, as
long as you think long and hard
about what it would be like
to listen to your talk, that
is that open communication part,
and you adjust accordingly,
I'm sure that you'll
shine no matter
what approach you choose.
I really like
slides when it comes
to using them to guide
audience attention and help
people follow the narrative
of your talk track.
One fundamental thing
that you can do for that
is make heavy use of overlays.
Overlays might allow you to
fill a slide with information
in that comparative
mode whilst still
keeping the audience with you
as you make individual points.
You can also use
color systematically
on the slide to create
distinctions and highlight
different pieces of information.
If you use it
consistently, then people
will figure out that you're
using color for one concept,
and that will really help
them key into the structure
of your ideas.
Take an accessible
color palette,
and then this can
really be your friend
when it comes to communicating
with an audience.
You can also use size to draw
attention to things, and boxes,
and arrows, and
other devices to help
people navigate, especially
complex information
displayed on your slides.
This is incredibly useful
when you are, for example,
displaying a figure of
results, to have boxes
as overlays on the individual
comparisons and results
that you want to highlight.
Same thing for a model diagram.
You could show the
whole model diagram
and then use boxes to highlight
different pieces of information
in the diagram as you talk about
them in your narrative talk
track.
And that can be
incredibly valuable
when it comes to helping people
navigate what would otherwise
be a very complicated
looking slide.
Of course, you could
offer the information
that I just delivered in
the more minimalist version.
This would be like overlays,
color, size, boxes, and arrows,
and so forth.
For particular styles,
that might be exactly
the right moment to talk about
guiding audience attention.
You can probably see that
it's not really my style,
but it's certainly a valid style
that can be very effective.
Some more mundane things.
Turn off any notifications that
might appear on your screen.
If you're on up in front of an
audience of hundreds of people
and we see a notification
about a friend's email,
well, it will certainly
be an entertaining thing
for your audience to
see, but it might not
be something that you wanted
to be part of your talk.
Make sure your computer
is out of power-save mode
so that the screen doesn't
shut off while you're talking.
Projectors can be finicky.
And even one time,
losing your screen
could cause you to
lose the projector
and burn through a
bunch of the time
that you have allotted
for your talk.
And that could be really sad.
Shut down running applications
that might tax your computer
or otherwise get
in your way, again
with notifications
and things like that.
Make sure your desktop is
clear of files and notes
that you wouldn't
want the world to see.
In this day and
age, your desktop
might flash for a second
before the slides come up.
And for all you
know, this talk is
going to end up on YouTube
for the whole world to see.
So think about the
privacy aspects of this.
If you're using PowerPoint,
or Keynote, or Google Slides,
or something like that,
create a PDF as a backup.
If your program fails
or the internet fails,
you might not have access
to your primary version.
Having a PDF backup will
certainly be helpful.
And be prepared
for the worst case.
What if the projector fails?
You might really
be glad that you're
prepared to give the
talk without any slides.
Imagine that scenario.
The audience will
be on your side
in the presence of such
a failure of technology,
and it could be really a
chance for you to shine.
And the one thing I'll
say is that if you're
prepared, genuinely prepared to
give your talk without slides,
the resulting talk
will be better
because the narrative
part of your talk
will be so much stronger.
Finally, the discussion
period, which
could be an exciting discussion
period or the most dreaded part
of this whole process.
It's an important part of
your presentation though.
It should be a chance
for the audience
to gain a deeper
understanding of your ideas.
And when the discussion
period actually has that aim,
it's really a joy
and it feels like you
and your audience are
moving forward together.
Sometimes other
things happen, though.
You could get a hostile
questioner, or a confused
questioner, or something
even more chaotic.
Be ready for this, and just
try to remain on an even keel
no matter what happens.
When you get questions,
after each one,
take a pause for a
second before answering.
This will serve two functions.
First, you'll make sure
that the person is actually
finished asking
their question, which
I think is socially useful.
And second, it will just make
you appear more deliberative,
which is good.
So even if you know exactly
what answer you want to give,
taking the pause will
create a good impression
on your audience.
Avoid where possible saying,
I have no idea in response
to things, and
leaving it at that.
If you truly are floored, you
might, say I have no idea,
but let's think about the
following other considerations.
There might be cases where
you actually just want to say,
I have no idea and
leave it at that.
But I think that that should
be used very sparingly.
Most questions won't
make total sense to you.
You have to remember that
your questioner doesn't know
the work as well as you do.
They might have lost track
of some of the details
or gotten distracted
for a moment.
The question might not
completely make sense.
You'll feel victorious though
if you can work every question
you get into one that makes
sense and leaves everyone
with the impression
that the questioner
raised an important issue.
Again, that's
another way that you
can create a collective
feeling that the discussion was
productive.
And as a group, move the
ideas forward as part
of this discussion period.
That's when this
is really exciting.
And you should do everything you
can to strive for such moments
knowing, though, that
things could go really awry.
And don't try to internalize
those too much either.
This is a messy process.
But fundamentally,
I think, it can
be quite rewarding in the end.