CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to part 6 in our
series on supervised sentiment
analysis.
This screencast is going to
cover two important methods
in this space, hyperparameter
search and classifier
comparisons.
So let's begin with
hyperparameter search.
And first, I'll just
offer the rationale.
Let's say that the
parameters of a model
are those whose values
are learned as part
of optimizing the model itself.
So for the classifiers
we've been studying,
the parameters are
really just the weights
that you learn on each of
the individual features.
And those are the things
that are directly targeted
by the optimization process.
The parameters of a model
are typically pretty
crisply defined because
they kind of follow
from the structure
mathematically of the model
under investigation.
Much more diffuse are
the hyperparameters.
We can say the
hyperparameters of a model
are any settings that are
outside of the optimization
process mentioned in 1.
So examples from models
we've seen, our GloVe and LSA
have that
dimensionality setting.
The model itself
gives you no guidance
about what to choose
for the dimensionality.
And the dimensionality
is not selected
as part of the optimization
of the model itself.
You have to choose it via
some external mechanism,
making it a hyperparameter.
And GloVe actually has two
other additional prominent
hyperparameters, xmax and alpha.
Again, those are not
optimized by the model.
You have to select them via
some external mechanism.
And for the classifiers
that we've been studying,
we have regularization terms.
Those are classic
hyperparameters.
If you have a deep
classifier, then
the hidden dimensionalities
in the model
could also be considered
hyperparameters.
Learning rates, any core feature
of the optimization method
itself could be considered
hyperparameters.
And even things that
might be considered
kind of architectural,
like the activation
function and the
deep classifier,
you might think of it as kind of
an intrinsic part of the model
that you're evaluating.
But since it's an easy choice
point for us at this point,
you'll be tempted to explore
a few different options
for that particular
architectural choice.
And in that way, it could
become a hyperparameter.
And at this point, even
the optimization methods
could also emerge
as a hyperparameter
that you would like
to do search over.
And so forth and so
on, you should probably
take a fairly expansive view
of what the hyperparameters
of your model are if you can.
Now here's the crux
of the argument.
Hyperparameter optimization
is crucial to building
a persuasive argument.
Fundamentally, for any
kind of comparison we make,
we want to put every model
in its very best light.
We could take it for granted
that for any sufficiently
complicated model there's some
setting of its hyperparameters
that's kind of
degenerate and would
make the model look very bad.
And so you certainly
wouldn't want
to do any comparisons against
that really problematic set
of choices.
Rather, what we
want to do is say,
let's put all the models
in their best light
by choosing optimal
hyperparameters for them
to the best of our ability.
And then we can say that one
model is better than the other
if it emerges victorious in
that very rigorous setting.
And the final thing I'll say
about this methodologically
is that, of course, all
hyperparameter tuning
must be done only on train
and development data.
You can consider that
all fair game in terms
of using it however
you want to choose
the optimal hyperparameters.
But once that choice
is set, it is fixed.
And those are the parameters
that you use at test time.
And that is the
fundamental evaluation
that you would use for any
kind of model comparison.
And at no point should you be
tuning these hyperparameters
on the test data itself.
That would be
completely illegitimate.
I hope we've made
it really easy to do
this kind of
hyperparameter search
in the context of
the work you're
doing for supervised
sentiment analysis.
Here are some code snippets
that show how that can happen.
In loading my libraries,
I have a pointer
to our sentiment data.
And here I have a fixed
feature function, which is just
a unigram feature function.
The change happens
inside the model wrapper.
Whereas before,
essentially, all we did
was set up a logistic
regression model
and then call its fit method,
here we set up that model
but also established a
grid of hyperparameters.
These are different
choice points
for this logistic
regression model
like whether or
not I have a bias
term, the value of the
regularization parameter,
and even the algorithm
used for regularization
itself, L1 or L2.
The model will explore the
full grid of these options.
It's going to do five-fold
cross validation, so test one
each five times on different
splits of the data.
And in that very
long search process,
it will find what it takes
to be the best setting of all
of these hyperparameters,
of all the combinations
that can logically be set.
And that is the model that we
finally return here, right?
So now you can see the
value of having a wrapper
around these fit methods.
Because then I could do
all of this extra work
without changing the interface
to sst.experiment at all.
The experiments look just as
they did in the previous mode.
It's just that they will
take a lot longer because you
are running dozens and
dozens of experiments
as part of this
exhaustive search of all
the possible settings.
OK, part 2 is
classifier comparison.
Once again, begin
with the rationale.
Suppose you've assessed
a baseline Model B
and your favorite model M. And
your chosen assessment metric
favors M. And this seems like
a little victory for you.
But you should still ask
yourself, is M really better,
right?
Now if the difference
between B and M
is clearly of
practical significance,
then you might not need to
do anything beyond presenting
the numbers, right?
If each one of your
classification decisions
corresponds to something
really important in the world
and your classifier
makes thousands
more good predictions
than the other model,
that might be enough
for the argument.
But even in that
situation, you might
ask whether there's variation
in how these two models
B and M perform.
Did you just get
lucky when you saw
what looked like a
practical difference
and with minor changes to the
initialization or something,
you would see very
different outcomes?
If the answer is
possibly yes, then you
might still want to do some
kind of classifier comparison.
Now there's this nice
paper by Demsar 2006
that advises using the Wilcoxon
signed-rank test for situations
in which you can afford
to repeatedly assess
your two models B and M on
different train test splits,
right?
And we'll talk later in the
term about the precise rationale
for this.
But the idea is just that you
would do a lot of experiments
on slightly different
views of your data
and then kind of
average across them
to get a sense for how the two
models compare with each other.
In situations where you can't
repeatedly assess B and M,
McNemar's test is a
reasonable alternative.
It operates on the confusion
matrices produced by the two
models, testing the null
hypothesis that the two models
have the same error rate.
The reason you might
opt for McNemar's test
is, for example, if you're
doing a deep learning
experiment where all the models
take a few weeks to optimize.
Then of course,
you can't probably
afford to do dozens and dozens
of experiments with each one.
So you might be compelled to
use McNemar's based on one
single run of the two models.
It's a much weaker argument
because, of course,
precisely the point is
that we might see variation
across different runs.
And McNemar's is
not really going
to grapple with that in
the way that the Wilcoxon
signed-rank test will.
But this is arguably better
than nothing in most situations.
So you might default to
McNemar's if the Wilcoxon
is too expensive.
And let me just
show you how easy
this can be in the
context of our code base.
So by way of illustration, what
we're essentially going to do
is compare logistic
regression and naive Bayes.
I encourage you, when you're
doing these comparisons,
to have only one
point of variation.
So we're going to fix
the data and we're
going to fix the
feature function
and compare only the
model architectures.
You could separately
say I'm going
to have a single fixed model
like logistic regression
and explore a few different
feature functions.
But I would advise against
exploring two different feature
functions as combined
with two different models
because when you observe
differences in the end,
you won't be sure whether that
was caused by the model choice
or by the feature functions.
We want to isolate these things
and do systematic comparisons.
So here, I'm going to do
a systematic comparison
of logistic regression
and naive Bayes
on the SST using
the Wilcoxon test.
And here's the setup.
The function is
sst_compare_models.
I point it to my training data.
You can have two
feature functions.
But in that case, you should
have just one model wrapper.
Here, I've got one feature
function used for both models.
And I'll have these
two different wrappers
corresponding to the
evaluation that I
want to do of those
two model classes.
I'm going to use the
Wilcoxon as advised.
I'll do 10 trials of each on the
train size of 70% of the data.
And as always, in
this setting, I'll
use the macro F1 as my score.
So what this will
do internally is
run 10 experiments on
different train test
splits for each one
of these models.
That gives us a score vector,
10 numbers for each model.
And then what the
Wilcoxon is doing
is comparing whether
the-- or assessing
whether the means of
those two score vectors
are statistically
significantly different.
And here it looks like
we have some evidence
that we can reject the null
hypothesis that these models
are identical, which is
presumably the argument that we
were trying to build.
Now, of course,
that's very expensive
because we had to run 20
experiments in this situation.
And of course, you
could run many more
if you were also doing
hyperparameter tuning as part
of your experimental workflow.
So in situations where you can't
afford to do something that
involves so many
experiments, as I said,
you couldn't default
to McNemar's.
That is included
in utils.mcnemar.
And the return values
of SST experiment
will give you all the
information you need.
Essentially from McNemar's you
need the actual goal vector
of labels and then
the two vectors
of predictions for each
one of your experiments.
So that's a simple
alternative in the situation
in which Wilcoxon's
was just too expensive.