CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is Part 5 in our series
on methods and metrics.
We're going to be talking
about essential selected
topics in model
evaluation in our field.
Here's our overview.
I'd like to start by talking
about baselines and their role
in experimental comparisons.
Then we'll discuss
hyperparameter optimization,
both the process
and the motivations,
as well as compromises
that you might
have to make due to
resource constraints
and other constraints.
We'll touch briefly on
classifier comparison,
which is a topic we covered in
the sentiment analysis unit.
And then we'll close with
two topics that are really
pressing for deep learning
models, which is assessing
models without convergence and
the role of random parameter
initialization in shaping
experimental results.
So let's begin with baselines.
The fundamental insight
here is that in our field
evaluation numbers can
never be understood properly
in isolation.
Let's consider
two extreme cases.
Suppose your system
gets 0.95 F1,
then you might feel like you can
declare victory at that point.
But it will be
natural for people
who are consuming your
results to ask, well,
is the task too easy?
Is it really an achievement
that you've got 0.95?
Or would even
simpler systems have
achieved something similar?
At the other end
of the spectrum,
suppose your system
gets 0.6 F1, you
might think that means you
haven't gotten traction.
But we should ask two questions.
First, what do humans get
as a kind of upper bound?
And also, what would a
random classifier get?
And if your 0.6 is
really different
from the random classifier
and human performance
is kind of low, we might
then see that this 0.6
F1 is a real achievement.
Now it kind of shows
you that baselines
are just crucial for strong
experiments in our field.
So defining baselines
for you should not
be an afterthought, but
rather central to how you
define your overall hypothesis.
Baselines are really important
for building a persuasive case.
And they can be used to
illuminate specific aspects
of the problem that
you're tackling
and specific virtues of
your proposed system.
But this really comes down
to is, right from the start,
you might be saying,
for example, here's
a baseline model, here's my
proposed modification of it.
And the way we test
your hypothesis
is by comparing the performance
of those two systems.
In that context, you can see
that the baseline is playing
a crucial role in quantifying
the extent to which
your hypothesis is true.
And therefore, careful model
comparisons at that level
are going to be
really fundamental
to successful pursuit
of the hypothesis.
When in doubt, you could
include random baselines
in your results table.
They are very easy
to set up and can
illuminate what it's
like if we're just
making random predictions.
And here I'm showing you
that scikit-learn kind of
has you covered on this point.
They have two classes,
DummyClassifier
and DummyRegressor, each with
a wide range of different ways
that they can make random
guesses based on the data.
And I would encourage you to
use these classes because it
will make it easy for you
to fit the random baselines
into your overall experimental
pipeline, which will reduce
the amount of code that you
have to write and possibly avoid
bugs that might come from
implementing these baselines
yourself.
So strongly encouraged.
And kind of at the other
end of the spectrum,
you might think, for
your task, whether there
are task-specific baselines
that you should be considering.
Because they might
reveal something
about the dataset, or
the problem, or the way
people are going about
modeling the problem.
We saw an example of this
before in the context
of natural language inference.
We saw that hypothesis-only
baselines tended to make
predictions that were as
good as 0.65 to 0.70 F1,
which is substantially better
than the baseline random chance
which would be at about 0.33.
And that's revealing to us that
when we measure performance,
we should really be
thinking about gains
above that
hypothesis-only baseline.
Comparisons against
random chance
are going to vastly overstate
the extent to which we
have made meaningful
progress on those datasets.
The story of the Story Cloze
task is somewhat similar.
Here the task is to distinguish
between a coherent and
incoherent ending for a story.
And people observed
that systems that
looked only at
the ending options
were able to do really well.
There is some bias in coherent
and incoherent continuations
that leads them to be pretty
good evidence for making
this classification decision.
Again, you might
think that reveals
that there's a fundamental
problem with the data set.
And that might be true.
But another
perspective is simply
that when we do comparisons
and think about the model's
performance, it should be
with this as the baseline
and not random guessing.
OK, let's talk about
hyperparameter optimization.
We discussed this in our
unit on sentiment analysis.
And we walked through
some of the rationale.
Let me quickly reiterate
the full case for this.
First, hyperparameter
optimization
might be crucial for obtaining
the best version of your model
that you can, which might
be your fundamental goal.
Probably for any modern model
that you're looking at there
is a wide range of
hyperparameters.
And we might know that
different settings of them
lead to very different outcomes.
So it's in your best interest
to do hyperparameter search
to put your model in
the very best light.
We also talked at
length about how
this is a crucial step in
conducting fair comparisons
between models.
It's really important that
when you conduct a comparison
you not put one model in
its best light with its best
hyperparameter settings and
have all the other models
be kind of randomly chosen
or even poorly chosen
hyperparameter
settings, because that
would lead to unfair comparisons
and exaggerate differences
between the models.
What we want to do
is compare the models
all with their best possible
hyperparameter settings.
And that implies doing extensive
search to find those settings.
And the third motivation
you might have
is just to understand the
stability of your architecture.
We might want to know for some
large space of hyperparameters
which ones really matter
for final performance,
maybe which ones lead to
really degenerate solutions,
and which space
of hyperparameters
overall perform the best.
So that we have more than just
a single set of parameters
that work well, but
maybe real insights
into the overall settings of
the models that are really good.
There's one more rule that
I need to reiterate here.
All hyperparameter
tuning must be done only
on train and development data.
It is a sin in our field to
do any kind of hyperparameter
tuning on a test set.
All of that tuning should
happen outside of the test set.
And then as usual,
you get one run
on the test set with
your chosen parameters
and that is the number that
you report as performance
on the test data.
That's the only way
that we can really
get a look at how
these systems behave
on completely unseen data.
So this is really crucial
for understanding progress
in our field.
Now hyperparameter optimization,
as you can imagine,
can get very expensive.
And let's review that and then
talk about some compromises,
right?
The ideal for
hyperparameter optimization
is that you identify a large
set of values for your model.
You create a list of all the
combinations of those values.
This will be the cross
product of all the values
of the features
that you identified.
And for each of
the settings, you
should cross validate it on
the available training data.
And then choose the settings
that are the best at step
three, train on all the training
data using those settings.
And then finally,
evaluate on the test data.
That is the ideal here.
And let's just think about how
that's actually going to work.
Suppose for our example that
we have one hyperparameter
and it has five values.
And we have a second
hyperparameter with ten values.
Then the cross product
is going to lead
us to have 50 total settings
for those hyperparameters.
Suppose we add a third
hyperparameter with two values.
Now the number of settings that
we have has jumped up to 100.
If we want to do
5-fold cross-validation
to select those
optimal parameters,
then we are talking about doing
500 different experiments.
That's probably
perfectly fine if you're
dealing with a
small linear model
with some hand-built features.
But if you are fitting a
large transformer-based model
where each experiment
takes you up to one day,
this is going to be
prohibitively expensive
in terms of time or
compute resources.
And that's going to compel
us to make some compromises.
This is the bottom line here.
The above picture,
that ideal, is
untenable as a set of laws
for our scientific community.
If we adopted it,
then complex models
trained on large data sets
would end up disfavored
and only the very wealthy
would be able to participate.
And just to give you a
glimpse of just how expensive
this could get,
here's a quotation
from this nice paper
on NLP and machine
learning for health care.
In their supplementary
materials,
they report that
performance on all
of the above neural networks
was tuned automatically using
Google Vizier with a total
of over 200,000 GPU hours.
For me as a private
citizen, that
could easily cost a
half a million dollars
just for the process of
hyperparameter optimization.
And that's what I mean by this
being kind of fundamentally
untenable for us.
So what should we
do in response?
We need a pragmatic
response here.
Here are some
steps that you take
to alleviate the problem in what
I view as kind of descending
order of attractiveness.
So starting with
the best option,
you could do some
random sampling
and maybe guided
sampling to explore
a large space of hyperparameters
on a fixed computational
budget.
You could do search based
on just a few epochs
of training, right, rather
than allowing your model
to run for many epochs,
which could take a whole day.
You might select hyperparameters
based on one or two epochs,
on the assumption that settings
that are good at the start
will remain good and settings
that are bad at the start
will remain bad.
That's a heuristic assumption.
But it seems reasonable.
You could possibly bolster
it with some learning curves
and so forth.
And that could vastly
cut down on the amount
that you have to spend
in this search process.
You can also search based
on subsets of the data.
This would be another
kind of compromise.
However because a lot of
hyperparameters are dependent
on dataset size,z think
of regularization terms.
This might be riskier
than the version in 2
there where we just
trained for a few epochs.
You also might do some
heuristic search, maybe
by defining which
hyperparameters matter less
and then set those by hand
based on this heuristic search.
And then you might just describe
that process in the paper
that via few observations
you made some guesses
about parameters
that you could fix
and therefore explored a smaller
subset of the space that you
might have liked to explore.
Again, I think if
you make the case
and you're clear
about this, readers
will be receptive because
we're aware of the costs.
You can also find
optimal hyperparameters
via a single split of
your data and use them
for all subsequent splits.
That would be justified if
the splits are very similar
and your model performance
is very stable.
And that would reduce all
that cross-validation that
did cause the number
of experiments
we had to run to jump
up by a large amount.
And finally, you might
adopt other's choices.
Now the skeptic will complain
that these findings don't
translate to new data sets,
but it could be the only option
that you just
observe for example
that for some very large
model, the original authors use
settings X, Y, and Z,
then you might simply
adopt them even knowing that
your dataset or your test
might call for different
optimal settings.
It isn't the best.
But if it's the only
thing that you can afford,
it's certainly a
reasonable case to make.
Finally some tools for
hyperparameter search.
As usual scikit-learn
has a bunch
of great tools for this,
GridSearch, RandomizedSearch,
and HalvingGridSearch.
GridSearch will be
the most expensive,
RandomizedSearch
the least expensive,
and HalvingGridSearch
will help you
kind of strategically
navigate through the space
of hyperparameters.
And if you want to go even
further in that direction,
the scikit-optimize
package offers a bunch
of tools for doing model-based
performance-driven exploration
of a space of hyperparameters.
And that could be
very effective indeed.
All right, let's talk briefly
about classifier comparison.
We've-- it's a topic
we've reviewed before,
but I'll just briefly recap.
The scenario is this.
Suppose you have assessed
two classifier models.
Their performance is probably
different to some degree
numerically.
What can be done to establish
whether those models are
different in some
meaningful sense?
As we've discussed, I think
guidance from the literature
is that first we could
cover practical differences.
If you just observed that one
model makes 10,000 more highly
important predictions
than another,
then that might be
sufficient to make the case
that it's the better model.
For differences
that are narrower,
again the guidance is that we
might use confidence intervals
on repeated runs.
Or the Wilcoxon signed-rank
test to give a single summary
statistic of whether or
not the different runs are
truly different in their
means and variance.
You could use McNemar's
test if you can only
afford to run one experiment,
whereas the Wilcoxon
and confidence
intervals will require
you to run 10 to 20 different
experiments, which again, could
be prohibitively expensive.
And in those situations,
you might fall back
to McNemar's test, because it's
less expensive and arguably
better than nothing,
especially in scenarios
where it's hard to tell whether
there are practical differences
between the systems.
Finally, let's talk
about two topics
that seem especially pressing
in the context of large scale
deep learning models.
And the first is assessing
models without convergence,
right?
When working with linear
models, convergence issues
rarely arise, because
the models seem
to converge quickly based on
whatever threshold you've set.
And convergence implies kind
of maximized performance
in a wide range of cases.
With neural networks
however, convergence issues
really take center stage.
The models rarely converge even
based on liberal thresholds
that you might set.
They converge at different
rates between runs,
so it's hard to predict.
And their performance
on the test data
is often heavily dependent
on these differences, right?
Sometimes a model
with a low final error
turns out to be great.
And sometimes it turns out
to be worse than one that
finished with a higher error.
Who really knows
what's going on?
Our only fallback
in these situations
is just do experiments
and observe
what seems to work the best.
So I think a very natural
and easy to implement
response to this that
proves highly effective
is what I'm calling your
incremental dev-set testing.
This is just the idea
that as training proceeds,
we will regularly collect
information about performance
on some held out dev-set as
part of the training process.
For example, at every
100th iteration,
you could make predictions
on that dev-set
and store those predictions
for some kind of assessment.
All the PyTorch
models for our course
have an early stopping
parameter that
will allow you to conduct
experiments in this way
and keep hold of what
seemed to be the best
model, performance-wise,
and then
report that based on
the stopping criteria
that you've set up.
And with luck,
heuristically, that
will give you the best
model in the fewest epochs.
And the early_stopping
parameter has a bunch
of different other
settings that you
can use to control
exactly how it behaves,
which might be important for
particular models structures
or data sets.
Here's a bit of our
motivation for early stopping.
You might be
thinking, why not just
let my model run to
convergence if I possibly can.
In the context of these large,
very difficult optimization
processes, that could lead
you really far astray, right?
So here is a picture of
a deep learning model.
And you can see its error
going down very quickly
over many iterations.
And it looks like you
might want to iterate out
to even to 80
epochs of training.
However, if you
look at performance
on that held-out dev set you
see that this model actually
very quickly reached
its peak of performance.
And then all that
remaining training
was just either wasting time
or eroding the performance
that you saw early
on in the process.
And this is exactly why since
this is our real goal here,
you might want to do some
kind of dev-set testing
with early stopping.
The final thing I'd want to
say here is that all of this
might lead us to get out
of the mode of assuming
that we should always
be recording one
number to summarize our models.
We're dealing with
very powerful models.
In the limit, they
might be able to learn
very complicated things.
And we might want to ask
different questions like how
quickly can they learn, and how
effectively, and how robustly.
And that might imply that
what we really want to do
is not report summary
tables of statistics,
but rather full learning curves
with confidence intervals.
This is a picture from a paper
that I was involved with.
And I think it's
illuminating to see
a by category breakdown of
how the model is performing
in addition to the
overall average.
Because you can see that
while this red model
is arguably much better than
the yellow and the gray overall.
It's kind of hard to
distinguish it globally
from this blue model.
But for various of
the subcategories,
you do see some differences.
Whereas for others,
you do see that they're
kind of indistinguishable.
It's a very rich picture.
You can also see that early on
for some of these categories
some of these models are
really differentiated.
They learn more efficiently.
Whereas by the time you've
run out to 100,000 epochs,
many of the model
distinctions have disappeared.
That's the kind of rich picture
that is already giving us
a sense for how different
values and different goals
we have might guide
different choices about which
model to use and different
choices about how to optimize.
And I would just
love it if our field
got into the habit of reporting
this very full picture, as
opposed to reducing
everything to a single number.
The final topic is the
role of random parameter
initialization.
This is kind of yet another
hyperparameter that's
in the background that's much
more difficult to think about.
Most deep learning models have
their parameters initialized
randomly, or many
of those parameters
are initialized randomly.
This is clearly meaningful for
these non-convex optimization
problems that we're posing.
But even simple
models can also be
impacted if you're dealing
with very small data sets
with very large feature spaces.
In this classic paper
here, these authors
just observed that
different initializations
for neural sequence
models that were doing
named entity recognition led
to statistically significantly
different results.
That is one and the same model
with a different random seed
was performing in ways that
looked significantly different
on these data sets.
And a number of recent
systems actually
turned out to be
indistinguishable in terms
of their raw performance
once this source of variation
was taken into account.
That's just a powerful example
of how much a random seed could
shape final performance in the
context of models like this.
Relatedly, at the other
end of the spectrum,
you can see catastrophic
failure as a result
of unlucky initialization.
Some settings are great and
some can be miserable failures.
We don't really know ahead
of time which will be which.
And that means that we just have
to be really attentive to how
we're initializing these systems
in a wide range of settings.
And you'll notice that
in the evaluation methods
notebook that I've distributed
as a companion to this lecture,
I fit a simple feed-forward
network, a very small one,
on the classic
XOR problem, which
is one of the original
motivating problems
for using deep
learning models at all.
And what you see is that it
succeeds about 8 out of 10
times, where the
only thing that we're
changing across these
models is the way they
are randomly initialized.
And that again just
shows you that this
can be powerfully shaping final
performance for our systems.
And probably what
we need to do is
be thinking about this as
yet another hyperparameter
that we need to tune
and optimize along
with all the rest.