CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone.
This is the first
screencast in our series
on natural language
inference, or NLI.
This is one of my
favorite problems.
What I'd like to do
is give you a sense
for how the task is
formulated and then
situate the task
within the broader
landscape of ideas for NLU.
As usual, we have a
bunch of materials
that would allow you to get
hands-on with this problem.
The core module is nli.py, and
then there are two notebooks.
The first introduces
the three data
sets that we'll be exploring
in detail, SNLI, multiNLI,
and adversarial NLI.
And the second notebook offers
a bunch of different modeling
approaches.
It really covers core
approaches that people
have taken to NLI
in the past, and I
hope it points to some
avenues for modifying
those architectures, possibly
in the service of developing
an original system
for a final project.
There's also an associated
homework and bakeoff.
I emphasize that this is not
required for us this quarter.
I'm mentioning it because
I think the problem is
an interesting one.
It's a word
entailment task which
is an interesting
small-scale problem
that I believe could be
used to stress-test an NLI
system in interesting ways.
The core readings cover
the three datasets
that will be in focus for us.
And then the final
reading listed here,
was I think, the paper that
introduced attention mechanisms
into the study of NLI and
that had an impact that
went well beyond this task.
And then, for
additional readings,
I'm kind of suggesting
a range of things.
Some of these readings
cover core fundamentals
for deep learning
that I think will
be useful in the
context of studying NLI.
Some of them help you with kind
of a foundational understanding
of the NLI task and how
you might think about it.
And then some of them
are meant to push
us to stress test our system,
think adversarially, and maybe
find artifacts in our datasets.
And those are going to be
themes of later screencasts
in the series.
To begin getting a sense for
how the task is formulated,
let's start with some
simple examples here.
So in NLI, we have as our
inputs a premise sentence
and a hypothesis
sentence, and the task
is a classification one.
So in this simple example
here, the premise sentence
is, "a turtle danced."
The hypothesis sentence
is "a turtle moved."
Both of those are system
inputs, and our task
is to assign one
of three labels.
In this case, the correct
label would be "entails."
The second example looks
simple, but it actually
begins to suggest how the
task is actually formulated.
We have as our premise, turtle.
And as our
hypothesis, linguists.
And what we would like to
do in the context of NLI
is assign that the
contradicts label.
Now, you might pause
there and think,
it's not a logical fact that
turtles can be linguists,
so surely contradiction
is too strong,
but it is a common
sense that to kind
of natural inference
about the world
we live in that no
turtles are linguists,
and it's for that reason
that we would choose
the contradicts label, and that
begins to key into the fact
that fundamentally NLI is
not a logical reasoning
task, but a more general
common sense reasoning task.
"Every reptile danced"
is neutral with respect
to "a turtle ate" which is
just to say that these two
sentences can be true or false
independently of each other.
And now, with entails
contradiction neutral,
we have the three labels
that are standardly used
for NLI datasets at this point.
Look at some
additional examples.
"Some turtles walk"
contradicts "no turtles move."
I think that's straightforward.
Here's one that shows how
intricate this could get.
So the premise is "James
Byron Dean refused
to move without blue jeans."
Entails "James Dean didn't
dance without pants."
This highlights two
aspects of the problem.
First, you might have to do
some complex named entity
recognition on James
Byron Dean and James Dean
to figure out that these
are coreferring expressions.
And you also might encounter
real linguistic complexity,
in this case, emphasizing
things involving how negations
interact with each other.
This next example begins to show
how much common sense reasoning
could be brought into the task.
So the premise is Mitsubishi's
new vehicle sales in the US
fell 46% in June,
and the hypothesis is
Mitsubishi's sales rose 46%.
And we would standardly say that
that is in the contradiction
relation.
Now again, you might
pause and think
it is certainly possible
even in our world
that Mitsubishi
could see a 46% rise
and fall in the same month.
So surely these should
be labeled neutral.
But I think what you'll find
in NLI datasets is that these
are called contradiction
on the informal assumption
that the premise
and hypothesis are
talking about the same event.
And in that context, we would
say that these are common sense
contradictions.
Here's another example
that highlights
how much pragmatics could
be brought into the problem.
The premise is Acme reported
that its CEO resigned,
and the hypothesis is
that Acme's CEO resigned.
We would probably
say entailment there.
Even though, in a
strict logical sense,
the premise does not entail the
hypothesis because, of course,
the company could be reporting
things that are false.
But here, we kind of
make an assumption
that the company is an
authority and will likely
report true things
about facts like this,
and therefore we
allow that this would
be in the entailment relation.
Again not logical but much
more like common sense.
So just to emphasize
this, here is
kind of the fundamental
question that we confront.
Does the premise justify an
inference to the hypothesis?
Commonsense reasoning,
rather than strict logic.
Two other characteristics
of this task
in the modern era
are, first, there's
a focus on local
inference steps.
That is just one premise
and one hypothesis,
rather than long
deductive chains.
And the second is
that the emphasis
is really on the variability
of linguistic expressions,
so when people have created
the large benchmark tasks
in this space, they have largely
focused on just collecting
a lot of data and not
placed any special emphasis
on collecting examples that
have a lot of negations
or quantifiers or
something that would really
shine a spotlight on linguistic
and semantic complexity.
So that's worth keeping
in mind about how
we're thinking about the
task in the present day.
If you would like
additional perspectives
on this, including some disputes
about exactly how to think
about the problem, and what
would be the most productive,
I would encourage you to check
out of these three papers
by a lot of Stanford
researchers.
I think the fundamental
outcome of this
is that we do want to focus
on common sense reasoning,
even though that's
a kind of amorphous
and difficult to define concept.
It's nonetheless arguably
the useful one for us
when we think about
developing practical systems.
Now, in a visionary paper
that really set the agenda
for NLI, Dagan et
al, 2006, they make
a lot of connections
between NLI and the broader
landscape of NLU.
So let me just read this
opening statement here.
It seems that major
inferences, as needed
by multiple
applications, can indeed
be cast in terms of
textual entailment.
Consequently, we hypothesize
that textual entailment
recognition is a
suitable generic task
for evaluating and comparing
applied semantic inference
models.
Eventually, such efforts
can promote the development
of entailment
recognition engines
which may provide useful generic
modules across applications.
So wonderful vision and
a spin we might put on
in the present day is that
what we might hope from NLI
is that since reasoning about
entailment and contradiction
are truly fundamental
to our use of language,
that pre-training
on the NLI task
might give us representations
that are useful in lots
of different contexts.
And Dagan et al
actually continue
by showing that we can formulate
a lot of traditional tasks
as NLI tasks.
And here are just a
few examples of that.
If our task is
paraphrased, we might
say that in the
NLI context, that
means we want equality or mutual
entailment between the text
and the paraphrase.
That is premise
and the hypothesis.
For summarization, we
would do something weaker.
We would hope just that the
text, the original text,
entailed the summaries
allowing that the summary might
be weaker or more general.
For information retrieval,
we kind of do the reverse.
Here we want to find documents
that entail the query.
And then for question
answering, it's kind of similar.
We could formulate that
as an entailment task
by saying that what we want
is to find answers that entail
the question, and the way we
might think about entailment
for questions is kind
of illustrated here,
where we would informally
convert a question like,
who left?
Into someone left, to
give us a statement.
And then we could say that Sandy
left is an answer to, who left?
In the sense that it
entails someone left.
And I think there are
many other tasks that we
could formulate in this way.
And it does show you just
how fundamental entailment
and contradiction are to
reasoning and language.
And finally, let me give you a
sense for the model landscape
and how it has changed.
NLI is a pretty old problem
in the field, and as a result,
we've seen a wide spectrum
of different approaches.
In the earliest
days, you had a lot
of systems that were kind of
focused on logic and theorem
proving.
And I've characterized
those systems here
as offering really
deep representations,
but they weren't especially
effective in the sense
that they worked only for
the domains and examples
that the system designers
had been able to anticipate.
So they're kind of brittle.
Following that, you have
a kind of exploration
of what Bill MacCartney called
natural logic approaches.
Bill was one of the early
innovators in this space.
I think he actually coined
the term natural language
inference.
And he explored
natural logic, which
has some of the aspects of
logic and theorem proving,
but it's kind of more
open and easily amenable
to tackling a lot of data.
And so those systems
were consequently
a little less steep but
also more effective,
and a similar thing happened
with these semantic graphs,
which is providing rich,
conceptual representations
of the underlying domain
that we want to reason about.
Another interesting thing
here is that, until recently,
it was the case that clever
hand-built features, which
I'll show you some a bit later
in the screencast series.
They were really in the lead
and simple n-gram variations,
traditional models with
hand-built features,
they were the best models.
There was a kind of faith
early on in the deep learning
revolution that eventually,
those models would prove
to be the best at this task.
But at the time, we just
didn't have the data sets
that would support--
that would provide evidence
for that kind of claim.
And so as a result, for a
while, deep learning systems
really lagged behind more
traditional approaches.
And I would say that it
was really in about 2017
that deep learning pulled ahead.
And that's a result of
modeling innovations,
and also the arrival of
some really large benchmark
datasets that would allow
us to train systems that
were effective for the task.
And it's at that point you see
that deep learning kind of took
over, and as a result, in
subsequent screencasts,
we too will be focused on
deep learning architectures
for the NLI problem.