CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Hello everyone.
Welcome to part 6 in our
series on distributed word
representations.
This can be considered
an optional part
but it's on the irresistibly
cool idea of retrofitting
vectors to knowledge graphs.
Here are the central goals.
On the one hand, as we've seen,
distributional representations
are powerful and
also easy to obtain,
but they tend to reflect only
relatively primitive semantic
notions like similarity, or
synonymy, or connotation,
or relatedness, so that
might feel limiting.
On the other hand,
structured resources
like knowledge graphs, while
sparse and kind of hard
to obtain, support
really rich learning
of very diverse
semantic distinctions.
So the question
naturally arises,
can we have the best
aspects of both of these?
And the inspiring answer
given by retrofitting is yes.
We can combine them.
The original method
for doing this
is due to this lovely
paper Faruqui et al., 2015,
which I'm going to be giving a
brief summary of in the screen
cast.
So here is the
retrofitting model.
It consists of two sums
and they constitute
kind of opposing forces.
Imagine that we have an existing
embedding space, like GloVe,
or some embedding space that you
built yourself-- that's q-hat.
And we're learning
these qi's and qj's.
The term on the
left is basically
saying, remain faithful
to those original vectors
as you learn these
new vectors qi.
Try not to be too dissimilar
from where you started.
That pressure is balanced
against the pressure
on the right, which is
saying, make representations
that look more like the
neighbors for the current node
in the knowledge
graph, which is defined
by this set of
relations E. So two
opposing pressures,
on the one hand,
we're saying to be
faithful to the original,
on the other hand, we're saying
look more like your neighbors
in the knowledge graph.
If we set alpha
to 1 and beta to 1
over the out-degree for the
node that we're targeting,
then we have basically
balanced these two pressures.
If we set alpha
really large, we'll
mostly want to stay faithful
to the original vectors.
If we set beta
comparatively very large,
then we'll mostly want to
look like the neighbors
in the knowledge
graph, and we won't
remain so tethered to the
original embedding space
that we started with.
This illustration
kind of nicely depicts
what happens in the model--
the gray vectors of the
original embedding space.
We have these
knowledge graphs that
connect the associated nodes.
And because they're connected
in the retrofitting space which
is given in white, these nodes
are kind of pulled together
and look more similar.
There's a bunch of code
for doing retrofitting
in the course
repository, and I'll just
show you a few quick
illustrations using that code.
Let's start with a simple case,
we have a very simple knowledge
graph where node 0 is
connected to node 1 and node 0
is connected to node
2, just directionally.
What happens when we run
the retrofitting model is
that 0 is called equally
close to 1 and to 2, kind
of equidistant between
them and closer to both
than it was in the
original embedded space.
Here's a situation
in which every node
is connected to every other node
that's represented on the left
here.
That's where we
start, and as a result
of running the retrofitting
model with alpha and beta set
in their default
parameters, what happens
is that triangle
just gets smaller
in kind of fully symmetric
way as the nodes become
more similar to each other
because of the graph structure.
Here's a kind of
degenerate solution.
If I set alpha to 0,
I have no pressure
to be faithful to
the original vectors.
All I care about is
looking like my neighbors
from the term on the right.
And as a result, all
these vectors shrink down
to be the same point
after the models run
for a few iterations.
If instead I had
done the opposite,
I've made alpha really
large comparative to beta,
then basically
nothing would have
happened in the learning
of the triangle.
It would remain
its original size.
It's worth considering
some extension.
So I think the fundamental
limitation of this model
is that it is kind of assuming,
right there in its objective,
that to have an
edge between nodes
is to say that they are similar.
But of course, the
whole point might
be that your knowledge
graph has very rich edge
relations corresponding to
different linguistic notions
like antonymy.
And we certainly wouldn't want
to treat synonymy and antonymy
as the same relation and just
assume that it meant similarity
in our model.
So there are various extensions.
I think the most general
extension that I've seen
is from a paper
that I was involved
with led by Ben
Lengerich, which is called
functional retrofitting,
which allows you
to very flexibly learn
different retrofitting
modes for different
edge semantics.
And once you start
down that road,
you have a really natural
connection with the literature
on graph embedding,
that is learning
distributional representations
for nodes and knowledge graphs.
And this paper led
by Will Hamilton
is an outstanding overview
of methods in that space.
And then you have this nice
synergy between NLP methods
and methods that
are more associated
with work on knowledge
graphs and social networks
and so forth.
And finally, here are some
code snippets just showing
some simple
illustrations of the sort
that I showed you earlier
in the screen cast.
And I would just
mention at the end
here, if you would like to apply
these methods to WordNet, which
could be a powerful ingredient
for the first assignment
and bake off, I would encourage
you to check out this notebook
bsm_03_retrofitting,
because it walks through all
the steps for doing that.