CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome, everyone,
to part 2 in our series on
natural language inference.
We're going to focus
on the three data sets
that we'll be concentrating
on this unit, which are SNLI--
the Stanford Natural
Language Inference Corpus--
MultiNLI, and Adversarial NLI.
I think they're
interestingly different,
and they're all
big benchmark tasks
that can support
the training of lots
of diverse kinds of systems.
So let's begin with SNLI,
which is the first to appear
of these three.
The associated paper is
Bowman, et al., 2015.
Sam Bowman was a student
in the NLP group,
and I was his advisor,
along with Chris Manning,
and a bunch of us
contributed to that paper.
An important thing
to know about SNLI
is that the premises are all
image captions from the image
Flickr30K data set.
So that's an important
genre restriction
that you should be aware of
when you think about training
systems on this data.
All the hypotheses were
written by crowdworkers.
I'll show you the
prompt in a little bit.
But the idea is they were
given this premise, which
was an image caption,
and then they
wrote three different
texts corresponding
to the three NLI labels.
Unfortunately, as is common
with crowdsourced data sets,
you should be aware that
some of the sentences
do reflect stereotypes.
I think this traces to the
fact that crowdworkers,
trying to do a lot of work, are
faced with a creative block.
And the way they
overcome that is
by falling back on easy
tricks, and some of those
involve stereotypes.
Completely
understandable, and this
is something that
the field is trying
to come to grips with as we
think about data set creation.
It's a big data set.
It has over 550,000
training examples.
And it has dev and test sets.
Each have 10,000
examples balanced
across the three classes.
Here's a look at the
mean token lengths.
It's just sort of noteworthy
that premises are a little bit
longer than hypotheses.
I guess that comes
down to the fact
that crowdworkers were
writing these sentences.
In terms of clause types,
mostly, we talk about NLI
as a sentence task.
But in fact, only
74% of the examples
are sentences that is S-rooted
in their syntactic parses.
It has a large
vocabulary, but may
be modest relative to
the size of the data set,
and that might come
back to the fact
that the genre is
kind of restricted.
We had about 60,000
examples that
were additionally validated
by four other annotators.
And I'll show you the response
distributions, which suggests
some sources of variation.
They had high
interannotator agreement.
So given that
validation, about 60%
examples had a
unanimous gold label.
And we rate the overall
human level of agreement
at about 91.2% for
the gold labels.
And that's the measure
of human performance
that's commonly used for SNLI.
And the overall
Fleiss kappa measured
interannotator
agreement was 0.7, which
is a high rate of agreement.
And then for the
leaderboard, you
can check out this link here.
Sam has been good about curating
all the systems that enter,
and you can get a sense for
which approaches are best.
It's clear at this
point, for example,
that ensembles of
deep learning methods
are the best for this problem.
I mentioned before, the
crowdsourcing methods
I think it's worth thinking
about precisely what happened
here.
So here's the
crowdsourcing interface.
There's some
instructions up here.
Here's the caption--
that is, the premise
sentence in our
terms-- a little boy
in an apron helps his mother.
And then the crowdworker had to
come up with three sentences.
One definitely correct--
that's an entailment case.
One may be correct--
that is our gloss on neutral.
And one definitely
incorrect, which is our
gloss on contradiction.
So you can see here
that there's an attempt
to use informal
language connecting
with informal reasoning, common
sense reasoning in the prompt
here.
And then those get
translated into our three
labels for the task.
And here are some examples
from the validated set.
And I think they're sort
of interesting, because you
get high rates of
agreement, but you
do find some examples that
have a lot of uncertainty
about them, like
this last one here.
And I think that might be a
hallmark, actually, of NLI
problems.
Now, one really
fundamental thing
that I mentioned in
the overview screencast
as definitely worth
being aware of
relates specifically to
the contradiction relation.
And there's discussion
of this in the paper.
It's a tricky point.
What we say for SNLI, using
these simple examples here,
is that both of them are in
the contradiction relation.
The first one is "a boat
sank in the Pacific Ocean."
It has premise and
hypothesis, "a boat
sank in the Atlantic Ocean."
You might ask, of course,
those could be true together.
They should be neutral,
not contradiction.
The reason we call
them contradiction
is because we make an
assumption of event coreference,
that we're talking about the
same boat in the same event.
And therefore, the locations
contradict each other
in a common sense way.
And the second example is an
even more extreme case of this.
Ruth Bader Ginsburg was
appointed to the Supreme Court
and I had a sandwich
for lunch today.
We say those are in the
contradiction relation.
Of course, they could
be true together.
But they couldn't, in our terms,
be true of the same event.
They're describing
very different events.
And for that reason, they
get the contradiction label.
If a premise and
hypothesis probably
describe a different photo,
then the label is contradiction.
That's kind of anchoring back
into our underlying domain
that you might have in mind.
We can mark progress on
SNLI, because Sam has
been curating that leaderboard.
As I mentioned before, we
estimate human performance
up here at almost 92.
And along this x-axis
here, I've got time.
And you can see that very
quickly, the community
has hill-climbed toward systems
that are superhuman, according
to our estimate.
But down here at 78
is the original paper.
That was from an era when deep
learning systems were really
not clearly the winners in
this kind of competition,
but SNLI helped change that by
introducing a lot of new data.
So a very rapid rise in
system performance, and then
basically monotonic
increase until 2019,
when we saw the
first systems that
were, in these
restrictive terms,
better than humans
at the SNLI task.
Let's move to MultiNLI,
which was a kind of successor
to SNLI.
This was collected by Idina
Williams and colleagues,
including Sam Bowman.
The train premises,
in this case,
are going to be
much more diverse.
They're drawn from five genres--
fiction; government reports,
and letters and things;
the Slate website; the
Switchboard corpus; which
is people interacting
over the phone;
and Berlitz travel guides.
And then interestingly, they
have additional genres just
for dev and test.
And this is what they call
the mismatched condition.
And those are the "9/11 Report,"
face-to-face conversations,
fundraising letters,
and nonfiction
from Oxford University
Press, as well as
articles about linguistics.
So this is noteworthy because
in the mismatched condition
that MultiLNI sets
up, you are forced
to train on those
training examples
and then test on
entirely new genres.
And you can just see how
different, for example,
Berlitz travel guides might
be from the "9/11 Report."
I think this is an
interesting early example
of being adversarial
and enforcing
our systems to grapple with
new domains and new genres.
And I think that's a really
productive step in testing
these systems for robustness.
It's another large data set,
slightly smaller than SNLI.
But actually, the example
lengths tend to be longer.
They did the same
kind of validation,
and that gives us our
estimates of human performance.
And once again, I
would say that we
can have a lot of confidence.
There was a high
rate of agreement.
92.6% is the traditional measure
of human performance here.
For MultiNLI, the test
set is available only
as a Kaggle competition, and you
can check out the project page
here.
I love the fact that
MultiNLI was distributed with
annotations that could
help someone kind of do
out-of-the-box error analysis.
What they did is have
linguists go through
and label specific
examples for whether or not
they manifested specific
linguistic phenomena, like do
the premise and hypothesis
involve variation
in active-passive morphology?
Which might be a clue
that the sentences are
synonymous or in an
entailment relation,
but nonetheless hard for
systems to predict because
of the change in word order.
We also have things like whether
there are belief statements,
conditionals,
whether coreference
is involved in a
nontrivial way, modality,
negation, quantifiers--
things that you might think
would be good probes for the
true systematicity of the model
you've trained.
And you can use
these annotations
to kind of benchmark
yourself there.
I think that's
incredibly productive.
How are we doing on MulitiNLI?
So again, we're going to
have our score over here
and on the x-axis, time.
We have that human
estimate at 92.6%.
And since it's on Kaggle, we
can look at lots more systems.
For SNLI, we just have
the published papers.
But on Kaggle, lots
of people enter
and they try lots
of different things.
As a result, you get much
more variance across this.
It's much less monotonic.
But nonetheless, you can see
that the community is rapidly
hill climbing toward superhuman
performance on this task,
as well.
And again, I would just want
to reiterate, recalling themes
from our introductory
lecture, this
does not necessarily
mean that we have systems
that are superhuman at
the task of common sense
reasoning, which is a very human
and complex thing, but rather,
systems that are just
narrowly outperforming
humans on this one particular
very machine-like metric, which
gives us our estimate of
human performance here.
Still, startling progress.
And then finally,
adversarial NLIs,
kind of a response to that
dynamic that looks like we're
making lots of progress.
But we might worry that
our systems are benefiting
from idiosyncrasies and
artifacts in the data sets,
and that they're not
actually good at the kind
of human reasoning that we're
truly trying to capture.
And that gave rise to the
Adversarial NLI project.
The paper is Nie,
et al., which also
involves some authors from
earlier data sets, SNLI
and MultiNLI.
It's another large data set.
A little bit smaller,
but you'll see why
it's special in some respects.
The premises come from
very diverse sources.
We don't have the
genre overfitting
you might get from SNLI.
And the hypotheses were again,
written by crowdworkers.
But here, crucially, they were
written not in the abstract,
but rather with the goal
of fooling state-of-the-art
models.
That's the adversarial
part of this project.
And this is a direct
response to this feeling
that results in findings
for SNLI and MultiNLI,
while impressive,
might be overstating
the extent to which we've made
progress on the underlying
task of common sense reasoning.
So here's how the
dataset collection
worked in a little more detail.
I think this is a
fascinating dynamic.
The annotator was presented
with a premise sentence and one
condition, which would just
correspond to the label
that they want to create.
They write a hypothesis, and
a state-of-the-art model makes
a prediction about the
premise-hypothesis pair,
basically predicting one of
these three condition labels.
If the model's prediction
matches the condition,
the annotator returns
to step 2 to try again
with a new sentence.
If the model was fooled, though,
the premise hypothesis pair
is independently validated.
So in this way, we're
kind of guaranteed
to get a lot of
examples that are
very hard for
whatever model we have
in the loop in this process.
Here are some more details.
So it has three
rounds, this data set,
for its first release.
Overall, that results
in that large data set.
And you can see that
in subsequent rounds,
the model is going
to be expanded
to include previous
rounds of data,
in addition, possibly,
to other data resources.
And so what we're hoping
is that as we progress
through these rounds,
these examples
are going to get harder and
harder in virtue of the fact
that the model is
trained on more data
and is getting better
as a result of seeing
all these adversarial examples.
In terms of the
splits, the train set
is a mix of cases where the
model's predictions were
correct and where
it was incorrect,
because sometimes in that
loop, the annotator was
unable to fool the model
after some specified
number of attempts.
And we keep those examples,
because they're nonetheless
interesting training data.
However, in the
dev and test sets,
we have only examples
that fooled the models.
So with respect to the
best model for each round,
the test set is as adversarial
as it could possibly get.
The model has gotten every
single example wrong.
And Adversarial NLI is
exciting because it's
given rise to a whole
movement around creating
adversarial datasets.
And that's represented by this
open-source project, Dynabench.
And we just recently
published a paper
that's on the Dynabench
effort, reporting
on a bunch of tasks that are
going to use approximately
adversarial NLI techniques
to develop datasets that are
adversarial in lots of domains.
And you've actually seen one of
these in the Dynasent dataset
from our previous unit
on sentiment analysis.
And here's the
Dynabench interface.
And I guess I'm
just exhorting you,
if you would like to get
involved in this effort,
it's a community-wide thing to
develop better benchmarks that
are going to get us closer to
assessing how much progress
we're actually making.
And then finally, there
are a lot of other NLI
data sets that I didn't mention.
So let me just
run through these.
The GLUE benchmark
has a lot of NLI tasks
in it, as does SuperGLUE,
which is its successor.
I mentioned before, in
the context of ANLI,
this NLI-style FEVER dataset.
FEVER is fact verification,
and I've just translated
the examples into NLI ones.
Here's an NLI
corpus for Chinese,
and here's one for Turkish.
The Chinese examples
are all original,
and the Turkish one
is a translation
with validation of SNLI
and MultiNLI into Turkish.
XNLI is a bunch of
assessment data sets
that is dev-test splits for
more than a dozen languages,
drawing on the
MultiNLI examples.
Those are human-created
translations
that could be used to benchmark
multilingual NLI systems.
And then there are
a few others down
here kind of pointing out
trying to get genre diversity,
and then NLI for
specialized domains.
Here is medicine and science.
And those could be interesting
for seeing how well a model can
grapple with
variation that comes
in very specific and
maybe technical domains.
So there's a wide world
of tasks you can explore,
and I think that makes NLI
a really exciting space
in which to develop original
systems, and projects,
and so forth.