CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome back, everyone.
This is part 3 in our series on
supervised sentiment analysis.
This screencast is going to
focus on the Stanford Sentiment
Treebank.
Let me start with a
quick project overview.
The associated paper
is Socher et al.
2013.
I think this paper is a kind
of model of open science.
At this website
here, you can see
the full code, all
the data of course,
as well as an API that will
let you try out new examples
and kind of interact
with the core models
that are motivated in the paper.
It's a sentence-level corpus.
It's got about 11,000
sentences in total.
And all of those
sentences are originally
from Rotten Tomatoes.
So they are sentences
from movie reviews.
The sentences themselves
were originally
released by Pang
and Lee in 2005.
It's a kind of classic data set.
And what the SST did
was expand the data set
by labeling not only the
full sentences but all
of the sub-constituents
according
to a kind of traditional
parse, syntactic parse,
of each of the examples.
And those are all
crowdsourced labels.
So what this means is that we
have vastly more supervision
signals all throughout the
structure of these examples
than we would get from the
original, where we just
had a single sentiment label
for the entire sentence.
The labels themselves
and the underlying corpus
are five-way labels that are
extracted from workers' slider
responses.
So there's kind of an
initial layer of aggregation.
They made a slider choice.
They were all grouped
together into five labels.
And then we are going to
work with a formulation that
is even more collapsed
down to ternary sentiment.
I'll return to that a bit later.
The fully labeled
tree thing is one
of the really exciting
aspects of this corpus
that we will be able to take
advantage of, especially
during training.
So the way that worked
is, there were parses.
This is a simple constituent
parse of a sentence,
NLU is enlightening.
And as I've indicated
here, we have
labels in that
space, 0 through 4,
on all of the lexical items,
NLU, is, and enlightening,
as well as all the
subconstituents in this phrase.
And so you can see
that "is" is neutral.
But since "enlightening"
is positive,
the whole verb phrase, "is
enlightening" is positive.
We can say that NLU is neutral.
But in the context
of this sentence,
the overall contribution
is a highly positive one.
So label 4 on the root.
In the first screencast
for this unit,
I motivated sentiment
analysis with some cases
that I thought were
kind of difficult
from a syntactic point of view.
This is one of them, they
said it would be great.
I love how this
is being handled.
We can see that down
here, "be great"
is kind of clearly positive.
But by the time we have filtered
that through this report,
they said just kind of
displacing the sentiment
onto another agent.
The speaker is not
necessarily endorsing
the claim of greatness.
What we get in the end is
more like a neutral sentiment.
I think that's interesting.
And we can extend that
even further, right?
These are actual predictions
from the model that's motivated
in the underlying paper.
If we take that constituent
that I just showed you
and conjoin it with
"they were wrong,"
which is clearly negative,
strikingly the model
is able to figure out that the
overall sentiment is determined
by this second clause here,
and assigned negatives
to the entire thing, despite the
fact that there are obviously
subconstituents in
here that are positive.
And that exactly the kind
of mixing that I think
is correct for
how language works
in the domain of sentiment.
And it's kind of
encouraging to see
that this model
is able to capture
at least some aspects of it.
Here's a similar case that I
think is pretty good as well.
Although, maybe not as
strikingly positive in the end
here.
I've just changed from
the previous example,
"they were wrong,"
to "they were right."
It knows that right is correct.
And it seems to get that
this is middle of the scale.
And I'd hope this
was a 3 or a 4.
But I think that
still we're seeing
some interesting
interactions between what's
happening in subconstituents
in these examples
and the prediction that's
made at the root level.
So it's very encouraging.
There are a bunch of ways that
you can formulate the SST task.
Kind of the raw one that
comes from the paper would
be a 5-way classification
problem where we have
these numerical labels here
with the meaning of kind of 0
is very negative, 1 is negative,
2 is neutral, 3 is positive,
and 4 is very positive.
I think this is fine,
but there are two gotchas
underlying this kind of scheme.
First, it's not really a fully
ordered scale in the sense
that 4 is stronger than 3,
but 0 is stronger than 1,
because we have kind
of this polarity split
with neutral in the center.
So that's a kind of
conceptual difficulty.
And then the other part is that,
by and large, classifier models
that you pick will not give you
partial credit for being close.
We might hope that a model
that predicted a 1, negative,
was kind of right or
certainly more right
if the true label is 0 than
a model that had predicted 4.
But of course, if
these are all treated
as independent
classification bins,
then you're just
equally wrong no matter
which prediction you made
relative to the gold label.
And that seems
unfair to our models.
We are going to
work with what I've
called the ternary problem.
I think this is the minimal
problem that really makes sense
conceptually.
For this one, we grouped 0 and
1 into a negative category,
3 and 4 into a
positive category,
and reserved 2, as before, for
what we're calling neutral.
And this kind of avoids
the false presupposition
that every sentence is
either negative or positive,
because it does allow
us to make predictions
into this neutral or
non-sentiment laden space.
It's very common, and
you see this in the paper
as well as in a lot
of work on the SST,
to formulate this
as a binary problem.
For the binary
problem, we simply
remove the middle of the
scale and treat 0 and 1
as negative and 3 and 4
as positive, as before.
I think that has two drawbacks.
First, we have to
throw away some data.
And second, then we're making
this false presupposition
that every sentence is either
classified as negative or as
positive when for a wide
range of cases in the world,
that might be inappropriate.
Now, I focused here on
the root level problem.
You can see that the numbers
here for train and dev
are small, and the test set
numbers are a little bit larger
than for devs.
So they're comparable.
But we can also think of
this as the all nodes task,
because recall that a
hallmark feature of the SST
is that every single
subconstituent
in these examples has been
labeled by crowd workers.
So we could treat
each one of those
as a kind of independent
classification problem.
We have the same range
for all of the values
that they can take on.
So we can do similar
kind of collapsing down
into the ternary problem
or the binary problem.
And of course, here, we
have a much larger dataset.
For us, we're going
to, by and large,
work with the data in one
particular way, which I think
is common in the literature.
As I said, we're going to
have the ternary formulations.
Our labels will be positive,
negative, and neutral.
When we do the
dev and test step,
we are going to test
only on full examples.
So for them, we will
not make predictions
into the subconstituent space.
And then as a default for
the code, as you'll see,
it is set up to train
only on full examples.
So for these two cases,
NLU is enlightening
and not enlightening
here, if those
were two independent
sentences in the corpus,
we would train just on those
two independent examples,
one negative labeled positive
and the other labeled negative.
However, you might imagine that
you'll get a lot more strength
in training if you also trained
on all the subconstituents,
which would mean
essentially expanding
this example into its
full root version,
NLU is enlightening,
but also all
of the sub-pieces that
are captured and labeled
in the corpus.
So that would give you many
more examples and much more
diversity.
And then of course,
"not enlightening"
would be split apart as well.
And then you could decide
for yourself in addition
whether you want to treat
this as two instances
of "enlightening" or one.
And the code
facilitates all this.
So you can formulate it as a
root only training scenario
or as a subconstituent
training scenario.
And you can keep or
remove duplicates.
This is going to
impact the amount
of computational resources that
you need for training models.
But of course, bigger could
be better in this space,
because you're just seeing much
more gold labeled information.
So that's the overview.
And for much more
on this, and how
to work with our
distribution of the corpus,
and so forth, I
would encourage you
to work through this notebook
that I've linked at the bottom
here.