CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Hello, everyone,
welcome to our final
screencast in our unit
on distributed word
representations.
Our topic is going to be
deriving static representations
from contextual models.
That might sound awfully
specific, but as you'll see,
I think this could be
really empowering for you
as you work on your original
system for your assignment
and the associated bake-off.
So let's dive in.
A question on your
minds might be,
how can I use BERT or related
models like RoBERTa or XLNet
or ELECTRA in the
context of deriving
good static
representations of words?
You probably have heard
about these models
and heard that they lift
all boats and the question
is, how can you take
advantage of those benefits?
But there's a tension here.
We've been developing
static representations,
but these models like
BERT are designed
to deliver contextual
representations of words.
And I'll return to what
that means in a second,
but that is the central tension
between static and contextual.
So the question is,
are there good methods
for deriving static
representations
from the contextual ones
that these models offer?
And the answer from
Bommasani et al is yes.
They are effective
methods for doing this
and it's those
methods that will be
the focus of this screencast.
I really want to do two things
though for this lecture.
I would like to get
hands on a little bit
with a high-level overview
of models like BERT.
We're going to look later in
the quarter in much more detail
at how these models work.
So for now, we're just
going to treat them
as kind of black box.
It's just like you might look
up a GloVe representation
of a word and just get back
that representation and use it.
So too here, we can think
of these models as devices
for feeding in sequences
and getting back
lots and lots of representations
that we might use.
And later in the
quarter, we'll come
to a deeper understanding
of precisely
where those
representations come from.
And in addition,
of course, I want
to give you an overview of these
exciting methods from Bommasani
et al in the hopes that
they are useful to you
in developing your
original system.
So let's start with
the structure of BERT.
BERT processes
sequences, here I've
got a sequence, the class
token, the day broke, SEP, class
and separate designated tokens,
the class token typically
starts the sequence and
then SEP ends the sequence.
It can be also used
internally in sequences
to mark boundaries
within the sequence
that you're processing.
But the fundamental
thing is that we
have the short sentence,
"the day broke."
BERT processes those into an
embedding layer and then a lot
of additional layers.
And here I depicted 4, but it
could be 12 or even 24 layers.
What we're seeing here, the
rectangles represent vectors.
They are the outputs of
each layer in the network.
A lot of computation goes into
computing those output vector
representations at each layer.
We're going to set that
computation aside for now
so that we can just think
of this as a grid of vector
representations.
Here is the crucial thing
that makes BERT contextual.
For different sequences
that we process,
we will get very
different representations.
In fact, individual
tokens occurring
in different sequences will get
very different representations.
I've tried to signal
that with the colors
here so like the two sequences
both contain the word "the"
and the word "broke."
But in virtue of the fact that
they have different surrounding
material and different
positions in the sequence,
almost all of the
representations
will be different.
The class and SEP tokens
might have the same embedding,
but through all of these
layers because of the way
all these tokens are going
to interact with each other
when we derive the
representations,
everything will be different.
We do not get a static
representation out
of these models.
And I've specified that
even in the embedding
layer, if the positions
of the words vary,
one and the same token will
get different representations.
The reason for that is that
this embedding layer is actually
hiding two components.
We do at the very
center of this model
have a fixed static embedding,
where we can look up
individual word sequences.
But for this thing that I've
called the embedding layer,
that static
representation is combined
with a separate
positional encoding
from a separate
embedding space, and that
delivers what I've called
the embedding layer here.
And that means that
even at this first layer
because, for
example, "the" occurs
in different points
in the sequence,
it will get different
representations even
in the embedding space.
And from there, of course, as
we travel through these layers,
we expect even more
things to change
about the representations.
A second important
preliminary is
to give some attention to
how BERT and models like it
tokenize sequences.
And here I'm giving you a
bit of code in the hopes
that you can get hands-on
and get a feel for how
these tokenizers behave.
I'm taking advantage of
the Hugging Face library.
I have loaded a BERT
tokenizer and I load that
from a pre-trained model.
In cell 3, you can see that I've
called the tokenize function
on the sentence.
This isn't too surprising and
the result is a pretty normal
looking sequence of tokens.
You see some punctuation
has been separated off,
but you also see a lot of words.
When you get down
to cell 4, though,
for the sequence "encode me"
this is a bit surprising.
The word encode in
the input that's
been broken apart into
two subword tokens, "en"
and then "code" with these
boundary markers on it.
BERT has broken that apart
into two subword sequences.
And if I feed in a sequence
that has a really unfamiliar set
of tokens in it, it will
do a lot of breaking apart
of that sequence, as you can
see in cell 5 for the input
"snuffleupagus" where a lot
of these pieces have come out.
This is the essential
piece for why
BERT is able to have such a
small vocabulary, only about
30,000 words, compare that
with the 400,000 words
that are in the GloVe space.
The reason it can
get away with that
is that it does a
lot of breaking apart
of words into subword tokens.
And of course, because
the model is contextual,
we have an expectation that,
for example, when it encounters
code here in the context of
"en" at some conceptual level,
the model will recognize that it
has processed the word "encode"
even though there was two
tokens underlining it.
Let's flesh this out a bit by
looking at the full interface
for dealing with these
models and, again,
taking advantage
of Hugging Face.
I'm going to load a BERT
model and a BERT tokenizer.
It's important that they use the
same pre-trained weights, which
Hugging Face will download
for you from the web.
And so those are
tied in and I set up
the tokenizer and the model.
If I call tokenizer.encode
on a sequence,
it will give me back
a list of indices.
And those indices will
be used as a lookup
to start the process of
computing this entire sequence.
In cell 6, I actually
use the model
to derive that grid
of representations.
Hugging Face is
giving us an object
that has a lot of attributes.
If I call output_hidden_states
equals true when I use
the model here, but I can call
.hidden_states and get that
full grid of representations
that I showed you before.
This is a sequence
with 13 layers.
That's 1 embedding layer plus
12 of the additional layers.
And if I key into one
of the first layer,
that will be the embedding.
You can see that its
shape is 1 by 5 by 768.
This is the batch
of one example.
It has five tokens.
The three that we can see here
plus the class and SEP tokens.
And each one of those tokens
in the embedding layer
is represented by a
vector of dimension 768.
And that remains consistent
through all the layers
in the model.
So I went to the
final output states,
I again just index into
.hidden_states here.
The shape is the
same and that will be
consistent for all the layers.
Those are the preliminaries.
And let's think about
how we could derive
some static representations.
The first approach that
Bommasani et al considered
is what they call the
decontextualized approach
and this is like the
simplest thing possible.
We are just going to process
individual words as though they
were sequences and see if we
can make any sense of them.
So we would start by feeding
in a word like "kitten"
and we would allow the
model to break it apart
into its subword pieces.
And then we simply process
that with the model,
we get a full grid
of representations.
Now because we potentially
have subword tokens here,
we need some pooling function.
So what we can do is
just pool using something
like mean to get a fixed static
representation of dimension 768
for this individual word.
And of course, we don't
have to use the final layer,
we can use lower down layers.
And we don't have to use
mean as the pooling function.
You could consider
something like max or min
or even last, which
would just disregard
all of the representations
except for the one
corresponding to the
final subword token.
This is really simple.
It's potentially
unnatural, though.
BERT is a contextual model.
It was trained on
full sequences.
And especially if we leave
off the class and SEP tokens,
we might be feeding in
sequences that BERT has really
never seen before.
And so it might be
unknown how it's
going to behave with
these unusual inputs.
Nonetheless, though, we
could repeat this process
for all the words
in our vocabulary
and derive a static
embedding space
and maybe it has some promise.
However, to address this
potential unnaturalness
and potentially take more
advantage of the virtues
that BERT and
related models have,
Bommasani et al consider
also the aggregated approach.
So in this approach, you
process lots of corpus examples
that contain your target word.
You've got that sort
of glimpse of a corpus.
Our target word is
kitten, of course,
we allow it to be broken
apart into subword tokens.
The full sequences
in these examples
would also be broken
apart into subword tokens.
But the important thing
is that our target word
might have subword tokens.
We pool those as we did before
for the decontextualized
approach and we're
also going to pool
across all of the
different context examples
that we processed.
And the result of that should
be a bunch of natural inputs
to the model.
But in the end, we derive
a static representation
that is some kind of average
across all of the examples
that we processed.
This seems very natural.
It's taking advantage
of what BERT is best at.
I will warn you, though, that
this is very computationally
demanding.
We're going to want to
process lots of examples,
and BERT requires
lots of resources
because it develops really large
representations as we've seen,
but it might be worth it.
Now, Bommasani et al
offer lots of results
that help us understand
these approaches
and how they perform.
Let me give you a glimpse of
them as a kind of summary.
So what we've got here is
results for the SimVerb 3,500
dataset, a word
similarity data set
that's very similar to
the ones that you'll
be working with on the
homework and bake-off.
Our metric is Spearman
correlation and higher
is better.
That's along the y-axis.
And along the x-axis, I
have the layer in the model
that we're keying into.
And then, of course,
what we should watch
is that we have two
pooling functions f and g.
f is subword pooling
and g is context pooling
for models that
have it, and it's
decont for the
decontextualized approach.
Now we have a very clear
result across these results,
and I think across all
the results in the paper.
Lower layers are better.
Lower layers are giving us good
high fidelity representations
of individual words.
As we travel higher
in the model we
seem to lose a lot of that
word level discrimination.
In addition, your
best choice is to do
mean pooling for the
context and subword pooling
seems to matter less, right?
All of these lines here
are all for the context
pooling model with mean as
your context pooling function.
The very best choice,
though, I think consistently
is mean for both of these
pooling functions here.
You can see that in
this result, and I
think that's consistent across
all the results in the paper.
But the overall takeaway
here is that, as expected,
the aggregated
approach is better
than the decontextualized
approach.
However, if you don't have the
computational budget for that,
then mean pooling and the
decontextualized approach
looks really competitive.
That's not so
evident in this spot,
but if you look across all
the results in the paper,
I think that's a
pretty clear finding.
So that would be a good choice.
And one thing is clear,
that simple approach
is better than some
kinds of context
pooling where you choose the
wrong context pooling function
like min or max.
Despite all of the effort that
went into this set of results
and also these,
they're all kind of
down here entangled with the
decontextualized approach.
But mean as the pooling
function there is really
an outstanding choice, as you
can see from these results.