CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Hello, everyone.
Welcome to part 5 in our
series on grounded language
understanding.
We're going to be talking
about the rational speech acts
model or RSA.
This is an exciting
model that was
developed by Stanford
researchers Mike Frank and Noah
Goodman.
And it's a chance for
us to connect ideas
from cognitive and
psychology and linguistics
with large-scale problems
in machine learning.
Now what I'm going to
do for this screencast
is kind of queue up
the high-level concepts
and the core model
structure as a way
of leading into the
next screencast, which
is going to show you
how to incorporate
pieces of this model into
standard machine learning
models.
If you would like a deeper
dive on the conceptual origins
of this model and how it works
in a kind of mathematical way,
I would encourage you to check
out these resources here.
So this first paper,
Goodman and Frank,
from the developers of
RSA, is a nice overview
that shows not only
all the technical model
details with real rigor,
but also connects the ideas
with decision theory, game
theory, cognitive psychology,
and Bayesian cognitive
science, and also linguistics.
From there, you could watch
this technical screencast
that I did.
This is on YouTube, and here are
the associated slides for that
if you want to follow along.
And from there, I have this
Python reference implementation
of the core RSA model, and
that would be a great way
to get hands-on with
the model and begin
to think about how you
could incorporate it
into your own project
or original system.
Without further ado, though,
let's dive into the model.
And I'm going to
begin with what I've
called pragmatic listeners.
And we can also, as
you'll see later,
take a speaker perspective.
So the model begins with what's
called the literal listener.
This is a probabilistic
agent, and you
can see that it
conditions on a message.
That is, it hears or
observes a message
and makes a guess
about the state
of the world on that basis.
And the way it does that is by
reasoning essentially entirely
about the truth conditions
of the language.
Here I've got these
double brackets
indicating that we have a
semantic lexicon mapping
words and phrases to
their truth values.
This agent also takes
the prior into account,
but that's the only way
in which it's pragmatic.
Otherwise, it's kind of a
fundamentally semantic agent.
From there, we built
the pragmatic speaker.
Speakers in this
model observe states
of the world, things they
want to communicate about,
and then they choose
messages on that basis.
And the core thing
to observe here
is that the pragmatic
speaker reasons
not about the semantics
of the language
as the literal listener
does, but rather
about the literal
listener who reasons
about the semantics
of the language.
And for this pragmatic
speaker here, it
does that taking cost of
messages into account.
And it also has this
temperature parameter, alpha,
which will help us control
how aggressively it
reasons about this lower
agent, the literal listener.
Other than that,
you can probably
see that this model is a kind
of softmax decision rule, where
we're combining the literal
listener with message costs.
And then finally, we have
the pragmatic listener,
which has essentially the same
form as the literal listener.
It observes the message
and makes a guess
about the state of the
world on that basis.
And it has the same overall
form as the literal listener,
except it's reasoning not
about the truth conditions,
but rather about the
pragmatic speaker, who
is reasoning about the literal
listener, who is finally
reasoning about the
semantic grammar.
So you can see that
there's a kind of recursive
back and forth in this model.
You might think of this as
reasoning about other minds,
and it's in that recursion that
we get pragmatic language use.
Here's a kind of shorthand
for the core model
components of a
literal listener's
reasoning about the lexicon
and the prior overstates.
The pragmatic speaker reasons
about the literal listener
taking message
costs into account.
And finally, the
pragmatic listener
reasons about the pragmatic
speaker taking the state prior
into account.
And then you can see nicely
this point of indirection
down to the semantic lexicon.
And as I said, it's
in that recursion
that we get interesting
pragmatic language use.
Let me show you how that happens
with a small example here.
So along the rows in
this, I have the messages.
We're imagining a very
simple language in which
there are just three messages.
You can think of them
as shorthand for like--
the person I'm referring
to has a beard.
The person I'm referring to
has glasses and so forth.
And we have just
three reference.
And I'll tell you that
this is David Lewis, one
of the originators of
signaling systems, which is
an important precursor to RSA.
This is the philosopher
and linguist,
Paul Grice who did foundational
work in pragmatics.
And this is Claude Shannon,
who, of course, is the developer
of information theory.
And in this table here, we have
the semantic grammar, the truth
conditions of the language.
So you can see that Lewis
has this wonderful beard,
but neither Grice nor
Shannon have beards.
Glasses is true of
Lewis and Grice,
and tie is true of
Grice and Shannon.
The literal listener,
assuming we have flat priors,
simply row normalizes
those truth conditions.
So we go from all these ones
to an even distribution,
and you can see
that already beard
is unambiguous for this
listener, but glasses
and a tie present
what looks like
an insurmountable ambiguity.
On hearing glasses,
this listener
just has to guess about whether
the referent was Lewis or Grice
and same thing for tie.
When we move to the
pragmatic speaker,
we already see that
the system starts
to become more efficient.
So we take the speaker
perspective along the rows now.
And we-- because we're going
to assume zero message cost,
we can, again,
just row normalize
in this case from the previous
matrix having transposed it.
And now you can
see that on trying
to communicate about Lewis,
the speaker should just
choose beard as an
overwhelming bias for that.
And down here on observing
Shannon or wanting
to talk about
Shannon, the speaker
should say tie, that's
completely unambiguous.
But we still have a problem.
If we want to refer
to Grice, we have
kind of no bias about whether we
should choose glasses or a tie.
But already, we have a
more efficient system
than we did for the
literal listener.
And then, finally, when we
move to the pragmatic listener,
we have what you might think
of as a completely separating
linguistic system.
On hearing beard, infer Lewis.
On hearing glasses,
your best bet is Grice.
And on hearing tie, your
best bet is Shannon.
And in this way, you
can see that we started
with a system that looked
hopelessly ambiguous,
and now in the back and
forth RSA reasoning,
we have arrived at a system that
is probabilistically completely
unambiguous.
And that's the sense in which
we can do pragmatic language use
and end up with more
efficient languages
as a result of this reasoning.
Now for natural language
generation problems,
it's often useful to take
a speaker perspective,
as we've discussed before.
And I just want to
point out to you
that it's straightforward
to formulate this model,
starting from a speaker.
We would do that down
here at the bottom.
This has the same form
as the previous speakers.
We're going to subtract
out message costs,
and we have the softmax
decision rule overall.
But now, the speaker, of
course, will reason directly
about the truth conditions
of the language.
And we have our
pragmatic listener.
There's just one for
this perspective,
and it looks like just those
other listeners accepted
reasons, not about
the truth conditions,
but rather about
that literal speaker.
And then finally, for
our pragmatic speaker,
which is the one that you might
focus on for generation tasks.
It has the same form as
before, except now we're
reasoning about the pragmatic
listener, who reasoning
about the liberal speaker.
So we have that same
kind of indirection.
And once again, here's a kind
of shorthand way of thinking
about the speaker perspective.
So the literal speaker
reasons about the lexicon,
subtracting out costs,
the pragmatic listener
reasons about that literal
speaker and the state prior.
And then finally,
the pragmatic speaker
reasons about the
pragmatic listener,
taking message
costs into account.
And again, you see
that recursion down
into the lexicon.
Now I've given you a glimpse
of why this model might
be powerful, but let's
close with some limitations
that we might address in the
context of doing modern NLP
and machine learning.
So first, we had to
hand-specify that lexicon.
In cognitive psychology
and linguistics,
this is often fine.
We're going to run a
controlled experiment,
and hand-specifying the lexicon
is not really an obstacle.
But if we would like
to work in open domains
with large corpora, this
is probably a deal-breaker.
A related problem arises
if you look more closely
at the way the speaker
agents are formulated.
In their denominator, they
have this implicit summation
over all possible
messages, where
we do this computation here.
But in the context of
a natural language,
what does it mean to sum
over all messages that
might be an infinite set?
And even if it's finite, because
we make some approximations,
it's still going to
be so large as to make
this calculation intractable.
So for computational
applications,
we will have to address
this potential shortcoming.
It's also RSA--
what you might think
of as a very high biased model.
We have relatively few
chances to learn from data.
It hardwires in a particular
reasoning mechanism
and is inflexible about how
that mechanism is applied.
Relatedly, we might then
run up against things
like it's difficult
to be a speaker,
and speakers, even
the pragmatic ones,
are not always perfectly
rational in the way
the model might
portray them to be,
and we might want
to capture that,
if only to do well
with actual usage data.
And relatedly, even setting
aside the pressures on speakers
to be rational, they just
might have preferences
for certain word
choices and other things
that the model is simply
not even trying to capture,
and we might hope in the
context of a large scale
machine learning model, that
we would have mechanisms
for bringing those in.
And finally, it's
just not scalable.
And you can see that in the
first two bullet points,
and there are many
other senses in which
RSA, as I've presented
it, just won't
scale to the kind of
big ambitious problems
that we're trying to
tackle in this class.
The next screencast
is going to attempt
to address all of
these limitations
by bringing RSA into large-scale
machine learning models.