CHRISTOPHER POTTS:
Welcome to part 4
in our series on grounded
language understanding.
Our topic is varieties
of contextual grounding.
What I'd really like to
do is make connections
with additional tasks as a way
of drawing out what I think
is one of the central
insights behind the work
that we're doing, which is
that speakers should try
to be informative in context.
Let me explain a bit more
about what that means.
So our task is this task of
color reference in context.
The speaker is given three color
patches, one of them designated
the target, and
the speaker's task
is to communicate
which of the three
is the target to the listener
who's in the same context,
but of course doesn't
know what the target is.
And what I think you see running
through the human data here
is that speakers are striving
to be informative in context.
In this first case,
the speaker can just
say "blue" because the
contrasts are so clear.
But in the second case,
merely saying "blue"
would be really unhelpful.
It would be uninformative
in the context
because there are
these two blues.
And as a result, the
speaker is pushed
to do something
more interesting,
the darker blue one,
making implicit reference
to the context in an effort
to communicate effectively
with the listener.
And that communication aspect,
I think, can be so powerful
and runs through lots of tasks,
both ones that explicitly
involve communication
and ones that
involve a more general setting.
One case of the latter is I
think discriminative image
labeling, which is tackled in
this lovely paper, Mau et al.
2016.
The task here is given an
image to label entities
that are in those images.
And for many, many contexts,
it would be a shame
if our goal was to label
these two entities here
and we simply called
them both dog.
It's uninformative
in the sense that it
doesn't distinguish
the two entities
in the context of this picture.
What we might hope is that we
would get fuller descriptions,
like a little dog
jumping and catching
a Frisbee and a big dog
running, fuller descriptions
in the sense that they provide
more detail that distinguishes
the two dogs.
And we could extend that to
full image captioning as well.
Again, given these
three images, it
would be a shame if our
image captioning system just
labeled them all dog.
We might have the
intuition that we
would like the image captioning
system to produce descriptions
of these images that would help
a listener figure out which
image was being described.
And we might have a
further goal for this image
captioning system that as we
change the set of distractors,
it's sensitive to
that and produces
different descriptions,
trying to be informative
relative to these new
contexts that we're creating,
amplifying some
kinds of information
and leaving out other
to the extent that they would
help the listener achieve
that task of figuring out which
image was being described.
Machine translation
is another area
that might benefit from
this notion of informativity
and context.
This was explored
in a lovely paper
by Reuben Cohn-Gordon
and Noah Goodman in 2019.
So let's say our task is to
go from English to French.
Reuben and Noah just observed
that at the time, these two
English inputs, "she
chopped up the tree"
and "she chopped down the
tree" were both mapped
to the same French
translation, which
is a shame given how different
those two English inputs are
in terms of their meanings.
What we would like is to
have the English inputs map
to different French sentences.
And their intuition
about how to achieve
that would be to achieve
some kind of invariance
so that given the translation
from English to French,
we should be able
to do the reverse,
figure out from the French which
underlying English state was
being, quote, referred
to in this context.
So its language on both sides,
but it's drawing on this idea
that we want translations that
are informative in the sense
that they would help
someone figure out
what the original
system input was.
Same guiding idea, drawing on
this metaphor of communication,
but now to achieve
good translations.
And in other domains,
it's just very intuitive
to think about
informativity in context.
So Daniel Fried et al,
we have a lovely paper
exploring how to give
navigational instructions
drawing on pragmatic ideas
like informativity and context.
And for example, they have both
speaker and listener agents,
and they observed
that the base speaker
is true but uninformative,
whereas their rational speaker,
which brings in
pragmatic ideas, is
more sensitive to the
kinds of information
that a listener would need
to follow an instruction.
And the same thing is
true on the listener side.
The base listener is
unsure how to proceed,
but the rational listener
was able to infer
that since this instruction
didn't mention this couch over
here, it was probably not
relevant to the instruction,
and therefore,
this listener stops
at this point in interpreting
the navigational instructions.
And Stefanie Tellex
and colleagues
have explored this
idea in the context
of human-robot interaction.
They've called their central
mechanism inverse semantics.
And this is, again,
just the intuition
that a robot producing
language ought
to produce language
that reduces ambiguity
for the human listener.
In this context
here, where the robot
is trying to get
help from the human,
it shouldn't just say help me.
The human won't know
how to take action.
But it also shouldn't do
something simple like,
hand me the leg.
The robot should be
sensitive to the fact
that there are multiple
table legs in this context,
and the robot needs to ensure
that the human listener is not
faced with an
insurmountable ambiguity.
And that would, therefore,
push this robot,
in being aware of
the listener state,
to produce descriptions
that were more like hand me
the white leg on
the table, fully
disambiguating from the
perspective of the listener.
And I'd like to push this idea
of informativity in context
even further by connecting
with one of the classic tasks
in machine learning, which is
optical character recognition.
Even this task, I
believe, can benefit
from notions of contrast and
informativity in context.
On the left, I have
four digits, and you
can see that this
is a speaker who
puts little hooks at the
top of their 1s and slashes
through their 7s.
And those two pieces
of information
would help us disambiguate
the final digit
and infer that it was a 1.
On the right here, we're pushed
in a very different direction.
This is a speaker who
does not put hooks
on the top of their 1s or
slashes through their 7s,
and that would lead us to think
that this final digit here
is a 7.
Notice that, in terms of
what's actually on the page,
these two digits are
identical, but the context
is what's leading us in
very different directions,
and we can assume that at
some fundamental level,
the speaker is going to be
informative in the sense
that they're going to write
in ways that are consistent
and draw an intended contrast
between their digits,
and that's what guides us
toward what are ultimately
the correct classification
decisions, even
for this apparently
mechanical-seeming environment.