So far, we have been
talking about the problem
where we are given
a query graph and we
want to predict
or identify a way
that a given query graph is
a subgraph in a larger target
graph.
Now, we are going to generalize
this approach we just
talked about to the problem
of finding frequent subgraphs.
So let me tell you
what this problem is.
What we would like to do is to
talk about frequent subgraph
mining.
So first, we discussed
in the previous lecture
about subgraphs and motifs
and we defined them.
And then we talked about the
problem of a neural subgraph
representation and be
able to quickly say
whether a given query graph is
a subgraph in a bigger target
graph.
Now, we are going to
further expand this
to frequent subgraph mining.
So here is the problem, the
idea is that given a large graph
we would like to identify
what are the building blocks?
What are the
frequently occurring
subgraphs that are part of
this bigger target graph?
And this is called the
frequent subgraph mining
where basically we
want to identify
these frequently occurring
building blocks of a big graph.
And generally, using
combinatorial approaches
the way you would approach this
problem is that, by the finding
most frequent size-k
subgraphs requires
solving two challenges.
First is that, we want
to enumerate or consider
all size-k connected
subgraphs, right, and then
each of these connected
subgraphs of size-k acts
like a query which we then want
to identify in the target graph
to count its occurrence.
So basically this
means that, in order
to identify frequent subgraphs
of a given size we first
have to identify what is
the universe of subgraphs
of a given size.
And then for each
of these subgraphs
find its frequency in
the given target graph.
So this is how traditional
approaches to this would work.
So for example,
if I'm interested
in connected subgraphs
undirected of size-3
then there are two possible such
subgraphs that are shown here.
I generated them so this is step
1, and then for each of them
I would want to ask, what is the
frequency of them in the larger
target graph?
And here basically I
would need to count them.
So for example, for this let's
say motif subgraphs of size-3
here these different
green polygons
show the instances
of this given motif,
so its frequency equals to 3.
So this is a hard
combinatorial problem
because just knowing if
a certain subgraph exists
in a given larger graph is a
hard computational problem,
right?
This is essentially a
subgraph isomorphism problem.
The frequent subgraph
counting is even bigger,
it's kind of even a harder
problem because first we
want to know the frequency
of a given subgraph
and then we want to
find the subgraphs that
are the most frequent out of all
possible subgraphs of a given
size.
So because the number of
subgraphs of a given size
increases
super-exponentially, you
are basically battling two
exponential algorithms.
First is the counting
and the second one
is the number of possible
things you have to count, right?
We saw how the number of motifs
or how the number of subgraphs
increases super-exponentially
with their size.
So traditional
combinatorial approaches
can only handle subgraphs
between size, let's say 3,
to 5, 6, maybe 7.
Because the number of them
increases so drastically
and then just counting
each one of them
to determine their
frequency is computationally
expensive as well.
So what we are going to
do in this lecture is
we are going to talk about
how can we use representation
learning and graph
neural networks to solve
this hard combinatorial problem?
As I said finding
frequent subgraphs
is computationally hard because
there are two problems that
are both exponential.
First is you get a
combinatorial explosion
in the number of
possible patterns,
possible subgraphs
of a given size.
And then given one of
these possible subgraphs
you have to count it, you
have to find its frequency
in the big target graph
so that then you can say,
here are the let's say
10 most frequent when
you kind of sort them by
their decreasing frequency.
So both of these by
themselves are hard.
So we are going to
elegantly sidestep
these hard
combinatorial problems
by using representation
learning and show how
we can tackle these challenges.
The combinatorial explosion
will be of possible subgraphs
will be attained by organizing
the search space cleverly.
And then the problem of subgraph
isomorphism and subgraph
counting will be tackled
by graph neural networks.
So let me give you a bit
more details about how
we are going to do this.
So for counting, we are actually
using the graph neural network
to predict a frequency
of a given subgraph.
So basically what
we are going to do
is we are going to take a big
target graph and embed it.
And then when a small
query graph comes
we are going to
predict its frequency.
So that rather than
directly counting it
we are just going to
predict its frequency.
So that will be the
first innovation.
And then the second
innovation, now,
rather than predicting the
frequency of all size scale
let's say k's 5, 10,
20, connected subgraphs
because there is super
exponentially many of them,
we are actually going to
develop a search procedure that
will start with a
small subgraph and grow
it node by node until it
reaches a desirable size,
and this way we will also
try to grow it in such a way
that its frequency
will be higher.
The important point
here is because we
are talking about
frequency subgraph mining,
we are only interested in
the most frequent subgraphs
and the most frequent
motifs and not
the frequency of all the motifs.
So that's why the search
procedure will be useful.
So let's look into
this problem more,
let's try to
understand it better.
So the problem set up for
the frequent motif mining
is the following.
We are given a
large target graph
G sub T and a subgraph
size parameter k,
as well as the number
of desired results r.
And the goal is to identify
among all possible graphs
on k node out of them that have
the highest frequency in G sub
T, right?
So I want to find r most
frequent subgraphs on k nodes
in a given target graph G sub T.
And here for the
frequency definition
we are going to use what we
call the node level frequency
definition, where this is the
number of nodes u in target
graph T, G sub T for which
some subgraph of G sub T
is isomorphic to our query and
the isomorphism maps node u
to node v.
And perhaps the best way
to understand this is,
imagine I have my
target graph, it's
a kind of a star with
100 spokes and imagine
I have a query graph that
is a star on 6 spokes.
And imagine that I say this
is the anchor I care about,
then the frequency of this
given query in the target graph
will be exactly 1 because
the anchor is going
to map to the center node
and that's the only way how
to map this query graph
to the target graph
while also mapping
the anchor node to one
of the nodes in the
target graph, right?
So rather here having G
sub Q frequency of 100 to 6
it will have just frequency
of 1 because there
is only one way to map this
anchor node to the underlying G
sub T. So this
frequency definition
is more robust to this
combinatorial explosion
when like I try to
illustrate here.
So that's the frequency
definition we care about.
So now the method that
we talk about is SPMiner
and it's a neural network model
to identify frequent motifs.
And the way this is going
to work is the following.
We are going to give
an input graph G sub T
and we are going to
decompose it into
node anchored neighborhoods.
And then we are going to use a
graph neural network to embed
each of these neighborhoods.
And this is exactly what we have
been talking in lecture 12.2,
right, where we talked
about how do you basically
take the graph, decompose
it into node overlapping
node anchored neighborhoods--
and then use the encoder,
use the graph neural network to
basically embed every dot here
as a different neighborhood
and you embed it
in the embedding space.
So this will be
the encoder part.
What is new in this
part of the lecture
is the last part
where we will have
what we call a search procedure
to find frequent subgraphs
by growing our motif.
So we are going to start
with a trivial motif of two
nodes and an edge
and then we are
going to iteratively
grow it while trying
to preserve its frequency.
We are going to say, how
do I grow this motif so
that its frequency remains high?
And when I reach the
desired size of the motif,
the size-k I'm going to stop
and say, here is the motif,
this is its predicted frequency.
So the point is that,
rather than trying out
let's say all possible
graphs on 10 nodes,
we are going to grow
a graph on 10 nodes
iteratively while trying
to maximize its frequency.
That is the idea,
this is the overview.
So now let's dive deeper
into this lecture.
So the key idea of SPMiner is
to decompose the input graft
Gt into a lot of
small neighborhoods.
And we are going to embed these
neighborhoods into an order
embedding space.
And the key benefit of
order embedding space
will be that we'll be
able to quickly predict
the frequency of a
given subgraph G sub Q.
So essentially rather
than taking G sub Q
and trying to match it in many
different places in the G sub
T, we are just going
to encode G sub Q
and then predict its
frequency in the G sub T.
That's the kind of
the idea is that we
have a very fast
frequency predictor that
will use graph neural networks.
So here is how we are
going to do this frequency
prediction, right?
So the idea is that we take
a set of subgraphs, these
are our node anchored
neighborhoods G sub
N of big target graph G sub T.
And the idea will be that
we are going to estimate now
the frequency of our given
subgraph of a given target
graph G sub Q by counting
the number of neighborhoods
such that their embedding
satisfies the order embedding
property.
So basically we are going to
say, for a given graph G sub Q
we are going to embed it into
some point in the embedding
space, and we are going to ask
how many neighborhoods of G sub
T are to the upper
right of it, right?
Basically with
this notation I try
to say how many
neighborhoods N sub
I are there whose
individual coordinates are
all greater than the embedding
coordinates of my query graph
Q.
And this is exactly
a consequence
of order embedding
space property
that we have discussed, right?
So intuitively when my G sub Q
arrives, I'm going to embed it
and I'm going to say
its frequency is simply
the number of node
anchored neighborhoods
that are embedded into the
top right of it, right?
So number of node anchor
neighborhoods whose embedding
coordinates are greater
than the embedding
coordinates of my query point.
So basically there is this
what we call a super graph
region, where basically all the
points, all the neighborhoods
in the red shaded region
corresponds to neighborhoods
in G sub T that contain G
sub Q as a subgraph, right?
So basically this will be
now our frequency estimation
and the benefit
will be that now we
have a super fast subgraph
counting frequency estimation
method because when a new
motif arrives we just embed
it and then determine
how many points
fall to the top right of it and
this can be done super fast.
So now that we know how
to estimate the frequency,
now let's talk about
the search procedure
that is actually going
to find the motif.
So the way we are going to
do this is the following.
We are going to randomly pick
a starting node u in the target
graph G sub T and then we
are going to basically expand
the neighborhood around this
target node u in the G sub T
to get the query
graph, and we are
going to use the
graph neural network
to estimate its frequency.
And we are going to
grow it in G sub T
while trying to keep the
frequency as high as possible.
And the way you can
think of this as that,
we are going to start
with an individual node u
and its embedding will
be somewhere all the way
to the lower level because an
individual node is a subgraph
of all neighborhoods, right?
Because the neighborhoods
are composed of nodes
so this individual node is a
subgraph in all neighborhoods,
right?
So here the point is
that each dot here
represents a neighborhood
in the target graph
that contains the
motif pattern, right?
And whatever is in the
red shaded three regions.
These are the neighborhoods
that contain that motif.
And of course, initially
all neighborhoods
contain the motif because
the motif is a single node.
So now that we have a
partially built motif S
we want to grow it
until it reaches
size-k such that its
frequency of this size-k motif
will be as large as possible.
So the way we are
going to do this is we
are going to do it through
an iterative procedure that
is going to grow the motif
iteratively meaning node
by node and edge by edge,
by basically traversing
the neighborhood of this
chosen node u in G sub T
and adding neighbors
of that node.
The neighbors of neighbors
to S and at the same time
we are going to use the order
embedding space to now take
S, embed it, and ask what is
the frequency of that bigger
subgraph, right?
So the way you
can think of it is
we are going to start
with the individual node
and we are going now to say,
an individual node and that's
our S, and then we are going
to add one neighbor of it to S,
so now S will be bigger.
And for every possible way
to add this new node or this
to the S we are going to ask,
what is the best node to add
to the S so that the frequency
remains as high as possible?
And we can use this kind of
gritty search procedure that
is going to grow our motif
node by node until it
reaches the desirable size.
And now of course,
what we need to decide
is how do we decide what
node to include next, right?
How precisely do we grow this
underlying motif, node by node?
And the way we are
going to do this
is that, we are going
to grow it with the goal
to maximize the number
of neighborhoods
that are in the red shaded
region after the k steps,
right?
So basically in the end,
we want to reach out
some point which that
describes a graph of a given
size-k such that the
number of neighborhoods
that are to the top
right of it, meaning
that are in these red-shaded
regions is as high as possible.
Because whatever are
the neighborhoods
to the top right of it,
these are the neighborhoods
that our red dot
is a subgraph of,
that's the order
embedding property that we
have worked so hard to establish
in the previous lecture.
So that's the idea.
So right then we'll be growing
this motif node by node
until it reaches the
desired motif size,
until it reaches size-k.
And then we are
going to terminate,
and what we are
going to return, we
are going to return whatever is
the motif we terminated and we
are going to return its
predicted frequency, which
is the number of neighborhoods
in this red shaded region.
The reason why we are--
just kind of
noticed that, we are
only interested in
the subgraph's motifs
that have high frequency.
So as we are building it we
are kind of greedily deciding
how to grow that motif so that
its frequency will remain high.
So to now answer the most
important question, which
is how do I decide which
node to pick and add
to my current subgraph motif S?
And the way we are
going to do this
is, we are going to define
the notion of total violation
of a subgraph, let's
call it G which
is the number of
neighborhoods that
do not contain this subgraph G.
So this is the number
of neighborhoods
that do not satisfy my
order embedding property.
Which basically it would be the
number of neighborhoods where
at least one of the
coordinates in the embedding
space of the neighborhood
is less than the embedding
coordinate of my graph G.
So this is the same thing,
this G is this cubed.
And this means that basically
minimizing the total violation,
means maximizing the frequency.
And you can then use many
different search heuristics
but one possible such
heuristic is greedy, right?
Basically, at
every step you want
to add a node to the subgraph
S that results in the smallest
total violation.
Basically, you want
to add a node that
will keep the number
of neighborhoods
to the top right
of that subgraph S
to be as high as possible.
And you can think of this,
right, we start with one node,
we add the second node,
we add the third one,
we add the fourth one, and
you are kind of dancing,
as you are building the motif
you are kind of moving up.
And the goal is to reach a
motif of a given size that
has the largest number
of neighborhoods
in the red shaded region,
so in the region that
is up and above from it.
And that's essentially the idea.
I can show you some
experimental results
to show that this really
works quite remarkably well.
Where for example, we can
say let the ground truth
be the most frequent top
10 most frequent motifs
in a given target graph.
And we are going to do these
four motifs of size 5 and 6
because this is what
kind of this brute force
exact enumeration counting is
able to do in a couple of days,
right?
So then we can ask is, what
are the frequency of the top 10
most frequent motifs
that this search
procedure is able to identify?
Where basically we pick a random
node u in the target graph G,
we kind of grow the motif
around it and at the same time
as we are of growing
that motif we
ask what its frequency as
predicted with the order
embedding space?
And then this graph
tries to illustrate this,
these are the top 10
most frequent motifs
just rank ordered, and the
y-axis is their frequency.
And exact is the
ground truth, right,
so this would be the frequency
of the most frequent motif,
the second most frequent, third
most frequent, fourth, fifth,
all the way down to tenth.
Now, what we also
did in our case,
is we use this neural
network order embedding
space based method to identify
top 10 most frequent motifs
that it finds.
And let's compare
their frequency
to what the exact
counting finds.
And of course, the frequencies
drop as the rank of the motif
gets higher, that's okay.
But you notice, for example
that SPMiner is basically able
to identify the top in this
case, top eight motifs perfect
out of the top ten.
And then the other two
are their frequency
are just a bit lower so these
two were not exactly identified
so their frequencies are lower.
Here is top eight are
perfectly identified here,
for size 6 it's
actually top nine that
are perfectly identified.
And these are some traditional
approximate searching methods.
You see that they fail
much, much, much worse.
And perhaps, if
the mfinder method
finds the top 10th,
the motif at rank 10,
its frequency is only 5,
raised to the times 1,000.
Our SPMiner is able to
find the tenth motif that
has the frequency of around
let's say, 15,000, right?
So much, much more accurate.
So this is for small
motifs, you can also
do this for very large motifs
because the search procedure
is very cheap.
So you can identify large motifs
for example, motifs of size 14,
17, 20, that still have
very high frequencies.
And you can do this in two
different real world networks
and really find large
motifs with high frequencies
computationally
very, very cheaply.
And the motifs you find
tend to be much, much
more frequent than what
kind of random search
traditional kind of
heuristic-based baselines
can do.
So to summarize this
lecture, here we
talked about
subgraphs and motifs
that are important concepts
that provide insights
into the structure of
large graphs, right?
And the frequency of
these subgraphs or motifs
can be used as features
of nodes or graphs.
And they can kind
of also tell us
what is the organization of
networks, what are the building
blocks of a given graph?
And I talked to you about how
it is computationally hard
combinatorially to
identify frequently
occurring subgraphs of a given
size in a big target graph.
And we covered neural
approaches for prediction
of subgraph isomorphism
relationship.
We developed this notion
of an order embedding space
that has a desirable property
and allows us to quickly say
whether a given graph is a
subgraph of a bigger graph,
or it allows us to
quickly say, what
is the frequency of a given
subgraph in a bigger target
graph.
So that prediction happens
super quickly and is accurate.
And then the last
thing we did was
we talked about this neural
embedding guided search that
starts with a small
motif, iteratively
grows it n node by
node such that it
allows us to identify
a large motif that
also has a high frequency.
And we saw that these methods
are extremely practical,
they are extremely fast
and lead to high accuracy
of identified motifs and
identified subgraphs.
So with this we have
finished the treatment
of subgraph identification,
subgraph counting,
and frequent subgraph mining.
Thank you very much.