So now I wanna talk about the second method about, uh, community structure,
and we'll call this, uh, BigCLAM,
is the name of the method and this is for detecting
overlapping communities in networks, right?
So so far we made assumption about this type of structure of the network.
So like we have these clusters,
each one has a lot of connections and then a few connections across.
But in many cases, you know,
people- humans, we belong to multiple social communities at once.
So you can have these social groups,
uh, that overlap, right?
So how could we extract this type of overlapping community structure?
To give you an example,
this is actually a Facebook network of one of the students,
uh, uh, in my group.
These are his friends and these are collection- connections between his friends.
Um, and you can ask, you know,
what is the community structure of this network?
What kind of communities does this PhD student of- uh,
uh, from my group, uh, belong to?
Um, and you know, if you look at this, perhaps you say,
there is- I see one big group here,
maybe I see another one here,
maybe there is something down here.
What is actually interesting if you look at it and you ask the student to- to, uh,
put his friends into different social groups,
uh, here are the social groups he came up with.
He basically said, I- I- I have friends from four different social groups,
uh, and here are the social groups.
And of course, some friends belong to multiple of these social groups.
Um, and then you can ask the- the student to label these groups.
And he said, "Oh, these are my friends from high school.
These are the friends from an internship I did in a given company.
These are the Stanford friends I play basketball with,
and these are these other Stanford friends I play, uh, squash with."
Uh, and of course there are some people here, right?
That are both- that went to the student to the same high school,
they are now at Stanford and they play both basketball and squash with him.
And, you know, that have some from the same high school
who only- who did the internship with him at this company,
but are not currently at Stanford, right?
So we see how these, um, communities overlap differently.
Another thing that I wanna notice you in this picture is that
nodes are either solid or they are kind of gray.
Um, and the point here is what I'm trying to show is that for- for a given- uh,
for a given network,
uh, we can- for this given input,
we can ask our community detection method,
our BigCLAM to identify the clusters.
And the big- BigCLAM identifies these four clusters,
and then we, uh, color the nodes.
The node is full if it was assigned to the correct cluster,
and it is gray if it- if it was not assigned to the great- to the correct cluster.
Uh, and what is amazing here is basically that only on the network structure alone,
only on this unlabeled network structure,
we can assign nodes to the correct clusters,
to the correct social communities without knowing anything about them.
Which is remarkable and super impressive, right?
It's a super hard task.
So, uh, this was one example,
another example I wanna show you is in, uh, biological networks.
This is a protein-protein interaction network,
and if you identify functional modules here,
you see how these functional modules,
uh, overlap with each other.
So this is, um, very interesting to think
about overlapping community structure in networks.
So just to contrast what we have been talking about so far,
we talked about networks having
this kind of clustering structure where dense clusters, few connections across.
If we think about this in terms of the graph adjacency matrix,
then the adjacency matrix would look like this,
where basically you have one cluster, you know,
the orange one, you have the green cluster,
a lot of connections.
And then these areas of the adjacency matrix means, you know,
an orange node linking to a green node and there is, uh,
less connections here because we assume there is less connections across the two clusters.
In the overlapping case,
it actually- the situation gets much more tricky.
If you have two overlapping clusters,
then these red nodes here are in the overlap.
And if you think of it from the, um,
um, adjacency matrix point of view, this is the picture, right?
You have one cluster,
you have the other cluster.
And here in the overlap,
you have even more connections because these connections kind of,
uh, come either from one cluster or,
uh, the other cluster.
And the point here wouldn't be to say, oh,
there is this set of people that are super strongly connected with each other.
The point is to say, oh,
there are two clusters that overlap in the set in the middle.
So now, how are we going to detect,
uh, this type of structure, uh, in the network?
How we are going to extract communities.
Um, our plan of action is the following.
We are going in step 1,
define a generative model for graphs that is based on node community affiliations,
and we'll call this model Affiliation Graph Model.
And then we are going to define an optimization problem that, uh, will, uh,
optimize the log-likelihood of,
uh, the model to generate, uh, the graph.
So what we are going to learn today is an instance of, uh,
generative modeling of networks and how to feed a generative model to a given graph.
So this is, uh,
kind of very useful and very fundamental.
So first, let me define the model.
The model will be the following.
Uh, we will have a set of nodes at the bottom,
and a set of communities at the top.
And a node will be connected to a community if a given node belongs to a community.
So in this case, you know,
blue nodes belong to A alone, green nodes, uh,
belo- uh, belong to B alone,
and then the red nodes belong to both.
So they are connected both to A and B, um,
and this is how we are going to de- describe
the community structure of the- of the network.
Now, we wanna build a generative model which says, you- I'm given,
uh, uh, an assignment of nodes to communities,
I want to generate the edges of the network.
How do I generate the edges?
And we are going now to describe the generative process,
how to turn the, uh,
affiliations of nodes to communities into edges of the network.
Our model will have a set of nodes,
a set of communities,
and a set of memberships of nodes to communities, right? Like this.
And then we are going to assume that each community,
C up here, has a single parameter,
P sub C. And this parameter will have the following, uh, role, right?
So basically we'll say given the- given our- our model,
given affiliations in this community parameters,
we wanna generate the edges of the underlying network.
And we are going to say that nodes in community
C will connect to each other by flipping a coin with, uh,
bare ground with a probabili- that is going to create
an edge with probability C. So the way to think of this is,
you know, this pair of nodes says, oh,
we belong to the same community A,
let's flip this coin P sub A, and, uh,
if the coin says yes,
we are going to create a connection between us.
Why? For example, these two nodes here,
they belong both to A and B.
So they are going to flip the first coin and if the coin says yes, they'll create a link.
Um, then they'll flip the second coin and if the coin says yes,
they are going to create a link.
So basically if at least one of these two coins says yes,
they are going to, uh, link to each other.
So this means that long- nodes that belong to
multiple communities get multiple coin flips,
which means they are more likely to,
uh, link to each other.
So in some sense, if the- if they are unfortunate the first time,
they might- might be luck in creating
a connection next time for the second community they have in common.
So one way you can write out the probability that U
and V connect with each other is through this formula.
And let me just explain it.
So basically what this is saying is this is the probability that, um,
at least one of these coin flips with biases,
P sub C comes up heads, right?
So basically we are saying, let's go over to
all the communities that nodes U and V have in common,
for each community we flip a coin of each probability C. So 1 minus,
uh, P sub C is the probability that, uh,
the coin says, let's not create an edge.
Now multiplying this says,
what if you are super unlucky and for every coin flip,
the coin flip comes up and saying no edge.
So this is now the total probability that all the coin flips say no edge
and 1 minus that is that at least one of these coin flips came up,
uh, uh, positively and the edge is created.
So basically we say a pair of nodes is connected if at least one of these coin flips,
uh, was successful, and that's kind of the formula for this.
So what did we learn so far?
We learned that if you give me the model,
uh, specified by the nodes,
communities, the memberships, uh,
and the parameters, uh,
then we know how to generate a- a network.
Um, this model is super flexible because it allows, uh,
us to- to, uh,
express a variety of community structures.
We can create this type of traditional one that's- two dense clusters.
Um, with this type of structure.
We can create overlaps by saying this orange nodes belong to both communities,
so they are in the overlap or we could even have a hierarchical structure,
where we say, you know, ah,
um, violet nodes belong to A,
uh, green nodes belong to, uh, C, ah,
and then all the nodes belong to B so that there is this kind of A and B are
embedded or included are subgroups of the bigger group, ah, B.
So, uh, that's the way, ah,
the flexibility of this model to give you some, uh, intuition.
So what we know to do so far is,
how do we go from the model to generate the network?
What we'd like to do next is to go the other way around, right.
Given the network, we'd like to say, what is the model?
So essentially this is called maximum likelihood estimation,
where basically we'll say, we'll define the following reasoning.
We say, assume there is some model that nature uses to generate graphs.
And we will assume that AGM is the model that nature uses to generate graphs.
Then we are going to say,
let's assume that our real-world graph was generated by AGM.
So we are going to say,
what is the model F that is most likely to have generated my data?
So in our case we say, given a graph,
find the most likely, ah,
model AGM, ah, that have generated the data.
So what do we mean by model?
It means, we need to decide that the number of communities,
we need to assign- decide how nodes belong to communities,
and what is every parameter P_C of every community?
So we say, what are the values of these parameters such that
this graph that I observe in reality
would most likely have been generated by my model?
So now, as I said,
basically we want to fit our model to the underlying graph.
And the way we do this is using maximum likelihood estimation.
So basically given a real, uh, graph,
we want to find the parame- the model parameters
F which maximize the likelihood of our graph.
So the way I wri- say this is to say,
given some model parameters,
I wanna generate a synthetic graph.
And then I wanna, ah, ah, I wanna say, uh,
what is the correspondence between the synthetic graph, uh, and the real graph?
So in some sense, I wanna maximize the probability
of my model F generating the real graph, right?
So basically, I wanna be able to efficiently compute this, ah,
likelihood that F generated my data G and then I need to- a way to,
uh, optimize over F to maximize this probability,
to maximize this likelihood.
So let me now first tell you how likelihood is defined over a graph, right?
So I'm given a real graph G and I'm given a
model F that assigns a probability to every edge.
And I want to genera- ah,
compute the likelihood that my model F has generated the graph
G. And the way I can do this is to say, that is a graph.
Here's an adjacency matrix.
This is my input data.
I have my model and my model assigns a probability to every edge that can happen, right?
Every- the model says,
A has a self-loop with itself with,
ah, you know, probability 0.25.
Of what- node 1 links to node B,
uh, to node 2 with probability 0.1.
So now I can ask,
what is the total probability that this kind of
probabilistic adjacency matrix would generate a given graph G?
I can simply do this as a- as a product.
Uh, and I go, ah-ha,
I wanna go- I wanna go over all the edges of G. I wanna go over
all the entries of this adjacency matrix where there is a value 1.
And I want these coin flips to land up heads.
I want them to- I want to multiply these probabilities together because I want,
uh, you know, this will be,
uh, with, ah, will have value of 1 with probability 0.25 and so on and so forth, right.
Then I also want to go over all the entries that are missing.
So basically, over all the edges that don't exist in the network.
And here I want the- the- the coin to land on the tail.
I want no edge.
So I go over all the non-edges of the network and I multiply 1
minus the probability of edge occurring, right?
And this is how likelihood of a graph under a given model is defined.
Basically, I go over, ah, all,
ah, all the, ah,
all the edges of the graph.
I see what is the probability that the model assigns to this edge.
And I want the product of these probabilities to be as high as possible.
And then I want to go over all the non-edges of the graph,
over all the 0s.
And I wanna multiply together 1 minus the probability that the edge is there.
And again, I want these 1 minuses to be as high as possible.
So our likelihood will be high,
where the model will assign high probabilities to edges that appear in the graph.
This is this part,
and it will assign low probabilities to edges that don't appear,
ah, in my, ah,
graph, uh, G, right?
Because this is- this goes over nodes and edges of the G. And this
now gives me the likelihood that model F generated the graph,
uh, G. So now, um,
the- the question becomes,
how do I find my model?
How do I find parameters of F?
And the way I'm going to find parameters of F is that I'm going to what we call,
relax or extend my model a bit to account for membership strengths.
So the way I'm going to do this now is rather than saying that every community C has a,
um, has a parameter.
I'm going to, uh,
assign a membership to have a strength.
So this would be the strength of our membership of node u to community A, okay?
And, uh, if the strength is 0,
this means, node is not a member of that community.
Um, so now, how are we going to write out, ah, ah,
the probability that node u and v link to each- to each other, ah,
if they are a member of a common community
C. And the way we are going to parameterize this is to say
it is the strength- is a- it's a product of the strengths of memberships.
And memberships can only be a non-negative,
so 0 or more.
So it's a product of the memberships.
And, uh, I'll take the negative value of this,
uh, exponentiate it, and take minus 1 of that.
So this now means that this should be a valid probability,
it will be between 0 and 1.
Um, and the higher,
the stronger the memberships,
the bigger the number here will be.
So E to the minus negative would be something close to 0.
Which means the probability of link,
uh, will be higher, right?
So basically, if membership strengths are low,
the probability of the edge is low.
If membership strengths are both high,
then the product is going to be high,
which means the probability is going, ah, to be high.
So this is how we parameterize it.
So now, uh, nodes v and u can connect via multiple communities, right?
They can have multiple, uh, communities in common.
So the way we are going to do this is using the same formula as we had before.
We are going to say the probability that u and v linked to each other is that they
create- they link to each other
through at least one of the communities they have in common.
So this is again P_C that we have des- derived here.
And but now I say, out of all these communities they have in
common at least one of these coin flips has to come up,
uh, heads, has to create a connection.
And this is uh, very nice because it, uh,
allows me to simplify this expression by quite- by quite a lot, right?
So now this is what we had on the previous slide.
Probability of a link is parameterized the following way,
where P_C is, uh,
parameterized this way by the product of the strands of, uh,
node u and node v belonging to the common community
C. So now if I write it- if I write is all out, it- this is, you know,
it's 1 minus product or our common communities,
1 minus- 1 minus,
uh, e to the minus product of Fs.
So here is how it simp- simplifies this to,
1s kind of uh- uh,
subtract each other out.
Then what I can do, I can take this product and, um, uh,
distribute it inside and the product of, uh,
exponentials becomes a sum of the exponents.
So here it is and why is this elegant?
Because this now means that this is simply a dot product of- of- of vectors,
of community memberships of nodes u and nodes v. So
I can simplify this whole expression into simply saying probability is, uh,
1 minus e raised to the dot-product of the community membership vector for node u times
the community membership vector for node v. So
this is super cool because it's a very nice type expression.
So now that I have defined the probability of an edge between a pair of nodes
based on their vector representations of the community memberships,
now, you know, how will my graph likelihood look like?
It's a product over the edges times the product of 1 minus,
uh, probabilities of non-edges.
And I simply, you know inserted this in, this is here.
When I insert it here again, these, uh,
1s will, um, cancel out and I just get the exponent.
Now, if I take this,
uh- uh likelihood and further simplify it a bit,
I can write it in the following form, right?
It's basically rather than directly optimizing the likelihood,
we like to optimize the log-likelihood.
And the reason why we optimize log-likelihoods is for numerical stability, right?
Probabilities are small numbers,
product of small numbers are even smaller numbers and then
numerical instabilities and imprecisions started to play a role,
so you never work with raw probabilities,
you always work with logarithmic probabilities,
a logarithm of the probability.
So if I apply now, uh, a logarithm here,
and it is a valid transform because logarithm is a monotonic transformation.
So when I maximize the max- maximum is attained at the same position,
regardless of whether I- whether I pass this through
a logarithmic transformation because it's, um, monotonic.
So if I apply a log and the log products become summations,
so I get this summation over log 1 minus the first term plus a summation,
over the log x- the second term and log and exponent again cancel each other out.
So here only the summation survive.
And this is now our objective.
We'll call it the log-likelihood that we tried to, uh, optimize.
So we have simplified it, uh, a lot.
So how do we, uh,
optimize, uh, this likelihood F?
We simply start with random memberships, uh,
Fs, and then we iterate until convergence.
We basically, uh, update the membership F of
node u while fixing the memberships of all other nodes.
Um, and we can do gradient descent,
where we take small changes in F that lead to the increase in the log-likelihood.
Uh, and that is um- uh,
all- all we do.
And, uh, just to say one more is when we compute
this derivative- partial derivative of log-likelihood,
uh, here is the expression.
What we find out is that this depends,
it is a summation over the neighbors of node, uh, u.
And, uh, you see how we're now multiplying the,
uh- the- the- the,
uh, community membership vectors.
We multiply it with, uh,
community membership vector of node v. But
then the term that is very expensive to compute is
the second term because here the summation goes over non neighbors of node u.
And because usually nodes have small number of neighbors, uh,
this means that this summation goes over- over the entire network, right?
Basically this plus this is the entire network and this is too slow,
uh, in practice to do.
But we can efficiently approximate these, uh,
computing this expression by realizing that this blue part,
um, is, uh, slow to compute.
But we can expand it, um,
and uh- uh, make it,
uh, to compute much faster.
And basically the idea is very simple, right?
If you wanna sum, over, um, uh,
a set of nodes that are not neighbors of a given node,
then you can write out this summation the following way.
You say, let me sum up over all the nodes in the network,
but then only subtract the contributions from
the nodes that are actually neighbors of this node u. All right?
So this now is the summation over all nodes that are non-neighbors of node u.
It's basically all the nodes minus the u itself,
minus the neighbors of node u.
Uh, and the point is because mo- most of the nodes have low degree,
you can cache this part,
you just compute it once,
and then you only have to update these terms.
And this way, you can make your method, uh, scale, uh,
much- much faster and run uh- uh,
to be able to be applied to much bigger graphs.
So let me summarize,
uh, the part of this lecture- this part of the lecture.
We talked about generative modeling of networks.
We talked about how we can fit a generative model to
the underlying network using log-likelihood and gradient descent.
In our case, we have defined our generative model of networks,
uh, that is based on node community memberships.
So what this means is that by feeding our model to the underlying network structure,
we can then, uh,
get the co- node community memberships out of that model.
So essentially we are doing community detection by
fitting a generative model to the underlying,
uh- to the underlying, uh, graph.
So BigCLAM is a method that- that defines a model,
uh- affiliation graph model based on the- based on
the node community affiliations and then generates the underlying network structure.
So what we then did is defined the fitting procedure that says,
given that the underlying network structure and
the assumption that the network was generated by the BigCLAM,
what is the optimal assignment of nodes to communities such that,
uh, we- we get the underlying,
uh, real network.
Um, in this procedure of model fitting,
we defined the notion of log-likelihood, um,
and then said, you know,
what is the most likely model to have gen- generated this data?
And we were able to feed the model, uh, to the data.