So for today's class,
what we are going to talk about is generative models for graphs, right?
So far we were working on the assumption,
or we talked about methods where, uh,
given- where we said the graph is given and we wanna do some modeling,
learning, prediction, community detection on top of it.
What we are going to, uh,
look at for the next two lectures is a different problem.
It is a problem about how do we,
um, generate a graph, right?
How would we generate a synthetic social network?
How would we generate a synthetic economic network?
How would we generate a synthetic communication network, right?
How are- what are some of the processes that would
allow us to generate these types of graphs, right?
Um, and the way we can, uh,
we can do this is that we wanna generate realistic graphs using generative models, right?
So the idea will be that we are gi- given a,
uh, graph generative model and, uh,
we wanna be able then to, uh,
generate a synthetic graph that is somehow similar or,
uh, matches, uh, the real graph.
So, uh, this is what we would,
uh, like to do.
So why do we wanna do graph generation? Why should we care?
Uh, first is that we wanna understand how real graphs form, right?
So these- these generative models can provide us insights
about what kind of processes take place,
let's say in social science, in- in humans,
when we generate- when we create our own,
uh, social networks and social connections.
Uh, it allows us to make predictions in a sense, you know,
how do we expect this graph to evolve, uh, in the future?
Synthetic graphs are also very useful because they, um,
allow us to understand, um,
various kinds of processes,
uh, that lead to, uh,
generation of, uh, new graphs,
and then we can use them as datasets for understanding corner cases
and understanding the performance of various kinds of, uh, graph methods.
Um, and the last is about anomaly detection in a sense that we,
many times, require a null model,
a model that would say, uh-huh,
this is what I would expect.
This is the network I would expect.
Let me compare it now to the real world network and see what the differences are, right?
So we want these type of null models to then be able
to have a reference point for what is expected,
and then whatever your data we have,
we can kind of compare it to that, um,
expected, the reference point to the,
uh, to the- to the null model.
So, uh, the road-map for graph generation and for the lecture today is the following.
First, I'm actually going to talk to you about properties of real world graphs, right?
Because when I generate a- a graph,
I wanna feed some properties,
I wanna match some properties of the real network,
and the question is, what properties are
interesting and what properties should we try to match?
And then I'm going to talk about, uh,
the second part of the lecture about traditional graph generative models,
uh, where basically each comes with a different set of assumptions.
These models are relatively simple,
but they come up with a lot of insight and they really
allow us to kind of understand the network formation.
And then, uh, next week, Tuesday,
I'm going to talk about,
uh, deep graph generative models,
where we wanna learn the graph formulation process from data,
uh, and this is what we are going to cover in the next lecture.
So today's lecture won't be kind of, uh, machine-learning flavored,
it will be more about traditional graph generation and a lot of cool insights,
and then next lecture we'll be thinking about
graph generation as a purely machine learning process.
And of course, there is valuing both.
There is valuing formulating things as
pure machine learning problems where you say I wanna predict the graph, um,
and there is also valuing generating graphs through
these traditional models because that comes up with a lot of theory,
a lot of insights, and, uh,
much more kind of inductive bias into
underlying processes that could be taking place in these networks.
So, uh, the plan is to ask first,
what are some of the important properties of networks,
uh, that, let's say,
these generators should match or that we can
compare the generated network and the real network?
And in particular, we are going to characterize graphs,
we are going to measure graphs according to these four different properties.
First, we'll call degree distribution, clustering coefficient,
connected components, and, uh,
the shortest path lengths.
Um, and, uh, we are- we have introduced some of
these notions already at the beginning of the class,
so let's do a quick, uh, recap.
So first, degree distribution.
Degree distribution simply says,
what is the probability that a randomly chosen node will have a given degree?
Um, and simply this is just a normalized count, right?
You say, uh, it's,
in some sense, a normalized, um,
histogram where you say, uh-huh,
for every degree k,
I wanna ask what fraction of nodes has that degree?
And I can simply plot degree versus fraction of nodes with that degree.
And I can think of this as normalized histogram,
or if I ignore this uh- uh- uh,
factor N, then it's simply a histogram of the count versus degree, right?
How many nodes have a dif- different- have a given degree.
That's what is called degree distribution.
The second thing we already talked about is clustering coefficient,
which is all about trying to understand how connected are the neighbors of a given node?
Um, and in particular,
we say clustering coefficient of node i is simply defined twice the number of
edges between its neighbors divided by
the degree of the node times the degree of the node minus 1.
So clustering coefficient will have value between 0 and 1,
and the reason why it is this way is basically saying,
I have k neighbors,
so k times k minus 1 divided by 2 is k choose 2.
It's number of possible pairs of neighbors you can select.
So this is the- the total number of edges that is possible between a pair of nodes-
a- a- a pair of neighbors of a given node with
degree k_i and e_i is actually the actual number of,
um, edges that- that occur, right?
So if I have no edges between the neighbors,
then clustering coefficient is 0, if I, let's say,
have three out of six possible 1s,
then clustering coefficient is,
uh, one-half and if I have all the six,
uh, edges between the four neighbors that are possible,
then my clustering coefficient is 1.
And this is now defined,
uh, clustering coefficient of a given node.
Now if you wanna do the clustering coefficient of an entire network,
what people usually do is they simply compute
the average clustering coefficient across all the nodes,
or they define, uh- or they actually plot
the distribution of clustering coefficient, uh, values.
Um, so those are, uh,
two ways how to characterize this notion of how many
triangles- how often friend of a friend is also a friend, right?
You can say basically, how likely am I to see this kind of edges between,
uh, pairs of nodes that have a friend in common?
And in social networks in particular,
clustering coefficients tend to be very high because of
this triadic closure that we have
discussed in the last lecture about community detection.
Um, so these were the first two,
degree distribution, clustering coefficient.
The third one we will look at is connectivity, and in lecture 1,
we dis- we dis- defined this notion of the,
uh, connected components in the graph.
And we said that lets- one thing,
how we can simply characterize connectivity is to ask,
what is the largest connected component size, right?
What- what fraction of nodes,
um, belongs to the largest connected component?
So if I have some graph that may not be connected,
I'm asking what fraction of nodes are in the largest connected component,
where connected component is simply a pair of- uh,
a set of nodes that can reach each other,
let's say, on an undirected network.
Um, the way I find connected components is by simple, uh, breadth-first search.
And I would say that, you know,
giant component exists if- if this largest component is large.
I know more than half of the nodes belong,
uh, to this largest, uh, connected component.
And then the last thing that- the way we are going to characterize networks is
through what is called shortest path lengths or the notion of diameter.
So mathematically, we define the diameter of the network as
the maximum shortest path distance between any pair of nodes in the graph.
So you take- essentially to compute it,
it would- it would mean take any pair of nodes and find the shortest path between them.
Um, now the problem with this maximum is that you can have
a long string of edges somewhere and that will severely increase your,
uh, diameter of the graph.
So for real networks,
you wanna use this- some more robust measure of the diameter,
for example, average shortest path length, where you say,
let me go over all pairs of nodes,
i and j, that are connected,
and let me, uh- let me compute the average,
um, shortest path length between any pair of nodes.
Um, and, uh, you know,
many times if the graph is disconnected,
then the shortest path length between two nodes that
are in different components is infinite,
so you would only do this over the largest connected component,
or you would, uh,
ignore the pairs of nodes that are not reachable from, uh, each other.
But the idea is that you wanna get some sense of how many hops
it takes to get from one node to another on average,
uh, in this, uh, network.
So these are the now four different ways,
how do we mathematically, uh,
empirically characterize properties of a given network.
And just for the, uh,
case- for the kind of- for the rest of the lecture,
I'm going to use one realistic large-scale network that we are going to characterize,
and then we will say, can we come up with
a generative model that could generate this network?
So for example, what we are going to use is we are going to use, um, uh,
network coming from this chat application called Microsoft Instant Messenger.
So this was like a WhatsApp plus Slack, uh, type
application before all these- all these other services existed,
you know, uh, it has- er,
it had- at that time it had,
uh, around 250, er,
million, er, monthly active users,
about 180 million actually exchange- engage in
conversations that were more than 30- 30 billion conversations over a month,
so about, uh, 1 billion conversations a day,
and you know, uh,
hundreds of billions of exchanged, uh, messages.
So what we can do with this now is we can take this communication,
um, data and we can represent this as a graph.
So the way we are going to represent this as a graph is we're going to put, uh,
we'll have people, um,
and we will connect to people if they exchange at least one message, uh,
and here is actually the dots,
here it represent the geographic locations, uh,
of the users of these Microsoft Instant Messenger,
and basically what you see is that they come from or- all over the world,
um, except from North Korea, right?
It seems that, you know, there was no users in North Korea but everywhere else,
uh, there are some users of this thing.
Um, so in total,
we'll now have a network of 180 million people with
1.3 billion undirected edges, uh, between them.
So now let's start characterizing this network.
Let's start measuring it and say,
how does this communication network of,
you know, people all over the world exchanging,
uh, short messages look like.
So the first thing we can do is we can characterize the degree distribution.
So what I'm plotting here is simply the degree of the node.
This is number of different people
a given node exchange of messages with in a given month,
um, er, times and on the y-axis is the number of,
uh, such nodes with such degree.
So I- I plot the count,
so it's probability times the total number of nodes,
so it's kind of an unnormalized, uh, histogram, right?
Um, what do you see?
You see this super, funny, strange,
however you wanna call it, uh,
interesting, um, histogram, right?
It seems that basically that is this huge number, right?
Like notice these dots here of nodes that have the degree very close to 0.
So basically we have a lot of people that only communicate with,
I don't know, 1 to a couple of different nodes,
and then it seems that we have
all these other nodes here that have very large degrees but,
you know, there's very,
very few of them, right?
For example, you know, you have maybe only one person with- that talks to 2,000
other people and the- and the person or the bot or whatever this thing was,
uh, that talks to the most people was about 6,000, right?
So it means out of 180 million people,
there is one node whose maximum degree is only 6,000, right?
Out of 180 million possible people to talk to,
these bot only talks to, uh, 6,000.
So what is very interesting is that this histogram
is kind of very much axis-aligned, right?
It seems a lot of people or a lot of nodes with super small degrees and,
you know, just one node, er,
one- one count for every degree that is- that is,
you know, higher than just, you know,
this, uh, super small number.
Um, so this does not seem- kind of this plot does not reveal too much,
but what you can do is you take the same data,
but you just plot it differently.
The way we are going now to replot this data is we
are going to replot it on- on logarithmic,
uh, scales, on logarithmic axis.
So what we did now it's exactly the same data,
the same counts, the same degrees,
but now this axis is logarithmic.
Right here is 10, here is 100,
here is 1,000, and now all of a sudden you see this very nice shape, right?
You see that basically I have majority of the nodes.
Yeah, this is 10^7,
so that's, you know, 10 million,
um, 50 million nodes that, you know,
have degree 1, 2, 3.
So large majority of the nodes have degree less than 10,
and then you see how here at the end we have very few nodes.
You know, maybe 1, 2 nodes,
um, for each degree above,
uh, several hundreds and you know,
the largest degree here I said is, uh, 6,000.
So now you see this beautiful pattern appeared that before it was not obvious at all.
Like when I plot this on linear scales,
just the histogram, it's just axis-aligned.
I- I don't even know how to interpret it.
So right here, now on same data,
just the axis are different,
I'm basically plotting log degree versus log count.
I see this, uh, very nice, uh, shape, uh,
this kind of what is called a heavy-tailed or a power law, uh,
distribution that, uh, people like to,
uh, call this types of shapes.
So the second thing is how about clustering coefficient?
If we take this network and compute clustering coefficient,
we find out that the clustering coefficient of this network is, uh, 0.11.
So it means that, you know,
11 percent of the,
uh, of the neighbors,
uh, are connected with each other, um,
and that may seem a little,
but it's actually a lot,
and the reason why this is a lot is because you have
these super large degree nodes, um, right?
That have a lot of possible connections between the friends, um,
and the- um, actually it turns out that 0. 11,
uh, is- is quite a lot.
Right now, it seems like, "Oh, you know,
the clustering coefficient is between 0 and 1."
You know, 0.11 is kind of closer to 0 than closer to 1,
so it seems that clustering of this MSN network is low,
but because we will have null models,
we are actually able to establish that the clustering is actually quite high,
so let me now tell you why- why 0.11 is high and,
you know, why is it not low even though it seems kind of a tiny number.
So this is what we are going to, uh, figure out.
So this was clustering.
Now, uh, this- the third metric was connectivity, right?
How big is the largest connected component?
And what I'm plotting here is the, uh,
size of the connected components: how many nodes belong to
a given component versus number of components of such a size.
What you see is that
the largest connected component has about 200 over more than- uh, right?
This is 10 to the 8th is,
uh, 100 million, um,
so this is, you know, uh,
almost like close to 200 million,
so pretty much 99.9% of all the nodes belong to the largest connected component,
so the network is connected,
and of course then we have, you know,
some small number of very small components of, you know, 20,
30 nodes all the way to, uh,
let's say 1 million of nodes of- that are isolated,
so connected components of size 1.
So this means that our graph is well connected with a- with a very small number of,
uh, small- small- very small isolated islands,
but the giant component is definitely there and 99.9% of all the nodes, uh,
belong to, and then the last thing I want to mention is the shortest path length.
So here is the distribution of, uh,
shortest path lengths between different pair- uh,
be- across pairs of nodes.
So I ask here how many pairs of nodes,
uh, are at shortest path Distance 5.
You know, how many are at shortest path Distance 10 and so on,
uh, and here the y-axis is logarithmic.
So notice that most pairs of nodes are reachable, uh,
with each other in around, um,
5, 6, uh, 7 hops.
So it means actually that the average shortest path length of
this giant network of 180 million people living all over the world, uh,
is only 6.6, and it turns out that you can reach
90% of the nodes of this network on average in less than eight hops.
So it takes you eight friendships to get to,
uh, 90% of the nodes,
and just to give you another way,
how you can think of this is to say,
"Let's start breadth-first search at a given node."
Right? So at zero steps,
it is one node.
Now this node has degree 10,
so at Step 1, there's 10 other nodes I can reach, right?
Then these 10 nodes have further connect to other nodes,
so at Step 2, I am at 75 nodes,
and notice how the-, uh,
how the number- how the number of reachable nodes increases,
and here for example at Steps, uh,
6, 7, and 8,
I'm- I- I can reach, you know,
28 millions, 80 million,
52 million, and then again,
you see how this quickly, uh,
decays down where, you know,
the- the- at hop Distance 25,
I can still reach, uh, three more nodes.
So notice again basically this kind of shape here
demonstrated by this single node, uh, example.
So this is, um,
what I wanted to show in terms of the shortest path length, right?
It's even though our network is massive,
the- the amount of, um,
the- the shortest path length tend to be very, very,
very small, and this is what is called,
uh, the small world phenomena, right?
That basically, even though the network is large,
the diameter, the shortest path lengths are actually quite small in this networks.
So what we have seen so far is that there are,
uh, key properties of this messenger network, right?
The degree distribution is heavily skewed.
Average degree is- degree is about 14,
clustering coefficient is 0.11, um,
connectivity has one giant component with 99.9% of the nodes,
and the average shortest path length is 6.6,
and as I give you these numbers, right?
You should be asking yourself,
are these values expected, are they surprising.
You know, is there- should I make fuss about it or,
you know, we just forget about it.
Like is it interesting?
What does this teach us, right?
And in order for us to determine whether- whether this is
interesting is that we need- we need a null model.
So basically what we are going to look at next is
different null models on which we can
make these same measurements and then be able to say,
"Ah-ha, you know, messenger network has high clustering coefficient.
Messenger network has I don't know,
um, low- low- low,
uh, average path length."
Or something like that because we will have this reference point.
So what we are going to talk about next is talk about this reference points,
uh, these, uh, types of models.