Welcome to the class.
Today we are going to
discuss deep generative
models for graphs.
So let me explain
that in more detail.
So, so far we talked about how
to classify nodes and edges
and perhaps entire graphs.
But now we are going to
talk about a new task, which
is the task of
generating the graph.
The idea is that we want to
have a generative model that
is going to generate
a synthetic graph that
will be similar to
the real-world graph.
An application of this
type of graph generation
happens in many
different places.
You can imagine that you can
represent molecules as graphs
of bonds between the atoms.
And then in this case,
you want to generate
novel molecular structures
based on this generative model.
Or for example in
material design,
you may want to generate
optimal material structures
and this is what you can do.
In social network
modeling, you may
want to generate
synthetic social networks
so that you can then use
them for various kinds
of downstream tasks.
And even in some other
applications for example,
if you think about generating
realistic road layouts.
If you want to think
about generating
realistic layouts of cities,
all these types of things
you can model as a graph
generation process.
And even for example, some
combinatorial problems
like the satisfiability problem
or the Boolean satisfiability
problem, you can generate
artificial instances
of that problem by representing
the satisfiability instance
as a graph and then learning
how to generate those graphs.
So in all of these
cases basically,
the goal is that
we want to learn
how to generate a
graph that is somehow
similar to the underlying
real-world graph.
And the field of
graph generation
has a rich tradition.
And the way this
started, it started
with the study of properties
of complex networks
like real-world networks.
And identifying what are
the fundamental properties
that these real-world
networks have
like power or scale-free
degree distributions
and also like the
small world property
and so on and so forth.
Based on these fundamental
properties of complex networks,
then there have been
a lot of development
of generative models
for graphs, which
generally fell into two camps.
One camp was very
mechanistic generative models
like the preferential attachment
model, that basically allowed
us to explain how could
certain properties
like the scale-free
property of networks
arise from this microscopic
preferential attachment type
model.
Another set of models
for generating graphs,
came mostly from the statistics
and the social networking
literature where basically, the
idea was that there is maybe
some, that there might be
some latent social groups
and based on those
latent social groups,
edges of the social
network get created.
And then the question is,
how can you take that model,
fit it to the data and
perhaps discover the groups?
However, today and
in this lecture,
we are going to
use deep learning
and representation
learning to learn
how to generate the graphs.
So in contrast to prior work in
some sense that either assumed
some mechanistic
generative process
or assumed some statistical
model that was motivated
by the-- let's say
social science, here
we want to be kind of
agnostic in this respect.
And the goal will be that,
can we basically given a graph
or given a couple of graphs,
can we learn how to gene--
what the properties
of those graphs are,
and how can we
generate more instances
of those types of graphs?
So we'll be kind of
completely general,
we'll just learn from the data
in this kind of representation
learning framework.
So this is one way how
we can look into this.
Another way how we
can look into this
is that, so far in
this class we've
been talking about the deep
graph encoders, where basically
the idea was that, we have a
complex network, complex graph,
complex relational
structure on the input
and you want to pass it
through several layers
of this representation and
a deep learning network that
at the end produces-- let's
say node embeddings, edge
embeddings, entire
graph embeddings, right?
So this is what we call
a deep graph encoder
because it takes the
graph as the input
and encodes it into some
kind of representation.
The task of graph
generation actually
goes in the other direction.
It wants to start on
the right-hand side
and then through a series of
complex nonlinear transforms
wants to output the
entire graph, right?
So our input perhaps will be
a little small noise parameter
or something like
that and we'll want
to kind of expand
that until we have
the entire graph on the output.
So we will be kind of decoding
rather than encoding, right?
We'll take a small
piece of information
and expand it into
the entire graph
rather than taking
a complex structure
and compress it into or
into its representation.
So we are talking about
deep graph decoders,
because on the output we want
to generate an entire network.
So in order for us to do
that, I want to first tell you
about kind of how are we going
to set up the problem in terms
of its set up, in
terms of its kind
of mathematical
statistical foundation.
And then I'm going to talk
about what methods allow
us to achieve the goal
of graph generation
using representation learning.
So let's talk about
graph generation.
Generally, we have two
tasks we will talk about
in this lecture.
First, is what we will call
realistic graph generation,
where we want to
generate the graphs that
are similar to a
given set of graphs.
And I'm going to define
this much more rigorously
in a second.
And then the second
task, I'm also
going to talk about is what
we call goal-directed graph
generation.
What basically you want
to generate a graph
that optimizes a
given constraint
or a given objective.
So if you are generating
a molecule you could say,
I want to generate molecules
that have a given property,
maybe the property
is solubility,
maybe the property is that
these molecules are non-toxic.
And you say I want to generate
molecules that are non-toxic.
So how do I generate the
most non-toxic molecule?
Or how do I generate the
molecule that is most soluble
and still looks like drugs?
Imagine another case
I was giving example
before if I want to generate a
road network-- a realistic road
network of a city, that is
a graph generation problem.
I could say, I want to
generate the optimal road
network of a city,
right, whatever
the optimality constraint is
that is kind of, we assume
it is given to us, right?
So that's what we mean by
goal-directed graph generation
where you want to generate
a graph with a given--
with a given goal that optimizes
a given black box objective
function.
So that's the two parts
of the lecture today.
But first, let's
talk about how do we
set up this graph generation
task as a machine learning
task?
So we are going to proceed
in the following way.
We are going to assume that the
graphs are sampled from this p
data distribution.
So basically nature is
sampling from p data
and is giving us graphs.
Our goal will be to learn
a distribution p model
and then be able to learn how
to sample from this p model.
So basically, given
the input data,
we are going to learn a
probability distribution p
model over the
graphs, and then we
are going to sample new
graphs from that probability
distribution.
And right, and our
goal somehow will
be, that we want this p model
distribution to be as close as
possible to this unknown
p data distribution
that we don't have access to,
that only nature has access to,
right, the data set creator
has access to this p data.
We want to approximate
p data with p model.
And then as we have approximated
p data with p model,
we want to draw
additional instances,
we want to generate
additional graphs,
we want to generate additional
samples from the p model
and those would be the graphs
we will want to generate.
So if we want to do
this, then there are--
this is an instance of what we
call generative models, right?
We assume we want to learn a
generative model for graphs
from a set of input graphs,
let's call them x i.
Here, as I said before p data
is the data distribution which
is not known to us and we
don't have access to it,
all we have access
to it are samples
x that are sampled from
this unknown p data.
We also will have another family
of probability distributions,
let's call them p model
that are defined by theta,
theta are parameters
of our model.
And we will want to use
this p model distribution
to approximate p data.
And then, what
would be our goal?
We have two-step goal.
First goal is to find parameters
theta so that p model closely
approximates p data, and this
is called a density estimation
task.
And then we also want to be
able to sample from p model.
Basically means, we want to
be able to generate new graphs
from this now p model
distribution to which we
have access to, right?
We want to generate new
samples, new graphs from it.
So let me give you
more details, right?
Our goal is to make p model be
as close to p data as possible.
And the key principle we
are going to use here,
is the principle of maximum
likelihood estimation,
which is a fundamental approach
to modeling distributions.
Basically the way you can
think of it is the following,
we want to find parameters
theta star of our p model
distribution such that the
log likelihood of the data
points x of the graphs x that
are sampled from this p data
distribution, their log
likelihood under our model--
under p model that is basically
defined or parameterized
by theta, is as large
as possible, right?
So our goal is to
find parameters theta
star, such that the
observed data points x.
So basically, the
observed graphs
have the highest log likelihood
among all possible choices
of theta, right?
And of course here,
the important thing
will be that p model needs
to be flexible enough
that it's able to model p data.
And then the question
is, how do we search over
all the instances of probability
distributions captured
by this p model?
So we actually kind of capture
by these parameters theta, so
that the likelihood of
the data that we observe
is as high as possible, right?
And in other words,
the goal is to find
the model that is most likely
to have generated the observed
data x, right?
Find the p model that
is most likely to have
generated the observed data x.
Now, this is the
first part, which
is the density estimation.
The second part
is also important,
because once we have the
density that's not enough.
We need to be able to draw
samples from it, right?
We want to create samples from
this complex distribution.
And a common approach how
you can generate samples
from a complex distribution
would be the following.
Is that first, you start with
the simple noise distribution
just like a simple,
let's say a scalar value
that's a normally distributed
0 mean unit need to variance.
And then you want to have
this complex function that
will take this
little noise kernel
and is going to expand it
until you have the sample x.
So in our case, we'll start
with a little random seed,
and we are going to expand
it into a full graph x.
Where of course, now the
hope is that x will follow
the distribution of p model.
So in our case, how do we
design this function f?
We are going to use
deep neural networks,
and train them so that they can
start with the little kernel
and generate the graph.
So that's how we are
going to do this.
So now in terms of
deep generative models,
our model will be an instance
of an auto-regressive model.
Where this p model will be used
both for density estimation
and sampling, right, because
we have these two goals, right?
And in general you don't have
to use the same neural network
to both do the
density estimation
and to do the sampling and
there are other approaches
that you could choose to do here
like variational autoencoders
or generative adversarial
networks and so on.
But in our case, we are going
to use an auto-regressive model.
And the idea is
that, we are going
to model this complex
distribution as a product
of simpler distributions.
And the reason why
we can do this,
is of the chain rule in
probability and Bayesian
networks.
So we're basically--
which basically tells us,
that any joint distribution
on a set of variables
can be exactly
modeled or expressed
as a product over the
conditional distribution,
right?
So basically I'm
saying this p model
that is a complex
distribution over my x, which
may be a set of
random variables,
I can write it out as a product
over all these random variables
from the first one
to the last one,
where all I have
to now express is
this probability of a
random variability t given
the values instances of all
the previous random variables,
right?
So in our case for example,
if x would be a vector,
then x sub t is the t-th
coordinate of that vector,
right?
If x is a sentence, then x sub
t would be the word, right?
So I'm basically saying,
rather than generating
an entire sentence or to write
out the probability of a given,
let's say sentence,
I'm going to--
I can model that
as a product where
I say, given the words
so far, how likely
or what is the probability
of the next word?
And if I multiply this
out, I have the probability
of the entire sentence.
And we can do this without
any loss of generality
or any approximation,
if we really
condition on all the
previous words, all
the previous elements, right?
In our case, what this
means is that the way
we apply these two
graphs is that, we
are going to represent
a graph as a sequence
as a set of actions.
And we are going to say, a-ha,
the probability of next action
is conditioned on all
the previous actions.
And now what will the actions
be, it will be add a node,
add an edge, right?
That's the way we are
going to think of this.