So.
Now, we are ready to look
about our generative model
for graphs, and this generative
model is called graphRNN.
And, it will allow us to
generate realistic graphs
without making any kind of
inductive bias assumptions.
And the model will
be as we will see--
extremely general and
scalable, and being
able to generate
a vast diversity
of different types of graphs,
of different sizes and shapes,
and structures, and so on.
So the key idea that
this is-- that we
are going to harness
here, is that we
want to generate
graphs via sequential
adding of nodes and edges.
And why do we want
to do it this way?
We want to do it this
way-- exactly what I
explained at the end of
the previous segment.
Which is, that
basically, we want
to model a complex distribution
that captures distribution
over graphs.
Modeling that complex
distribution--
we don't know how to do.
So we are going to break
that complex distribution
into many small parts.
And the way we break
creation of the graph,
we are going to break it
into many small parts,
into many small actions.
And we are simply--
all we'll have to do is model a
model transition probabilities.
Basically saying,
given the graph,
given the actions we have made
so far, conditioning on that,
what is the next
action we want to take?
And this way, by
multiplying these together,
we are able to model the
entire distribution--
all the dependencies in it.
So in our case, the
idea is that, imagine I
have this graph, and
I want to generate it.
The way I'm going to describe
the generation process,
is that, I'll start
with the first node,
and then, I'll add
the second node.
The second node will
link to the first one.
Now I have already built
a bit of the graph,
a third node is added and
links to the first node,
then node number 4 is added
and links to two and three,
and then node number 5 is added
and it links to three and four.
So that's basically,
the generative
process I want to model
and I want to capture.
And in this part
of the lecture, I'm
going to explain to you
the model called graphRNN.
And, here is the
link to the paper,
so if you want more details
you can read the paper
that I'm citing here.
So let's think about this
modeling graphs or generating
graphs as sequences.
A graph with node
ordering pi can
be uniquely mapped into a
sequence of nodes and edge
additions S. What
do I mean by this?
Graph is a set of nodes
and a set of objects,
and apriori graph has
no ordering to it.
So we need to this node
ordering, this permutation pi,
that determines the order
in which the nodes appear.
And given that ordering
in which the nodes appear,
then the sequence to generate
the graph is uniquely defined.
Because, first, I
add the second node.
Sorry.
First, I add the first node,
then I add the second node,
I add the third node.
And then, in terms of adding
edges I can always say I go--
I ask, should the
link the node 1?
Yes, no.
Should I link to node 1?
Until all the nodes after
already present in the graph.
So that is basically the
key-- the key idea is
that we need some node
ordering, and given
that no node ordering,
then generating the graph
is simply a sequence problem.
Another observation that is
important for graph generation,
is that, this sequence is
actually a two-level sequence.
There is a sequence
of adding nodes,
and there is a sequence
of adding edges.
Right at node level sequence,
at each step we add a new node.
And then, we also
have the second level
after a node is added the edges
need to be added for that given
node.
So this means we s a two-level
sequence where we will first
have the-- we have the high
level node level sequence.
And then, the low level
edge level sequence.
Node level, a step--
we do one node
level step and then
we do a lot of edge level steps.
And then, we do a
node level step,
and we do a lot of
edge level steps.
And each edge level
step is simply
an addition of a new edge.
So you can think of node
level steps being, add node 1,
add node 2, and node 3.
While the sequence elements
in the edge level are,
should I add this node--
this new node that I have added,
should be connect it to node 1?
Should I connect it to node 2?
Should I connect it to node 3?
And you can think of
this as generating
a binary sequence that says,
don't connect, connect,
connect, So that's the idea.
So a summary of what
we have learned so far,
is that, a graph
plus a node ordering
gives us a unique
sequence of sequences
to generate a given graph.
A node ordering for now, let's
assume is randomly selected
or somehow it's given to us,
will come to this question
later.
And the way you can think
of this is right if--
basically is to say, Oh, if I
have a partially built graph
and I want to add a new
node, then adding this node
to the graph simply
means I have to print out
this particular column
of the adjacency matrix.
So I'd basically
saying, node 4 doesn't
link to node 1, node
4 links to node 2,
and node 4 links to node 3.
This is first node,
second node, third node,
and we just generated the
column of the adjacency matrix
for the node number 4.
So node level sequence is
going to add one new column
to the adjacency matrix.
And edge level sequence is
going to kind of print out
the rows-- the entries
of this column, where
0 means the edge
does not exist and 1
means that the edge exists.
So.
So far we have transformed
the graph generation problem
into a sequenced
generation problem.
Now, we need to model the
two processes, the process
of adding new nodes, where
basically, we want to generate
a state for a new node.
And then, we want to generate
edges for the new node
based on it's state.
And will be the
edge level sequence.
So the point will be that, an
approach we are going to use
is-- we are going
to use what are
called recurrent neural
networks to model
this two-level sequence.
And we are going to do use a
nested recurrent neural network
as I'm going to explain.
So the idea is the
following, what
are recurrent neural networks?
Recurrent neural networks are
designed for sequential data.
And a recurrent neural
network sequentially
takes an input sequence to
update its hidden state.
And based on the hidden state--
the idea is that
this hidden state
summarizes all the information
input to the RNN so far.
And then, the
update is conducted
via what is called RNN
cells, for every time
step I have a new RNN cell.
So the way you can
think of it is,
I initialize the RNN
with some hidden state,
I give it the input.
The RNN is going to update its
hidden state and put it here,
and it's going also
to create an output.
And now, the second time
step this hidden state--
next cell is going
to take as the input.
It's going to take as the input
the input from the environment,
it's going to update its hidden
state, here denoted as S2,
and it's going also to
produce me an output.
So basically, the idea
is that this hidden state
s keeps memory of what the
RNN-- what kind of inputs
the RNN has seen so far.
So to tell you more and
give you more mathematics,
S sub t is the state of
the RNN at the step t.
X sub t is the input to
the RNN at that time,
and Y sub t is the output
of the RNN under that time.
And the RNN is-- has
several parameters,
and these parameters
are called W, U, and V.
These are trainable
parameters, this
could be trainable vectors,
trainable matrices.
And the way the
update equations go
is the following, hidden state
gets updated by basically
saying, what is the hidden
state in the previous time step?
Let's transform it.
What is the new input
of the current time?
Let's transform it.
Pass It through
the nonlinearity,
and that is my
updated hidden state.
And then, the output Y is
simply a transformation
of the hidden state
and this is what the--
what we are going to output.
In our case, S, X,
o t will be scalars.
So basically, we
are going to output
a scalar that will tell us
whether there is an edge
or not.
Of course you can have
more expressive cells
like GRU, LSTM, and so on.
But here I am talking
about RNN, which
basically, is the most basic
of this sequence based models.
So.
So far we learned what is RNN.
Now, we want to talk
about how to use
the RNN to model the node level
and the edge level sequence.
And the relationship between
two RNNs is the following,
is that, node level RNN
generates the initial state
for the edge level RNN,
and then, edge level RNN
is going to produce the sequence
of edges for that new node.
And then, it's going to pass
its state back to the node level
RNN, who's going to generate
a new node, update the state,
and push it down to
the edge level RNN.
So this is how this
is going to work.
So to give you an idea, we will
initialize the node level RNN
with a start of a
sequence, and we will--
the node level RNN is
going to create a node.
Now, the edge level RNN--
given this node is
created a node level
RNN will add a new node, and
then, ask the edge level RNN
to generate edges for it.
So node 1 is already there.
Now, node level
RNN decides to add
one more node, node number 2.
Now, the edge level RNN has
to say, does 2 link to 1,
and this number 1 here,
would say that 1 links to 2.
And, here is now the new graph.
Now the node RNN says, OK,
let's add a new node, number 3.
Now, we ask the edge
level RNN to generate
the edges for the node 3.
And node 3 will say, it
links to the first node,
but does not link
to the second node.
So now our new
graph is like this.
And again, the node
level RNN decides,
let's add one more
node, let's add node 4.
And the edge level RNN
prints out-- basically,
a sequence of zeros
and ones that will mean
does falling to node 1?
Does it link to node two?
Or does it link to node 3?
And 4 links to 2 and 3.
So, here is now
the current graph.
And then, node level RNN says,
OK, let's add one more node,
node 5.
Edge level RNN
outputs the-- four
every previous node it tells
us, whether 5 should link to it
or not.
And that's how we get the graph.
And the generation
will stop when
the node level RNN
we'll say, I'm done,
I won't create any new nodes.
So this is the idea, where
edge level RNN sequentially
predicts if a new
node will connect
to each of the previous nodes.
Now, how do we do this with RNN?
So let me give you more ideas.
So in terms of how we use the
RNN to generate the sequence,
we are basically going
to take the output
from-- of the previous
cell, and put it
as an input of the next cell.
So whatever the
previous decision output
was, for example, whatever
was the previous edge--
that would be the input to
the next cell or the next time
step.
How do we initialize
the input sequence?
We initialize it to
have a special token.
We basically train
the neural network
that when it gets
this special token--
we'll call this token
SOS, so start of sequence.
As the initial
input, the network
started generating the output.
Usually, SOS-- when I
say a special token,
it could be a
vector of full zeros
or it could be a
vector full ones.
For example, just
something you reserve.
And then, when do we
stop the generation--
we stop the generation when
the end of sequence token
is produced.
And if end of sequence is
0, then RNN will continue
generation , and if end of
sequence is one the RNN will
stop the generation.
So to give you an idea now.
How do this-- how does
this fit together?
Will somehow initialize the
hidden state, will input
the start of sequence token.
The RNN is going to
generate some output
and then we are going
to connect this output
as the input to the next step.
And of course, the hidden
state will get updated.
And now, given the
hidden state, and given
the output from
the previous state,
this is again going
to be combined here,
another output is
going to be produced,
and another hidden state
is going to be updated.
This is all good.
But the problem with the model
as I've wrote it right now,
is that, it's all deterministic.
It's all a set of
deterministic equations
that are in a deterministic
way generating these edges
and nodes.
So what we want is, we
want the stochastic model.
We want a model that will
have some randomness to it.
So our goal is to use RNN to
do-- to model this p model
and RNN really is--
we are using it
to model this product of
conditional distributions.
So this marginal distribution of
p of Xt given everything else.
And let's write that
Y sub t is the p
model of X sub t
given all the X's that
were previously generated.
Then this means we need to
be able to sample Xt plus 1
from Yt.
So essentially, we
want to be able to get
to sample from this p model,
from this single dimensional
distribution.
This means that
each step of RNN--
Now, it's going to output a
probability of a single edge.
So each step of
the edge level RNN
is going to output the
probability of a single edge.
And then, based on
that probability,
we are going to
flip a coin, if we
are going to sample from
the Bernoulli defined
by that probability.
And then, whether
we get 0 or 1, that
is actually going to be
input to the next step.
So rather than saying the
RNN generates an edge,
RNN generates a
probability, and then, we
have a stochastic event,
a coin flip without bias,
that then lands heads
or tails, zero or one,
and we use that as an
input to the next step.
So that is essentially the idea.
So at the generation
time, at the test time,
let's assume we have
already trained the model.
Then, how this is
going to work, is
that, our Y sub t will be a
probability, will be a scalar,
will be basically a
Bernoulli distribution.
And let's use this square to
mean that this is a probability
and this square takes
value 1 with probability p,
and it takes value 0 with
probability 1 minus p.
So the idea will be
that, we will start--
we'll start our RNN, it
will output a probability.
And now, we are going to
flip a coin without bias
to create-- to decide whether
there is an edge or not.
And whatever is the
output of this coin,
we are going to use this as
an input to the next state--
to the next cell.
And again, we are going to
get another probability,
flip the coin, get
the realization,
and include that as an input
to the RNN cell who's going
to give me another probability.
So this is how we are
going to generate,
or how we are going
to unroll this RNN.
Now, the question is, how
do we use the training data?
How do we use the training
graphs that we are given?
Write this Xs.
And, in order to
train the model,
we are assuming that
we are observing
the graph that was given to us.
So this means we observe
a sequence of edges,
we basically assume--
we observe how the given
graph was generated.
So we observe zeros
and ones whether--
that corresponds to where
the edges exist or edges
don't exist.
And we are going to use this
notion of teacher forcing,
this technique of feature
forcing that place--
that replaces the input and the
output by the real sequence.
So the point will
be the following.
We are going to start
the model, and the model
is going to output some
probability of an edge.
But at the training time, we
are not going now to flip a coin
and use that as an
input to the next cell.
We're actually going to say, OK,
what was the true value there?
Oh, the true value
was, there was no edge.
So we are going to force this
as an input to the next step.
So teacher is kind of,
forcing the student, whatever
the student does
in the next step--
teacher correct the
student and the student
starts from the right--
with the right input
for the next step.
So the point, is
that, the inputs will
be the correct sequence,
not the sequence generated
by the model, and this is
called teacher forcing.
Now, of course we need
to define the laws that
measures the discrepancy
between the output of the model,
the output of the student,
and the ground truth
sequence that we try to
teach the model to generate.
And we are going to use binary
cross entropy, loss function,
which you can write
out the following.
You can-- the star is the--
why is a binary variable 0, 1.
1 means edge exist, 0 doesn't--
means that does not exist.
And Y without the star is
the probability of the edge.
And basically, the idea is
that because Y star is either
0 or 1--
if only one of
these two terms is
going to survive when we
actually implement it,
because when the
Y star comes in.
And basically, the idea is, if Y
star is 1, then we are really--
the loss really boils
down to minus log Y1.
So basically, in order for
us to minimize the loss,
we want to make log of Y1 to
be as close to 0 as possible.
Which means we want to make
Y as close to 1 as possible.
And then, if we want to--
now, on the other hand
if the edge is not
present, then we
want to minimize minus
log of 1 minus Y1.
And here we want
to make Y1 lower so
that the entire expression
again is log of something
close to 1, which
will be close to 0.
So this way, Y1 is fitting
to the data samples Y star.
And again, just to remind you
Y1 or this Y's are computed
by RNN, and the loss is going
to adjust the RNN parameters,
those matrices W, U, and
V, using back propagation
to try to minimize the loss.
Minimize the discrepancy
between the true sequence
and the generated
probabilities .
And basically, the point
is that the loss will say,
wherever there is a 0,
generate a probability
that's close to 0, and
wherever there is a 1,
generate a probability
that is close to 1.
OK.
So we do this, let's
put things together.
So do-- our plan
is the following,
we want to have two RNNs.
First, we want to
have an RNN that
will add one node
at each step, and we
will use the output of it to
initialize the edge level RNN.
And then, the edge
level RNN is going
to predict what other nodes--
what existing nodes does
the new connect to?
And then, we are going
to add another node,
and we will use the last hidden
state of the edge level RNN
to initialize the node
level RNN for one more step.
And then, how is this--
how are we going to
stop the generation--
if the edge level RNN is going
to output the end of sequence
at step 1, we know that no edges
are connected to the new node,
and we are going to
stop the generation.
So it's actually the edge level
RNN, and that, we have decided
will determine whether we stop
generating the graph or not.
So let me give you
now an example.
So that you see how
all this fits together.
So this is what is going to
happen under the training time.
For, let's say, a
given training--
observed training graph.
We are starting with the start
of sequence and a hidden state.
The node level RNN
will add the node,
and then, the edge
level RNN will be asked,
shall this node that
has just been added,
shall it link to
the previous nodes?
Yes or no.
It will update the probability.
And we are then going to flip
a coin that will determine--
with this given bias that will
determine whether the edge is
added or not.
And then, and then, we'll take
this and use it as an input--
as an initialization
back to the node level
RNN who's now going to
add the second node,
and this would be node number 3.
And then, the edge
level RNN is going
to tell us, will node
3 link to node 1,
will node 3 link to node 2.
And again, it's
outputting probabilities,
we are flipping
the coins, whatever
is the output of that coin is
the input to the next level
RNN.
So here are the
probabilities 0.6.
Perhaps you were lucky,
the output was 1,
so this is the input
for the next state.
And then, after
we have traversed
with all the previous
edges, we are going over
all the previous
nodes, we are again
going to ask node RNN
to generate a new node.
And so on and so forth.
And this is going to continue
right until the last node has
been added, then the node
RNN will add one more node,
but the edge level
RNN will say, I'm
not willing to connect
it to anyone else.
So this is the end of
sequence and we stop.
So basically, it's like,
when we add an isolated node,
we know that's the signal
that we want to stop.
So that's the idea.
And then, for each
prediction, here we
are going to get
supervision from the ground,
from the ground truth.
So the point is that, we will
be doing teacher forcing.
So, even for example,
here, when this was 0.6
and we did a coin flip
and maybe we were unlucky
and we got a zero, we are going
to output the true edge as we
said, the teacher--
the teacher forcing.
And then, the structure
of our neural network
when we do back propagation,
will be basically doing back
propagation through time.
We are going to basically back
prop from all these events all
the way to the beginning--
to the beginning of time,
to the firr-- to the first
node in the graph to update
the parameters of the RNN.
And then, how about at the test
time, at the generation time?
We are basically going to
sample the connectivity based
on the predicted distributions,
predicted probabilities,
and we are going to replace
the input at each step
by the RNNs own
prediction or own output.
So here we are going
to flip the coin,
the coin will say what it will
say, and it will go as an input
to the next one.
And I think, here, we are
going to do the coin, whatever
is the output here, should be
the input to the next step,
so it should be a 0
here, it's a mistake.
OK.
So that's the idea.
So the summary is we have costed
the problem of graph generation
as a problem of
sequence generation.
Actually, a problem of a
two-level sequence generation,
node level sequence, and
an edge level sequence,
and we use recurrent
neural networks
to generate the sequences.
And what I want to
discuss next is, how do we
make the RNN tractable?
And how do we evaluate?