What I want to discuss
next is how do we
make the RNN tractable?
And how do we evaluate it?
So we are first going to
discuss about tractability.
How do we make our
model more scalable?
And the issue is that
in a graph in principle
any node can connect
to any prior node.
So this means there
might be a lot of steps
for edge generation, right?
When node 1,000 joins, we
may need to generate now
1,000 possible edges, right?
Does it link to node 999, and
then 998, all the way down
to node let's say
number 1, right?
So this would mean
that in principle we
need to generate a
full adjacency matrix.
And this is complex,
and it's like--
it leads to very kind of
long-range edge dependencies.
Because you have to memorize--
the model needs
to memorize a lot
in terms of what
previous nodes were added
and which previous nodes does
a new node want to connect to,
right?
So if you have a node
ordering like I show you here,
then for example,
the way you generate
this graph would be add node
1, add node 2, add node 3,
and only now start
creating edges, right?
Then this doesn't
feel like natural, it
seems that like this
when I added node 3,
I needed now to remember that
1 and 2 were already added
and all that, right?
And the point is that a
new node needs to link to--
can in principle link to
any previous node, right?
Even node 5 could
link to node number 1?
And the question is, how would
we limit this complexity?
And how would we limit these
long range dependencies, right?
Because this means that
the hidden state of node 5
somehow has to remember that
node 1 was added at all the--
at the beginning and
that 5 should link to 1.
And that's a lot to kind
of ask our model to do.
So if we can help it in any
way that would definitely help.
So the way the insight
is that we can take a--
because the insight
is that we can come up
with an node ordering that makes
our model much more tractable.
So the insight is that,
rather than having
a random node ordering and
having the model to worry
about long-range
dependencies, we
are going to use a node
ordering that helps
the model learn better.
And the node ordering
we propose is
called the breadth-first
search node ordering.
Basically, we are going to
start at some random node
in the graph.
We are going to label
it as node number 1.
We are going to label its
nodes as, let's say 2 and 3.
Then their neighbors
are 4 and 5, right?
And this leads now to a
much more natural recipe
to generate the graph, right?
We are saying add node 1,
add node 2, connect 2 to 1,
add 3 connect it with 1, add
4 connect it with 2 and 3.
It's kind of much more nicely
interwoven, these things are.
And if you say, how would
you draw this graph?
You'd probably draw it this
way, not some other way
that you first put all the nodes
down and then connect them,
right?
So the BFS ordering,
what does it buy us?
It buys us the following,
because node 4 does not
connect to node 1, we
know that no other node
is going to connect to
1 from now on, right,
because it's a breadth-first
search ordering.
So if for example, node 5
were to connect to node 1,
then its ID wouldn't be 5, it
would be less than 5, right?
So we know that all
of node 1's neighbors
have already been traversed
when a given node does not
link to it.
Therefore, node 5, and
all the following nodes,
right, as I said, will
never connect to node 1.
And why is this important?
Because this means
that when node 5 comes
I don't need to worry about
node 1 anymore, right?
Node 1 I can kind of forget, I
need to have much less memory,
right?
I don't need memory, I only
need memory of two steps
rather than memory of
remembering what I did
all the way at the beginning.
So the BFS ordering,
the key insight
is that node 5 will
never connect to node 1.
And this means that we only
need memory of two steps,
rather than the memory
of n minus 1 steps where
n is the number of
nodes in the network.
And this also means
that it reduces
the number of possible
orderings, right,
rather than considering all
the possible orderings which
is n factorial of them.
We only have to kind of consider
the number of distinct BFS
orderings.
And it also reduces
the number of steps
for edge generation
because of this insight
that we know that
5 won't link to 1.
And this is important.
Because so far, I
explained to you,
I said, the edge level
RNN generates the column
of the adjacency matrix.
But if you take this
BFS based ordering,
then the edge level
RNN does not really
need to generate
the entire column.
It can-- it only
needs to generate
a small part of the
column because we
know that the rest is 0, right?
So, rather than
generating connectivity
to all previous
nodes, and having
to remember all this with
the proper node ordering,
we are guaranteed
that all we need to do
is generate just a small band
of this adjacency matrix.
And again, this
doesn't prevent us
from generating any
kind-- like graphs,
this is still fully
general, it is just
exploiting the ability that
we can re-number the nodes.
We can order the nodes in
whatever order we want.
And because real
graphs are sparse,
a favorable ordering
gives us a lot of benefit
because it's much
easier to learn
to generate just this
blue part, than to learn
to generate this
entire upper triangle
of the adjacency matrix.
So this was the
discussion of how
do we scale up our model and
its insight, that we can come up
or we can decide on the ordering
and if you are smart about it,
it can really help us.
It could help the model learn.
The second thing I
want to talk about
is, how do we evaluate
graph generation, right?
And there are two ways
how you can do it.
One is that we
visually look at them
and see whether
they are similar.
And that's good to
get some intuition,
but we also want to define a
statistical notion of graph
similarity.
And of course, you
could try to say,
I'll take two graphs and I'll
somehow align them one on top
of the other, but that is very
expensive and for big graphs
you cannot do that.
So we have to define some kind
of statistical measure of graph
similarity between two graphs.
So first, let me show
you some visual examples
of what GraphRNN is able to do.
So what I'm showing here is
three input training graphs.
These are the output
graphs from GraphRNN,
and here are some output from
three traditional generating
models.
This is the Kronecker
graphs generating model,
this is the mixed membership
stochastic block model,
and this is the
preferential attachment
to the Barabasi-Albert model.
And what you notice
is that GraphRNN,
if you give it grids it's
going to generate you grids.
You see little mistakes because
the model is stochastic,
so it may make some little
mistakes, that's OK.
But you see that other
models completely fail,
they are not able to
generate the grid.
And this is not surprising
because none of these models
was developed to generate grids.
They were developed
to generate networks
for different types
of properties.
So that's OK, right?
GraphRNN can generate the
grid the others cannot.
What is interesting though,
is, even if you for example
give GraphRNN examples
of graphs with two
clusters with this kind
of community structure,
GraphRNN is able to learn
that these graphs have
that structure and is
able to generate you
graphs with such a structure.
Why?
For example, Kronecker graphs or
Barabasi-Albert, they cannot--
they were not done to
generate graphs with community
structures.
So they cannot do that, but
mixed membership's stochastic
block model was developed
for community structure.
So it does a good job, right?
And what I want to say
here is the following,
right, is that GraphRNN
is super general, right?
It's basically able to
take these input graphs
and learn about the
structure and then
generate new graphs with
similar structure, right?
You don't have to tell it,
Hey, I have communities.
Hey, this is a grid.
You just give it the graph, and
it will figure it out by itself
that the given graph
is a grid and it
needs to generate a grid, or
that it's a community structure
graph or anything else.
So it's quite remarkable that
such a diversity of graphs,
the same model can
cover and you don't even
have to tell it what
the input graphs are.
So now, how about doing
more rigorous comparison
about statistical
similarity, right?
How do we do that, right?
we-- as I said we cannot do
direct comparison between two
graphs, trying to
do graph alignment,
because graph isomorphism
testing as we have seen is
an NP, is a hard
problem, let's say.
So the solution is to
compare graph statistics,
and the typical graph statistics
we have already discussed
would be like degree
distribution, clustering
coefficient, or orbit count
statistics from the graphlets
that I discussed, I think
in lecture number two.
So the point would
be that given a graph
we are going to describe it
with a set of statistics,
and then we are going to
say that the two graphs are
more similar if their
corresponding statistics are
more similar.
And in our case, each
of these statistics
we are going to think of it
as a probability distribution.
And I'm going to explain
why is this important.
OK.
So first, is that,
given two statistics,
maybe two graph
properties, maybe degree--
two degrees sequences,
two degree distributions,
two orbit count distributions.
We want to compare this
on sets of training graphs
as well as on the
syntactic graphs.
You want to see how similar
is a set of training
graphs to the set of
synthetically generated graphs.
And we'd like to measure
the level of similarity
between the two.
And we are going to
do a 2-step approach.
In the first step, we are
going to do the following.
We are going to take
each of these graphs
and we are going to describe
it with a set of statistics.
We'll say here is the
degree distribution,
here is the clustering
coefficient distribution.
And now, we'll take
and we are going
to this for all the input
graphs, training graphs,
as well as, for all
the generated graphs.
And now, we are going to take,
let's say, degree distribution
of a synthetic graph and degree
distribution of a real graph,
and we want to see how much
of these distribution differ.
And to measure--
to quantify that we
are going to use something
that we call the earth mover
distance.
And now, that we have compared
the statistic individual
statistics.
Now, we need to aggregate
and measure how--
once we have a measure of
degree distribution similarity,
we have a measure of clustering
coefficient similarities.
Now, we need to take
these similarities
and further aggregate them to
get the overall similarity.
And for this second
level aggregation,
we are going to
use what is called
the maximum mean discrepancy
that will be based on the earth
mover distance.
So let me tell--
let me first define the
earth mover distance and then
the MMD.
So the earth mover
distance, kind of
tries to measure similarity
between two distributions,
or similarity between
two histograms.
And the way you
can-- the intuition
is that, what is the
minimum amount of effort,
minimum amount of Earth, minimum
amount of probability mass
to move from one
pile to the other,
so that one pile gets
transformed to the other,
right?
So I say, I have a distribution,
I have two distributions,
how much more?
How much mass?
How much of this yellow--
dirt, yellow earth,
do I have to move
between these
different pillars, so
that I will make
it and transform it
into this type of distribution?
So if I have distributions
that are very different,
then the earth mover
distance would be high.
And if they are kind of similar,
the earth mover distance
will be low.
And earth mover distance can
be solved as an optimal flow,
and is found by using a linear
program optimization problem.
We're basically saying, the
amount of work I have to do
is, how do I take
F and transform it.
How much earth do
I have to move,
so that it minimizes
the overall cost
didj between the probability
distributions x and y.
So that's the intuition behind
the earth mover distance
metric.
And then, the
second part will be
that, we are going to use
the maximum mean discrepancy,
or MMD.
And the idea of
maximum discrepancy
is to represent distances
between distributions,
as distances between mean
embeddings of their features,
right?
And here I give you
the formula for it.
But basically, the MMD between
two distributions p and q,
you can think of it--
is-- that this is the--
if I write it in terms
of some kernel k,
it's kind of the expectation
over these elements x and y
that are drawn from
distribution p and q,
and taking the expectation over
the distribution of p and q.
And of course, we need
to have this kernel k.
In our case, the kernel
will be the L2 distance.
So now, let me just summarize.
How do we put all this together?
We are given two sets
of graphs and we want
to see how similar they are.
The way we are going to do
this is, for every graph
we are compute--
we are going to
compute its statistics.
We are then going to
use earth mover distance
to measure to the discrepancy
between the two statistics,
between the two distributions.
And then, we are going
to apply the mean--
the maximum mean
discrepancy to measure
the similarity between
these sets of statistics.
Where the similarity
between sets elements--
which means the
individual distributions
in your statistics is computed
with the earth mover distance.
And this means, for
example, that, this way
we can rigorously evaluate
the correspondence
between the
particular statistic--
set of statistics on
the training graph,
as well as, on the
testing graphs.