So now we are going to move forward and we are going to move to the next topic,
which is called identity-aware graph neural networks, right?
So in the previous part of the lecture, we talked about,
how does the node encode its position in the network?
How does the node know where in the network, the node is?
Now in the second part,
we are going to develop a more expressive graph neural network that is
going to take care of
all these different symmetries that can account- that can appear in the network and uh,
in the underlying graph,
and it - it will make the graph neural network more expressive.
So what we have learned so far is that
classical GNNs would fail for position-aware tasks.
And we said, let's use, um,
let's use anchors to improve graph neural network performance on position-aware tasks.
Now, we are going to switch back and to- and focus more on structure-aware tasks.
And say, can GNNs perform perfectly on structure-aware tasks?
And as we have seen before,
the answer here is unfortunately no.
Uh, and the issue is that
GNNs exhibit kind of three levels of failure cases in, uh structure-aware tasks.
And I'm going to show you some,
you know, failure cases.
And of course, all these failure cases are kind of worst-case scenarios uh,
that are very intricate in a sense that uh,
due to the symmetries,
the GNN is going to fail.
So perhaps they don't necessarily appear in practice uh, too often,
but they may appear in some parts of the data,
and they are still very useful uh, to study.
So here is the first uh, failure case.
Uh, this is for the Node-level tasks.
Imagine you wanna do a Node-level classification,
you want to do Node-level prediction.
Here, different inputs from the same, uh,
basically different inputs, but at
the same computational graph will result in the same embedding.
So if I have these two nodes,
v_1 and v_2, uh,
you know, residing in these types of connected components, as we said before,
their computational graphs, um,
if you work it out are exactly the same because they have
two neighbors and each of their neighbors has two neighbors and so on and so forth.
So this means that these nodes v_1 and v_2 will be embedded into
exactly the same point in the embedding space
and we won't be able to assign them different labels.
Now, the same type of things can happen also, for example,
for link prediction, where for example,
you can have this type of input graph.
And you want to decide whether you know,
v_0 should link to v_1 or should it link to v_2?
And again, if you look at the computation graphs,
um, the -the computation graphs are the same.
So nodes v_1 and v_2 are going to have the same embedding.
And because they have the same embedding,
the neural network will give the same probability to- to edge A as well as to edge B.
And perhaps that is not uh, the most realistic.
So that's our failure case again for a different type of uh, input graph.
And then, you know,
for graph level tasks,
there are also uh,
well-known failure cases because
different input graphs will still
result in the same graph neural network based embedding.
Um, and why- why is that the case?
It's because if you, for example,
uh, in these types of- in these types of networks,
all the nodes have the same degree, um,
but you notice that these two graphs are different because
here the nodes link to exactly the immediate nodes.
Here the- the nodes link kind of a bit farther out.
But if you look at the computation graphs,
the two computation graphs uh, will be the same.
So again, uh, these two- these two entire graphs will get the same embedding.
So again, this is, um,
a very kind of highly symmetric uh, input graph.
But still these two graphs are different.
They are non-isomorphic.
But you know, this is kind of a corner case for
WL test and it is also a corner case for graph neural networks.
So here again, uh, graph,
A and graph neural network without
any useful node features will always classify nodes A and B,
uh, or graphs A and B into the same position, into the same class.
So now, how are we going to resolve this?
What is the big idea here?
And the big idea in this second part of the lecture,
is that we can assign a color to the node we want to embed.
And that's why we call this identity-aware,
because the neural network,
as we unroll it,
will know what is the starting node,
what is the node where we started?
So the idea is, if I want to embed nodes v_1- v_1,
I'm going to color it.
And if I go, um,
and because I'm going to give it a color,
um, now, the graph, the computational, uh,
graph will be different because I will remember whenever I unroll uh,
the computational graph, I will remember the color of this colored node.
Right? So this means that, uh,
now our computational graph,
will- will- will remember whenever it hits the node of interest v_1.
So it we'll have these colors um, and you know,
why- why is this,
um, uh, why is this useful?
This is useful because it is inductive.
Right? It is invariant to the node ordering, um,
or identities of the nodes because the only node we color is the node where we started.
And then we just look,
how often does this node,
where we start appear in the computation graph, right?
So eventually, right, like if- if
our graph is- is connected as- as we go deeper into more layers of a graph neural network,
there will be some cycle that will lead us back to the starting node,
and we will remember that and have that
node colored in the computation graph, uh, as well.
And the important point here is because- because the node coloring is inductive,
even though I- I have these two,
let's say, different input graphs,
but I have labeled, uh,
or numbered the nodes differently, right?
I have 1, 2,
3 versus 1, 2,
3, the underlying computational graphs will be the same,
which is good because they don't change under, uh,
permuting the IDs or identities, uh, of the node.
So this is a great feature to have because it
means our models are able to generalize better.
So let's now talk more about this, uh,
inductive capability of node coloring.
And let's look at the node level task.
Um, and the point is that
this inductive node coloring helps us with node classification tasks.
For example, I have here,
um, the case, we have already,
uh, looked at before.
I have the node on a triangle,
I have a node on a square,
um, I colored the root.
And now I say, let's create the computation graphs.
Here I create the computation graphs and you, um,
very quickly see that the computation graphs,
um, are quite- are quite different.
And in particular they- they become different at, uh,
at the bottom level,
where in the- in the part B here,
when I go to two hops- when I go two hops out,
I only hit these nodes while in the- in the first case,
um, I actually get- go and hit again the starting node.
So now these two computation graphs are different because we also consider colors.
So we will be able to successfully differentiate between nodes v_1 and nodes v_2.
So, uh, this is a very elegant solution to the- to- to this, uh,
to this, uh, uh problem that where
a classical graph neural network, uh, would fail.
Um, and similarly, we can do the same thing,
uh, for- um, for graph classification, right?
If I take my two input graphs, uh,
the way I created the- aga- the embedding of the graph is to create an embedding,
uh, of nodes and then aggregate those.
So if I look at node-specific, um, uh,
computation graphs, uh, structurally,
they might be the same,
but- but- but because I have labeled the starting node and
now I- I know whenever my computation graph returns back to the starting node,
you'll notice that now the coloring pattern between these two graphs,
uh, is different- these two nodes is different,
which means their embeddings will be
different which means that when we aggregate the embeddings,
the embeddings for the graphs will be different,
which means we'll be able to take these two input graphs,
A and B, um,
and embed them into,
um, different points and assign them different classes.
So this is exactly what we want.
And then, you know,
for the edge level tasks,
again, ah, if, you know,
I start with V_0 and I say,
you know I want to assign a different, uh, uh,
probability to, um, uh, to nodes,
V_1- to the edges A and B,
I can say what will be the embedding of V_1, uh, here?
What will be embedding of V_2?
And I see that their corresponding computation graphs, uh,
will be different because, uh,
V_1 is going to hit V_0 sooner than, uh, V_2.
So, um, here, the point is that when I'm embedding nodes for link prediction,
I'm given a pair of nodes and here,
I'm going to color,
um, both- both nodes,
the- the- the left node and the right node and this way,
I'll be able to distinguish, um,
uh, the two computational, ah, graphs.
So this means it will allow us to, uh,
assign a different probability to the node- to the edge A versus,
uh, the edge B, which is, uh, what we want.
So what you- what I have demonstrated so far is that
this node coloring where we color the identity of the- uh,
of the starting node or in link prediction of the- of this- of these both, uh,
nodes in involving the link prediction task
allows us to differentiate and distinguish, uh,
these types of symmetric, uh,
corner cases that make classical neural network- graph neural networks, uh, fail.
So now, the question is,
how do you build a- a GNN that uses this node coloring and that you- it will allow us,
uh, to distinguish these different colored, uh, computation graphs.
The idea is the following and the model is called identity aware, uh,
graph neural network and what we wanna do
is you've wanna utilize inductive node coloring in
the embedding computation and the key idea
is that you want to use heterogeneous message passing, right?
Normally in a GNN,
we apply the same message aggregation computation
to all the children in the computation graph, right?
So whenever we- we are, uh, aggregating, uh,
masters and transporting messages,
we apply the same aggregation in the same neural network operator, right?
So, um, this is what we classically do.
In our graph neural- identity aware graph neural network,
we are going to do heterogeneous message passing.
So we are going to use different types of aggregation, um,
different types of message passing applied to different nodes based on their color.
So it means that in an IDGNN,
we are going to use, um,
different message and aggregation, uh,
functions, uh, for nodes with different, uh, colors.
So it means that for example,
whenever we are aggregating into a color node,
we are going to use one type of, uh,
transformations and message passing operator
and whenever we are aggregating into a non-colored node,
we are going to use a second type of,
uh, aggregation and transformation.
So this means that in a given layer,
different message and aggregation, uh,
functions would be used to nodes based on the color,
uh, of the node and this is the key, right?
Because if the node- nodes is color and it
can use a different aggregator, this means that,
uh- that the- the- the message will get transformed differently,
which means the final results will be different depending on whether
the nodes with colors were involved in aggregation versus nodes without colors,
uh, uh, being involved in aggregation.
So um, you know why does this heterogeneous message-passing work?
Right? Suppose that two nodes,
V_1 and V_2 have the same computational graph structure,
but they have different node coloring, right?
Um, and since we apply different neural network embedding computation,
right- different, um, uh,
message passing and different aggregation, right,
we have different parameters for nodes with one,
uh, color versus the nodes with the other color,
this means that the final result, uh,
will be different and this means that the final output-
the final embedding between V_1 and V_2 is going to be, uh, different.
So, you know, what is the key, uh,
difference between GNN and identity aware GNN?
If we look at this,
uh, you know- uh, use, uh,
this case- uh, this example we have looked so far,
if I have nodes V_1 and V_2 I wanna distinguish them,
in the classical GNN computation,
the two computation graphs are the same,
uh, all the nodes are the same,
there is no differentiating node features,
so the aggregations across these two, uh,
trees will be the same,
so we won't be able to distinguish A and B.
In the case when we actually color
the starting node and now the two computation graphs are different,
so all we have to account for now that- is
that when we aggregate the information from the- um, uh,
from the leaves to the root of
the graph neural network that this information about the color is preserved
or somehow accounted for so that the final message will have
a different value depending on one, uh, versus the other.
And this is exactly,
um, the case what is happening,
and this is why IDGNN allows us,
uh, to make this distinction.
Um, another thing to think about it,
what is G- IDGNN really doing?
IDGNN is really counting cycles of different lengths,
uh, uh starting at a given,
uh, given the root node, right?
So if I start here,
IDGNN will now able to count or realize that there is a cycle of length 3, right?
So here- this is now basically a cycle.
You get off- you go from yourself to the- uh,
to the neigh- to the neighbor, uh,
and then to another neighbor,
and you'll come back to the node, right?
So this is a cycle of three hops.
While- while in this case you- we- we'll
reali- graph neural network is going to realize that this is a cycle of length 4,
because you have to go to the node,
to the neighbor, um,
to the first neighbor, to the second neighbor,
to the third neighbor, and from here,
you only arrive, uh,
to the starting node itself, right?
So here we'll real- the- the computational graph will be able to capture
that- or be able to compute that- that node is part of a cycle of length,
uh, 4, but no cycles of length 3.
While here, these will be able to capture that
the node is a part of cycle of length o- uh,
3 but not, uh, let's say 4.
So this is what IG- IDGNN is able to do.
It's able to count cycles and it's able to learn and count- count them through the,
uh, uh, message passing of the graph neural network.
So, um, how do you now,
uh, uh, how do you do this now?
So as I said, one is to use,
uh, heterogeneous message passing.
Um, and, uh, and the second way how you can do this is that,
um, we can- based on the intuition we have, uh, just proposed,
you can also use a simplified version of the IDGNN,
where basically the idea is to include identity information
as an augmented node feature, um, and, uh,
sidestep the- the heterogenous node, uh, uh,
message passing and the idea here is basically you can augment the node feature,
by using the cycle counts in each layer
as an- as an augmented node feature and then apply,
a simple GNN, right?
So basically, you want to use cycle counts in each layer as
an augmented feature for the root node and then simply apply het- uh,
homogeneous message-passing, basically drop the colors, right?
So the idea would be that every node gets now,
um, ah, uh, gets a description that simply says,
how many cycles of length 0 are you part of,
how many cycles of length 2- like- cycles of length 3s,
and, uh, and so on.
And this way, you will be able to, um, uh, uh,
to distinguish the node- uh,
the two computational graphs,
and be able to distinguish the two nodes, uh,
into two different, uh, classes.
So let's summarize the identity aware graph neural networks.
Uh, the- this is a general and powerful extension to graph a neural network framework.
Um, it makes graph neural networks more expressive.
Uh, the IDGNN, this idea of inductive node coloring and
heterogeneous message passing can be applied to any graph neural network architecture,
meaning, um, gra- graph convolutional neural network,
GraphSAGE, um, GIN,,
so graph isomorphism network and- and any other, uh, architecture.
Um, and IDGNN will provide a consistent performance gain in many node-level, um, er,
as well as edge and graph-level tasks,
because it allows us to break the symmetries and allows
us to the- basically identify how the node,
uh, belongs to different, uh, cycles.
This means that IDGNNs are more expressive than their, uh,
graph- kind of classical graph neural network, uh, counterparts.
Um, and this means that IDGNN is kind of this- the, uh,
uh, the simplest model that is more expressive than 1-WL test.
Um, and it can be easily implemented because it's basically just you color the root node,
and that's all the information,
uh, you need to, uh, worry about.
So, uh, this is quite cool because it allows us now to
distinguish this node on a triangle versus node on a square.
Um, this was the first and the key idea is here to have this inductive node coloring,
and then we also talked about position aware graph neural networks,
where the idea is that you want to distinguish the position of the node in the graph,
and the key idea there was to use the notion of
anchors and characterize the location- the position of the node,
by the location, uh,
by the distance of the node to the anchors.
And we talked about we want to have anchors- anchors of different sizes.
And we wanna have a lot of anchors of size 1,
we wanna have a lot- uh,
fewer anchors of size 2,
even fewer of size 4 and so on and so forth.
Um, and the- the distance of a node to the anchor
is the distance of the node to the- any node that is part of this,
uh, anchor or, uh, anchor set.
[NOISE]