Uh, in this lecture, I will introduce the use of hyperbolic graph embeddings in learning,
uh, representations for graphs that exhibit certain hierarchical and tree-like structure.
Um, so in previous lecture, uh,
we have focused on graph representation learning in the Euclidean space,
uh, which is the R_ n. Um, however,
Euclidean embeddings cannot always capture complex graph structure.
So here we have an example of a tree structure,
uh, a, uh, complete binary tree,
where the first level we observe there,
uh, there's one node,
and the second level we have two nodes,
and the third level we have four nodes, etc.
So in this kind of tree-like structure often, there, uh,
there is an exponential increase in the number of nodes,
uh, as the depth of the tree increases.
So these kind of trees are, uh,
difficult to be embedded in the Euclidean space, uh,
as you have seen, uh, because the slide itself is a 2D plane.
And we can see that, uh,
as the depth increases,
uh, the nodes that are, uh,
leaves become closer and closer to each other to the point that they can no longer,
uh, the embedding space could no longer represent,
uh, the distance between them, um, faithfully, uh,
because they are very, very clustered together due
to the exponential increase in the number of nodes.
So here we are focusing on these kind of,
uh, graphs with, uh, such tree-like structure.
Um, so we define these kind of tree-like graphs as,
uh, graphs that are similar to a tree.
For example, the binary tree as shown above,
but it can still contain a very few cycles.
Uh, for example, in real-life, uh, uh, situations,
we can have things like knowledge graph that are organized hierarchically because,
uh, many of the human knowledge are organized hierarchically.
And, uh, at the same time,
there could still exist a certain kind of loops in- in- in the structure.
So it's most- mostly a tree but with a certain,
uh, a number of loops in- in the graph itself.
So here, uh, we're considering this kind of structure and, uh,
we want to notice that embedding geometry has been very important in terms of,
uh, capturing this kind of special graph structure.
Um, here we consider some,
uh, other, uh, interesting graph structure.
For example, if we have graphs with,
uh, very, uh, many, very large cycles.
Uh, uh, these kind of graphs are best embedded into spherical geometry.
Because in a spherical geometry with the positive curvature, the, um,
the graphs, uh, uh,
we can actually embed many,
many cycles because the sphere contains many, many cycles.
Um, whereas a- if you- if we have a grid-like graph,
um, Euclidean space is the best.
Uh, because as you can see,
the Cartesian coordinate itself is a grid-like structure.
So it could, uh, a Euclidean space with zero curvature would be the best.
So how about hierarchical tree-like graphs?
Um, for these kind of graphs,
we are considering the use of hyperbolic space,
which is an alternative, uh,
embedding space to model, uh,
embeddings for trees with tree-like structure.
Um, the advantage of hyperbolic embedding, uh,
space, um, allows it to,
uh, naturally model trees.
And we will, um, elaborate on these advantages, uh,
in the later, uh,
later slides where we explain the definition.
However, there are certain challenges, uh,
when we combine deep learning, and hyperbolic spaces.
The primary reason is that existing deep-learning toolboxes can only be applied,
uh, to, uh, uh Euclidean space.
Uh, whereas in hyperbolic space,
we need to define special operators to,
uh, to perform this kind of deep-learning, uh, operations.
Um, uh, let's first define what is a hyperbolic space.
So hyperbolic geometry differs from Euclidean geo- geometry by its, um,
uh, fifth axiom of, uh,
Euclidean, uh, geometry, which is the parallel postulate.
So in Euclidean geometry,
the parallel postulate says that in a given plane,
given a line and a point that is not on the line itself,
at most one line parallel to the given line can be drawn through the point.
Um, and- and this- this seems very obvious in the Euclidean space.
If we have, uh, if we- if we have a line then the line parallel to itself is, uh,
kind of unique, uh,
if we only consider,
uh, lines that pass through one point.
Um, however, in, uh, hyperbolic geometry, uh,
there are infinites number of lines that are parallel to a given line through the point.
This might not seem very, uh,
intuitive because we are very familiar with Euclidean space.
But here is a representation of a
hyperbolic space in terms of Poincare ball.
So we will explain what is a Poincare ball there.
Um, but it's basically a way to visualize the hyperbolic space in Euclidean space.
And you can see the blue line here.
Um, it looks like a curve, uh,
but it is actually a straight line, uh,
uh, in- in the hyperbolic space.
And we can- we can also define a redpoint here,
which is another point that is not on the line.
Um, and hyperbolic geometry states that, uh,
there are infinite number of lines that are parallel to the line.
And these lines are actually drawn in the visualization.
So all these are curved, uh,
black lines that's, uh, we draw here.
They're actual- actually straight lines, uh,
hyperbolic geometry, and they also pass through the redpoint.
And at the same time,
they are also parallel to the blue curve, uh,
sorry, it- to- to the blue straight line in the hyperbolic space.
Uh, and that's, uh,
mainly how it differs from the Euclidean space.
Uh, so because of these special properties,
hyperbolic space cannot be naturally represented in
the Euclidean space because it violates the fifth,
uh, uh, the fifth axiom of Euclidean space,
which is the parallel postulate.
So, um, we currently use
two geometry models to represent or to visualize hyperbolic space,
um, by embedding it as a subspace of the Euclidean space.
And, uh, they are also equivalent.
So we can also map between
these two models that visualize hyperbolic space and Euclidean space.
So the first model that we're going to introduce is the Poincare model.
Uh, this is a model,
uh, where we represent, uh,
uh, where you represent the hyperbolic space as a open, uh, an open ball.
So, um, a visualization of it is, uh,
on the right where,
uh, we can see a ball.
Um, and this, uh, by open,
we mean that's- the set of all points in this hyperbolic space,
uh, do not ex, uh, do not include the boundary of the ball.
So the- the outer circle,
uh, is not part of the, uh, ball,
but everything inside the circle, uh,
is part of the Poincare, uh, Poincare ball.
And the radius is proportional to the square root of
K. And we will introduce what is K later.
Uh, K is actually the inverse of the curvature.
Um, and- and, uh,
the important property here is that each triangle in the figure has the same area.
So, uh, it might not, uh, again,
it's not very intuitive in Euclidean space, uh,
as we see like all the triangles in the middle tend to have a larger, uh,
seems to have a larger area in the Euclidean definition of, uh, uh, Euclidean metric.
Uh, but, um, uh,
but every triangle here actually have the same area.
And, uh, you can see why this space is very amenable to embedded,
uh, hierarchical or tree-like structure.
Because you notice that in the middle or in the center, uh, of the, uh,
uh, Poincare ball, there are very few of these triangles that are, uh,
in- in hyperbolic space, whereas, uh, uh,
towards the edge of the,
uh, or of the circle, uh,
you can see like there are exponentially many of these,
uh, smaller triangles, uh,
albeit with the same, uh,
area, um, that are embedded, uh,
towards the edge of
the hyperbolic space or the- to- towards the edge of the Poincare ball.
So this exponential increase in- in terms of the area or the volume, um, uh,
as the, uh, the r- radius or the norm increases,
allow us to embed, uh, hyperbolic trees.
So basically trees, um,
can be embedded by embedding its, uh,
roots in the center,
um, because there are very few of them.
Um, and embedding all the leaves on the edge of the Poincare ball, um,
because there are exponentially many of these leaves,
uh, uh, at the, uh, as the depth increases.
Um, and we're going to introduce another alternative model that, uh,
models the hyperbolic space,
which is called the hyperboloid model,
um, and also called Lorentz model.
Um, this is basically an upper sheet of
a two sheet hyperboloid and that is visualized in the figure below.
And this is also a set of Euclidean space.
So, um, unlike Poincare model as you can see,
there are exponentially many, um,
triangles towards the edge of the,
um, Poincare, uh, Poincare ball.
And, here hyperboloid model is numerically more stable,
meaning that you don't have to have
extremely high machine precision to represent all these,
uh, small triangles, uh,
in terms of their embeddings,
uh, towards the edge of the Poincare ball.
Uh, here, um, it is basically in the hyperboloid and there is no upper bound.
So it can go,
um,- um,- um - the numbers can grow very large, but,
uh,- uh, it does not require a very high number of, uh,
floating-point precisions to represent the, um, uh,
exponentially many, um - um, uh,
points in that - that are towards the edge of the Poincare ball.
So, um - um,
papers have shown that hyperbolic model is numerically more stable and,
um, it also have the advantage of, uh,
having a slightly simpler formula to represent its, uh,
metric and, uh, as well as, uh,
distances, um, in - in this hyperbolic model.
So a lot of times, uh,
we do derivation and we, uh,
represent the, uh, um,
neural network architecture inside this hyperboloid model.
Uh, so these two are,
um- so the Poincare ball and the hyperboloid model,
these two are equivalent in the sense that we can have a mapping, um,
that, uh, that are between the Poincare ball and the hyperboloid.
And this mapping is one-to-one,
so, um, it's a projection.
Um, so - so given uh,
the brief introduction of the, uh, uh,
hyperbolic space, uh,
we want to also define our task here.
So the task is the typical graph representation learning,
uh, which we have, um, uh, we learned, uh,
throughout this lecture, and tasks could
be things like link prediction or node concentration.
Um, and an example, um,
um, example embedding space that achieves this, uh,
kind of, task is the, uh, Poincare embedding,
um, um, by nickel, uh, in 2018.
Um, so in this visualization,
which is in the form of a Poincare ball,
we can see that entities are embedded inside this, um, Poincare ball.
Um, and towards the center of it is, um - um,
they contain the nodes with very high hierarchy
or nodes that there are toward the roots of the tree.
So for examples of entities,
we have, uh, physical entity,
we have, uh, abstraction or - organ, uh, organism.
These are all very abstract and high
level nodes that can contain many many different childrens.
And - and towards the edge of the, uh,
uh, embedding space, there are many many different,
uh- exponentially many entities can be,
um, um, embedded there,
and these are typically nodes that are in
the lower hierarchy or towards the leaves of the tree like graphs.
For example, things like, um, uh,
arrival, metabolic, uh, metabolic rates.
These are very concrete and, uh,
very detailed, uh, um - um, uh,
description of certain entity, um,
and there are exponentially,
many of them which can be embedded towards the edge of the Poincare ball.
And this is, uh, basically the, kind of,
embedding we want to achieve so that we can perform things like link prediction,
which means that we can predict whether an entity and, uh,
another entity, uh, in this,
uh, in this knowledge graph are connected.
Um, um, meaning that, uh, uh, for, uh,
for example, whether the bread and food are connected,
it could be connected through an hierarchical relations,
or it could be connected through a non-hierarchical relation.
So, um, um, this is link prediction and we can also perform node classification,
um, by, um, um, predicting a label for each of these, uh, nodes in the graph.
Okay. And, um, before going into, uh,
the detailed architecture, uh, let's first,
um, um, also, um, look into, uh,
how hyperbolic space are mathematically represented.
So formal definition of the hyperbolic, uh,
geometry is a manifold, um, um,
which is, uh, which is, uh,
basically a high dimensional surface,
a 2D surface in - but in high dimensional.
Um, and a Riemannian Manifold, um,
is a special manifold,
uh, which is equipped with two things.
One is the inner product.
So the inner product, uh,
between two points had to be defined,
and it is, uh, uh,
it will define a metric space or like how
distances are computed in - in this, uh, Riemannian manifold.
And the other thing that is, uh, um,
that is necessary for Riemannian manifold is the tangent space, um,
which is a Euclidean space that approximates the manifolds,
uh, but only locally.
So you can I - imagine it is tangent to the surface, um,
at a certain point, uh, touching the surface at a certain point at xX. Um,
both function has to, uh- Riemannian manifold,
states that both functions, uh,
which is the inner product and the tangent space,
has to vary smoothly,
or, uh, called differentiable on a manifold.
Um, there are also other, uh,
concepts that are, uh, needed.
So here, uh, we also considered the geodesics.
Geodesics, um, is defined as the shortest path in the manifolds,
uh, which is analogous to the straight line in R^n.
So if you remember the - the plot where we have the parallel postulate,
uh, in hyperbolic space,
um, all these curves are actually geodesics,
so they are the shortest path between two points in the - in the manifold.
And that's why, um, we can say that there are
infinitely many straight lines passing through the points,
um, that are parallel to a given line.
Um, the hyperbolic space, uh,
is a Riemannian manifold with a constant negative curvature.
Um, here we represented as negative 1 over K,
where K has to be greater than 0.
Um, so as you can see, uh,
when becomes very very large, um, um,
the hyperbolic space curvature becomes very very close to zero,
um, and zero just means a flat space.
So it will become more and more Euclidean as to,
um, uh, as K increases.
Uh, but , uh,
the more negative is the curvature.
So when K is small, uh,
the more curved the space will be.
And, um, here we look at a little bit of how does
the curvature affect the - affect the embedding space.
Um, so we use our negative 1, uh,
1 over K to denote the curvature and,
uh, uh, root K is also the radius of the Poincare ball.
Um, um and that's how, uh,
uh, the radius is related to the curvature.
So, um, um, yeah.
Uh, uh, if we look at the hyperboloid model, um,
the - the - the formula is actually very simple.
So this is the, uh, inner product definition,
which is also called the Minkowski inner product,
uh, in hyperbolic space.
Um, so if we have a d-dimensional hyperbolic space,
the hyperboloid model, um,
will have a d plus 1 dimension.
And the, um, the inner product is defined,
um, by these two things.
So, um, there is the negative parts of the inner product,
and there is also the positive part of the inner product,
which behaves almost identical to the Euclidean components.
But we also have the negative part, which is, uh,
um, which has negative sign,
uh, in this inner product.
And based on this, uh,
inner product definition, the, uh,
distance between two hyperbolic points,
um, can be computed as such.
So given two points, x and y in the hyperbolic space, um,
you - we can compute this, um, uh,
Minkowski inner products and divide by K,
which is related to the curvature.
And the arcosh means the,
uh, the inverse of the hyperbolic cosine function.
So we use this function, uh,
to compute the distance between two points.
Um, and another important concept is called the tangent space.
Uh, so as we mentioned that,
uh our tangent space is basically a Euclidean, um,
uh, Euclidean approximation on a local,
uh, point of the manifold.
So a local neighborhood of the manifold.
Uh - uh we can have a Euclidean space that is tangent to the manifold,
but only touching the manifold at, uh, uh, at this one point.
So for example, in this visualization,
we have this hyperboloid model,
again, um, um, representing the hyperbolic space, um,
and, um, the, the tangent space,
uh, at the North Pole,
which is the bottom of the hyperboloid,
uh, is drawn over here.
Um, and we can, uh, define certain mapping here.
So this, um, this line,
um, um, this is actually a straight line.
Of course it looks like a curve in a hyperbolic space,
but if we also map it to the tangent space, this,
uh, becomes a straight line because the tangent space is the Euclidean space.
And the tangent space is defined, again,
through this, uh, Minkowski inner product.
Um, uh where, um, if we do inner product between v and x,
um - um, it is 0.
So that is the, uh, that is the curve - that defines the,
uh, the set of all points, uh,
v such that the inner product between v and x equals to
0 defines the entire, um, tangent space, uh,
at the point x. Um,
and finally, we, um,
we discuss a little bit about geodesic distances.
Um, geodesic distance, as- as we mentioned
is analogous to the shortest path in the Euclidean space,
and, um, it's also the concept of straight line in hyperbolic space.
And the more negative the curvature, uh,
the more the geodesics will bend inwards towards the center.
So - and - and the distance between,
uh, two points will also increase.
So here is an example plot where, uh,
we compute distance between, uh,
two points, x and y,
with the same coordinate.
So, um, uh - uh - uh, say, uh,
like imagine something like x is 0.5,
0.6, y is 0.2,
0.3, and the distance between them actually increases
if the curvature increases- sorry if the curvature becomes more negative.
So, um, towards, uh, the more active parts,
the - the distance between them actually increases more.
So it can be more visualized in - in - in this figure, where,
um, we have these, uh,
two points here, x and y in hyperbolic space.
Here we just represent it in the Poincare, um, Poincare ball.
And here, uh, 0 is the origin,
um, uh, root K is the,
uh, is the radius,
which is also inversely proportional to the curvature of the space.
And the dark blue, um,
curve means, um, is the boundary of the uh,
hyperbolic space where, um,
the curvature, uh, is more negative, right?
Uh, and the more negative the curvature is, uh,
the- the smaller the radius will be.
So, uh, you can see that the geodesics are also drawn here.
So, um, if the, uh,
in the dark blue - so in higher - higher curvature of
space the - the geodesics is more bends towards the center,
towards, uh, the center of the hyper- uh hyperbolic space.
Uh, whereas, uh, for the lighter blue, um,
version or the lighter blue space which has larger curvature,
the, uh, geodesic is less bends inward.
And, um, in the extreme case where,
um, the, um, x, y, uh, uh,
the space is Euclidean meaning that the Poincare ball is kind of infinitely large,
then the geodesics does,
uh, does not bend at all,
which recovers our Euclidean concept of shortest path,
which is basically a straight line here.
Um, and another important concept, um,
based on, uh, all these definitions is the exponential and logarithmic manner.
So this is a map that we can map from the tangent space to the manifolds and vice versa.
So the exponential map maps points- any point in the tangent space to the Euclid- um,
um, uh, from the tangent space to the Euclidean- um, uh, sorry,
from the Euclidean tangent space to the hyperbolic, um,
manifolds and the logarithmic maps, uh,
from the, uh, manifolds,
um, back to the Euclidean tangent space.
Um, so here, uh, it- it is a visualization,
and we use the norm, um,
to represent the inner product between,
uh, two points, uh,
u- using this, uh,
special, uh, Minkowski in the product definition.
Um, so we can uh, conceptually, um,
visualize it as, um, you know, uh,
we have v in the tangent space of x.
And if we want to map it back to the hyperbolic space,
it becomes the point y,
which is on the hyperbolic space.
Uh, and inversely, we can use logarithmic map to map from this y, the blue point,
back to the red point v,
which is in the Euclidean space,
is a Euclidean, uh, coordinate,
and it's in the tangent space of x.
So here this notation, we use, um,
x here as the- the point that is touching- uh,
so the tangent space of x, um,
is the- is the Euclidean space that we want to map to and from.
And K is the curvature,
uh, so it is the- uh,
this- um, the inverse of the curvature that we have, uh, defined.
And here, notice that we have to use this cosh and sinh function,
which are the- uh, which are the hyperbolic,
uh, uh, trigonometry here.
Um, the formulas are- are really very complicated.
Um, um, um, but, um, um,
if the high-level concept is that there exists- you just
need to know that there exists such mapping between the- uh,
the tangent space as well as the,
uh, um, uh, manifolds.
And, um, uh, we can use such mapping to, um,
perform operation in the Euclidean space and ma- map it back to the hyperbolic space.
Um, so given all these preliminaries,
we can now introduce the, uh, hyperbolic GNN.
So the main challenge that, uh,
we are focusing on here is, uh,
that, uh, input features are usually Euclidean.
Um, um, but we want to map it, uh,
to the hyperbolic space to- uh,
to compute the node embedding on the hyperbolic space.
And the second challenge is that, uh,
we need to perform aggregation in the hyperbolic space,
uh, uh, so that we can perform message passing.
And, uh, the third challenge is that a hyper- uh,
we do not know what is the right amount of curvature
for the hyperbolic space that can perfectly embed the graph.
So, uh, this is also something that we need to learn in the meantime.
Um, so if you recall,
the- um, the, um,
uh, GNN, uh, formulation is mostly very similar.
So, uh, here is an outline of the, uh,
GNN architecture where we first compute
the messages between all the neighbors as well as the central nodes.
And- and then we aggregate all your neighbors', uh, messages, uh,
to compute- uh, to compute a representation- uh,
the hidden representation after the aggregation.
And finally, uh, we will, uh,
make an update, uh,
um, of the representation, um, so that, uh,
the- the next level representation will- um,
will, uh, uh, capture the information of the previous layer representation.
Um, so this is- this will be the,
uh, typical like message,
aggregation, and update function,
um, but in a hyperbolic space.
So notice that here we are writing,
um, some, uh, superscripts.
For example, like K_l minus 1,
so this will indicate the curvature or the inverse of curvature at the layer l minus 1.
And here, it is K_l minus 1, K_l,
meaning that the update function needs to convert the point from the,
uh, uh, hyperbolic space of the previous layer, so, uh,
in the layer l minus 1 to the hyperbolic space of a layer l. Um,
and the high-level concept, uh,
is- is also visualized in the- um, in the figure here.
So we have a bunch of points, uh,
which are the previous layer embedding of the graph in the previous hyperbolic space.
And we perform, um,
a message computation of these- um,
uh, uh, between these points as well as this center point here.
Um, and after we perform these messages,
we need to aggregate all these messages.
And we perform this aggregation in this,
uh, tangent space of the, uh,
hyperbolic space because there is no natural definition
of neural network operations in the hyperbolic space.
Um, but if we map them into the tangent space,
then we can, uh,
do something like a center of gravity inside this tangent space,
uh, at the point x.
So we perform this, uh,
aggregation in the tangent space.
And after the aggregation,
we have the green point here which is, um,
then mapped back to the- um,
an- another hyperbolic space of a different curvature.
So you notice that here,
it is the layer l minus 1, sorry,
layer l plus 1, and in the previous layer, uh,
it will be layer l. So this is
a completely different hyperbolic space with a different curvature that we- um,
but we can use the, uh,
exponential and logarithmic map to map the aggregated results back to the- uh,
the- um, the hyperbolic points in
the new embedding space- in the new embed space with a different curvature.
Um, so the, uh,
formula for all these computations are very complex,
um, and un- understanding them requires like, uh,
uh, entire lecture on differential geometry.
So I won't go very much into the detail,
but there are some high-level, uh,
concepts that you can get from- uh, get- get from here.
So, for example, in the message computation, because, um,
hyperbolic space has no natural neural network operations that can be defined here,
we can use this, um, um,
um, linear and- uh,
so linear layer basi- the linear and addition, um,
of the bias term, uh,
in the tangent space of- um,
of the, um, um,
of the hyperbolic space.
So here, we use this,
um, circle and multiply it, uh,
to represent this- like multiply all the linear- linear operation, and this, uh,
circle and- um, and, um, plus, uh,
inside it, uh, to represent the addition,
so the Mobius addition.
Uh, and- and these are very ea- um,
and- and as you can see,
these are, uh, defined through this exponential and logarithmic map here.
So we first use the logarithmic map to map
the points- the hyperbolic points to the Euclidean,
um, tangent space, um,
on that point- uh, on the origin.
So this- here this o means origin.
So we first map it to the orig- um,
the tangent space of the origin.
We perform this ma- uh, matrix multiplication in the tangent space.
And because tangent space is Euclidean,
this operation is well-defined.
And after we perform this linear operation,
you can then map it back to- uh, to the- uh, um,
uh, to the hyperbolic space through this exponential map.
So, um, compared to the Euclidean operation,
basically ask this exponential and logarithmic back to
convert to and from the tangent space to perform this operation.
And similar is also true for,
um, addition, but here,
we need to have a special operator called parallel transpor- transport,
uh, which- um, which tells you how to move the vector around in the space.
So, um, this might not seem very intuitive because in Euclidean space, um,
a vector, uh, can be moved around the Euclidean space without affecting its length.
But actually, in hyperbolic space,
you cannot freely move the vector because as you can see in the visualization,
if we move the- uh, if we- we move a vector,
um, out towards the edge of it,
it will seem smaller, right?
The coordinates will- um, the- the norm of that vector will have to change.
So there's this also the parallel transport here, um, um,
and that, uh, represent the analogy of the,
uh, uh, addition operation in the hyperbolic space.
Um, and all these- notice that all these functions,
although they are very complex, are differentiable.
So we can also use PyTorch and any, uh,
different- uh, other differentiation software to perform these operations.
Um, and in the aggregation,
this is basically very similar to graph attention networks that we have learned.
So we have this attention, uh, weights here.
And we also map it- uh,
map the points, uh,
to the tangent space, uh,
use the, uh, attention weights to aggregate them
and then again map it back to the hyperbolic space.
And in the hyp- uh, update function,
it again follows the same- uh, same, um,
uh, rule where we map it to the tangent space,
we perform the non-linearity.
But note that here, we, uh,
map it back to a different curvature,
right, um, because the next level has
different coverage around different space definition.
Uh, so finally, just to show a little bit of results,
um, uh, here we can see a GNN embedding of a tree-like structure.
Um, and as you can see, because there are exponentially many,
uh, uh, points in the space and, um, uh,
the- the- the geometry is not very nicely preserved,
uh, because, uh, uh,
here we visualize the nodes as like the lighter blue nodes
represent the leaves and the dark blue nodes represent the, uh, roots.
And you can see that some of these leaves are
actually very embedded very close to the root,
which does not respect the tree structure.
Whereas in the hyperbolic geometry, uh,
using the hyperbolic GCN, we're able to, uh,
recover this tree-like structure very nicely, uh, and,
uh, all the points are, uh,
embedded in- in their respective hierarchy.
And we also discovered that curvature is very important,
and there is a sweet spot where we can embed the- um,
a tree with a low distortion,
but also very unstable- uh,
numerically, uh, very stable.
And, uh, finally, um,
we also evaluated in a bunch of, uh,
other- um, other, uh,
standard datasets, uh, graph datasets.
And we basically use this hyperbolicity to measure, like,
how good, uh, is the hyperbolic GNN,
uh, will perform in a given dataset.
So this metric can be found in this,
uh, Gromov, uh, hyperbolicity paper.
Um, and basically the lower, uh,
hyperbolicity, uh, the graph becomes more tree-like.
So here, for example, delta equals to 0,
uh, that means that the graph is,
uh, kind of a perfect tree.
Whereas here, if Delta is 11,
then the graph is not very hierarchical or not very tree-like.
So we can see that, uh, the hyperbolic GNN will per- tend to
perform very well or extremely well when hyperbolicity is 0,
so which means that the graph is, uh, very tree-like.
Whereas if the graph, uh,
does not look like a tree,
then the- uh, uh, uh, the performance tend to drop.
So, uh, that's why the hyperbolic GNN is
especially suitable for hierarchical and on tree-like graphs.
Uh, just to summarize,
uh, here we introduce the hyperbolic geometry.
And we have, uh, two models,
the Poincare ball and hyperboloid uh, model, uh, to,
uh, visualize and represent the hyperbolic, uh,
space in the Euclidean- as a subspace of the Euclidean space.
And we can use exponential logarithmic map to map points to and from the tangent space,
which is Euclidean, where neural network operations can be performed.
And finally, we show that we- uh,
we can use a learnable,
um, uh, curvature, um,
um, at every layer of the GNN so that we can trade off performance and stability.
Uh, thank you, and that's- um,
that's all for, uh, this part of the content.