So what I wanna talk next is,
how do we solve the PageRank equation?
How do we actually compute,
uh, the vector r?
The idea here is to use the method called, uh, power iteration.
And what I would like to do is,
we'd like to do the following.
Right? Given a graph on n nodes,
we want to use an iterate- we will use an iterative procedure that will, uh,
update over time our rank vector r. Um,
and the idea will be that we- we start the procedure by assigning
each node some initial random, uh, PageRank score.
And then we are going to repeat our iterative process until this,
uh, vector r stabilizes.
And the way we are going to measure whether it stabilizes,
we'll say, "Here is our previous estimate."
Now, t runs over the iteration of our algorithm,
where we say this is our previous estimate in the vector r. This is
our new estimating vector r. And if the coordinates,
the entries in the vector don't change too much,
they change less than epsilon, then we are done.
And the equation we are going to iterate is written here.
Basically, node j will say,
"My new estimate of my importance is simply,
take the estimate of the nodes i that point to me, uh,
from the previous step, you know,
divide each one by the out-degree of node i,
sum them up, and that is my new importance.
And we are just going to iterate this, um, you know,
a couple of times and it's ah,
it's guaranteed to converge to the,
uh, to this- to the solution,
which is essentially saying this is guaranteed to find
me the leading eigenvector of- of the underlying,
uh, matrix, uh, M. So, um,
the method that do- does this, what I explained,
is called power iteration, where,
um, basically, the way we are going to do this,
to just write it again in the very simple form,
we initialize vector r, you know,
let's call in- call it initialization to be times zero, to be simply,
uh, you know, every node has,
let's say the same importance or you can assign the random importances.
And then we will simply iterate, you know,
new estimate of r equals M times
previous estimate of r. And we are going to iterate this equation, uh,
for long enough until the- the, uh,
ent- the entry wise differences between estimating
the previous round and in the next round when the sum of these differences,
uh, is, uh, less than epsilon.
Again, notice that this equation is exactly this equation, right?
This is just written in two different ways,
but it's exactly the same thing.
Um, one last thing to say is,
you can use the- what is called L_1 norm,
so the sum of the absolute differences here.
You could also use, let's say, Euclidean norm.
So sum of the squares of absolute differences, uh, if you like.
Um, and generally, it takes about 50 iterations.
You have to compute about 50, uh,
50- you have to compute this product 50 times before you
reach this stationary distribution or this, uh, limiting solution.
So basically, you can compute PageRank by a couple of,
uh, matrix vector multiplies, uh, and you are done.
And this is important because, you know,
Google is computing this PageRank every day over the entire web graph,
write off tens of billions of- uh,
of nodes, uh, and I know hundreds of billions of edges.
All right? So this is really, really scalable and you can- you can compute
it on the- on the graph that captures the entire web.
So, uh, to give you an example, again, uh,
power iteration method, you know,
written again, in a different way.
Our matrix M, our set of flow equations.
Uh, and what I'm going to show you here is the iterations of the algorithm,
where we set node importances to be simply, ah,
1/3 at the beginning and now we multiply
it with matrix M. And you know after we multiply once,
here are the new values.
We multiply the second time,
here are the new values and,
you know, the third time,
and as we keep multiplying the- the- uh,
the value of- values of vector r,
then we'll converge to a stationary, uh,
vector so that m equals - r equals N times r. Um,
and the final importances would be 6/15, 6/15, and 3/15.
It means y and a will have importance of 6/15,
and m will have a lower importance of, uh, 3/15.
So, um, this is- this is what PageRank is going to, uh, give us.
So now that we, uh,
have seen these equations and everything seems beautiful,
uh, we need to ask a few questions.
So first question is, does this converge?
Second question is, does it converge to where we want?
And the third question is,
are the results reasonable?
Right? So basically, what I said right now is create the, uh,
graph represented as this matrix M around this uh, uh,
uh, iterative- power iteration procedure,
it will converge in about 50 steps and you will get your,
uh, vector r out of it.
Let's look at this, uh,
a bit more, uh, carefully.
So it turns out that with what I explained so far,
there are two problems.
The first problem is that some pages are what is called dead ends.
They have no out links.
And It turns out that for such web pages,
the importance, the votes kind of leak out.
I will tell you what I mean by that.
And then there is also a second problem called a spid- spider traps,
where all outlinks are within the same group
and the- the spider traps eventually absorb all- all importance.
So let me now give you an example and you will see what's happening.
So, um, first, spider traps.
Uh, here, in this case, right,
we have a links to b,
and then b has a self-loop.
So if you run this, um, er,
power iteration of what an adjacency matrix describing this graph,
what will happen is that in the end, a will have,
um, importance zero, and b will have importance 1.
And if you think of this, why is this happening is
because wherever the random walker starts,
uh, you know, it will traverse this edge and get into b,
and then it is going to- to- to be stuck here in b forever,
so really, you know,
after some number of time,
the random walker is- is in node b with probability 1,
and can never go back to a.
So this is called a spider trap because the random walker gets trapped, and at the end,
you know, this may be, uh, er,
all the importance will be,
uh, kept here in b.
And you can imagine these that, you know,
even if- if you have a super huge graph here, eventually,
the random walker is going traverse over this edge and then
be stuck forever in this, uh, self-loop.
So that's the problem of spider traps.
Um, and then here is the problem of dead ends.
The problem of dead ends is now that node b has no outlink.
And what this means that if you would simply create an adjacency matrix for this graph,
run the power iteration,
it will converge to all zeros.
And intuitively, why is this happening is
that as soon as the random walker gets to node b,
the random walker has nowhere to go so it kind of falls off
the cliff and the- and it gets lost.
Right? And this way,
the- the dead ends kind of this importance doesn't yet sum to one anymore,
but it leaks out, uh, of the graph.
So, um, this is- uh,
these are two problems that we are going to address.
And, um, you know, what is the solution?
The solution is this notion of,
uh, random jumps or teleports.
So the solution for spider traps is that
we are going to change the random walk processor.
So basically saying at every time
the random walker will not only choose a link at random,
but can also decide to teleport itself.
So let me explain what this means.
So we are going to have one parameter beta
that will allow random walker to do one of the two choices.
With probability beta, you know,
the random walker will decide and follow a link at
random the same way as we discussed, um, so far.
But with probability 1 minus beta,
the random walker is going to jump teleport to a random page.
And the common values of beta usually are between 0.8 to 0.9.
So it means that, you know,
if a random walker gets stuc- stuck in a spider trap,
it will stay here for a few steps,
but it's- eventually, it will- it will- it will be able to teleport out, right?
Because with some smaller probability,
the random walker will say,
"Let me just randomly teleport to a random page."
So it means that out of every webpage,
out of every node, there is a way for you to teleport yourself somewhere else.
So basically, randomly jump somewhere else.
And this is, um,
how now spider traps are no longer the problem because you don't get,
er, trapped, you can always, uh, jump out.
You can always teleport, you know,
the [inaudible] can all you - always kind of give you up.
That is kind of the idea.
Um, how about the dead ends?
The- the- the way you do this is also with teleports.
Essentially, what you say,
if you come to a dead end,
if you come to node m and there's nowhere for you to go,
what you- what you do is you simply teleport with probability 1.0, right?
So, uh, you know,
why were the dead- dead end is the problem?
Dead ends were the problem because m has no outlinks,
so our column of this, uh, matrix M,
the column stochastic adjacency matrix is not- is the- the- the column stochasticity is,
uh, violated because column for node m does not sum to 1 because m has no outlinks.
So what do we do is,
we fix this by basically saying,
when you arrive to node m,
you can- you can randomly teleport wherever you want,
you can jump to any node.
So this means in some sense,
now- now m is connected to all other nodes in the network,
including itself, and, um, you know,
the random worker can choose any of these links with equal probability.
And this, uh, solves the problem of dead ends.
It essentially eliminates them.
So why do teleports solve the problem, right?
What are- why are dead ends and spider traps a problem,
and why do teleports solve both of them, right?
Spider traps, in some sense,
are not a mathematical problem,
in a sense that the eigenve- the eigenvector is still well defined,
the power iteration is going to- to converge,
everything is fine, uh, mathematically.
But the problem is that the PageRank score is not what we want, right?
We don't want to say there is one page on the web that is important,
uh, has all the importance,
and everyone else is zero important, right?
So the solution here is to add teleports.
This means the random walker never gets,
uh, trapped in a spider trap, um,
and it will be able to teleport itself out in a finite number of steps,
which means that all the nodes on the web will now have some importance.
So this basically is,
um, solves us, uh, this particular issue.
So spider traps are not a mathematical problem,
but a problem that PageRank,
uh, value is not- becomes not what we want.
And then dead ends are a problem mathematically
because our matrix M is not column stochastic anymore, uh,
and our initial assumptions are not met, so power iteration,
as a method, does not- does not, uh,
does not work, uh, and does not converge.
So the solution here is to make the column-
the matrix column stochastic by always teleporting when there is nowhere to go, right?
Whenever you come to a node without any outlinks,
you always randomly teleport,
um, and this is now means that basically,
the same solution of teleports both give-
gives us PageRank the way we want it to define intuitively,
and also fixes the underlying mathematical problems
that all these concepts that I discussed, um, are well-defined.
So what is the final solution or the Google solution to this problem?
Um, the solution is that at each step,
the random walker has two options;
you know, it flips a coin,
and with some probability Beta,
it's going to follow an outlink- outlink at random,
and with the remaining probability,
it's going to jump to a random page.
So the way now our PageRank equation that was defined by,
um, uh, Sergey and Brin, um,
or Page and Brin, uh,
back, uh, in, uh,
1998, is the following: we say the importance of node j
equals the Beta times the importances of node i that,
uh, point to it, right?
Divided by their outdegrees plus 1 minus Beta,
1 over N. So the way you can think of this is to say,
if a random if a- how likely is a random walker likely to be at node j right now?
It- with probability Beta,
it decided to follow on, uh,
an outlink, and this means it was,
at node i, with what- with some probability r_i,
and it decided to follow an out- outlink towards,
uh, node j, following, you know,
picking the right outlink out of the d_i outlink has the probability 1 over d_i,
so that's what's happening here.
And then we say, oh, and also,
the random walker could come to the node j,
um, by basically teleporting,
1 minus Beta is probability of teleporting.
Now, how likely is the random walker to land at node j?
Node j is just one out of N nodes,
so the probability that it landed at specific node j is 1 over N. And uh, this is essentially,
uh, the PageRank, uh,
equation and iteration one can run.
Uh, just note that this formulation here assumes M has no dead ends.
The way you can do is you can pre-process matrix M to remove all the dead ends,
um, and or- or explicitly follow random teleports with probability 1.0 out of dead-ends.
So that's how you can, uh, fix this.
But you can see again, this is very fast and very simple, uh, to iterate.
So I just gave you the equation in this,
um, the, uh, flow-based formulation in some sense.
You can also write it in a matrix form,
where you say my new matrix, uh, uh, G, right?
So this should be G equals Beta times the stochastic matrix M plus 1 minus Beta,
um, times the, uh,
the matrix that has all the entries, uh,
1 over N. So this is the random teleportation, uh, matrix,
and this is the- the transition matrix over the edges of the graph.
Um, and then you have this, again,
recursive equation that r equals G times r,
and you can iterate this, uh,
power i- power iteration would still work, um,
and if you ask what should be the Beta value that I- that I set, in practice,
we take Beta to be between 0.8, uh, and 0.9,
which means that you- the random walker takes
about five steps on the average before it decides to jump.
Uh, just to be very clear,
the random walk is just the intuition,
and we'd never simulate the random walk, right?
In the previous lecture,
we actually said, "Let's simulate the random walk."
Here, we don't simulate the random walk,
but, uh, in some sense,
we think of it as being run infinitely long,
and then we say- we show that actually,
we can compute this infinitely long random walk
by basically solving this recursive equation by basically
computing the- the leading eigenvector of this graph-transformed matrix,
uh, that I call,
uh, G, uh, here.
So the random walk is just an intuition because we never truly,
um, we never truly, uh, simulated.
So to show you how this works, here is my, uh,
little graph on three nodes, uh,
here's the matrix M. Notice that, uh,
the node m is a- is a spider trap,
so what do I do now is I add also these,
um, random teleport, uh, links,
so I have this matrix, uh, uh,
1 over N. Let's say that my Beta is 0.8,
so now, my new stochastic transition matrix G is written here, right?
It's 0.8 times the, uh,
matrix of link transitions plus point to the,
uh, matrix of random jumps, where basically,
you can think of this that every column says,
if a no- if a random surfer is at a given node,
then this is the probability distribution where the random surfer is going to jump.
And if you add these two together,
you get a new, um,
transition matrix now that includes both traversing over the links of the graph,
as well as randomly jumping.
Uh, here is how you can think of this in terms of transition probabilities.
These are now, in some sense,
transition probabilities of a random walker,
random surfer, um, and then you can multiply,
uh, r with G multiple times.
Here is the r_0, and now,
we are multiplying it over and over and over again, and you know,
after some number of iterations,
it's going to converge,
and it converges to 7 over 33,
5 over 33, and 21 over 33.
So it means that node m in this graph will be the most important,
followed by y, followed by a, right?
And the why m is so important is because it's kind of a spider trap,
but we also are able to teleport out.
Now, if intuitively, this is, uh, you know,
node m kind of collects too much importance,
you can increase, uh, value of beta,
and the importance of node m is going to, uh, decrease.
And just to show you an idea how this-
how this looks like in- in a bit more interesting graph,
this is a graph where node size corresponds to it's PageRank weight,
and also, there is a number that tells you what's the PageRank score of the node?
What do you notice?
For example, why is PageRank so cool?
It's cool because, for example, first,
notice all nodes have non-zero importance.
So even this nodes here,
um, that have no inlinks,
they still have some importance because a random jumper can always jump to them.
Another thing to notice is that for example,
node B has a lot of inlinks,
and it- so that's why it has high importance, right?
Notice that, for example, node E has, you know,
it has five inlinks, six inlinks,
and, uh, node B also has six inlinks.
But because node E gets most of the inlinks from this unimportant pages,
its importance is, you know,
eighth, versus B, who is 38,
so B is much more important because it gets, uh,
inlinks from these other nodes that have higher importance than this,
uh, little blue nodes.
Um, another thing to notice is,
for example, node C has only one inlink,
but because it gets it from this super important node B,
its importance is also very, very high, right?
You see, for example,
also that, uh, here,
node E has some,
uh, s- uh, you know, some importance,
uh, D has less,
uh, F has less, uh,
they both have the same importance, D and F,
because they both get one inlink from node E. So notice how these, uh,
importances are very nuanced,
and they take a lot of different considerations into account that all make sense,
in a sense of I want a lot of inlinks,
I want inlinks from, uh,
important nodes, even if I have one inlink,
but some were the very important links to me,
that means I am very important,
um, and so on- so on and so forth.
So, uh, this is why this notion of PageRank is so,
so useful, and also,
there is a lot of mathematical beauty,
um, uh, behind its, uh,
its definition, and we can efficiently compute it,
uh, for very large-scale, uh, graphs.
So to summarize, we talked about how do we solve the PageRank, uh, scores.
We solve them by iterating this, uh,
equation, r equals G times r, um,
and this can be efficiently computed using
power iteration of the stochastic matrix G, um,
and adding uniform teleportation solves both the issues with dead ends,
as well as the issue with spider traps