So to, uh, talk about the third method, uh,
we discussed today, I'm going now to,
uh, talk about belief propagation.
So this is the final method around collective classification we are going to talk,
um, in this, uh, in this lecture.
And really this will be all about what is called,
uh, no- uh, message passing, right?
We can think of these methods that we have talked about so far,
all in terms of kind of messages,
beliefs being sent over the edges of the network,
a node receiving these messages update- updating
its own belief so that in the next iterations its neighbors are able to- to get this,
uh, new information and update their own, uh, beliefs as well.
So this is, um, basically what, uh,
uh, what is, uh,
the core intuition we are trying to explore today,
which is all about passing information across the neighbors,
either pushing it or receiving it,
and updating the belief about, uh, oneself.
And, uh, the algorithm that- that does this is also known as loopy belief propagation.
Loopy because we will apply it to graphs that may have cycles, um,
and belief propagation because these messages,
these beliefs are going to be passed over the edges,
uh, of the network.
So let me give you a bit of context and where does this,
uh, notion of loopy belief propagation come from.
Belief propagation is a dynamic programming approach
to- about answering the proba- probabilistic queries,
uh, uh, in a graph, right?
By probabilistic queries, I mean, you know,
computing the probability that a given node belongs to a given class.
And it's an iterative process in which
the neighbor- neighboring nodes talk to each other by passing messages to each other.
And, you know, the way you can,
uh, think of this is really like, you know,
if- if there wouldn't be COVID,
we'd be nicely sitting in school and, you know,
you can- you can pass messages between, uh,
one another if you are, you know,
seat close together or if you are connected in the network, right?
So node v will say,
"I, you know, I believe you,
um, that you belong to this class 1 with the following, uh, likelihood."
And then- and then a given node can
then collect these beliefs from its neighbors and say,
"This now makes me more sure,
or less sure, I also belong to class 1."
And when this consensus, uh,
is reached as these messages are being, uh, passed around,
we- we arrive to the optimum,
we arrive to the kind of the final belief about the- the class or label,
uh, of every node in the network.
So let me show you some basics about message passing,
and we are first going to do this on simple graphs.
We're going to do this on a line graph,
then we are going to generalize this to a,
uh, tree-type graph, and then we are going to apply this to general graphs.
And just for simplicity, uh,
let's assume we want to count the number of nodes in
a graph using message passing, right?
So each node can only interact,
meaning it can only pass messages,
with its neighbors, right?
Other nodes it is connected to.
So, um, you know, as I said before,
note that there might be issues when we- if the graphs contains cycles,
but for now let's assume there are no cycles,
or let's ignore the cycles, right?
So the idea is I have a line graph,
I have nodes 1-6 linked in this type of linear structure.
So the task is that we want to compute,
or count, the number of nodes in the graph.
And the way how we can do this using message passing is that we define some ordering,
uh, on the nodes, right?
And this ordering, let's say,
results in a path,
and then edge directions, uh,
we can think of them according to the ordering of the nodes, right?
So, um, and this edge direction
determines the- the order in which messages are being passed.
So let's say we consider the nodes in order 1, 2, 3, 4, 5,
6, so the messages will start at one and be passed to node 6.
And the way these messages will go is that node i will compute the- the message and then,
um, uh, you know, it will- the message will be sent from node i to node i plus 1.
Um, and the idea will be that, um,
as the message passes to the node,
a node gets to look that message,
may transform it, and pass it on.
So if now we want to go back to this task of counting the number of nodes in the graph,
uh, the idea here is,
um, uh, simple, right?
Uh, each node can only interact with its, uh, members,
its neighbors can only pass messages,
um, and the idea is that each node says,
"What- however many nodes are in front of me,
I also add myself to the count and pass on this message,
uh, to the next node."
So this means that each node listens to the messages from its incoming neighbors,
updates the message and passes it forward.Uh,
and we will use the letter M to denote the message, right?
So for example, the way to think of this node 1 will say, "Oh,
there is one of me," and then it will pass this message M to the neighbor, number 2.
Neighbor number 2 is going to,
uh, get the incoming message and say, "Oh,
there is one node in front of me,
but there is me here as well,
so this means there are- there are two nodes so far."
So it will update the belief that there are,
you know, n plus 1 messages, uh,
ahead of it, and then it's going to send
this message forward with- the message will now have value 2.
And then node 3 is going to collect this message with value 2,
update it, it will say, "Oh,
there is me as well," so it will add one plu- to it,
so it will become a three,
and it will send it on.
And this way, you know,
like when- when we arrive to node, uh, six,
we will be counting the number of nodes, uh,
on the path because every node increases the message value by one and passes it on.
So at the end, you know,
the final belief of node 6 will be that there are six nodes, uh, in the graph.
And then the, you know,
we could even like now take this message and pass it back to the beginning node, uh, 1,
but the main idea here is that each node collects a message from its neighbor,
updates it, and passes it forward.
That's the core operation that I wanted to illustrate here.
And you can see how this works nicely on a- on a line graph,
um, with the proper, uh, ordering of the nodes.
Now we can do the same algorithm also on a tree, right?
If you have a graph that has this acyclic tree-like structure,
then we can perform, uh,
message passing not only on a path graph but also on a tree-structured graph.
The important thing here is to propagate or do
the message passing from the leaves to the root of the node- of the- of the tree.
So the idea is, right,
that first, uh, leaves, um, five,
six and seven, um,
will- and, uh, number 2 will say, "Oh,
we are one- I'm one node,
I'm the first node", and will set the message value to one,
and then they will send messages to their,
uh, to their parents, um, right?
Who are- who are, uh,
here, uh, above them.
And then the parents are going to sum up the values of the messages from the children,
add one to it and pass that message on.
And then again recursively,
the next level, you know,
it is going to sum up the- the incoming here,
it will be 2 plus 1 it's 3,
plus 1 for itself,
it's 4 to send it on,
and then this here is going again to sum up 1, uh,
plus 4 is 5 plus itself equals to 6, um,
so and there should be, uh,
six messages here, actually it should be seven,
so I lost a count of one somewhere.
But you get the idea, right?
So the idea is to say,
"I am one descendant,
I send information on.
I'm one descendant, I send it on."
This one sums the messages,
adds one to them, um, and says, "Oh,
there is three of us,
let me send this forward."
Right? So there will be a value of three here.
Um, there will be, um.
Again, uh, similarly, here it will be a value of one,
so that'll be, uh,
1 plus 3 is 4 plus 1 is 5.
So there'll be five here.
There is one descendant here.
So the two together will be 6 plus 1 for this node at the end,
the final belief will be that,
there is seven nodes, uh, in the graph.
Again, the basic information in this algorithm is this local message computation,
where messages come in,
they get collected by the node,
the node collects them, uh,
processes the messages, creates a new message, and sends it on.
So the loopy belief propagation, uh,
algorithm, what it does,
it, um, you know,
if you say what message will be sent from node i to node j,
it will depend on what node i hears from its neighbors, right?
The content of this message here is going to depend on
the incoming messages from its downstream, uh, neighbors.
So each neighbor passes a message to i to, uh,
i will now take these messages up,
uh, collect them, compute them,
update them, create a new message,
and then send this new message to node, uh, j.
And that's essentially what loopy belief propagation, uh, does.
The way we can think of this a bit more formally, uh, is the following.
We are going to have what is called label-label potential matrix.
So here we are going to capture dependencies between,
uh, a node and its neighbor in terms of labels.
And you can think of this as a- as a- one way to say is, uh,
what is the- if node, uh,
i has label y and node j has,
you know, some other label, uh,
y sub j, then, um, um,
the label-label potential matrix,
the entry of that, uh, um, uh,
cell will be the proportion, uh,
or will be proportional to the probability that node j belongs to class, uh,
Y sub j, given that its neighbor i belongs to class,
uh, Y sub, uh, i.
So this means that here,
if homophily is present,
this matrix will have high values on the diagonal.
Meaning, if- if, uh,
j belongs to Class 1,
then i should also belong to Class 1.
But given that we have this label-label potential matrix,
if there are big values, um,
off the diagonal, this will mean that, you know,
if my neighbor is of Class 1,
then I'm likely to be of class 0.
So it also can capture the cases where the, actually,
nodes that are connected are of the opposite labels,
are of the opposite, uh, classes.
So that this label-label potential matrix that tells us if a node j is of one label,
how likely am I of- uh,
of a different or of some,
uh, other type of label, if I'm node i.
Then we are also going to have this, uh, Phi,
which is the prior belief about what is- what should be the label of node i, so right?
So Phi of, uh,
Y_i is proportional to the probability,
prior probability of node i belonging to class Y_i.
And then we have this notion of a message where message goes from node i to node j.
And this means that it is i's message or estimate of
node y being in class Y sub- Y sub j. Um,
and L will be the set of all, uh, class labels.
So to give you now the formula, firstly,
in the initial iteration, in the utilization,
we are going to initialize all messages to have Value 1.
And then we are going to repeat for every node,
uh, the following formula,
where basically we are right now at node i
and we'd like to compute the message that you are going to send to
node j and we are in this message will be i's belief that j belongs to a given class.
So the way we are going to do this is to say, okay,
let's sum over all the states or over all the possible labels.
Let's take the- the belief that i belongs to a given, uh, label.
And, uh, this is the belie- this is the potential that
the j will belong to the label Y sub j, right?
So this is the label-label potential ma- matrix
that I have introduced in the previous slide.
Now, we are going to multiply that with a- with a, um,
prior probability of node i,
uh, belonging to class Y sub i.
And now here, what we are doing is we are going to sum over all the neighbors, uh, uh,
k of node i, um,
omitting the j, j will- is the uh uh,
the node to which we are sending the message.
So we are summing over everyone but the j or multiplying go- everyone by j.
Where now for every neighbor,
uh, k here, these three neighbors, we are asking,
what is your belief about node, um,
Y being in class,
uh, Y sub i, right?
So now basically what this means is that node i
collects beliefs from its downstream neighbors,
um, aggregates the beliefs,
multiplies with the- its pra- its- its belief what its own class should be.
And then- and then applies the label potential, um,
matrix to now send a message to node j about
how i's label should influence j's, uh, label.
And this is the core of, uh,
loopy belief, uh, propagation, right?
And, uh, we can keep iterating this, uh,
equation until we reach,
uh, some convergence, right?
When basically we collect messages,
uh, we transform them,
and send that message onward to the next level, uh, neighbor, right?
And after this approach,
this iteration is going to converge.
Um, we will have the belief about what
is the- what is the likelihood or probability of node i,
belonging to a given class or to a given label,
uh, Y sub, uh, i.
And essentially the way- the way this will look like
is that our belief will be a product of
the prior belief about what's the label of that node
times the messages of what other nodes downstream,
uh, here labeled as j.
Uh, think about what the label of node, uh,
i, uh, is, and this is encoded in these messages.
So this is the idea how belief propagation algorithm works.
Um, here, I call it loopy belief propagation,
because in practice, people tend to apply this algorithm to, um,
graphs that have cycles or loops as well,
even though than any kind of convergence guarantees and this kind of
probabilistic interpretation that I gave here, uh, gets lost.
So, um, if you consider graphs with cycles, right,
there is no- no longer a fixed ordering on- of the nodes which is, er,
which, um, otherwise the fixed ordering exists in terms if the graphs are trees.
But if a graph has a cycle,
you cannot- you cannot, uh,
sort, uh, the nodes, uh,
in- in a- in a- in a nice order.
And basically the idea is that we apply the same algorithm as in the previous slides,
but we start from arbitrary nodes and then follow the edges to update the messages.
So basically, we kind of propagate this in some kind of,
uh, random order, again,
until it converges or until, uh,
some fixed number of, uh,
iterations is, uh, is reached.
So, uh, to give you an idea how this would look like,
for example, on a - on a graph with cycles, um,
the issue becomes that,
if our graph has cycles,
messages from different subgraphs,
from different subbranches, are no longer independent, right?
So it means that for example,
when our graph was a tree, we could say, "Oh,
let's collect information from the left child,
from the right child,
and add it up, and send it to our parents."
So it means that, kind of,
children don't talk to each other,
and these messages really are coming from disjoint - disjoint parts of the tree.
However, if there is a cycle, then this,
uh- this idea of something being disjoint or independent,
is no longer true, right?
Like, for example, when node u would collect messages,
it would collect message from i and k. But really,
these messages are no longer independent because they
both depend on the message they got from j.
So in this sense, it comes- in some sense,
j is talking to u twice,
once through i and once through k. So this creates problems,
uh, uh, in terms of, uh,
theory and in terms of convergence.
Um, but what people tend to do in practice,
and not what works really well in practice,
is that you still run this belief propagation,
even though the graph has cycles, right?
And here what tried to show you is that when- once you are in a cycle, kind of,
the information will- uh,
will- will amplify, um,
artificially because it gets on a cycle.
And this is similar,
if you think about it to- when we talked about PageRank,
and we talked about spider traps, right,
that- where the random walker kind of gets- gets infinitely lost in this- uh,
in this spider trap.
It starts cycling.
And- and the problem with cycles or with loops is that
these messages start cycling, um, again, as well.
So the problem, um,
in this case, if the graph has cycles,
is that the beliefs may not converge.
Um, message is based on initial belief of i and not on separate,
kind of, independent evidence coming from nodes of i.
So the initial belief about i,
uh, which could be incorrect,
is reinforced, uh, let's say,
uh, through the cycle in this case.
Uh, however, as I said, in practice, uh,
loopy belief propagation is still very good heuristic, uh,
for complex graphs because, uh,
complex real world networks tend to be more like trees,
and they tend to have a relatively small number of cycles.
So the cycles, in reality,
are not such a big problem,
as they might be in this kind of,
wore ca- worse-case scenarios.
Um, and to give you an example, right, imagine,
we are doing belief propagation and we have two states.
We have a state, or,
a true or a false.
And now, you know, this node here sends, uh,
a message to the following node and says,
"You know, I think you are true,
with, you know- s- on a- with my belief about you
being true is 2 and my belief about you being false is 1."
So now this node will take this and s- and pass it on, and this is now,
kind of, going to be,
let's say, updated or,
uh, passed on in a- in a cycle.
But when it comes back to this node,
this node is now going to collect messages from both- uh,
from both of incoming, uh,
messages, this message and that message.
So now it will say, "Oh,
my belief that I'm- I am in- uh,
I am true is actually 4.
And my belief that I'm- I'm false is,
let say, only 1, or,
uh, let's say only 2.
And what this means is that now in this cycle,
this is going, kind of,
to an- uh, to amplify.
Um, and the cycle is going to amplify our belief that the state is actually, uh, true.
So this means that messages loop around and around and are more- more and more
convinced that these variables actually have state true and not state false.
And, uh, belief propagation, kind of incorrectly,
will treat these messages as separate evidence,
uh, that the variable T is true.
Um, and the issue is that these messages
are no longer independent because there is a- there is a cycle,
uh, on the graph.
Um, and this can cause- uh,
this can cause problems.
As I said, in practice,
real graphs, uh, tend to look more like trees.
So they don't- uh,
the cycles are not, uh, a problem,
uh, in- uh, in practice, right?
This is, as I said, an extreme example.
Often, in practice, the cycles- the influence of cycles is weak.
Our cycles are long,
or, uh, include, uh,
at least one weak, uh, correlation,
so that the message strength, uh, gets broken.
So, um, what are some advantages of belief propagation?
Advantages are- ea- that it's easy to- to code up,
and it's easy to paralleli- parallelize.
It is, uh, general.
It means that we can apply any graph model with any form of potential.
I showed you this label-label potential matrix,
but you can also, uh,
think of more complex, higher order potentials.
Um, so this is nice because label propagation or belief propagation does not, uh,
consider only homophily anymore,
but can learn more complex patterns,
where labels change, based on the labels of the neighbors, right?
So far, in- in previous methods, we only said,
"My label is- uh,
depends on the label of my neighbors.
So if- whatever my neighbor preference is,
my- why a- whatever my label- my neighbor's label is,
this is also my label."
In belief propagation, the labels can flip because we have this notion of,
uh, label-label, uh, affinity matrix.
Um, the challenge in belief propagation is
that convergence is not guaranteed so we generally don't know when to stop,
um, especially if there are many, uh, closed loops.
So the trick here would be to run a belief propagation for a short,
uh, number of steps.
Um, and of course, these potential functions,
this label-label, uh, potential, uh,
matrix, uh, this needs to be- um,
it requires training, uh,
data analysis to be able to, uh, estimate it.
So to summarize, uh,
we learned how to leverage correlations in graphs to make predictions of nodes.
We talked about three techniques.
Relational classification, where basically we say,
my label is a sum of the labels from my neighbors,
which basically means my label is, kind of,
the label of my neighbors.
Um, this uses the network structure but doesn't use feature information.
Then we talked about iterative classification that use both node feature information,
as well as the summary of the labels captured in the vector z around a given node.
So this approach use both the feature information about the nodes, as well as,
labels of the neighbors, but still,
kind of, would depend on homophily-type principle.
And then we talked about loopy belief propagation.
That- that, um, included this label- uh,
label-label potential matrix, uh, and,
uh, thought about this as collecting messages,
transforming messages, and sending a message to the upstream neighbor, as well.
This process is exact and, uh,
well-defined on, uh, chain graphs and on trees.
But on graphs with cycles,
um, it creates, uh, problems.
However, as I said in practice,
cycles tend to be, uh,
few or tend to have weak connections,
so that in practice, cycles don't, uh,
cause, uh, too much problem,
and loopy belief propagation is
a very strong allegory or a very strong approach for semi-supervised,
uh, labeling of nodes, uh, in the graph.
So, um, with this, uh,
we have finished the lecture for today.