So now we are shifting gears and we are talking about theory of graph neural networks.
And we are in particular going to ask ourselves how expressive are graph neural networks,
what are graph neural networks able to learn,
and what are they not uh, able to learn?
This is really the question for uh,
this part of the lecture.
So we talk about deep uh,
neural networks applied to graphs,
where through several um,
layers of non-linear propagation,
we are trying to come up with the embeddings of nodes, embeddings of networks.
So we can do various kinds of machine learning prediction tasks.
The key idea that graph neural networks have is this idea of aggregating
local neighborhoods around a given node
of interest to generate the embedding for that node.
Right, So this is kind of the classical picture we've been showing
several times in our discussions so far.
Right, so the intuition is that nodes
aggregate information from their neighbors using neural networks.
And so far we discussed what kind of design choices you have when deciding how to,
how to operationalize or how to design
this message transformation and aggregation operations.
So today, right now we are going to talk about the theory of graph neural networks.
And in particular, we are going to ask how powerful are graph neural networks.
How expressive are they?
What can they learn and what can they not learn?
This is especially important because there are many different and GNN models.
Right, we talked about the GCN, graph convolution neural network.
We talked about that, the graph attention network.
We talked about the GraphSAGE network and we talked about
the entire design space of these types of models.
So the question is, what is their expressive power?
Which basically means what is their ability to distinguish different nodes,
different graph structures, and how
expressive are they in learning different types of patterns?
And then what would be super cool today is that we will be actually able
to design the maximally expressive GNN models.
So in some sense, we'll be able to design
the most powerful graph neural network there is which is super cool.
So that's the- that's the plan.
So background is, we have many graph neural network models,
they all have different,
they all differ in terms of how they propagate,
aggregate, and transform messages.
And the question is,
can we understand what is their expressive power and how these different design choices
actually lead to different type of models.
So for example, in a graph,
convolutional neural networks, GCN.
It's using what is called mean pooling.
Right, so basically when,
when we aggregate information from neighbors,
we use  element-wise mean pooling.
And then we use a linear transformation plus a ReLU, nonlinearity.
That's for example, what a GCN is.
For example, GraphSAGE uses a multi-layer perceptron plus element-wise,
let say maximum pooling which is- which is different.
And the question is, what is better?
Is max better than, than average?
Or what's the difference between the two in terms of,
let's say, theoretical properties and expressive power?
Um, there is an important note I wanna- I wanna make so that we don't get confused later.
In graph neural networks,
we have two aspects.
We have the aspect of node features,
node properties, and we have the aspect of a graph structure.
And for the purpose of this lecture,
I'm going to use colors of nodes to represent their feature vectors.
What I mean by this, if two nodes are of the same color,
then they have the same feature vector,
they have the same feature representation.
Right? So for example,
in this graph here,
numbers represent node IDs.
So I can say I'm talking about node 1,
I'm talking about node 2,
but the features these nodes have are all the same.
So there is no featured information that would
allow me to distinguish nodes from one another, right?
So we don't, the color means what is the feature vector of the node.
So now for example, the question would be,
how well can a GNN distinguish different graphical structures, right?
Because if every node has
its own unique feature vector then it's easy to distinguish the nodes.
You just look at their feature vectors.
But if all the feature vectors are the same, like in this case,
all nodes are yellow,
then the question is, can you still distinguish the nodes?
Can you learn that node 5 is different than node 4,
for example, in this case.
So and in graph neural networks,
we are particularly interested in this notion of local neighborhood structures.
Where basically we are interested in quantifying
the local network neighborhood around each node in the graph.
So for example here,
let's say I'm interested in nodes 1 and 5 and I
say could I learn to distinguish nodes 1 and 5?
Distinguishing them would be quite easy
because they have different neighborhood structures,
even if you look at the number of edges that is adjacent to each of them,
you know, node 1 has degree 2 and node 5 has degree 3.
So it'll be very easy to distinguish them.
If you can capture the degree of the node in a graph neural network,
then you can differentiate between nodes 1 and 5.
Let's look now at the second example.
How about nodes 1 and 4?
Are they distinguishable?
Right? If you look at it from the single layer,
single hop neighborhood, then node 1 has degree 2.
And node 4 has degree 2.
So if I only am able to capture the degree of the node itself,
I cannot differentiate between 1 and 2, right?
They have the same feature vector and they have the same degree.
However, 1 and 2 are still different because if I look at,
let's say the second-degree neighborhood.
Right? You could say, ah-ha,  node 1 has two neighbors.
One has degree 2 and 1 has degree 3.
While node 4 also has two neighbors,
but one has degree 1 and the other one has degree 3.
So if I'm able to capture the degree of the node
4 of the node itself plus the degrees of the neighbors,
then 1 and 4 are distinguishable because their neighbors have different degrees.
Right? So now you see how maybe immediately two- two nodes look the same.
But if you go deeper into the network here,
I go to the neighbors,
then the two nodes become distinguishable.
And that is very interesting.
So now let's continue this investigation and look at another pair of nodes.
Let's look at nodes 1 and 2.
What is interesting is that 1 and 2- actually, um,
in this graph neural,
in this network are indistinguishable from one another.
Because they are kind of symmetric in the graph, right?
They both have degree 2, um, uh,
their neighbor, um, they both have two neighbors.
Uh, one of degree- of degree 2 and one of degree 3.
Um, if you go to the second hop neighborhood,
it's, uh, the node number 4,
uh, that has degree 2.
So basically their- their, uh,
network neighborhood is identical
regardless how deep or how far do we explore the network.
Because in- in both cases,
you know, they have,
each- each of them has one node of degree 2,
one node of degree 3.
At two-hop neighborhood, um,
they both have one neighbor of degree 2.
Three hops away they both have one neighbor of degree 1.
So you cannot distinguish one and two unless somebody gives you
some feature information that would allow you to s- tell 1 from 2.
But based on the graph structure,
you cannot distinguish them because they're kind of symmetric.
Their- their positions are isomorphic,
uh, in the graph, right?
So that's an exa- an- an example,
kind of trying to build up intuition how this,
uh, will all, uh, work out.
So the key question we wanna,
uh, look at is,
can a GNN node embedding distinguish different local neighborhood structures, right?
Local meaning neighborhoods structures around a given node.
And if it can, the question is when and if not,
what are the failure cases of graph neural networks?
So- so what we'll do next is we need to understand
how a GNN captures local neighborhood structures.
And we are going to understand this through this key concept of a computational graph.
So let me now talk about, uh,
what is a computational graph, right?
The way you think of this is that each, uh,
layer, uh, a GNN aggregates,
uh, neighborho- neighboring embeddings.
So in a GNN, uh,
we generate an embedding through
a computational graph defined on the node neighborhood structure.
So for example, if I say here is node 1,
the computational graph- let's say if I do
a two-layer GNN for node 1 is created here, right?
Node 1 aggregates information from nodes 2 and 5. Here they are.
Node 5- node 5 aggregates information from its neighbors,
5 has neighbors 1, 2, and 4.
And node 2 here,
aggregates information from its neighbors,
node 1 and node 5.
So this is what we call a computation graph.
It simply shows us how the messages gets- get aggregated from level,
uh, level 0 to level 1 to level 2.
And this is now the computation graph that describes
the two-layer graph neural network for,
uh, node, uh, node ID, uh, 1.
That's the idea here.
And what is interesting is that now if I take, for example, uh,
node I- node, uh,
number 2 and I create a computation graph for itself,
uh, here it is, right?
Two aggregates from nodes 1 and 5, uh,
5 again aggregates from,
uh, uh, 1, 2 and 4.
And, uh, node number 1 aggregates from 2 and 5, right?
What you notice is that computational graphs for nodes 1 and 2 are actually identical.
They both have, uh,
two children at- uh,
at level 1 and they have,
you know, one- one has 2,
and one has fi- uh,
one has 3, uh,
at level, uh, 0.
So what this means is,
because a GNN is only doing message-passing information,
uh, without any node IDs,
it only uses node feature vectors.
This means that, you know,
if you look at these propagation,
uh, trees, these computation graphs,
right now they are different because you say, oh,
obviously here is node number 1 and here is node number 2.
So obviously these trees are different.
But if you only look at the colors- if you only look at the node feature information,
then this is how these trees look like.
They look identical and there is no way to tell nodes apart from each other.
So in all cases,
all the graph neural network can do,
can aggregate, you know,
the information from these nodes.
They all have yellow color and here it can aggregate yellow color.
So all it can do it is to say,
oh, I have three yellow children.
This guy can say I have two yellow children.
And then this- here we can say, uh-huh you know,
I have two children an- and one of them has two and
the other one has three, uh, further children.
And that's how we can describe this computation graph.
But the point is that for two different nodes,
1 and 2, the computation graphs are the same.
So without any feature information,
without any node attribute information, uh,
these two- these two nodes,
these two computation graphs are the same.
So these two nodes will be embedded into the same point in the embedding space.
And what this means is that they will overlap so the graph neural network won't be able,
uh, to distinguish them,
uh, and won't be able to classify node 1 into a different class than node 2,
because their embeddings will be exactly the same.
They will overlap because the- the computation graphs are the same,
and there is no distinguishable, uh,
node feature information because that's kind of our assumption, uh, going in.
So if there is an important slide of this lecture,
this is the most important slide,
is that basically we- GNNs capture
the local neighborhood structure through the computation graph.
And if computation graph of two nodes are the same,
then the two nodes will be embedded exactly into the same point in the embedding space,
which means that we are not able to classify one into one class,
and the other one into the other because they are- they are identical,
they are overlapping, so we cannot distinguish, uh, between them.
So this means just kind of to summarize,
is that in this simple example,
a GNN will generate the same embedding for nodes 1 and 2 because of two facts.
First is that because the computational graphs are the same, they are identical.
And the second important part is that
node feature information in this case is identical, right?
All- all nodes the assumption of this lecture
is that node features are not useful in this case,
so all nodes have the same feature.
They are all yellow, right?
And because GNN does not care about node IDs,
it cares about the attributes,
features of the nodes and aggregates them.
This means that this GNN is not able to distinguish nodes 1 and 2.
So 1 and 2 will always have
exactly the same embedding so they will always be put into the same class,
or they will be assigned,
uh, the same label.
Which, uh, which is interesting and, uh,
which now seems, uh,
quite- uh, quite daunting,
a bit disappointing, right?
That we so quickly found a corner case,
or a- or a failure case for graph neural networks
where they basically cannot, uh, distinguish nodes.
So the important point that I wanted to make here is that in general,
different local neighborhoods define different computation graphs, right?
So, uh, here are computation graphs,
uh, for different nodes.
These are computation graphs for nodes 1 and 2, uh,
computation graphs for nodes 3 and 4,
as well as computation graph,
uh, for node 5.
So now we already know that we won't be able to
distinguish 1 and 2 because they have the same computation graphs.
That's- that's some- that's fact of life.
There's not much we can do.
But the question still remains,
how about 3 and 4?
Or 3 and 5?
Will our graph neural network be able to distinguish these nodes,
because obviously they have different computational graphs.
So perhaps the graph neural network is able to remember,
or capture the structure of the computation graph,
which means that nodes 3 and 4 will get a different embedding,
because their computation graphs are different, right?
That's the- in some sense,
the big question, right?
So basically what I'm- what is the point is?
The point is that computational graphs are identical to
the rooted subtree structures around each node, right?
So we can think of this rooted subtree as it defines
the topological structure of the neighborhood around, uh,
each node and two nodes will be able to distinguish
them in the best case if they have different rooted subtree structures,
if they have different computation graphs.
Of course, maybe our graph neural network is so imperfect that is
not even able to distinguish nodes that have different computation graphs,
meaning that the structure of these rooted trees is different.
And what we are going to look at next is under what cases,
you know, can 2 and 3 be distinguished,
and in what cases 2 and 3 will simply be lumped
together into the same, uh, embedding. So-
Kind of to continue on this, right?
GNN's node embeddings capture rooted subtree structures.
They basically cap- they wanna capture the structure of the graphing- of the,
uh, computational graph of the network neighborhood around a given node.
And the most possible expressive graph neural network will map different, uh,
rooted subtrees into different node embeddings,
uh, here, for example,
represented by different, uh, colors, right?
So one and two,
because they have exactly identical computation graphs and exactly identical features,
will be mapped to the same point.
There is nothing we can do about
that with the current definition of graph neural networks.
Um, but for example,
nodes 3, 4 and 5,
they don't have identical computation graph structures,
so they should be mapped into different,
uh, points in the embedding space, right?
So the most expressive graph neural network will basically be
able to learn or capture what is the structure of the computation graph,
and based on the structure of the computation graph assign
a different embedding for each computation graph.
Um, that's the main, uh,
uh, premise, uh, that,
uh, we are making here.
So we wanna ensure that if two nodes have different computation graphs,
then they are mapped to different points in the embedding space.
And the question is,
can graph neural networks, uh, do that?
There is an important concept for mathematics that will allow us, uh,
to make further progress in understanding whether
a graph neural network can take two different computation graphs,
two different, um, rooted subtrees
and map them into different points in the embedding space.
And that is this notion, uh,
or definition of what an injective function is.
And a function that maps from the- the- from the domain X,
uh, to domain Y is called injective.
If it maps different elements into the different outputs.
So what this basically means that f retains the information of the input, right?
It means that whatever- whatever inputs you get,
you'll always map them into distinct,
um, distinct points, sort of distinct outputs.
Meaning, for example, it's not that 2 and 3 would
collide and you would give the same output A.
So every input maps to a different output.
That's a definition of an injective function.
And we will- this is a very important concept because we will use it,
uh, for the lo- rest- rest of the lecture, uh, quite heavily.
So we wanna know how expressive is a graph neural network.
And most expressive graph neural network should map these subtrees,
these, uh, computation graphs to node embeddings injectively,
meaning that for every different subtree,
we should map it into a different point in the embedding space,
um, and if this mapping is not injective,
meaning that two different inputs,
two different subtrees get mapped to the same point,
then, um, this is not an
injective mapping and that is, uh, the issue.
So we wanna have and show that graphed- what we wanna develop
a graph neural network that has this injective mapping where
different subtrees get mapped into different points,
uh, in the embedding space.
So the key observation, uh,
that will allow us to make progress is that trees of
the same depth can be recursively characterized,
uh, from the leaf nodes,
uh, to the root nodes.
So what I mean by this is if we are able to distinguish one level of the tree,
then we can recursively,
uh, take these, uh,
levels and aggregate them together into a unique description of the tree.
So what I mean by this is, for example, um,
the way you can characterize the tree is simply by the number of
children each node has, all right?
So for example, here you could say, aha,
at the lower level one node has three neighbors,
three children, and the other node has two children.
Um, and then you can say a-ha and then the node, uh, uh,
the- the- the- the root has,
uh, has, uh, um, has,
uh, two children as well.
So I can characterize this by saying, aha, um,
you know, uh, we have,
uh, two neighbors at, uh,
level 0, we have three neighbors at level 0, and, uh,
we have, uh, two neighbors,
uh, at level, uh, at level 1.
While for example, for this particular computation graph,
I have one child here, uh,
three- three children here,
and then, again, two children here.
So this description is different than their description.
So it means I'm able to separate out, um,
or to distinguish between these two- these two different, uh, uh trees.
Uh, the important thing is that trees can be decomposed level by level,
so if I'm able to capture the structure of a single level of the tree,
perhaps even just this level,
then I can recursively do this,
uh, level by level.
So what I mean is, um,
we only need to focus on how do we characterize one level of this, uh,
computation graph or this, uh,
rooted subtree around a given node, uh, of interest.
So, um, let's continue thinking and setting up the problem.
So if each step of GNN, uh,
aggregation process can fully retain the neighborhood information,
meaning how many children,
uh, neighbors does a given node have?
Then, uh, the generated node embeddings can distinguish different,
uh, subtree structures, right?
If I can say, um,
at level, uh, 1, uh,
in- in one tree I have two- two children in the other one I have three.
Um, and if I can kind of capture
this information and propagate it all the way up to the node 1.
And in this other tree I can kind of capture the information that one,
uh, one node has one child and the other node has, uh, three children.
And again, I'm able to retain this information, uh,
all the way to the top layer,
then obviously the- the number of children, um, is different.
So these two, uh, these two trees, uh,
we are able to, uh, distinguish them, right?
So the point is, in some sense,
are we able to aggregate information from the children and somehow
store it so that when we pass it on to our parent in the tree,
this information, uh, gets retained?
As in this case, the information that
two and three got retained all the way up to the root of the tree.
That's, uh, the question, uh, we wanna answer.
So in other words,
what we wanna do is we wanna say that
the most expressive graph neural network would use
an injective neighborhood aggregation for each step,
for each layer of the or for each level of the computation graph.
So this means that it will map
different neighborhoods into different, um, embeddings, right?
So we want to be able to capture the number of children at level 1,
oh sorry, at level 0, at level 1,
and then aggregate this- kind of retain this information as we are pushing it
up the tree so that the tree knows how many children each of its,
um, each of its, uh,
uh, inner nodes, uh, have.
So that's essentially the idea.
So the summary so far is the following.
To generate a node embedding,
GNN uses a computational graph that
corresponds to a rooted subtree structure around each node.
So if I have a node,
I have this notion of a computational graph that is simply a-
a rooted subtree structure that describes
the local neighborhood structure around this node.
And then different rooted subtrees,
different computation graphs will be distinguishable
if we are using injective neighborhood aggregation,
meaning we are able to distinguish different subtrees.
And GNNs can- as we are going to see, um,
GNNs can fully distinguish different subtree structures
if at every level its neighborhood aggregation,
meaning it's aggregation for the children, is injective,
which means that no information, uh, gets lost.
So then we can fully characterize, uh,
the computation graph and distinguish one computation graph, uh, from the other.