if i have a vector sitting here in 2d
space we have a standard way to describe
it with coordinates in this case the
vector has coordinates 3 2 which means
going from its tail to its tip involves
moving 3 units to the right and 2 units
up
now the more linear algebra-oriented way
to describe coordinates is to think of
each of these numbers as a scalar a
thing that stretches or squishes vectors
you think of that first coordinate as
scaling i-hat the vector with length 1
pointing to the right
while the second coordinate scales j hat
the vector with length one pointing
straight up
the tip to tail sum of those two scaled
vectors is what the coordinates are
meant to describe
you can think of these two special
vectors as encapsulating all of the
implicit assumptions of our coordinate
system
the fact that the first number indicates
rightward motion that the second one
indicates upward motion exactly how far
a unit of distance is all of that is
tied up in the choice of i-hat and j-hat
as the vectors which are scalar
coordinates are meant to actually scale
any way to translate between vectors and
sets of numbers is called a coordinate
system and the two special vectors i-hat
and j hat are called the basis vectors
of our standard coordinate system
what i'd like to talk about here is the
idea of using a different set of basis
vectors
for example let's say you have a friend
jennifer who uses a different set of
basis vectors which i'll call b1 and b2
her first basis vector b1 points up and
to the right a little bit and her second
vector b2 points left and up
now take another look at that vector
that i showed earlier the one that you
and i would describe using the
coordinates 3 2 using our basis vectors
i-hat and j-hat
jennifer would actually describe this
vector with the coordinates five-thirds
and one-third
what this means is that the particular
way to get to that vector using her two
basis vectors is to scale b1 by five
thirds
scale b2 by one-third then add them both
together
in a little bit i'll show you how you
could have figured out those two numbers
five thirds and one-third
in general whenever jennifer uses
coordinates to describe a vector she
thinks of her first coordinate as
scaling b1 the second coordinate is
scaling b2 and she adds the results
what she gets will typically be
completely different from the vector
that you and i would think of as having
those coordinates
to be a little more precise about the
setup here her first basis vector b1 is
something that we would describe with
the coordinates 2 1 and her second basis
vector b2 is something that we would
describe as negative 1 1. but it's
important to realize from her
perspective in her system those vectors
have coordinates 1 0 and 0 1
they are what define the meaning of the
coordinates 1 0 and 0 1 in her world
so in effect we're speaking different
languages
we're all looking at the same vectors in
space but jennifer uses different words
and numbers to describe them
let me say a quick word about how i'm
representing things here when i animate
2d space i typically use this square
grid but that grid is just a construct a
way to visualize our coordinate system
and so it depends on our choice of basis
space itself has no intrinsic grid
jennifer might draw her own grid which
would be an equally made-up construct
meant as nothing more than a visual tool
to help follow the meaning of her
coordinates
her origin though would actually line up
with ours since everybody agrees on what
the coordinates 0 0 should mean
it's the thing that you get when you
scale any vector by zero
but the direction of her axes and the
spacing of her grid lines will be
different depending on her choice of
basis vectors
so after all this is set up a pretty
natural question to ask is how we
translate between coordinate systems
if for example jennifer describes a
vector with coordinates negative 1 2
what would that be in our coordinate
system how do you translate from her
language to hours
well what her coordinates are saying is
that this vector is negative 1 times b 1
plus 2 times b 2.
and from our perspective b1 has
coordinates 2 1
and b2 has coordinates negative 1 1.
so we can actually compute negative 1
times b1 plus 2 times b2 as they're
represented in our coordinate system and
working this out you get a vector with
coordinates negative 4 1.
so that's how we would describe the
vector that she thinks of as negative 1
2.
this process here of scaling each of her
basis vectors by the corresponding
coordinates of some vector then adding
them together might feel somewhat
familiar
it's matrix vector multiplication with a
matrix whose columns represent
jennifer's basis vectors in our language
in fact once you understand matrix
vector multiplication as applying a
certain linear transformation say by
watching what i view to be the most
important video in this series chapter 3
there's a pretty intuitive way to think
about what's going on here
a matrix whose columns represent
jennifer's basis vectors can be thought
of as a transformation that moves our
basis vectors i-hat and j-hat the things
we think of when we say 1 0 and 0-1 to
jennifer's basis vectors the things she
thinks of when she says 1 0 and 0 1.
to show how this works let's walk
through what it would mean to take the
vector that we think of as having
coordinates negative 1 2 and applying
that transformation
before the linear transformation we're
thinking of this vector as a certain
linear combination of our basis vectors
negative 1 times i hat plus 2 times j
hat
and the key feature of a linear
transformation is that the resulting
vector will be that same linear
combination but of the new basis vectors
negative one times the place where i hat
lands plus two times the place where j
hat lands
so what this matrix does is transform
our misconception of what jennifer means
into the actual vector that she's
referring to
i remember that when i was first
learning this it always felt kind of
backwards to me geometrically this
matrix transforms our grid into
jennifer's grid but numerically it's
translating a vector described in her
language to our language
what made it finally click for me was
thinking about how it takes our
misconception of what jennifer means the
vector we get using the same coordinates
but in our system then it transforms it
into the vector that she really meant
what about going the other way around
in the example i used earlier this video
when i had the vector with coordinates 3
2 in our system how did i compute that
it would have coordinates 5 3 and 1 3 in
jennifer's system
you start with that change of basis
matrix that translates jennifer's
language into hours then you take its
inverse
remember the inverse of a transformation
is a new transformation that corresponds
to playing that first one backwards in
practice especially when you're working
in more than two dimensions you'd use a
computer to compute the matrix that
actually represents this inverse
in this case the inverse of the change
of basis matrix that has jennifer's
basis as its columns ends up working out
to have columns one-third negative
one-third and one-third two-thirds
so for example to see what the vector 3
2 looks like in jennifer's system we
multiply this inverse change of basis
matrix by the vector 3 2 which works out
to be 5 3 1 3.
so that in a nutshell is how to
translate the description of individual
vectors back and forth between
coordinate systems
the matrix whose columns represent
jennifer's basis vectors but written in
our coordinates
translates vectors from her language
into our language
and the inverse matrix does the opposite
but vectors aren't the only thing that
we describe using coordinates
for this next part it's important that
you're all comfortable representing
transformations with matrices and that
you know how matrix multiplication
corresponds to composing successive
transformations
definitely pause and take a look at
chapters 3 and 4 if any of that feels
uneasy
consider some linear transformation like
a 90 degree counterclockwise rotation
when you and i represent this with a
matrix we follow where the basis vectors
i-hat and j-hat each go
i-hat ends up at the spot with
coordinates 0 1 and j-hat ends up at the
spot with coordinates negative 1 0
so those coordinates become the columns
of our matrix but this representation is
heavily tied up in our choice of basis
vectors from the fact that we're
following i-hat and j-hat in the first
place to the fact that we're recording
their landing spots in our own
coordinate system
how would jennifer describe this same 90
degree rotation of space
you might be tempted to just translate
the columns of our rotation matrix into
jennifer's language but that's not quite
right those columns represent where our
basis vectors i-hat and j-hat go but the
matrix that jennifer wants should
represent where her basis vectors land
and it needs to describe those landing
spots in a her language
here's a common way to think of how this
is done
start with any vector written in
jennifer's language
rather than trying to follow what
happens to it in terms of her language
first we're going to translate it into
our language using the change of basis
matrix the one whose columns represent
her basis vectors in our language this
gives us the same vector but now written
in our language
then apply the transformation matrix to
what you get by multiplying it on the
left
this tells us where that vector lands
but still in our language
so as a last step apply the inverse
change of basis matrix multiplied on the
left as usual to get the transformed
vector but now in jennifer's language
since we could do this with any vector
written in her language first applying
the change of basis then the
transformation then the inverse change
of basis
that composition of three matrices
gives us the transformation matrix in
jennifer's language
it takes in a vector of her language and
spits out the transformed version of
that vector in her language
for this specific example when
jennifer's basis vectors look like 2 1
and negative 1 1 in our language and
when the transformation is a 90 degree
rotation
the product of these three matrices if
you work through it has columns 1 3 5 3
and negative two-thirds negative
one-third
so if jennifer multiplies that matrix by
the coordinates of a vector in her
system
it will return the 90-degree rotated
version of that vector expressed in her
coordinate system
in general whenever you see an
expression like a inverse times m times
a it suggests a mathematical sort of
empathy that middle matrix represents a
transformation of some kind as you see
it and the outer two matrices represent
the empathy the shift in perspective
and the full matrix product represents
that same transformation but as someone
else sees it
for those of you wondering why we care
about alternate coordinate systems the
next video on eigenvectors and
eigenvalues will give a really important
example of this see you then
you