do
eigenvectors and eigenvalues is one of
those topics that a lot of students find
particularly unintuitive
questions like why are we doing this and
what does this actually mean are too
often left just floating away in an
unanswered sea of computations
and as i've put out the videos of this
series a lot of you have commented about
looking forward to visualizing this
topic in particular i suspect that the
reason for this is not so much that
eigen things are particularly
complicated or poorly explained in fact
it's comparatively straightforward and i
think most books do a fine job
explaining it the issue is that it only
really makes sense if you have a solid
visual understanding for many of the
topics that precede it
most important here is that you know how
to think about matrices as linear
transformations but you also need to be
comfortable with things like
determinants linear systems of equations
and change of basis
confusion about eigenstuffs usually has
more to do with the shaky foundation in
one of these topics than it does with
eigenvectors and eigenvalues themselves
to start consider some linear
transformation in two dimensions like
the one shown here it moves the basis
vector i hat to the coordinates 3 0 and
j hat to 1 2
so it's represented with a matrix whose
columns are 3 0 and 1 2.
focus in on what it does to one
particular vector and think about the
span of that vector the line passing
through its origin and its tip
most vectors are going to get knocked
off their span during the transformation
i mean it would seem pretty coincidental
if the place where the vector landed
also happened to be somewhere on that
line
but some special vectors do remain on
their own span
meaning the effect that the matrix has
on such a vector is just to stretch it
or squish it like a scalar
for this specific example the basis
vector i-hat is one such special vector
the span of i-hat is the x-axis and from
the first column of the matrix we can
see that i-hat moves over to 3 times
itself still on that x-axis
what's more because of the way linear
transformations work any other vector on
the x-axis is also just stretched by a
factor of 3 and hence remains on its own
span
a slightly sneakier vector that remains
on its own span during this
transformation is negative 1 1.
it ends up getting stretched by a factor
of 2.
and again linearity is going to imply
that any other vector on the diagonal
line spanned by this guy is just going
to get stretched out by a factor of 2.
and for this transformation those are
all the vectors with this special
property of staying on their span those
on the x-axis getting stretched out by a
factor of 3 and those on this diagonal
line getting stretched by a factor of 2.
any other vector is going to get rotated
somewhat during the transformation
knocked off the line that it spans
as you might have guessed by now these
special vectors are called the
eigenvectors of the transformation and
each eigenvector has associated with it
what's called an eigenvalue which is
just the factor by which it's stretched
or squished during the transformation
of course there's nothing special about
stretching versus squishing or the fact
that these eigenvalues happen to be
positive in another example you could
have an eigenvector with eigenvalue
negative one-half meaning that the
vector gets flipped and squished by a
factor of one-half
but the important part here is that it
stays on the line that it spans out
without getting rotated off of it
for a glimpse of why this might be a
useful thing to think about consider
some 3-dimensional rotation
if you can find an eigenvector for that
rotation a vector that remains on its
own span
what you have found is the axis of
rotation
and it's much easier to think about a 3d
rotation in terms of some axis of
rotation and an angle by which it's
rotating rather than thinking about the
full 3x3 matrix associated with that
transformation
in this case by the way the
corresponding eigenvalue would have to
be 1 since rotations never stretch or
squish anything so the length of the
vector would remain the same
[Music]
this pattern shows up a lot in linear
algebra with any linear transformation
described by a matrix you could
understand what it's doing by reading
off the columns of this matrix as the
landing spots for basis vectors but
often a better way to get at the heart
of what the linear transformation
actually does
less dependent on your particular
coordinate system is to find the
eigenvectors and eigenvalues
i won't cover the full details on
methods for computing eigenvectors and
eigenvalues here but i'll try to give an
overview of the computational ideas that
are most important for a conceptual
understanding
symbolically here's what the idea of an
eigenvector looks like
a is the matrix representing some
transformation with v as the eigenvector
and lambda is a number namely the
corresponding eigenvalue
what this expression is saying is that
the matrix vector product a times v
gives the same result as just scaling
the eigenvector v by some value lambda
so finding the eigenvectors and their
eigenvalues of a matrix a comes down to
finding the values of v and lambda that
make this expression true
it's a little awkward to work with at
first because that left hand side
represents matrix vector multiplication
but the right hand side here is scalar
vector multiplication so let's start by
rewriting that right hand side as some
kind of matrix vector multiplication
using a matrix which has the effect of
scaling any vector by a factor of lambda
the columns of such a matrix will
represent what happens to each basis
vector and each basis vector is simply
multiplied by lambda so this matrix will
have the number lambda down the diagonal
with zeros everywhere else
the common way to write this guy is to
factor that lambda out and write it as
lambda times i where i is the identity
matrix with ones down the diagonal
with both sides looking like matrix
vector multiplication we can subtract
off that right hand side and factor out
the v
so what we now have is a new matrix a
minus lambda times the identity and
we're looking for a vector v such that
this new matrix
times v
gives the zero vector
now this will always be true if v itself
is the zero vector but that's boring
what we want is a non-zero eigenvector
and if you watch chapter five and six
you'll know that the only way it's
possible for the product of a matrix
with a non-zero vector to become zero
is if the transformation associated with
that matrix squishes space into a lower
dimension
and that squishification corresponds to
a zero determinant for the matrix
to be concrete let's say your matrix a
has columns 2 1 and 2 3 and think about
subtracting off a variable amount lambda
from each diagonal entry
now imagine tweaking lambda turning a
knob to change its value
as that value of lambda changes the
matrix itself changes and so the
determinant of the matrix changes the
goal here is to find a value of lambda
that will make this determinant zero
meaning the tweaked transformation
squishes space into a lower dimension
in this case the sweet spot comes when
lambda equals one of course if we had
chosen some other matrix the eigenvalue
might not necessarily be 1 the sweet
spot might be hit at some other value of
lambda
so this is kind of a lot but let's
unravel what this is saying when lambda
equals 1 the matrix a minus lambda times
the identity squishes space onto a line
that means there's a non-zero vector v
such that a minus lambda times the
identity times v
equals the zero vector
and remember the reason we care about
that is because it means a times v
equals lambda times v
which you can read off as saying that
the vector v is an eigenvector of a
staying on its own span during the
transformation a
in this example the corresponding
eigenvalue is 1 so v would actually just
stay fixed in place
pause and ponder if you need to make
sure that that line of reasoning feels
good
this is the kind of thing i mentioned in
the introduction if you didn't have a
solid grasp of determinants and why they
relate to linear systems of equations
having non-zero solutions an expression
like this would feel completely out of
the blue
to see this in action let's revisit the
example from the start with a matrix
whose columns are 3 0 and 1 2.
to find if a value lambda is an
eigenvalue subtract it from the
diagonals of this matrix and compute the
determinant
doing this we get a certain quadratic
polynomial in lambda 3 minus lambda
times 2 minus lambda
since lambda can only be an eigenvalue
if this determinant happens to be 0 you
can conclude that the only possible
eigenvalues are lambda equals 2 and
lambda equals 3.
to figure out what the eigenvectors are
that actually have one of these
eigenvalues say lambda equals 2
plug in that value of lambda to the
matrix
and then solve for which vectors this
diagonally altered matrix sends to zero
if you computed this the way you would
any other linear system you'd see that
the solutions are all the vectors on the
diagonal line spanned by negative 1 1.
this corresponds to the fact that the
unaltered matrix 3 0 1 2 has the effect
of stretching all those vectors by a
factor of 2.
now a 2d transformation doesn't have to
have eigenvectors for example consider a
rotation by 90 degrees this doesn't have
any eigenvectors since it rotates every
vector off of its own span
if you actually try computing the
eigenvalues of a rotation like this
notice what happens
its matrix has columns 0 1 and negative
1 0.
subtract off lambda from the diagonal
elements and look for when the
determinant is zero
in this case you get the polynomial
lambda squared plus one
the only roots of that polynomial are
the imaginary numbers i and negative i
the fact that there are no real number
solutions indicates that there are no
eigenvectors
another pretty interesting example worth
holding in the back of your mind is a
shear
this fixes i-hat in place and moves
j-hat 1 over so its matrix has columns 1
0 and 1 1.
all of the vectors on the x-axis are
eigenvectors with eigenvalue 1 since
they remain fixed in place
in fact these are the only eigenvectors
when you subtract off lambda from the
diagonals and compute the determinant
what you get is 1 minus lambda squared
and the only root of this expression is
lambda equals one
this lines up with what we see
geometrically that all of the
eigenvectors have eigenvalue one
keep in mind though it's also possible
to have just one eigenvalue but with
more than just a line full of
eigenvectors
a simple example is a matrix that scales
everything by two
the only eigenvalue is two but every
vector in the plane gets to be an
eigenvector with that eigenvalue
now is another good time to pause and
ponder some of this before i move on to
the last topic
i want to finish off here with the idea
of an eigen basis which relies heavily
on ideas from the last video
take a look at what happens if our basis
vectors just so happen to be
eigenvectors
for example maybe i-hat is scaled by
negative 1 and j-hat is scaled by 2.
writing their new coordinates as the
columns of a matrix notice that those
scalar multiples negative 1 and 2 which
are the eigenvalues of i-hat and j-hat
sit on the diagonal of our matrix and
every other entry is a zero
any time a matrix has zeros everywhere
other than the diagonal it's called
reasonably enough a diagonal matrix and
the way to interpret this is that all
the basis vectors are eigenvectors with
the diagonal entries of this matrix
being their eigenvalues
there are a lot of things that make
diagonal matrices much nicer to work
with
one big one is that it's easier to
compute what will happen if you multiply
this matrix by itself a whole bunch of
times
since all one of these matrices does is
scale each basis vector by some
eigenvalue applying that matrix many
times say 100 times is just going to
correspond to scaling each basis vector
by the 100th power of the corresponding
eigenvalue
in contrast try computing the hundredth
power of a non-diagonal matrix really
try it for a moment it's a nightmare
of course you'll rarely be so lucky as
to have your basis vectors also be
eigenvectors
but if your transformation has a lot of
eigenvectors like the one from the start
of this video enough so that you can
choose a set that spans the full space
then you could change your coordinate
system so that these eigenvectors are
your basis vectors
i talked about change of basis last
video but i'll go through a super quick
reminder here of how to express a
transformation currently written in our
coordinate system into a different
system
take the coordinates of the vectors that
you want to use as a new basis which in
this case means our two eigenvectors
that make those coordinates the columns
of a matrix known as the change of basis
matrix
when you sandwich the original
transformation putting the change of
basis matrix on its right and the
inverse of the change of basis matrix on
its left the result will be a matrix
representing that same transformation
but from the perspective of the new
basis vector's coordinate system
the whole point of doing this with
eigenvectors is that this new matrix is
guaranteed to be diagonal with its
corresponding eigenvalues down that
diagonal this is because it represents
working in a coordinate system where
what happens to the basis vectors is
that they get scaled during the
transformation
a set of basis vectors which are also
eigenvectors is called again reasonably
enough an eigen basis
so if for example you needed to compute
the 100th power of this matrix it would
be much easier to change to an eigen
basis compute the 100th power in that
system then convert back to our standard
system
you can't do this with all
transformations a shear for example
doesn't have enough eigenvectors to span
the full space
but if you can find an eigen basis it
makes matrix operations really lovely
for those of you willing to work through
a pretty neat puzzle to see what this
looks like in action and how it can be
used to produce some surprising results
i'll leave up a prompt here on the
screen it takes a bit of work but i
think you'll enjoy it
the next and final video of this series
is going to be on abstract vector spaces
see you then
[Music]
you