OK, hi everyone.
Welcome back, we're now
past the halfway point.
Week 6 of CS224N.
And so let me just give a couple
of quick announcements first.
So today is the day
that you have to have
done the mid-quarter survey by.
Hundreds of people have,
but if you haven't, this
is your last chance to get
the half-point for that.
Today is also the day that
final project proposals are due.
We really encourage you
to try and hand them
in on-time or nearly on-time.
That's really just to help you.
So we can more quickly
give you feedback
on final project proposals.
And in the background then,
there's also assignment 5.
You'll all have seen the message
that we're giving you one
extra day for that,
but we do certainly
encourage you to be hard at work
on assignment 5 at this point.
Hopefully it's a great,
exciting opportunity
to be learning all the latest
stuff about transformers.
And then today, delighted to
have our first invited speaker.
Let me just mention
that going along
within [INAUDIBLE] half-point
of participation credit
is you guys writing a
reaction paragraph talking
about something that
the speaker talks about.
And there are instructions
for that on Ed.
But without further ado,
let me introduce Danqi Chen.
So Danqi is one of the foremost
researchers in question
answering, and
she's particularly
well known in recent
work for being
one of the co-authors of the
Roberta paper, the SpanBERT
paper, and on using
dense passage retrieval
methods for open domain
question answering,
and is the professor at
the Princeton University.
But as one other comment,
Danqi once upon a time
was the head TA of CS224N.
So she's quite familiar with
the context of this class.
So I'm really delighted
to have Danqi here
to give this lecture
on question answering.
Thanks.
Thank you Chris, for
the introduction.
For me it's a great
opportunity for me
to come back to CS224N today
and to give this lecture.
albeit virtually.
So question
answering is the area
that I have been working quite
a bit in the last few years.
So today I'm very happy
to introduce to you some
of the fundamentals
in this field,
as well as on cutting edge
and state of the art topics.
So here's my plan
for this lecture.
So first, I would give
a brief introduction
of what is question answering,
and what kind of problems
that people are studying today.
Then I'm going to spend the
most of this lecture focused
on one type of question
answering problems called
reading comprehension.
So it's just the
base of the problems
of how we build systems
to answer questions
over a single passage of text.
So I know that many
of you are going
to do a different project on
the Stanford Question Answering
Dataset.
So understanding this
part will be very
crucial for your final project.
So at the end of
this lecture, I'm
hoping to spend hopefully
like 10-ish minutes
to talk about a more
practical, and in my opinion,
more exciting problem called
open domain question answering.
So basically try
to answer questions
over a very large
collection of the documents.
And so my point is to
try to quickly go over
some of those state of the
art measures in this area.
OK so let's just get started.
So first, what is the
question answering?
So it's the goal of
question answering
is to build systems
that can automatically
answer questions posed by
humans in our natural language.
Question answering, or,
let's say QA in short,
is one of the
earliest NLP tasks,
and the early systems can
even date back to the 1960s.
So here is one example
of one of the early QA
systems back to 1964.
So as you can see,
this system is
trying to answer a question
like, "What do worms eat?"
And they'll finally retrieve
the answer, that's the grass.
So this system is built to
try to find some kind of text
matching between the question,
and some kind of text segments,
and then by using some kind
of dependency analysis.
I'll assume that
you have already
learned the dependence
parsing in this class.
And there are many
different types
of question answering problems.
And we also have categories of
these question answer problems,
based on the information source,
or the type of the questions,
or the type of answers.
So for the
information source, we
have built a system that
can put like conditions
of short passage of text,
or very large collection
of documents, or
like a structure,
they have structured knowledge
bases, or even tables
or images.
So for the question
part, we can also
build systems that can
answer factoid questions
or non-factoid questions.
Our open-domain questions
or closed-domain questions
are simple questions versus
more complex or compositional
questions.
And for the answer
type, it can also
be a short segment in the text,
or a paragraph, or a document,
or a list or even the
yes or no questions.
So just have in mind
there's many different types
of questions in problems
and all these problems
may require very different
techniques or different data,
or even different
evaluation metrics
to evaluate all these
different problems.
And, the question and
answer has enabled
a lot of really useful
real world applications.
For example, today if you
just put your question
in a search engine like Google.
So for example, you can
put your question like,
where is the deepest
lake in the world.
So we can see that
it's the kind of system
that it can find a short
snippet of text, including
Lake Baikal in Siberia holds
the distinction of being both
the deepest lake in the world
and the largest fresh water
lake, blah blah.
And then you can actually
click on the correct answer,
which is actually our
concise answer, which
should be Siberia.
And those kind of
systems are also
able to handle more
complex questions
like how-to questions.
I guess this is the probable
question that everyone
currently cares about.
So the question is, how can I
protect myself from COVID-19?
So there isn't really a
simple and short answer
to this question.
So you can see that
the system actually
returns a very long
paragraph, including the best
way to prevent
illness is to avoid
being exposed to this virus.
And to help prevent
the spread of COVID-19,
you can do the following.
So actually this
paragraph is actually
a summary from CDC article.
If you just click this link
and read through the article.
So this is also one type of the
question answering problems.
Now, this is our
survey of the use cases
for the current digital
assistants such as Alexa
or Google Home.
So according to the survey
results in January 2020,
which is one year ago, so
you can see that as of--
people actually really
like to ask questions
on these digital assistants.
So you can see that ask
a question is actually
the second most used case.
Only ranks after listening
to music and before the check
the weather and set up timer.
So question answering
has been really useful
in digital assistants.
And another very famous example
of the question answering
system is this IBM Watson
question answering system.
So in 19-- in 2011, so
this IBM Watson QA system
has been shown to beat
two national Jeopardy
champions in answering
Jeopardy questions.
So this is a part of a
historical event, at least
in the NLP history.
So if you look at the inner
working of this kind of system
more closely, so you can
see that it is actually
a very complicated and
highly modularized system.
So the system is built on
both the unstructured text
and also the structured data.
So if I look at the system both
from the left to the right,
you can see that
this system consists
of the four stages,
including the question
processing, the candidate answer
generation and the candidate
answer scoring, and the
confidence merging and ranking.
And then if you
look at each stage,
you can see that there are many
different NLP techniques that
have been actually
included in this complex QA
system, including the question
classification, parsing,
relation extraction,
co-reference.
So it's actually, there are
really lots of NLP modules
that have included.
And now this system has been
over 10 years older, actually,
exactly 10 years now.
And this is actually
representative
of state of the art 10
years ago at that time.
So we know that this class
is about deep learning.
So today different
has completely
really transformed the landscape
of the question answering
systems.
So there's no doubt
that we can say
that almost all of the
states are question answering
systems today built
on top of the end
to end training of the
deep neural networks
and the pre-trained language
models such as BERT.
So today in this
lecture, we're also
going to know a lot of the
deep learning models used
for questions answering.
And this statement is probably
also true for almost all
of the NLP problems
that we can see today.
But we also argue that
question answering is probably
one of those fields that we
have seen the most remarkable
progress in the last couple of
years driven by deep learning.
So in this lecture, I
will be mostly focusing
on the text based, or textual
question answering problems.
So basically, we are
trying to answer questions
based on the unstructured text.
So before I jump to
that part, I also
want to quickly point out that
there are many other really big
question answering problems.
And each of them can be
really like a subfield in NLP
and they actually have
very different challenges
and also model designs.
So one bigger class of
question answering problem
is this knowledge-based
question answering.
So basically we wanted
you to question build
answering systems
to answer questions
that can answer questions
over a very large database.
So to solve this
problem, some approaches
need to take this question
and convert this question
into some kind of logic forms.
And these kind of
logic forms can
be executed against
this database
to give you the final answer.
And another class, bigger
class of the question answering
problems is called visual
question answering.
So basically you need to answer
questions based on the images.
So this problem
basically requires
both understanding of the
questions and also images,
and is actually a very active
field between the computer
vision and NLP.
So if you have interest
in these type of problems,
I encourage you to check
out those problems,
but I'm not going to dig
into these problems today.
OK.
So next, I'm going to
start with a part 2,
reading comprehension.
I just want to
quickly check if there
are any quick
questions I can answer
before I start us on part 2.
No, I think we're good for now.
OK.
So let's talk about the
reading comprehension then.
So reading comprehension
is a basic problem
that we want to comprehend
a passage of text and answer
questions about the content.
So it's an input of
this, probably basically
a passage of text or
question, and the goal
is to return the
answers that actually
can answer this question.
So here is one example.
So here is a passage of text.
And we want to
answer a question.
The question is what
language did Tesla
study while in school?
OK.
So I'm going to pause
like 5 or 10 seconds
and see if people can find the
answer to this question based
on this passage.
Any guess?
German.
People say it's German.
Yeah, German is correct.
So the answer should be German.
So basically to
answer this question,
so you need to find this
sentence, like, in 1861,
Tesla attended this school where
he studied German, arithmetic,
and religion, and only
German is a language.
So the answer to this
question should be German.
OK, here is another example, OK?
Another passage of text.
And the question is, which
linguistic minority is larger,
Hindi or Malayalam I think
5 seconds.
OK.
So the answer to this
question should be Hindi.
So this probably is not a
very hard question for humans,
it's actually a pretty
hard question for machines
because to get this
question correctly.
So the machines basically need
to understand for the Hindi.
Like 3.3% of the population
speaks Hindi and only like
1.27% speaks Malayalam,
this language.
And then also compared these
two numbers in the final case.
So 3.3% is a bigger number,
so the answer should
be Hindi to this question.
OK.
So next I'm going to
talk a little bit so why
do we care about this problem?
So why do we care about the
reading comprehension problem?
So besides that it has
actually many useful real-world
practical applications--
so as I've already showed us
some examples at the beginning,
I think there are also
two other reasons.
So the first reason, besides
applications, the first reason
is--
so reading comprehension
has been also viewed
as a very important
test bed for evaluating
how well computer systems
understand human language.
So this is really just similar
to how we humans actually
test the reading
comprehension test to evaluate
how well we actually
understand one language.
So this is also the
way that we actually
post questions to test
the machine's language
understanding ability.
So it actually has been
formally stated back in 1977
by Wendy Lehnert in
her dissertation.
She says that,
since questions can
be devised to query any
aspect of text comprehension,
the ability to
answer questions is
the strongest possible
demonstration of understanding.
So that's why
reading comprehension
can be a very important test
bed because we can design very
complex questions to testbed.
And also I think there is
another interesting and
important reason that reading
comprehension is important.
So in recent few
years, some researchers
actually found that, OK, well,
there are many other NLP tasks.
So we also reduce them to a
reading comprehension problem.
So I'm going to give
you two examples.
So one example is the
information extraction.
So basically if we want to--
so to answer about a personal
subject, Barack Obama.
key to our relation,
educated at.
So we want to fill in what is--
fill in this question
mark and figure out, OK,
where Barack Obama
was educated at.
So one way to solve this
problem is basically
trying to convert this
relation into a question.
So where did Barack
Obama graduate from?
And taking all of that
relevant piece of text
and then by applying a
reading comprehension problem.
Then basically,
we can find out--
the correct answer should
be Columbia University.
That is also the output of this
information extraction system.
And another example
is actually called
a semantic role labeling.
I'm not sure you have learned
this in the past year,
probably not.
But this is a class of
those-- semantic role
labeling is trying
to take one sentence
and then trying to identify
the roles for different words,
at least for words in this
case, in one sentence.
So basically try to--
given one sentence,
given one word,
"finish" trying to figure
out who did what to whom
and when and where.
So by trying to--
so the goal is to try to
figure out all these roles
with respect to the words.
So one way to solve
this problem is also
by converting all these
different roles into questions,
such as who finished something,
what did someone finish,
and what did someone
finish something as.
So by converting all these kind
of semantic role relations,
we can also just apply the
reading comprehension problem
and give you the correct answer.
So this is actually a very
interesting perspective,
that reading comprehension can
be actually very universally
useful to many other tasks.
So next, I'm going to introduce
this Stanford Question
Answering Dataset called SQuAD.
So if you are going to develop
for the final projects,
you will need to
use this dataset.
So Stanford Question
Answering Dataset
is actually a supervised
reading comprehension dataset,
which consists of 100K annotated
passage question and answer
triples.
So here is one example
from this data set.
And I just want to say that
also one important thing
to have in mind is that--
so this data set consists
of 100K annotated examples.
And this kind of a
large scale supervised
dataset are also
very key ingredient
for training the effective
neural models for reading
comprehension.
So after the SQuAD dataset,
many other later data sets
have been also
collected, basically
runs this size around 100K.
So 100K is actually
very important
to train these neural models.
So for these datasets--
so the passages is like a
single paragraph selected
from the English
Wikipedia, which usually
consists of 100 to 150 words.
And the questions are
crowd-sourced, basically
like from Mechanical Turking.
And this is a very important
property of the dataset,
is that each answer is
a short segment of text,
or we called it
span in the passage.
So as you can see
from this example--
so here are three
different questions.
And each of these answers
can be actually found off
on a short segment
text in the passage.
So this is actually an
interesting property
and it's also an important
property of this data set.
But also just to caveat, that
this is also a limitation.
Because not all the questions
have the answers in this way.
So only the questions that
you have found the answers
as a span in the
passage can actually
be included in this
dataset basically.
But today, so this dataset,
I forgot to say that.
This dataset was collected in
2016 by several researchers
at Stanford, so it's called
Stanford Question Answering
Dataset.
Today, after four
or five years now,
so SQuAD still remains the most
popular reading comprehension
data set.
So it's actually very clearly
a high quality dataset,
but is also not a very
difficult dataset.
So today, basically the SQuAD
dataset itself has been almost
solved, and the state-of-the-art
already exceeds estimated human
performance.
And I also want
to quickly mention
the evaluation for this Stanford
Question Answering Dataset.
So there are basically
two evaluation metrics
to evaluate how well the
system can do on this dataset.
The two metrics are the
exact match and the F1 score.
So exact match is basically
just a binary indicator, 0 or 1.
Basic measures can
actually be exactly matched
to the gold answer.
And the F1 score
basically can measure
kind of some partial credit,
enough to do the evaluation.
So basically for the
development and testing set,
there will be three
gold answers collected
because for some
questions, there might be
not just one unique
answer, there
could be multiple
plausible answers.
And the evaluation
matrix basically takes
the predicted answer and then
compares the predicted answer
to each gold answer
with some articles
and also the
punctuation excluded.
And basically you can
compare the exact match score
and also F1 score by
comparing the predicted answer
to the gold answer.
And then finally you
take the max scores.
And there are many different
examples in the dev or test
set.
And then finally, we
just take the average
of all the examples for both the
exact match and the reference
score.
So by using this
evaluation metric,
the estimated human performance
estimated by the researchers
at the time is--
the exact match score is 82.3%
and the F1 score is 91.2.
So here is just a quick example.
So here's the question what
did Tesla do in December 1878?
And there's three
possible answers.
So you can see that
the first two answers
are the same, left Graz.
And then the second answer
is left Graz and severed,
I think there's a typo here,
all relations with his family.
And then you find that
prediction is span,
which is left Graz and severed.
So we can see that
there is an exact match
score between the
predicted answer
and any of the gold answers.
So the exact match would be 0.
And the F1 score would
be taking the max.
I'm not going to talk about
how these are computed,
so I suggest you check
out the original paper.
So by computing these
scores and taking the max,
the final F1 score
will be 0.67, which
is F1 score for this predicted
answer on this dataset.
So Danqi, one question
you might answer is,
so if you can do other tasks
like named entity recognition
or relation extraction
by sticking something
on top of BERT and
fine tuning for it
or do it as a
question answering,
does one or the other method
work better and by how much?
That's an interesting question.
So I haven't really seen the--
OK.
So there has been
some claim, OK,
that all the tasks
can be converted
into question answering task.
But I'm not sure if there is
really a very fair comparison,
let's say a yarn and
entity recognition
by really converting that
into question answering task.
So I don't have
the answer to that.
So the kind of state-of-the-art
AER systems still have time
to just train or sequence
tagger on top of the word.
So yeah, I don't really have
a precise answer to that.
Shall I continue?
OK.
Yeah.
So next, I'm going
to talk about how
to build neural models
for reading comprehension,
and in particular, how
we can build a model
to solve the Stanford
Question Answering Dataset.
I also to just quickly
mention that because there
are many different
papers that actually
use different notions to
refer to the same thing,
so starting from--
so I'm going to use
the passage, paragraph,
and context, and
also question and
query basic interchangeably.
So they basically
refer to the same thing
because different papers
use also different notions.
So I just want to
quickly mention that.
OK.
So how can we build a model
to solve this problem?
So let's first
formulate this problem.
So the input of this
problem is let's
take a context or paragraph.
So C, which consists of
the N tokens C1 to CN.
And also we take
our question, Q.
And the question consists
of n tokens q1 to qN.
So N could be something like
between 100 and 200 for SQuAD.
And then N would
be much shorter,
it would be something
like 10 or 15.
And because the answer
has these constraints,
the answer must be a section
of text in the passage.
So the output can be
just written this way.
We are going to predict
a start and end.
So start and then end
would be within the range
between the 1 and the
N. So it's basically
just two checkpoints-- sorry,
two end points of the answer.
So SQuAD has been collected
beginning late 2016.
So after 2016, there
have been-- there
are two families of neural role
models to solving this SQuAD
data set.
So the first family
basically had
done a lot of
models that came out
during that period
between 2016 and 2018.
So this was a family of models,
basically LSTM-based models
with attention.
So these are just a list
of the representing models
that came out during
that period and including
some work that I did when I
was a PhD student at Stanford.
And the second class of
models that I put here
is really divided here before
the BERT and after BERT.
So after BERT came out--
so almost all these reading
comprehension models
were built on how
to fine tune the BERT models.
Not just BERT models,
for the BERT-like models.
So pre-trained language models
for these kind of reading
comprehension problems.
So here are the two--
the illustration of these
two families of the models.
So on the left is an LSTM-based
models with attention,
and on the right
is the BERT model.
And then we need to fine-tunel
this model for the reading
comprehension task.
So I know that for the--
so my plan today is
first try to talk
about these LSTM-based models.
So I'm going to spend a little
bit more time on this part
because I know that for
the default final project,
you will need to implement
this model from the scratch.
So I'm going to walk us through
hard to build this model
step by step, and
hopefully with that,
you'll have a good understanding
of how this model works.
And so I'm just
going to briefly tell
about how to build this
BER-- use the BERT models
for the reading comprehension.
OK, so before I start talking
about these LSTM models,
I know that you have
already learned the sequence
to sequence models
with attention
for machine translation.
So I want to draw some
connections between the machine
translation problem and the
reading comprehension problem
because they really share
a lot of similarities.
So first, in the machine
translation model
or this sequence
to sequence model,
there are like a source
and target sentence.
So basically there
are two sequences.
But in our case, in this
reading comprehension case,
we also have two sequences.
One is a passage and
another is our question.
But the length could
be slightly imbalanced
because a passage could be
much longer than the question.
But essentially, you
also choose sequences.
And so in the reading
comprehension,
we need to model which
words in the passage
are most relevant
to the question.
And if they are relevant
to the question,
so these are also
relevant to which
set of the question words.
So this is a very
key important thing
that we actually need to model.
And that is actually very
similar to the machine
translation model
that we need to model
which words in the
source sentence
that actually are most relevant
to the current target words.
So you can imagine that
attention would be also
really the key ingredient here.
Just like some sequence
to sequence model,
we need to model the attention
between the source sentence
and the target sentence.
We also need to model the
attention between the passage
and the question.
So this is actually
very similar.
So something that's
actually not very similar
is for the sequence
to sequence model,
we need to build a decoder,
autoregressive decoder,
to generate the target
sentence word by word.
But in this reading
comprehension problem,
we don't need to really
generate anything.
So we just take the
path into question.
So at least for
the SQuAD data set,
we just need to
train two classifiers
to predict the start and
end positions of answers.
So that part is
actually simplified.
So we only need to train the
decoder to generate the target
sentence.
OK.
So next, I'm going to talk
about this model called BiDAF.
So it stands for
Bidirectional Attention Flow
for Machine Comprehension.
So it was proposed by Minjoon
Seo and other folks in 2017.
Before the BERT
came out, It remains
one of the most popular
reading comprehension models
and achieved a very
good performance
at that time, at least
on the SQuAD data set.
So you can see that this model
seems to be pretty complicated.
But if you look at this model
from the bottom to the top,
it actually can be decomposed
into many different layers.
So next, I'm going to just
dissect this model layer
by layer and talk about what
this layer is actually doing
and how we can really build
this model from the bottom layer
to the top layer,
and the finally we
train this model in
an end to end way.
OK.
So the first part is actually
the bottom three layers
called the character embedding
layer, word embedding layer,
and the phrase embedding layer.
So I just put them
together and called this
as an encoding function.
So the idea here
is that OK, let's
take the context part of
the passage in question.
We need to encode
them separately.
So to do this, so
this model basically
proposed to use a concatenation
of the word embedding
as well as the
character embedding
for each word in the
context and the query.
So the word embedding
is straightforward.
So if you have the
word embedding,
you can just look at
the word for the--
just a word like "Seattle,"
just use the GloVe embedding
as a representation
for this word.
And for the character
embedding part,
so you basically
need to represent
each character in this
word, like Seattle,
and bypass this to a
convolutional neural network
with some kind of max
pooling operations.
And then finally,
you can just get
one representation at the top.
And then you just concatenate
the word embedding
and the character embedding.
So these character
embeddings have
been shown to improve the
representation for the unseen
or the real words.
So mathematically, we can
see that for each word
in the context of the
query, we can just
represent as GloVes with the
embedding and the character
embedding.
And then we just concatenate
them and pass this
to a highway network.
So I didn't write
the function here.
So you can just look
at the original paper.
And the second part.
So after we encode the
individual word, so next,
we are going to pass
this word embedding
into two separate
bidirectional LSTMs
separately to produce these
contextualized embeddings
for both the context
and the query.
So let's look at this equation.
So we take the
representation of this word.
And then we just--
basically, this
is one LSTM model
from one direction
and this is a LSTM model
from another direction.
So we just need to concatenate
the two hidden representation
in two directions.
And finally, we can get a
contextualized representation
for each single
word in the context.
And we can do a similar
thing for the question
representation.
I also want to quickly
mention, because I mentioned
the sequence to sequence model.
So sequence to sequence model,
we cannot really do these
bidirectional LSTMs for the two
sequences because the decoder
is an autoregressive model.
So that's why the decoder
is usually just implemented
as a unidirectional LSTM.
But because here we don't really
care about the generation,
so we can just use two
bidirectional LSTMs
to represent the
representations.
This is actually very important.
This bidirectional [INAUDIBLE]
is actually very important
to capture the context from
both the left and right side.
OK.
So the next component
is our next layer.
It's called the
attention flow layer.
So I just called
it attention here.
So the idea of
attention is trying
to capture the interactions
between the context
and the query.
And I think in this
paper, the BiDAF paper,
they proposed two
kinds of attention.
So the first type
of attention we
called context-to-query
attention.
So the idea is for
each context word,
can we find the
most relevant words
from the question
for the query words.
So is one example.
So here the context
is Barack Obama
is the president of the USA.
So for each context
word, we need
to find our alignment
because we find
which words in the question
can be actually aligned
with this context word.
So we can see that both
Barack and Obama can
be aligned with who,
and the president can
be aligned to leads, and the
USA is aligned to United States.
So basically for
each context, we're
trying to find the most
relevant query words.
And then the second
type of attention
is called the query
to context attention.
So it's basically in
the other direction.
So here the idea is
to choose some context
words that are most relevant
to one of the query words.
Because the context
can be very long.
So a lot of the context
could be just not relevant
to this question.
So we just ran over several
examples you can see there.
The first thing we need to do
to try to locate which part
of the sentences in this
context can be actually
relevant to this question.
So this type of the query
to context attention
is trying to capture which
context words actually
can be most relevant to
one of the query words.
So for this example,
the question
is which city is
gloomy in winter.
So because the question
asked about gloomy,
so you guys can
try to figure out,
OK, gloomy cities is actually
very relevant to this question.
Now we also find this in winter
because "in winter" is also
mentioned in the question.
So this part of
the context words
can be also relevant
to this question.
So these context
words probably need
to be captured in this attention
that OK, this is actually
relevant to this question.
OK.
So this is actually just
an intuition of these two
types of attention.
And this is also
why this model is
called a bidirectional
attention flow because there's
a context-to-query
attention and there is also
a query-to-context attention.
So let me just talk about,
go through how to actually do
this query-to-context attention
and the context-to-query
attention in this model.
So the way they do this is
first to compute a similarity
score for every pair of the
contextualized vector ci
and then for every pair
of the question with qj.
So this is actually the
output from an encoding layer.
So this already the output
from the LSTM layers.
And the way they basically
just compute our similarity
score by taking the
ci, qj, and also
the element-wise multiplication
of the ci and qj.
So they just concatenate
these three vectors.
So the output would be
a 6H dimensional vector.
And they just multiply this
to compute the dot product
of another learnable vector.
And they finally just
basically give you
one scalar or one
number, the sij,
which measures the similarity
between this context word ci
and also this question word qj.
So if I learned the
attention before,
so this is actually just
one choice of this model.
So there could have
been many different ways
to define this similarity
and similarities scores.
So this basically just one
design choice of this model.
OK.
So after you find the
similarities for sij--
so the context-to-query
attention again,
like which question words
are most relevant to ci.
So the way they do
this is basically
just taking these metrics,
the similarities for sij,
for each row.
Each row basically correspond
to one context word.
For each row, let's
say they are going
to compute a softmax
for each row,
and this can give us
normalization scores alpha ij,
which is our probability
distribution over all
the question words alpha ij.
So this is just really similar
to all the attention mechanisms
that you probably have
seen in this class.
So basically for
each context words
taking the softmax over
all the question words and
get us a probability
distribution.
And finally, you just take
the weighted combination
of this attention score alpha
ij and also the question vector,
the qj, and then
finally, you can
get a vector ai, which is
actually a 2H dimensional
vector.
So this context-to-query
attention basically
just tries to capture
which questions are most
relevant to each context word.
So the next part is a query to--
sorry, there's a
typo here, sorry.
This is actually the
query-to-context attention.
Which means that
which context words
are relevant to
some question words.
So a lot of context
words will be
not relevant to this question.
So the idea is to do this.
They do this, is for
each row of this sij,
it basically just takes the max
scores over all the question
words.
And after taking this max score
to compute the softmax over all
the context words here.
So here, i actually enumerates
over all the context words.
And this can give us another
attention score of beta i,
which captures how important
this context word is
relevant to this question.
So after computing
this beta i, so we
can again compute this
like a weighted combination
by summing up the beta i and
also the context vector ci,
and then finally, you get
our vector bi, which is also
another 2H dimensional vector.
The final output of
this attention function
is actually very
complicated here.
It's also the design
choice of this model.
So it takes a context
vector ci and it
takes ai from this
context-to-query attention
and takes the element of
multiplication between the ci
and ai and also ci and
bi, and finally, it
takes the concatenation and can
produce 8H dimensional vector.
OK.
Maybe I want to
pause a little bit
and check if there are any
questions because this part is
a little bit complicated.
One question is why is
query-to-context and
context-to-query
attention not symmetrical?
That's a good question, yes.
So here because essentially
the goal you're trying--
because final
goal, you're trying
to find a span in the passage.
So the point of this
attention function
is trying to produce
a representation
for each single context
word in this context.
So we are not trying to generate
question representations.
Here, the goal is
trying to generate
context representations.
So the difference
between these two,
first it's trying to see
which question words are
relevant to this context word.
Another kind is
trying to figure out
which context word
can be relevant
and which context word
can be not relevant.
I hope this answers
your question, yeah.
Here's an easier question sort
of on the same topic which
might help.
Is there a reason why you
use both query-to-context and
context-to-query attention?
Is it sometimes advantageous
or OK to use just one?
Difficult question.
Yeah.
So I'm going to show us some
operations from this figure,
so way we just find both
directions can really
help by joining the
context-to-query
and query-to-context.
So there'll be some
operation studies.
So by using one set is
useful, but just not
with us using the
both directions.
Yeah.
Right.
Let's see.
In the bottom right,
we sum over i,
so why does the i remain in bi?
Is that correct or
is that a typo there?
This is another typo.
So again, I'm sorry.
I know it's all
getting confusing.
So the output of
this module is to get
a representation for each
context word at the end.
So both the output
for ai and bi-
i is actually enumerated from--
actually enumerated, iterates
over all the context words.
So bi will be still the--
just to try to aggregate
over all the context words.
But the beta i
measures the importance
of these context words compared
to all the context words.
So both ai and bi are
actually with respect
to the context words, yes.
So you can see that
here it's basically
doing some kind of a
element-wise multiplication.
So the output of gi will
actually range from the 1
to N, which is the number
of the context words.
There are lots of
questions about this.
What is the rationale for
the expression of the gi?
How does one come up
with such an expression?
OK, I don't know.
I guess the authors try
out a lot of things.
So, OK keep on
hearing and trying
to understand the roles of
the context-to-query attention
and query-to-context attention.
So I bet that there could be
many different combinations
to do this.
I also think the authors have
trialed many different variants
and those are the ones
that come up at the end.
I think there could
be smarter ways
to incorporate both
attentions, but it doesn't
have to deal with in this way.
I mean, one other
question would be
in the query-to-context
attention.
Why do you do a max
inside the softmax?
Yeah.
Sorry.
I should have explained
this more clearly.
So here again,
query-to-context attention
is trying to measure the
importance of these context
words with respect to
some question words.
So by taking the max for each
row in this matrix, so it's
basically trying to see, OK,
which question word is actually
most relevant to
this context word?
If this number is
still very low,
that means there
isn't any question
words that could be aligned
with this context world.
So after taking the max, if
this number is still very low,
that means this context
word is not very relevant.
So basically, that's why
we take the softmax--
take softmax over on
top of the max, yeah.
I know.
Do you want even more
or do you want to go on?
I probably should go on.
We have a lot of slides, but
I'm happy to answer questions
after those ones.
Maybe you should go on.
Yeah.
OK.
So the last part of this
model is actually the easiest,
the most simplest one.
Lastly, these are two
layers, modeling layer
and output layers.
So for the modeling layer--
so again, after the
attention layer,
they take the key
representation, so basically
the gi, which captures the
attention between the context
and the query, and
then basically just
pass this gi to another two
layers of bidirectional LSTMs.
And there's many
reasons they do this,
is the attention layer
is basically modeling
the interactions between
the query and context.
And by passing
this to another two
layers of bidirectional
LSTMs, the modeling layer,
the basic modeling
layer, can also
first model the interactions
within the context words.
So this is the formulation here.
So this is a two layer
bidirectional LSTM.
By taking the gi's
input and the output
will be on the mi, which
is another 2H dimensional
vector for each context
word in the passage.
OK.
So the final is
the output layers.
So final output
layers are basically
just two classifiers just trying
to predict the start and end
positions.
So they first concatenate
the gi and mi.
So this will be actually
a tanh dimensional vector.
And then by computing the
dot product of another vector
called W start and this
is resulting vector.
And they basically get a
score for each position
in the context.
And then you can just
apply your softmax.
And then this will
give you a probability
that OK, what is the
probability of this condition i,
would be actually based
on the start position
of the final answer string.
And they also have
another classifier
to predict the end
position of the answer.
But they also give something
a little bit more complicated.
So they actually pass the mi
to another bidirectional LSTM
here.
So they call it m prime i.
And they concatenate
gi and m prime i--
sorry, this is a typo.
So this should be w end.
So they compute the dot product
between w end and this vector,
and this can produce
all the probability
over all the conditions
which predict
how likely this position
will be the end the position
of the answer.
So by passing the mi to
another bedirectional LSTM,
their reasoning is
that they're trying
to capture some
kind of dependence
between the choice
of the start and end.
So you can imagine that
start and end shouldn't
be too separate.
So it could be
independent predicted
by the-- if it's a
claim that if you--
adding some kind of dependence
between the mi and the Pstart
and Pend, this can
actually perform better.
OK.
I'm done with this part,
describing the BiDAF model.
Any quick questions
I can answer?
I think you can actually go on.
OK.
Sorry, I forgot to mention this.
OK, the final
training loss will be
by taking these two
probability distributions.
And it is basically just
the negative log likelihood
of the start position
of the gold answer
and the end position
of the answer.
It's basically taking
the product of these two
probabilities, but
you apply it on log
so it is the sum of the
two negative log terms
of this final training loss.
And the whole model can
be just trained in an end
to end way from
the encoding layer
to attention layer to modeling
layer and to output layer.
So this just completes the
whole model of the BiDAF model.
OK, so this model is
actually achieved--
like on SQuAD data set, it
achieved a 77.3 F1 score.
So as I mentioned earlier, these
are sum of operation study.
They found that both
attentions in two directions
are actually important.
If you remove the one
direction, the performance
will actually drop quite a bit.
If you remove the
context-to-query attention,
the performance will
drop to 67.7 F1 score.
And then if you
remove this part,
it will drop a 4-point F1 score.
And then also the character
embeddings also help.
So if you remove the
character embeddings,
you'll get like a
basically 1.9 point drop.
And on the right of this slide,
you can see a very big table.
So it's basically
all the models that
account at that time
between 2016 and 2018.
So you can see
that BiDAF is here.
So you can check
the 77.3 F1 score.
And basically all of
the models are actually
a very similar ballpark.
So numbers range from
the highest number
here, 79.8 until after
the ELMo was introduced,
the numbers have actually
improved quite a bit.
So before the ELMo,
basically all the numbers
are actually kind of similar.
So each model actually
improved the previous model
by one point or two points.
And now here is our
attention visualization
to show that how this
smorgasbord of attention
actually can capture the
similarity between the question
words and the context words.
So a clear example
of a question,
where did the Super
Bowl 50 take place?
So it show the actual
question word here.
And each column's
matrix basically
indicates the attention score,
the similarity score that
has been learned by this model.
So you can see that on
the right it's basically
trying to print out or
display the context words that
had the highest scores.
So you can see that
the word has to be
aligned very well with the
at, the, Stadium, Levi.
And also the Super Bowl 50
basically aligns very well
with Super Bowl 50.
So basically this
theory tells us
that these kind of
attention scores
can actually capture those
negative scores pretty well,
yeah.
OK, so next, I'm going
to talk about BERT,
how to use the BERT model
to solve this problem.
So I know that you have learned
BERT in the last lecture,
so I'm not going to repeat this.
So very quick.
So BERT is basically a deep
bidirectional transformer
encoder pre-trained on
large amounts of text.
And it is trained on the
two training objectives,
including masked language
modeling and the next sentence
prediction.
And this model has
a lot of parameters.
So the BERTbase has
110 million parameters
and the BERT-large model
has 330 million parameters.
So, OK, we can actually use BERT
for our reading comprehension.
So it's actually very easy
and very straightforward.
The idea is to take the
question as our segment A.
So you got BERT
[INAUDIBLE] these
are our two segments for the
next sentence prediction task.
So then you apply the BERT over
the reading comprehension task.
You basically just take
the question as a segment A
and take the passage
as a segment B.
And then finally,
you go with trying
to predict two endpoints in
segment B. So here is one more
complex example.
So question is how many
parameters does BERT-large
have?
So you can see
that they basically
just take the questions here
and then take the passage here.
And then by putting the CLS
token and the SEP token,
and then by just concatenating
the questions past the tokens.
And also for the
questions that we just
need to pass the A to
a segment embeddings.
And the full passage, you
just need to cut upward
in the segment B embeddings.
And then finally, the training
loss is also the same.
So you basically
just try to maximize
the sum of the negative
log likelihood of both
the start and end positions.
Well here, the way that they
compute the start and end
probability is
slightly different.
So it's actually
very straightforward.
So you just have this
input attention into BERT.
And BERT can give you the hidden
vector hi that can actually
represent the
hidden vector that's
corresponding to
the context word ci.
So you can just introduce
another two vectors Wstart
and Wend by computing
the dot product
and then apply the softmax.
Then it can just give you a very
similar to what we had before.
But here the hi is the
output from the BERT encoder,
and then we are training
this two Wstart and Wend
for these two probability
distribution Pstart and Pend.
OK, so for this model, so
all the BERT parameters,
that is actually a
very large number.
If you use the BERTbase,
it's 110 million parameters.
As well the newly
introduced parameters,
Hstart and the Hend, which
is if you take the BERTbase,
the hidden side will be 768.
So it's only like
1,500 new parameters.
So we just have to
optimize together jointly
for this training objective L.
And it actually works really,
really well with this model.
So if you just take
this BERT model,
and by just optimizing all
the parameters together,
it can give you a
very high performance.
I will show you
BERT in a minute.
And even if you use a stronger
pre-training models or modern,
like a--
stronger models than
the BERT models,
they can even lead to
better performance on SQuAD.
And SQuAD has also
become a standard dataset
for testing these kind
of pre-trained models.
Let me show you some numbers.
So again, human performance
is 91 and BiDAF is 77.3.
And if we just do this
fine-tuning model,
so BERTbase can
give you of 88.5,
BERTlarge can give you 90.9.
So you can see that this is a
huge jump from the BiDAF model
to the BERT models.
And then finally,
if you see even
the latest pre-trained
language models, including
the XLNet or RoBERTa or Albert.
So these models
are either bigger
or these models are
trained on bigger corpus,
or the model size are bigger.
So basically these
models can give you
another like 3, 4 F1 score
compared to the BERTlarge
model.
So this is already way higher
than our estimated F1 score.
So this just works really well.
Any quick questions?
I think this may be OK.
OK, so yeah, I guess I
went a little bit fast
for these BERT models.
Next, so I want to also do
a bit of the comparisons
between the BiDAF models
and the BERT models.
So BERT model has many,
many more parameters.
So has it easily
110 more million
or 330 million parameters.
But BiDAF has only like
2.5 million parameters.
And the BiDAF is built on top
of several bidirectional LSTMs
while BERT is built on
top of their transformers.
So transformer means that there
isn't any recurrence structure
architecture.
So their transformers are
much easier to parallelize.
Another very key difference
between the BERT models
and the BiDAF models
is BERT models
are pre-trained while
BiDAF models only
builtd on top of the GloVe
vectors, which is pre-trained
and all the remaining
parameters need
to learn from this SQuAD
dataset or the other supervision
datasets.
So here it is very clear that
pre-training is a game changer
here.
Pre-training basically
can just change everything
and it also gives you a
very, very large boost
in terms of the performance.
But I also want to
raise another question.
So if we first think
of this pre-training,
these BiDAF models
and BERT models
are really
fundamentally different?
I don't think so, so this
is actually my argument.
So let's try to see how
these two models are actually
connected, especially in
terms of model design.
So BiDAF models
essentially are trying
to model the interactions
between the question
and the passage, right?
So both the question to passage
and passage to question.
And the BERT model
essentially, they're
trying to use a self-attention
on top of the concatenation
of the question and passage.
So this is a transformer model.
So you could take the
question and the passage,
so these are questions
in the passage,
and then you apply many,
many different layers
of the self-attention.
Essentially, this
self-attention is
able to capture the attention
between the context words,
the attention between the
passage words and the question
words, and the attention
from the questions
to the passage side, and also of
the attention from the question
words to other question words.
So compared to BiDAF, BiDAF
is trying to model this part.
But the BERT model essentially
can capture the attention
between all these four parts.
And actually after
the BiDAF cannot.
This is also before
the BERT can add.
So we were happy also
showing that if you just
add a little self-attention
layer for the passage side,
so basically, you are
trying to exclusively model
this attention between the
passage words and passage
words to the BiDAF.
This can also improve
the performance.
So we can see that
these two models,
you can really just
trying to model
the attention between
the passage and question
and also the attention
between the passage
words and the passage words.
And this is actually was
exactly the BERT model is doing.
So if there's no
further questions.
So at this point,
I'll talk about--
BERT models can do really
well on this kind of reading
comprehension data set.
And we just talk
about pre-training
can really change
the performance,
can be a game-changer in
reading comprehension.
Can I put in one--
Danqi, can I add
one question first?
People wonder whether
you can do well
with a transformer that
isn't pre-trained, right,
if you tried to build a
question answering system using
a transformer rather than
LSTMs but no pre-training.
Does that work?
That's a good question.
Yeah, it works.
But you probably cannot really
build a model as big as 110
million parameters or 330
million parameters models.
So as we train the model
between these family
of LSTM models and BERT models.
They're called
QANet from Google.
So QANet is actually built
on top of transformers
to be solved around
pre-training.
So that the model actually can
perform better than the BiDAF
models and other models.
But it actually under-performs
BERT models a little bit.
So just check it out on QANet.
OK.
I will just continue.
OK, so here, pre-training
has been so important.
So next I will
quickly talk about--
OK, a question here is
that can we actually
even design better
pre-training objectives
for reading comprehension
or question answering?
And the answer is actually yes.
So this is actually a work
I did with Mandar Joshi
and other folks one year
ago called SpanBERT.
So think about this.
So for SQuAD and other a
lot of extractable reading
comprehension
datasets, the goal is
trying to predict
the answer span
from the passage of the
question, the answer
to this question.
So there are two key ideas
being proposed in SpanBERT.
So first idea is
that instead of using
only the masking of
individual words,
we propose that we want
to mask a contiguous
spans of words in the passage.
Because the final
answer will be just
a section of text
in the passage.
So we are trying to mask out
all these possible answer
spans from the passage as
our training objective.
And the second idea
proposed in SpanBERT is--
because at the end
of it, it goes around
to predict an answer span.
So we're actually essentially
try to predict two endpoints as
well as the answer.
So the idea here is that can
you try to compress the two end
points of answer span to--
sorry, can we try to compress
all the information in the span
into the two end points?
So here the idea is that--
here, let's think about this.
If we mask by the fours here.
And can we try to use the two
endpoints here in this figure,
like x4 and x9, to predict
all the words in the middle?
So essentially, we are
trying to take the two end
points and also some kind
of position encoding.
And then finally we are
going to try to predict
all the words in this span.
So this is why it
is called SpanBERT.
So I encourage you to
check out our paper.
And this actually
really helps a lot,
at least for the question
answering data set.
So as you can see
from this figure--
so this is SQuAD 1.1
and this is SQuAD 2.0.
And these are many
other question answering
data sets as you can see here.
So the blue bars here,
we call it Google BERT,
are actually the
original checkpoints
that are released by
Google for researchers.
And our BERT is
actually just the--
is actually our
re-implementation
of the BERT model using
the same data where
we have been trying to train
this model for slightly longer.
So it's actually achieved
a better performance
than the original Google BERT.
So as you can see,
the yellow bars
here is actually the SpanBERT.
So SpanBERT actually
greatly outperformed
Google BERT and
other BERT basically
across all of the datasets.
So that really tells us
that OK, even if we are not
going to increase
the model size,
that we are not going
to increase the data,
by designing better
pre-training objectives
can also go a long way and
do a much better job at least
in the question answering
and the reading comprehension
datasets.
OK.
So I have several few
slides left in this part.
So so far, we've demonstrated
that by using BiDAF model
and by using BERT models, we
can get a very good performance
on the SQuAD dataset.
This number has already exceeded
even the human performance
on SQuAD.
Does this means that reading
comprehension is already
solved?
The answer is of course not.
So in the recent
last couple of years,
there's been a lot
of evidence showing
that the current systems
still perform poorly
on adversarial examples
or the examples
from out of domain
distributions.
So here is a very
classical example
proposed by Robin Jia
and Percy Liang in 2017.
So the idea is to take a passage
and then take a question.
And they're trying to just
insert a random sentence
to the end of the paragraph.
So you can see
that this sentence
has even a little sense entity,
in this context, Jeff Dean
here.
But this sentence
actually has some overlap
between the question.
It's actually very
similar to this question,
but actually the numbers
have been changed.
The entity length
has been changed.
And they found that these
kind of adversarial examples
are actually very easy to
fool the current systems
and makes the system to predict
the answer to be Jeff Dean.
So here the table
shows that by adding
a lot of these
adversarial examples,
they found the
performance actually drops
a lot for this BiDAF model.
So drops from 75.5
to even like 30%.
So for you, like
this kind of attack,
the performance level just
dropped to very low, like 4.8%.
So here is another paper that
actually just came out in 2020.
So there has to be
a lot of evidence
showing the similar things.
So today we compute a very good
reading comprehension data set
on the individual data sets.
But these systems trained on one
dataset basically cannot really
generalize to other datasets.
So the diagonal of
this table is basically
trying to model one
dataset and evaluate it
on the same dataset.
And all the other
numbers in this table
basically shows that if you
train one system on one dataset
and then evaluate
on another dataset,
the performance will
drop quite a lot.
So it basically really cannot
generalize from one dataset
to another dataset.
So finally, this is actually
a very interesting result.
So this table is actually
the best paper from ACL 2020,
it's called a checklist paper.
So the idea is that
these authors basically
try to propose some
kind of the test cases
to checker whether these models
can actually really answer
some simple questions when there
is some specific or particular
phenomenon.
They found that by just--
come up with a really
simple question.
For example here, Jeremy is
more optimistic than Taylor.
And who is more pessimistic?
And they found that a
BERTlarge model cannot solve
and basically failed these type
of test cases 100% of the time.
And now here is another table.
So here is another
coref example.
Victoria and Alex are friends.
Her mom is an agent.
Whose mom is an agent?
And so to get this
kind of question
correctly, so it
has to understand
the Victoria actually
refers to a female person
and Alex refers
to a male person.
So these kind of questions
also make the current models,
BERTlarge models
trained on SQuAD
totally fail on these
kind of test cases.
OK.
So I have 10 minutes left.
Chris, is there any question
I should answer at this point
here?
I think you can go on.
OK.
So in the last 10
minutes, I'm going
to give you a very,
very brief introduction
of what is open-domain
question answering
and what we have been trying to
do in the last couple of years.
So open-domain question
answering is a problem that--
so it's different from
reading comprehension
that we don't assume
a given passage.
So here, we use the
assumptions that we only
have access to a large
collection of documents.
So one example is just taking
the whole Wikipedia, which
has five million articles.
So we don't really know
where the answer is located.
And we're going to
return the answer
for any open-domain questions.
So this problem, there
isn't any single passage,
so we have to answer questions
against a very large collection
of documents or even
the whole web documents.
So this is actually a much
more challenging and also more
practical problem.
So if you look at the
example of Google example
I showed at the beginning,
so these techniques
will be very useful in the
practical applications.
So the term here open
domains is just in contrast
to closed domains that
deal with questions
under a specific domain, yeah.
OK, so how can we solve
this type of problem?
Because for the reading
comprehension problem,
we just make sure
to answer questions
based on a simple passage.
So this is a paper that I
wrote in 2017, four years now.
So the paper is called
Reading Wikipedia
to Answer Open-domain Questions
on a system we call DrQA.
So this paper basically
proposed the idea
that we can actually
solve this problem
by using a retrieval and
also a reader framework.
So the idea is that
let's take a question--
OK, so here, the
article is trying
to answer questions using a very
large collection of documents
such as the Wikipedia.
So the idea is that there
is a retrieval and also
reader component.
So the retrieval
text in the question
and try to find out a small
number of documents that to be
relevant to this question.
And this reader
model is basically
trying to read through
all the documents
that this retrieval
return and try
to find out the correct answer.
So formally defined here is that
the input is a large collection
of documents D and
the question Q.
And the output could
be our answer string A.
So we can just decompose
this problem into,
as I just mentioned, in our
retrieval and the reader
component.
So the retrieval
is basically trying
to take the large collection
of document D and Q,
and is trying to return a set
of documents or set of passages.
So here, this number K could
be very small, just like 100.
So it's basically trying to find
out 100 passages of documents
from let's say 5
million documents.
And finally the reader
basically takes the question
and takes this type
of the passages
and finally returns the answer.
So the second
problem is actually
the reading comprehension
model that we just learned.
So these are just from
2017 paper we wrote.
So it's actually doing
a very simple thing.
So the retrieval is just
standard information retrieval
model with a TF-IDF information
retrieval sparse model.
And the real model
essentially is just
the neural reading comprehension
model I just talked about.
So it's mainly trained on SQuAD
and some other question answer
datasets.
So the idea is very
simple, but it's
trying to bridge
with two things,
how to have a bridge as the
retrieval and also the reader
to do this kind of open-domain
question answering.
So I'm just going
to quickly go over
some really exciting
ideas that has
been happening in the
last two years basically.
So the first idea is that
this is retrieval part
can be also trained.
So we can actually
even do this kind
of training of the
retriever and the reader.
So here is actually--
so this idea has been first
proposed in Kenton Lee's paper
in 2019 called Latent Retrieval
for Weakly Supervised Open
Domain Question Answering.
So this part is
basically the first model
for reading comprehension,
and this part is basically
the retrieval model.
So to get this
retrieval model working,
they also tried to use the
BERT to encode the passage
and also encode the
question, and they
tried to use a dot product
between the question
representation and the
passage representation
to model the relevance, the
similarity between the question
and the passage.
But this is actually a very
difficult problem because
of scalability of this problem.
Because there are 20 million
passages in Wikipedia,
so it's actually very
hard to model this part.
So I encourage you to
check out this paper.
And also second paper I
want to quickly mention
is also work I did last year.
It's called the dense
passage retrieval.
So the idea is actually very
similar to the previous paper.
But the idea is an actually
much more simplified model
and a very easy, a very simple
and straightforward approach.
The idea is that we can also
really just train the retrieval
part by using two BERT models
using only the question
and answer pairs.
And this model kind
of works really well,
and it can largely outperform
the traditional IR retrieval
models.
If you see this figure,
so the blue curve
here is a traditional IR
approach, like a BM25 approach.
And so the other
curve, the orange curve
is basically training this kind
of retrieval using only one
solved and question
answer pairs.
So by looking at all these
different curves basically
using a different number
of training examples,
so it actually largely greatly
outperforms the traditional IR
models.
OK.
Again, really I don't
have time to talk
about the details of
all this projects,
so I just encourage you
to check out these papers,
and I think these results
are really exciting.
So here is actually
a really nice demo.
So demo is actually
hosted on this website
if you want to check out.
So again, the database
ferries the whole Wikipedia.
And you can see that if
you ask a question of who
tells Harry Potter that he is
a wizard in the Harry Potter
series.
And the system had
really found out
the correct article should
be Harry Potter films
series, and then finally
gave you the correct answer,
which is exactly what
you have seen here
from the Google example here.
So the answer would
be the Rubeus Hagrid,
which is actually the
person who told tells Harry
Potter that he's a wizard.
So this is actually the perfect
answer to this question.
OK, I'm going to
skip this slide.
And then finally, very quick.
So this is something that
came out very recently
that some researchers have
demonstrated that maybe you
don't even need this
retrieval stage.
If you just use a very
large language model,
you can also just use
all open-domain questions
answering.
So they way they
did this is that--
I hope that you have learned the
T5 model in this class already.
So they just take a
pre-trained language model T5.
And they are trying to
fine tune this model
by taking the question as the
input and the answer as output
without any explicit retrieval.
And they just fine-tune
this data set,
and they find this model can do
pretty well at the testing time
by just taking the question
and then directly generate
the answer without resorting
to any documents or a retrieval
system.
So this is actually
very amazing.
So this kind of QA model is
also called Coastal QA systems.
OK.
The last slide.
So this is one direction
that personally, I'm
very excited about.
So this is actually
a new direction
that basically shows that maybe
for the open-domain question
answering, maybe this
reader model is also
not necessary anymore.
So this idea was first
proposed by Minjoon Seo in 2019
and recently wrote a paper
called dense phrases that
tried to demonstrate
that maybe you don't even
need this reader model.
So instead we can just
record all the phrases
in Wikipedia using some
kind of dense vectors.
So what you just
need to do is just
to do this kind of nearest
neighbor search in the answer
space.
You just encode all the
phrases in Wikipedia,
encode them using vectors.
And by taking a
question, you can just
encode this question
in a single vector
and then we can just do the
nearest neighbor search.
And then it can directly
give you the answer.
So this particular
new paradigm is just
kind of the question
answering model.
You just need the retriever,
you don't need a reader.
So a great advantage
for doing this
is that for the
BERT reader model,
you essentially have
to run the BERT model
at the inference time.
This is actually very expensive.
Well, you just get a read
off the reader model.
You can just do the
similarities search,
you can just do the
nearest neighbor search
without running a BERT model.
So this could be very fast and
they can even run on the CPUs
without needing to run a very
expensive deep neural network
and then it can still run very
well, perform very, very well.
OK, finally, I hope this works.
So I actually prepared a
demo for the DensePhrases.
So I want to show you
how this actually works.
So you can see
that when you type
this question of who won the
Nobel Prize in peace in 2014.
So everything just types a
little piece of the input
question, and the system
can basically just find out
the relevant answer and
the relevant text passages.
And then finally, the
answer actually shows up.
It's actually very fast because
it has bigger real time.
We don't run the BERT
model, so it's just
our retrieval model here.
OK.
I'm actually done
with this lecture.
So it is already 5:15 now, yeah.
Thanks for joining me today.
Thank you very much Danqi for
that awesome survey of question
answering.
I guess given that
demo at the end,
people want to know
whether you're launching
your own search engine soon.
But at any rate, Danqi can stay
for a bit to answer questions,
but not forever.
but today, because she
doesn't have a Stanford login,
we're going to do
questions inside Zoom.
So if you'd like
to ask a question,
if you use the
raise hand button,
we can promote you so that
you appear in the regular Zoom
window and can just ask
questions and see each other.
And if you hang
around and don't leave
the Zoom for more
than a few minutes,
maybe we'll just promote
everybody who's still there
into people in the regular Zoom
for some bits of discussion.
But we'd welcome
anyone who'd like
to ask a question by asking
it themselves at this point.
OK.
I've got one volunteer.
I've got more volunteers.
Should I read those questions?
Should I look at the chat or?
No.
So there are now four
people who've been promoted.
There are four people.
[AUDIO OUT] was the
first, so maybe he
could start by
asking a question,
and then the other people
that we've promoted.
OK.
So thank you so much
for the lecture today.
My question is maybe if you
use a model like for example
BERT, how small can your
training dataset be for you
to get reasonable results?
So the question is how we can
train the reading comprehension
model using only a small
number of training examples.
Yeah, I think this is
a really cool question.
It's actually like
the, you probably
have heard of GPT
stream model that you
showed that if you only
use a very few examples,
you can also do open-domain
question answering pretty well.
But this kind of model is
huge, like what number?
How many parameters I forgot
in the GPT Stream model, yeah.
So it's a very large
variety of of model but--
OK.
So this is my answer, is
that if we can leverage
a very large and very powerful
pre-trained language model,
there is a possibility that we
can actually do the question
answering well with only a
small number of examples.
And also there are some
other promising directions,
including unsupervised
question answering so
by using some kind of
approach like some form
of unsupervised machine
translation, this kind of idea.
That can be borrowed--
can borrow the idea
from that and can also
work pretty well, reasonably
well in unsupervised question
answering.
Yeah, also I have
seen a lot of works
like [INAUDIBLE] showing that
synthetic Pure-DSS can also
help a lot in boosting
the performance if you
don't have enough
supervised examples, yeah.
So my question is I guess
it's kind of interesting
that there's not really
that strong of a transfer
effect between data sets that
are kind of ostensibly similar.
So my question is has there
been any research done
on how close I
guess the formatting
and the semantic content
of these question answering
datasets actually
adheres to the data
that BERT is pre trained on?
And if so, has there been
sort of any effect found
between those similarities
or differences?
Is the question asking whether
there has been like some kind
of--
OK, maybe I can just try
to clarify a little bit why
the current models cannot really
generalize well from one data
set to another data set, yeah.
So I actually truly believe
that most existing question
answering datasets or
reading comprehension
datasets have been collected
from Mechanical Turk.
So it is very difficult to
avoid some kind of artifact
though, like a simple clues
or superficial clues--
let's say not superficial
but some simple clues
that are for the
machines to pick up.
So let's take those
examples that--
so you can see actually if
you look at the dataset some
more closely, there
has been a lot
of examples of the
question having
more like a large
overlap in each
of the words between the
question and the passage.
So the model is actually
very good at picking up
these kind of clues to
get very high performance
on this dataset.
And a lot of dataset drop.
So it's basically about
comparisons with the two
numbers, something like that.
So that's the reason that
more specialized models that
have been trained very
well in one data set,
it's very easy to pick
up these kind of clues,
and is very hard to
generalize this kind of thing
to another data set.
What about the natural
questions data set?
Doesn't that avoid
that objection?
Yeah.
Natural questions
will be much better,
but there are some other issues.
I'm not sure if
you have seen that.
There is a recent paper
called a question or train
test overlap paper.
So that basically demonstrate--
Can I just interrupt?
So Natural Questions
was a dataset
that Google put out
about a year and a half
ago maybe where
they were actually
taking real questions
from Google search logs
and then trying to find answers
for them in web documents.
Sorry.
Go on Danqi.
Yeah, I think that
definitely natural questions
is a much better dataset because
the questions are natural,
like you're collecting
real questions that
are asked by users.
So it kind of avoids this
kind of superficial artifact
between the question
and the passage.
But there's some other
issues that people like
to ask some common questions.
So if you just do the remnant
debate of the questions
in your train, dev, and test.
And there's a
recent paper showing
that there is actually a--
it's inevitable that there is a
high overlap between the train
and dev.
So if you have
questions that you
are trying to test in the
dev set or the test set that
has already appeared in the
training set that is not
really generalization, right?
Yeah, but this is more
on the open-domain
setting not in the
really [INAUDIBLE] here.
Yeah.
Do you want to ask a question?
Yes.
So you mentioned in the last
part of the presentation
that the reader model
may not be necessary
and you presented the
DensePhrases which
also work well on CPUs.
So do we know how well it
performs on the question
and answering datasets compared
to other models including
BERT and those [INAUDIBLE]
on computer of course.
Yeah.
I just encourage you to
check out this paper.
So this model basically performs
on par with the dense passage
retrieval model.
So its performance on par
with all the retrieval
reader models.
But it is actually--
so I skipped one slide.
So right now, the
state of the art
is actually dominated by this
kind of dense passage retrieval
plus the generative model.
So using a T5 model has
a better data retrieval.
This actually
performed really well.
So I will just say dense
phrases work basically
similar in this block.
But compared to this
generative model,
we're still a few
points behind, yeah.
OK.
And what is kind
of the intuition
behind the dense phrases
apart from the answers
will probably be
in close proximity?
And what if the datasets has
answers to a specific question
like very far from the
actual information?
Say, the answers
to your question
may not resided
in close proximity
to the words in the question.
So let me just clarify this.
OK, the goal of this
project is trying
to ingest all the
phrases in the Wikipedia.
So these conversations
are built using
the training set of the
question answering datasets.
So the assumption is still
that the distribution
of the examples in
the dev and test set
would be similar to the
training set for sure.
Does this answer your question?
So basically, we're
still trying to consider
all the phrases in Wikipedia.
And our test now, we
just take the question
and try to compute
the dot products.
So if we use say a different
data set that does not
present the information
using the structure presented
in Wikipedias, this model
may not work as well as.
What do you mean by
structure represent?
So say if we lean more towards
structures like the passages
we see in standardized
tests where
the answers to the
question may not
be in close proximity to
where the information was
first introduced.
Oh, so the answer doesn't have
to be seen in the training set.
So basically, the goal is
to take the training set,
train and encode
them for the phrases.
And by using end to end,
we apply this encoder
to all the phrases, like 60
billion phrases in this region.
So the model is definitely
able to generalize
from the training set to all
the phrases in Wikipedia.
So it doesn't have to
have seen the phrase then.
Is this what you were asking?
I see, OK.
So it's actually similar to the
retrieval or the dense passage
retrieval.
So you still try to train
on passage representation,
here is the phrase
representation.
But the representation
is only using
the training set of the
question answering datasets.
But by taking the
encoder and then
we are going to encode
all the representation,
all the passages of
phrases in Wikipedia.
And then we can use text
as the representation,
can actually generalize well
for the unseen questions.
Yeah.
So the question is what if
the nearest neighbor search
doesn't return the answer?
So why do you think
the nearest neighbor--
I mean, you always can
find something, right?
The question is that whether
it's close enough or not.
Yes.
So the question is
what if in the datasets
that the answer is
not close enough?
Yeah, that's a good question.
I don't know.
If you really come up with
something that is really
very far away from
all the questions
that we have been seeing
in the training set,
that could be possible.
I don't know.
Basically it depend on how
the text are formatted.
The nearest neighbor
search may not
work as well as other models.
So again, the question
the representation
also returns the final
question encoder.
So the question is whether
this question encoder
can give you something
reasonable in that space
or not.
But I don't know.
So we have been testing
a lot with a random--
even the input
sentences or even--
the question doesn't have
to be a real question.
It could be a sentence.
It doesn't seem to be
a problem so far, yeah.
Maybe we should give a
couple of other people a go.
And you're allowed to
turn your camera on while
asking a question if you want.
So next person is [AUDIO OUT].
All right.
Hi.
Thank you for taking
the time to teach this.
My question is kind of quick.
So you mentioned
work, they brought up
a set of relatively
simple questions
that show how brittle or poor
the current models can be,
right?
I'm curious if that--
yeah, exactly.
Did that kind of
change the community
to improve how to
evaluate the models?
Because they're actually doing
pretty poorly on some of those,
right?
Yes.
So first these questions
are simple in terms of the--
the wording is very simple,
the template is very simple.
But they're still trying
to test a mutation
or temporal or
relational reference.
So the questions are not--
I mean, in terms of the
reasoning of the capacity,
it's not that simple, it's just
the wording that's very simple.
OK.
So this paper definitely
received a lot of attention,
it was the best paper last year
at the [INAUDIBLE] conference.
So I think a lot of people are
trying to solve the problem.
I cannot tell you that whether
we really have a solution
for this yet or not, yeah.
Cool, yeah, thank you
for bringing this one up.
It's really interesting.
OK.
Next is--
Hi, thanks for taking the time.
So my question is
kind of non-relevant,
but like computer robust
system of question answering.
In what extent can in
context learning help models
to be more robust with
respect to different domains?
Can you tell me what
you mean by in context?
So like basically you provide
the template generated by BERT.
And then instead of
directly predicting
the classes of text
classifications,
you just use some word
to represent that class
or predict the wordings there.
OK.
So I assume that
you are actually
referring to the in context
learning in logic history
or something like that.
OK, actually, I have been
through this something related
to that recently.
But I'm not sure of
how we can actually
use in context learning
in everything for SQuAD
type of model problems.
Yeah, so I don't know if that is
still done, robustness or not.
I even [INAUDIBLE] used that
technique for all the question
answering use.
I see, I see.
Thanks.
And the you also mentioned
that we can train a retriever
without a reader.
So is there a paper about that
current attempt to do that?
Yeah.
The paper is already
out so, yeah.
OK.
Thanks a lot.
Next is--
Hey, how is it going?
Thanks so much for the lecture.
A bit of a broader question
sort of about the future of NLP.
Do you think that in order
to solve NLP in the sense
that you can perform on par
with humans on all NLP tasks
it's sufficient to only
interact with text data?
Or do you think we'll eventually
need the sort of experiences
and common sense that you get
only from seeing and viewing
the world and having
a set of interactions
that we as humans have?
Yeah.
I mean, common sense is a very
difficult-- even in the context
question answering, common
sense is a very important topic
that I think still
remains unresolved.
For that part, the
answer is definitely yes.
And I also want to mention that
OK, so for a lot of the reading
comprehension data sets or
question answering data sets,
you have seen that all
we QR start to achieve
the human performance.
But we also see how critical
these systems are because they
cannot really generalize
or solve the easy problems.
So all these things
need to be resolved.
Do you think that the current
sort of benchmark data sets are
maybe a little bit too easy for-
[INTERPOSING VOICES]
Or just like that.
Yeah.
One final thought is that having
a lot of transversely trying
to have a lot of humans in
the loop of the frameworks
to evaluate these
kind of systems.
Just try to break
the current system,
come up with some
harder questions.
So yeah, that means maybe
the current static data sets
are not good enough to
measure the progress.
So we actually really need
some kind of dynamic evaluation
and also introduce more just
kind of adverse examples,
harder questions also,
things like that, yeah.
Are you still game for
a couple more questions?
Sure.
I did want to mention it is
9:10 PM on the East Coast.
OK.
So next is--
Hi.
Thanks so much for the lecture.
So in 2020, there was this
efficient open-domain question
answering challenge.
And from performance
it seemed like there
was quite substantial decrease
versus human accuracy.
Probably primarily due to
the quantization and drift
that occurred when
they were quantizing.
So I recently
encountered this paper
called Learnable Quantizers,
which essentially learns
baseless representation
for the quantizers
jointly with the
leads of the network.
And while this would
be extremely effective
if you were to just like,
say, train from scratch,
I was just sort
of curious, do you
think there is some way to do
this say a pre-trained BERT
model or something like that?
I had a few ideas with like
beam search for instance,
but I don't see a very
clear way of doing that.
Yeah.
I don't think I'm really an
expert to answer that question.
Yeah, I'm not sure if I
really have the answer,
but I also want
to quickly mention
that quantization
has been definitely
a very useful technique
to make the model smaller.
So we have been also
exploring the quantization
in the DensePhrases project
recently because the storage
has been still very large.
So we actually have been
trying to reduce that storage.
Yeah, I'm not sure
about the question
about the connection
between quantization
and also pre-training.
I'm not sure.
Yeah, I'm not sure I have
an answer to that for you.
Sorry.
Thank you.
Thanks.
Danqi is too modest
to mention that she
was one of the co-organizers
of the EfficientQA task.
OK.
Next question is--
Hi Danqi.
Thanks so much for
being here today.
So my question is
a bit different.
So one example you gave
that caught my attention
with this Alex Victoria
example in the checklist.
And I was thinking technically
Alex wasn't the wrong answer,
right?
It's gender neutral
and there wasn't
enough context in the
question to determine
who it's referring to.
So my question is how
concerned should we
be about potential encoding
sort of biases into these record
labels or how we
evaluate them, or is that
just more of a concern for
more open ended questions?
Yeah, this is definitely
very important.
Again, a lot of
people are trying
to study, OK, how much bias has
been encoded in these models
and how we can--
yeah, I'm not sure I
have a good answer to that.
Again, I just want
to say some people do
a de-biasing of the
pre-trained language models,
all these things
are very important.
And this is just one-- so you're
talking about this example,
right?
So this is just one test case.
Yeah, I don't know, yeah.
Right, so yeah, I guess I'm
just a little worried about who
comes up with the test cases?
Who determines what the
right answer is, thank you.
I mean, we will have more
discussion of toxicity and bias
coming up very soon, including
actually Thursday's lecture
as well as a later lecture, not
specifically about QA though.
OK.
Next person is--
Thank you for the lecture.
Yeah, my question is also
related to the open domain
question answering.
So I was just wondering how much
of the learning side of domain
sort of generalization or
domain alignment techniques
can be combined with language
level, like question answering.
Like to what extent
would they work,
and what kind of
language specific design
should you leverage to combine
with those to sort of like--
if we want like
higher performance
and stuff like that?
Is the question about
how to generalize
between different domains about
how to design open domain QA
system for different languages?
I'm not sure I get that.
Sorry.
Just wondering.
So there is some very specific
designs like domain server
alignments and efficient level
disentanglement techniques
that has shown some interesting
performance on other tasks.
And I saw recently some people
also leveraged similar things
for question answering.
So I was just wondering to what
extent these kind of techniques
can work on one
group of tasks, not
just limited to
question answering,
but mainly question answering.
Sorry.
Which work are
you talking about?
I'm still not sure.
What do you mean by disentangled
solutions or question
answering.
This is a little bit
more specific for--
so there's a paper
called domain--
I forgot the exact name.
It's sort of adversarially
aligned to domains
by disentangling--
[INAUDIBLE]
Got it.
OK.
I just want to be sure that
we are all on the same page.
So I have seem some
work sort of trying
to learn some kind of
disentangled representations
that can better generalize
to the different domains
on adversarial examples.
Is this what you're saying?
Yeah, yeah.
And the question is
whether this technique
can be generally applied
to question answering or?
Yeah, I'm just wondering to
what extent will they work.
Because I think language
has a lot of specific things
like dependency and other
sorts like these techniques
does not actually take care of.
Yeah, I'm not sure.
I think we have to try that.
But it's definitely
an interesting point.
Yeah, I don't know.
At least for the work
that I have seen so far,
it all applied or operated
at a very simple sentence
classification task.
Maybe that's not correct.
So [INAUDIBLE] is a
basic type of a encoder
applied to a simple
classification task
and take a hidden
representation through some kind
of a transformation
and make sure
that it can learn some kind
of envrironment features
that the hidden representation
is talking about.
Right, right, yeah, cool.
Cool.
Fair input.
Yeah, I'm not sure.
I feel like QA is a
more structured task
and also handles
longer bar sequences.
Yeah, so I don't
know if it works
unless people have tried that.
Thank you, thank you.
OK then we've got--
and maybe we should call
this the last question.
Hi, I'm just wondering what
is the intrinsic difference
between solving
question answering
with generative models like
T5 versus encoders like BERT.
OK.
That's a good point.
OK, so I skipped
this slide still.
Why this model works so well.
The reason is, actually,
it's not really
about the extractive model
versus generative model.
The reason is that
they [INAUDIBLE]
for the extractive model.
So if the retrieval returns
like, say, 100 passages,
so they have to
extract the answer
from each of the
passages and then finally
figure out which one
has the highest score.
But for the generative
model, essentially they
are trying to
aggregate all the 100
passages and the
dense representations
together and do the
generation jointly.
You understand?
So essentially, you're taking
the 100 representations
together through
the joint generation
instead of only
do the extraction
from each of the passages.
So I think that is actually
the key difference.
So that's why this
generative model
can do really well compared
to the extractive models.
So I also want to mention that--
OK, so if you look at this
RAG model, it's actually--
compare this DPR and RAG model.
So RAG model is always
doing the generative model.
But they are not doing
this kind of aggregation.
They're just trying to
take on the single passage
and then doing the generation.
So the RAG model
actually doesn't
perform as well as this model.
By the way, I also want to
mention RAG model is actually
not doing better than DPR
because it's base model,
this is large model.
So these numbers are a
little bit confusing.
So it's actually
basically really on par.
Their base perform similarity.
So the key difference
between the generative model
and the extractive model is
that for generative models,
you can actually leverage more
input passage together and do
the generation.
Is that clear or not?
Yes.
Thanks.
Yeah, otherwise, you should
just check out this paper here.
So this paper
actually explains it
pretty well why this
model works better
than the previous
generative model.
So are these generative
models do a simple question
answering over documents and
where there is span prediction,
can you use generative
models to generate the span?
You can.
Yeah.
You can definitely do that.
So you are talking
about this T5 model.
Yeah.
So I'm just wondering
about if you use encoders,
it's like you're
finding similarities
between the encodings.
And then generative
models are you're
remembering the whole
question and you
try to retrieve the memory
when you answer the question.
OK.
So for this model, there
isn't any retrieval.
So you can always find the
answer from the question,
right?
So this model really
has you relying
on all the parameters you
memorized, all the information.
So by just taking
this input, it has
to just rely on the parameters
to infer this answer.
So it's actually very hard to--
yeah, it's a definite
balance between memory
and the generalization
from it, yeah.
I see.
So I'm just going
to say what I--
like when you bar this question,
it's embedding in some space.
And using that
embedding, the generator
matches that with [INAUDIBLE].
Is that what is
going on in there?
Exactly, yes.
The model is very large,
like 11 billion parameters.
So the parameters
are basically trying
to memorize a lot of
information that has been.
Because the model has been
pre-trained on the text
and also has been fine-tuned.
So the model has been trying to
memorize a lot of information
from the text, yeah.
All right, thanks.
Do you want to call
it a night or do
you want one more question?
Either way, yeah.
It's up to you.
Sure, I'll take
one more question.
OK.
Let me just do--
One more question from--
OK.
The first question is about
how easily are these techniques
generalized to other
languages or say
languages that follow quite
different grammatical rules
like Chinese,
Japanese, or Arabic,
or some other languages?
Another followup question
maybe not exactly
in your domain
expertise is there's
a lot of interest in
modelling user behavior,
so online searching behavior
or browsing behavior
as a sequence using, say,
transformers of attention.
And then you can use that
to predict how users--
like embed users, so that you
can can predict user's actions.
How promising do you
think that would be?
I know this may not be
your domain expertise,
but there is a lot of interest
in extending these question
answering techniques or just
encoding techniques, embedding
techniques to
recommender systems.
I just want get your
thoughts on that.
OK.
The first question is whether
these techniques can be
generalized to other languages.
I think the answer is yes.
There has been a lot of actively
searching is this section.
But there has been
some constraints
that a lot of models or
systems that I described here
actually require a
lot of them, require
very strong pre-trained
language model
and also requires
lots of training
examples for the Pure-DSS.
So that'll be
actually I would say
a bottleneck for many low
resource languages, right?
So it's very hard to
collect so many examples
for other languages.
If we have, actually, I
think that the techniques
can be generally applied
to other languages.
And there has been
also a lot of work
trying to do cross-lingual
question answering
and stuff like that.