Hi, everybody.
Welcome back to CS224N but first
just a couple of announcements.
Originally this was going to be
the day when assignment 5 was
due, but as you've seen
we're giving you one
extra day so it's now
due Friday at 4:30.
We do realize that
assignment 5 has
been a bit of a tough
challenge for many people,
that we've been trying to help
people out of office hours
and otherwise.
So I hope at the
end of the day it
will seem like it was a really
good learning experience
to really get some much
more kind of close hands
on look at how
transformers work,
rather than simply being
loading up a transformers
as a black mystery box.
After Friday, I guess there's
no rest since we do really
hope that you can
sort of basically
immediately transition to
working on final projects
since there's basically four
weeks to go on final projects.
And in particular, we're hoping
to get feedback on your project
proposals back by next Tuesday
to help that process along
with people, we have to
get started on them soon.
And it's just
maybe a good moment
to say that we do
really appreciate
all the people putting tons of
effort into these assignments.
And we like that
several of the keenness
we're seeing from the students.
OK.
So with that out of
the way, today I'm
delighted to have giving today's
lecture on neural language
generation Antoine
Bosselut who is
at present a
postdoc at Stanford.
He's someone who's
done a lot of work
on natural language generation
in his previous life
as a University of
Washington PhD student.
And next year he's
going to be taking up
a position as a
professor in Switzerland.
OK.
So welcome, Antoine.
Thanks Chris, that's a
very kind introduction.
It's great to be here giving
this lecture in CS224N.
Particularly on one
of my favorite topics
in deep learning for NLP,
natural language generation.
So hopefully by the end of
this lecture most of you
will have at least learned a
bit about NLG with deep learning
and hopefully be motivated to
start doing some research on it
or launch a startup in
NLG, or perhaps go work
on it at a larger organization.
OK.
So to start, I think it might
be really helpful to define what
we mean at a high level when
we talk about natural language
generation because over
the last few years,
the definition has
actually sort of changed
and has really
grown as a sub-field
to really encapsulate
any part of NLP that
involves the production of
written or spoken language.
In other words, if
you're given some inputs
and your goal is to generate
text to describe, respond,
translate or summarize
that piece of text,
NLG really focuses on
how you can actually
build a system that
can automatically
produce a coherent and
useful written piece of text
for human consumption.
And it used to be a much
more limited research
area since many
tasks that we now
view as NLG problems
didn't actually
involve much text production
prior to neural networks.
But now that scope has
expanded considerably
and we have this much larger
area to sort of work in.
Unfortunately
we're not quite yet
at the level of the
types of AI NLG tools
that we've seen in pop culture
and that we like to imagine,
but we are starting to see
many areas where NLG tools are
having a massive impact.
To start with,
machine translation
is kind of the classical
example of an NLG task
thhese days, ever
since the tasks
moved to neural networks and
an NLG framework around 2014
or so.
And now we've seen
a rapid improvement
in the quality and applicability
of translation systems.
In fact, you can often
use Google Translate
for most of your kind of
retail translation needs
as a good starting point.
Similarly, NLG
technologies really
underpin some of
the dialogue systems
that you might interact
with on a daily basis.
Any time you use, let's say
Siri, Alexa, Cortana, Google
Home, Bixby, or pretty much any
other major company's dialogue
system, there's a good chance
that there's a neural NLG
component embedded
in that system that's
involved with providing you
an answer to your query.
And there's really
still a ton of progress
to be made in this
area, and it's
led to some major companies to
actually crowd source chat bot
technologies from researchers
and students such as yourself
to continue to try to make
big advances in this area.
We're also seeing lots
of NLG technologies used
in areas such as summarization
where systems often
have to aggregate
information from potentially
multiple sources and rephrase
the most salient content
in a shortened but
still very engaging way.
While our go to example
for summarization
is generally related to, let's
say generating news highlights,
summarization systems
have actually achieved
broad applicability
in many areas
where we address content,
such as summarizing
emails or summarizing
meeting transcripts.
And there's actually many
more areas not listed here.
I don't actually
put it on the slide,
but a few months
back a tool called
Semantic Scholar actually
developed a neural system
for generating summaries
of scientific papers, which
is something that I personally
end up using quite a bit
as an example of how
humans can interact
with these technologies.
But these modalities aren't
actually limited to text in
or text out.
So actually the classical NLG
area that I mentioned earlier
is how the tasks
used to be framed
was actually around what we now
call data to text generation.
So can you learn to
compile or let's say
summarize the most interesting
facts from a table,
or a knowledge graph, or
some type of data stream.
That way humans can get the most
interesting and salient content
that's being presented
in these data structures
rapidly, and in an
easier to adjust format
than having to look through
the structures themselves.
We've also seen a
lot of recent work
in visual description
that tries to use language
to describe the content
in images or videos.
So around 2014 or so we start
to see the first neural NLG
systems in the space,
and they've really
continued to mature
in the last six years.
And now we actually tackle much
more challenging description
tasks such as generating
full descriptive paragraphs
of scenes or generating
streams of visual, generating
descriptions for streams
of visual content
such as video captioning.
And these tools have
really broad applicability
in different areas of AI.
And finally the last
sort of application
I kind of want to mention
is that we've also
started seeing NLG
systems being developed
in more creative applications
such as story generation
where AI systems can
now help humans write
short stories, blog posts, or
even full books in some case
as creative writing assistants.
In another area such
as poetry generation,
we can actually have kind
of full automated settings
where you can have AI agents
that can generate something
like a sonnet, and
in fact condition
that on a lot of demands
that are given through a user
interface.
So I hope that by
this point I've
really given you a look into
the breadth of NLG applications
and how it sort of
encompasses any task
that you might think of that
involves production of text.
And each of these tasks really
requires different algorithms
and different models and a
different way of designing
the system to get right.
But what they have in
common is that a lot of them
are powered by next
generation advances
in deep learning for NLG.
And the goal of today
is to really give you
the introduction to these
topics that really allows
you to contribute to the next
era of these technologies
and in designing deep
learning systems for NLG.
And so I think to
start what might
be interesting to do is
to quickly recap topics
that you may have seen
in previous lectures
but which are going to
be very relevant today
when we're trying to
design an NLG system.
And what we're effectively
trying to do in the setting
is take a sequence
of tokens as inputs
and produce new text that is
conditioned on this inputs.
And then what we typically call
the auto regressive setting,
which is the most common sort
of text generation setting.
We take these produced
tokens of text
and we feed them
back into our model
to generate the next
token in the sequence
that we want to generate.
But so to really
understand what's
going on in an auto
regressive NLG system,
what we really
need to start to do
is look at what happens
for the generation
of an individual token
since further stages really
depend on taking
that generated token
and passing it back in as
input and doing the same thing.
So what happens at a low
level is that your model takes
in the sequence of
inputs, so these y's,
and it computes a vector of
scores using the model itself.
And each index in that vector
corresponds to the score
for a token in your vocabulary.
So the only tokens that
your model is actually
allowed to generate.
And then what you do is that
you compute a probability
distribution over
these scores using
what we call a soft max function
to compute a probability
estimate for each token
in your vocabulary
given the context
that precedes it.
And as a shorthand, I'll just
mention that sometimes I'll
remove the W from this
probability equation,
but just know that
when I write out
the probability of a token
y at time t, what I mean
is the probability that
y(t) is a particular word.
So it's kind of a
variable assignment.
But so what actually is the
output of what we typically
call the text generation
model at this point
is actually this
vector of scores,
and then that vector gets
passed to the softmax function
to give us a probability
distribution over the set
of tokens in the vocabulary.
And then to actually
generate a token,
we can define what we call
a decoding algorithm, that
is a function that takes in
this distribution peak over all
the tokens of the vocabulary.
And it defines a function
for selecting a token
from this distribution
as the next token that
is produced by our NLG system.
And for that distribution to
be calibrated in such a way
that it means anything, we need
to train the model to actually
be able to do the task.
And so the most common way of
training text generation models
is to use maximum
likelihood training.
And despite its name,
we don't actually
maximize likelihoods, we
actually minimize negative log
likelihoods.
And what that actually is just
a multi class classification
task where each word
in our vocabulary
is a class that can be
predicted by the model.
And so at each step
in the sequence
we're actually trying to predict
the class that corresponds
to the word that comes next
in the sequence of text
that we're trying to train on.
And this word is often called
the gold or ground truth token.
That was just kind of
interchangeable vocabulary
that we use.
And another term for this
deep training algorithm
is teacher forcing.
So you might see
these expressions kind
of used interchangeably if
you read papers on this topic.
But so at each
step, you're really
computing a loss term,
that is the negative log
likelihood of predicting this
gold token y1 at every step.
So in these slides whenever
you see an asterisk
next to a y, that means that
this is a gold token that
comes from a training sequence.
And you could do this
for multiple steps
adding up the log
likelihoods along the way.
Eventually, you're
going to arrive
at the end of your
gold sequence,
and you'll be able to compute
gradients with respect
to this summed loss term for
every parameter in your model,
which allows you to update it so
that the next time around, when
you see the sequence,
your model is more
confident in the probability
that the sequence is
a correct sequence,
given the same context it
has seen before.
But most of this
should just be a recap
from previous lectures on
language modeling and machine
translation.
But now that we've got
that out of the way,
let's get to the fun part and
talk about some new topics.
The first one of which is
decoding, which is actually
one of my favorite topics in
natural language generation
research.
So if you recall, your
decoding algorithm
is really the
function that takes
in this induced
probability distribution
from your model over
the next possible tokens
that can be
generated and selects
which one of those tokens
should be outputted.
So once your model was
trained, this distribution
should be meaningful,
and you want
to be able to generate
a sensible next token.
And then you can use these
generated next tokens--
so the blue y hats here--
as inputs in the next
step of the model, which
allows you to recompute
a new distribution,
decode a new token,
repeat the process,
and eventually end up
with a full sequence
that your model has now
generated given a fixed
starting sequence of text.
And so let's talk a bit
about the algorithms
that we can use to decode
tokens from this distribution.
So you've actually
already seen some
of these in a previous lecture
on neural machine translation
I believe where you started
off by seeing a relatively
simple decoding algorithm
that nonetheless remains
very popular, argmax decoding.
And with argmax decoding
you pretty much just take
the highest probability
token from your distribution
as the decoded token
and feed it back
into the model to get the
distribution at the next step.
And you keep repeating this
process, and it's very nice,
and it's very convenient.
And you've also I think
learned about beam search
where you can scale up these
greedy methods by doing a wider
search over the set
of tokens that follow,
the set of most
likely tokens that
follow to try to find a
subsequence that is a lower
overall negative
log likelihood even
if in the intermediate
step it tends
to be higher than what would
be the argmax decoded token.
And while these greedy
methods work great
for machine translation
and in other tasks
as well, such as
summarization, they
do tend to be problematic in
many other text generation
tasks, particularly ones that
end up being more open ended.
So one of these big
problems that they have
is that they often end
up repeating themselves.
So here in this example
from Holtzmann et al 2020,
we can see that after
around 20 or sorry,
yeah, 60 tokens or
so of generation,
the model really devolves into
just repeating the same thing
over and over again.
And this actually tends to
happen a lot in text generation
systems.
Repetition was actually
one of the biggest problems
that we tried to tackle in
text generation for many years
and still face to this day.
And I think it's worth taking a
look at why repetition happens
a bit more analytically
so that you can perhaps
better understand the
interaction between your model
and your decoding algorithm.
So just as a quick little
visual demonstration,
here I'm showing you the step
by step negative log likelihoods
from two different
language models,
one based on recurrent
neural networks
and one based on a transformer
language model called GPT.
And I'm showing this plot for a
particular phrase I don't know,
which for anyone who's
worked in chat bots
has probably seen many times,
potentially in nightmares.
It's not a very interesting
plot, though what we do see
is that the
transformer model does
tend to be a bit less confident
in the probability of each word
than the recurrent
neural network does.
What's more
interesting though is
what happens if I repeat the
same phrase multiple times
in a row.
And one of the things
that we notice here
is that the repetition
of this phrase
actually causes the
token level negative log
likelihoods to get
lower and lower for each
of these tokens, which actually
means that the model is
becoming more confident that
these are the right tokens
and that they should
probably follow the preceding
context as we generate
it more times.
And this doesn't really
subside as the sequence
gets longer and longer.
And as you keep repeating
the same phrases again,
over and over again, the model
becomes more and more confident
the next time around it
should say the same thing.
And while this actually
kind of makes sense
and that if you say the phrase
let's say I'm tired 15 times,
it's a fair bet
that on a 16th time
you're actually going
to say it again,
it's not necessarily
the behavior
that we want our generation
systems to get stuck in.
Another interesting thing
to note here as an aside
is that this
behavior is actually
less problematic in
recurrent neural networks
than in transformer
language models.
So you can see
that for the LSTM,
the curve flattens
after a certain point.
And so if you remember in
perhaps a previous lecture
on why we might transform
our language models,
one of their
benefits is that they
don't have the
temporal bottleneck
of tracking a state, which a
recurrent neural network tends
to have.
And so the removal
of that bottleneck
actually ends up
making them more
prone to repetitive
behavior when you use
greedy algorithms to decode.
And so what can we actually
do to reduce repetition
since it's a pretty big
problem in these systems?
Well, there are actually quite
a few proposed approaches
in the last few years, some
of which I'll summarize here,
which range from
the kind of hacky
but surprisingly effective,
don't repeat any n-grams
at inference time.
But there's also been training
time approaches to do it,
such as having a
loss function that
minimizes the similarity
between hidden
activations at
different time steps,
or coverage loss that
penalizes attending
to the same tokens over time.
So if you change the inputs
that your model is allowed
to focus on, it's
naturally going
to produce different
text, or more recently
an unlikelihood objective
that actually penalizes
outputting the same
words, which we'll
talk a bit more about later.
But the truth is
that the problem here
really lies in using greedy
algorithms in the first place.
In many applications
of human language,
humans don't actually speak in
a probability maximizing way.
So if you look at this plot
from Holtzmann et al 2020,
it shows the per time step
probability of human written
text in orange and beam
search decoded text in blue
on the same graph.
And what you can see
is that beam search
decoded text tends to
be very high probability
with little variance over time.
And this makes a lot of
sense because it's literally
trying to maximize the
probability of the sequences
that it produces.
And a big part of that
is maximizing the step
by step probabilities of
the tokens that it uses.
But meanwhile we can see
that human error in text
is a lot more variable, often
actually dipping into very
low probability territory.
That actually makes
a lot of sense
if we could always predict human
text with high probability,
there would really be no reason
to listen to each other speak
since we know what
we were going to say.
But so ultimately what
we want to be able to do
is to match the uncertainty
of human language patterns
in how we decode text, which
is why, in many applications
that tend to have this
higher variability sampling
from these distributions
has kind of become
a go to decoding
method particularly
in creative generation tasks.
And so with sampling,
we take the distribution
over tokens that's
produced by our model
and we generate a token
randomly according
to the probability
mass that is assigned
to each potential option.
So rather than doing
any type of greedy step,
we use the probability
on each token
to give us a chance that
that token is generated.
And so this does allow us
to kind of get much more
stochasticity in the types
of tokens that are generated.
But a challenge
that pops up here
is that these
distributions tend to be
over a very large vocabulary.
And so even if there
is clearly tokens
that have a higher chance
of being generated,
the tail of the
distribution can often
be spread over a much larger
number of possible tokens.
And so this becomes
a bit of a problem
because these tokens
in the long tail
are probably
completely irrelevant
to the current context.
So they shouldn't
have any chance
of being selected
individually, but as
a group it ends up that there's
a decent chance that you
could output a completely
irrelevant token.
Even if 90% of your probability
mass is on relevant tokens,
that means that you have a
1 in 10 chance of outputting
something that completely throws
off your entire text generation
pipeline and it's
completely inane.
So to mitigate
this, the field has
developed a new
set of algorithms
that tries to prune
these distributions
at inference time.
And so top-k sampling is
kind of the most obvious way
to do this.
So here we recognize that most
of the tokens in our vocabulary
should have no probability
of being selected at all.
So we just truncate
the set of tokens
that we're allowed
to sample from
to be the k tokens with the
highest amount of probability
mass of the distributions.
And common values of k are often
5, 10, 20, sometimes up to 100.
But really it's
a hyper parameter
that you end up setting as
the designer of this system.
In general though
what's important to note
is that the higher you
make k, the more you'll
be able to generate
diverse outputs,
which is good because that's
what we're trying to do.
But you're also
going to increase
the chance of letting that long
tail seep in and generating
something that's
completely irrelevant
to the current context.
Oops, sorry.
Meanwhile if you
decrease k, your outputs
are going to be safer from
these long tail effects,
but your text may end up
being boring and generic
because your sampling
algorithm starts to look
a lot more greedy in nature.
And this kind of
shows the problem
of having a fixed k as
the number of tokens
that you can generate
from your distribution.
If your distribution
at a certain point
is pretty flat such
as in this example,
she said I never
blank, you might not
want to truncate a lot of
interesting options using
a small value of
k when there's so
many good choices that could
fit in this potential context.
Conversely in a
different example,
you might want to cut off
much more than let's say
your minimum k options
because only a subset of them
end up being quite suitable,
and higher k than is really
necessary lts that long tail
seep in and potentially ruin
your generation.
And so in response to this,
top-p or nucleus sampling
is a way around this issue.
So here instead of sampling
from a fixed number of tokens
at each step, you
sample from a fixed
amount of probability mass.
And so depending on the
flatness of your distribution,
you end up including a
variable number of tokens
that is kind of dynamically
changing depending
on how that probability mass is
spread across the distribution.
And so to kind of
describe this visually,
if you have three
different distributions
at a particular step to
generate a particular token in,
they're each going to prune
a different number of tokens
from the available set that
you can sample from, depending
on what the value
of P is and what
the peakiness of
that distribution
actually ends up being.
So I keep talking about
this concept of flatness
of a distribution being kind
of critical in understanding
how many tokens we can
actually end up sampling from.
And in fact, as we try to
use sampling algorithms,
we might find that the
model that we've learned
may not actually be producing
probability distributions that
lend themselves very nicely to
using these types of sampling
algorithms.
The distributions might be too
flat, they might be too peaky.
And in fact, what
we might want to do
is re-scale those
distributions to better fit
the decoding algorithm
that we might want to use.
And we can do this
with a method that
goes by a variety
of different names
which I call
temperature scaling.
And here what you do is that
you apply a linear coefficient
to every score for each
token before you pass it
through the softmax.
That temperature coefficient
is the same for every token.
So it's not dynamically changing
amongst your vocabulary,
it stays the same.
But what happens is
that that change ends up
being amplified by
the soft max function.
And what ends up happening
is that if your temperature
coefficient is
greater than 1, you're
actually going to make your
probability distribution much
more uniform.
In other words, you're
going to make it flatter.
Meanwhile if your temperature
coefficient is less than 1,
these scores are
going to increase,
which is going to make your
distributions more spiky
and make the probability
mass kind of be pushed
towards the most likely tokens.
One last thing to
note about temperature
is that it's not actually
a decoding algorithm,
it's just a way of re-balancing
your probability distribution.
So in fact, it can be applied to
all of the sampling algorithms
I described before, and
some greedy decoding
algorithms as well.
The only one whose
behavior is not
affected by softmax
temperature scaling
is argmax decoding,
because even though you
change the relative
magnitudes of the probability
mass in your distribution,
you don't actually
change the relative
ranking amongst tokens
in that distribution.
So argmax decoding will give
you the exact same output
as before.
But now that we're
thinking about how
we might change the distribution
that's produced by our model,
we might realize
that we might want
to change more than the
relative magnitudes I mentioned,
and also instead change
how they're ranked
with respect to one another.
Maybe in fact our model is
not a perfect approximation
of what the distribution
over tokens should be.
Perhaps the training
wasn't done right
or we didn't have enough
training data to actually make
it well calibrated.
And so if we decide that our
model isn't well calibrated
for the task that
we're doing, we
may want to bring in outside
information at decoding time.
And so here I want to talk a
bit about new classes of methods
that let us change
our model prediction
distributions at
inference time rather than
relying on a fixed static model
that's only been trained once.
And a cool way of doing
this that came out last year
is to actually use k nearest
neighbor language models
which allow you to re-calibrate
your output probability
distribution by using phrases
statistics from let's say
a much larger corpus.
And so what you
do in this method
is that you initialize
a large database
of phrases along with
vector representations
for those phrases.
And then at decoding
time, you can
search for the most similar
phrases in the database.
And so what you do is that
you take the representation
of the context that you
have from your model
and you compute a
similarity function
with all the representations
of the phrases
that you have stored.
And based off the
relative differences
amongst these different phrases
to your current context,
you can compute a distribution
over these most similar
phrases, and then you can
take the next tokens that
follow these phrases and add the
statistics around those phrases
to the distribution
from your model.
And so this allows you to really
re-balance the probability
distribution that your
model has given you
with this induced
distribution over phrases
and interpolate them together to
get a different estimate of how
likely certain words are.
One question right now is,
how do you know what to cache?
Yeah, so that's a
really good question.
I guess the answer there
is that you could probably
decide on what might be
a salient set of phrases
depending on let's
say named entities
that you might be
interested in or phrases
that you know your model's
distribution doesn't handle
very well.
But I'm pretty sure
in this work they
took every phrase in
their training corpus,
cached it, and then relied
on very efficient algorithms
for doing the search over
representation similarity
to actually find the
most likely ones.
Though they did prune
the number of phrases
that they actually used
to make this distribution,
the phrase distributions that it
wasn't over the entire corpus.
So it's fantastic
that we can now
re-balance these
distributions if we find
that our model is doing poorly.
Particularly this
might be relevant
if let's say we're
jumping into a new domain.
So we've trained a
nice big generation
model on Wikipedia
text and now we're
going into something that's
more linked to the stories.
We might want to use
this type of system
to get distributions
from phrases from there.
But it's also possible
that we may not always
have a good database of phrases
to help us calibrate output
distributions for
all the types of text
that we want to generate.
And so luckily
last year, there's
also been new approaches
that look at doing
this in a gradient based way.
And so the idea here is
that you can actually
define some type of
external objective using
a classifier that we typically
call a discriminator.
But in this figure from
the paper that proposed it,
they called an attribute model.
And what that classifier
does is that it approximates
some property that you'd
like to encourage your text
to exhibit as you decode.
So perhaps it's a
sentiment classifier
because you are working
on a dialogue model
and you want to encourage
positive sounding comments.
So then what you do is
that as you generate text,
you input the output of
your text generation model
to this attribute
model, and there's
some tricks on how you should
do that in order to actually
not have it be a discrete token
that you provide to the model
but instead a
distribution over tokens.
But the important thing is that
if you do this the right way
by using the soft distribution
of tokens as inputs
to the attribute
model, it's going
to be able to compute a
score for the sequence
that it receives.
So that if it's a
sentiment classifier,
it can evaluate how
positive of the sequence
you provided to it.
And then what you can do is
that you can compute gradients
with respect to this
property and backpropagate
those gradients back to your
text generation model directly.
But instead of updating
the parameters, which
is what you would
do during training,
you instead update the
intermediate activations
at each layer of your model,
which you can then forward
propagate to compute
a new distribution
over the sets of tokens.
And so it's a neat
trick that allows
you to do real time
distribution updating based
on some outside discriminator
that's allowing you to update
your internal representations
of the sequence
such that it hopefully
generates something
more positive at the
outputs in this case.
So these distribution
re-balancing methods
either based off
nearest neighbor search
or on using some
type of discriminator
are quite promising
and interesting,
but they also end up being
quite computationally intensive.
In the first case,
you're essentially
doing a search over
thousands of phrases
to re-balance your distribution.
In the second you're
doing multiple
forwards and backwards
passes at every step
to try and make
the tokens exhibit
a particular behavior more.
And unfortunately,
neither of them
actually stop you from
decoding that sequences either.
It's possible that even
after you re-balance
your distribution,
you're still generating
something that looks terrible.
So in practice, something that
we often use in text generation
to improve our sequence outputs
are what are called re-rankers.
And so what we do here is
that we actually decode
multiple sequences perhaps
using sampling or a wider
greedy search, say maybe 10.
And then what we can do is
that we can initialize a score
to evaluate the
sequences we produce
and re-rank these sequences
according to the score.
And the simplest thing we can do
is to actually just score them
by the likelihood given
by the model for example.
Especially if we're using
a sampling algorithm,
we might want to make sure that
we didn't generate something
that totally deviated from
good text which would tend
to have a very high perplexity.
So this perplexity is perhaps
a good re-ranking function.
It's just important
to be careful as well
that repetitive sequences tend
to have very low perplexity as
well.
And so if you rank
by perplexity,
you're likely to just generate
something you were trying
to avoid in the first case.
But we can also make
our re-rankers evaluate
more complex behaviors.
In the same way that we could
use gradient based methods
to update our distributions to
exhibit more complex behaviors,
we can actually just take
those same attribute models
and use them as re-rankers
to re-rank a fixed
set of sequences
rather than have
them back propagate
gradients to the main model.
And so we can use
them to rank things
such as style, discourse,
factuality, logical
consistency.
But just be careful if
your re-ranker ends up
being poorly calibrated.
Just because you've
trained a classifier
to predict whether a sentence
makes a factual statement
doesn't actually
mean that it will
be good at ranking different
factual statements with respect
to one another.
And finally a nice
thing about re-rankers
as well is that you can use
multiple re-rankers in parallel
if there's multiple
properties you want to score
and come up with, let's
say, a weighted average
of different ranking
scores to decide
on what might be the
best sequence according
to different properties.
But so to recap what we've
talked about in terms
of decoding, I want to
mention that decoding is still
a very challenging problem in
natural language generation
that we haven't really
figured out yet.
Our algorithms
still don't really
reflect the way that humans
choose words when they speak,
and our best approaches
are currently
based on trying to calibrate
probability distributions
produced by models to perhaps
be more representative
of human likelihood.
But the truth is the human
language distribution
is quite noisy and doesn't
reflect the simple properties
that our decoding
algorithms often
capture such as
probability maximization.
But different
decoding algorithms
do allow us to
perhaps inject biases
that encourage
different properties
of coherent natural
language generation.
That's allowed us to make
promising improvements
in this area as well.
And in fact, some of the
most impactful advances
in NLG over the last
few years have really
come from simple but very
effective modifications
to decoding algorithms
because you can often
have impact across a very
large number of tasks
by making a good change
to a decoding algorithm.
But really there's
still a lot more work
to be done in the space,
and hopefully many of you
will be the ones to make
these next breakthroughs.
I'm happy to take
questions at this point
if any have popped up.
Oh, here's one question.
How do you evaluate,
how do you tell
whether re-balance
distribution is better?
And if I editorialized
from there,
I guess you're
admitting on this slide
that you can't just
look at the probability.
Yeah.
So yes, you can't just
look at the probability.
I mean, there is a
certain amount of trust
that happens that if you don't
trust that your ranker is
giving you a better assessment
of whether you've produced
a quality piece of text,
perhaps you shouldn't
be using that re-ranker
in the first place.
And hopefully you've actually
means tested that re-ranker
to actually show
that it has, that it
improves the quality of text.
But we're going to talk a lot
more about how you can actually
evaluate the quality of text
later on, though I should warn
you ahead of time that
the answers are not
as direct and complete as
you might want them to be.
And in fact, there's a lot of
room for interpretation in how
you would actually do that.
Maybe you should go
on about that later,
but I guess people are puzzled
on that because there's
another question that's asking.
It was saying that
you said, you don't
know how to make a model
choose words like a human,
how do we model different humans
from different backgrounds,
et cetera?
Yeah, that's a
really good question.
The answer to that is
that you could potentially
try to do kind of fine
tuning on the language
distribution of a particular
human starting from let's say
a pre-trained language model
since you'll probably never
have enough data to only use
a single human's outputs,
or you could try to do some
of these re-balancing methods
that we've spoken about to
perhaps use those to actually
make your distributions approach
a particular human's language
distribution more closely.
So in the gradient based
methods that I described,
I could perhaps train a
single language model only
on my type of language, even if
I have a much larger one that's
trained on a much larger
corpus of language
from different
speakers, but then
try to make it so
that my model ranks
the outputs of the main model.
I've got a question.
Yep.
So nucleus sampling
and top-k sampling
are really effective
in practice,
and you made the
argument that there
are all these little tiny things
with very little probability
mass but it sums up to
more probability mass.
But if it sums up to
more probability mass
than they actually should have
under the real distribution
of human language,
shouldn't our models
have been trained to put less
probability mass on them?
And so why aren't our language
models better in that case?
Like why do we have this
issue if they actually
are getting more probability
than they should?
Yeah, that's a
really good question.
I think the answer to that is
that the way we train them,
which I'll get to in a bit
is really trying to do,
is really trying to model the
distribution of human language
as it sees in its
training corpus.
And it's actually surprisingly
effective at doing that.
But at the same time,
when we actually
start to use these
language models out
of the box in the NLG task that
we work with, first of all,
there's always slight deviations
in the distribution of text
that we're actually trying to
model for the task we're doing,
and what the large
corpus we trained on
was in the first place,
which can make these decoding
algorithms less effective.
And the second
thing I would note
is that even though these
decoding algorithms are quite
effective in practice,
they aren't doing
what humans do when we speak.
At no point when
a human speaks are
we potentially
trying to maximize
the probability of a
potential next token
or randomly select a word
amongst a set of tokens.
We ultimately have
world models that
drive how we select the tokens
that we choose to say in order
to make our points.
And that's very
different from what
we get in probabilistic
language models.
Now should we throw away
probabilistic language models?
No, because as you mentioned
they end up working quite well.
But at some point
we also do need
to mitigate these differences
between how humans end up
speaking and how language
models end up modeling language.
Thanks.
So now that John has primed us
perfectly for what comes next,
let's jump back into the
training these models
because the pipeline that
I framed earlier being,
you train your model, then you
choose your decoding algorithm
depending on properties you're
interested in, is great.
But the truth is
there's interactions
between your decoding model
and your training algorithm
that you might want to be
thinking about during training,
which is not really what
we're doing right now.
And so if you recall
the training algorithm
that we've proposed
up to this point
is one where we just try to
minimize the negative log
likelihood of the next
token in a sequence
given the preceding
ones at every step.
And as I mentioned this
actually works pretty well
for training autoregressive
models of human language.
But it actually causes a few
issues, which John hinted at.
So in the next few
slides, I'm going
to talk a bit about
these issues and then
highlight some training
solutions to these problems
that I found
interesting, or that I
think are important
from the last few years.
So the first issue
is actually one
that I hinted at in
the last section, which
is that training with
maximum likelihood
tends to discourage
textual diversity.
And I showed the sequence
on a slide earlier
as an example of
greedy algorithms
being prone to generating
repetitive sequences, which
is just about the worst form of
diversity that you could get.
But greedy algorithms
are just trying
to maximize the probability
of the sequences
that they produce.
So it can really only be prone
to repetitive and un-diverse
phrases if those phrases
are scored highly
by the model to begin with.
And that ends up being
one of the issues
with maximum
likelihood training is
that it tends to end up
favoring generic expressions
because those are the ones
that are often the most likely
in human language production.
But as we all know and
as I mentioned earlier,
human language production isn't
about maximizing the likelihood
of the words that we produce.
So even though we might produce
generic phrases more often
than ungeneric phrases,
that's not the goal
that we're setting out
with when we speak.
There's a lot more
to communication
that really isn't synthesized
by a training objective that
tries to maximize probability
over the human language that's
being read.
So how can we end up
mitigating this problem?
So an interesting
approach that I really
like that came out
last year was actually
proposed by Welleck
et al, which was
called unlikelihood training.
And so here what you
do is that you actually
discourage the production
of particular tokens
by the model in
certain contexts.
And so what happens
that this loss term here
decreases as the probability
of the y-neg tokens decreases.
So for any token that you
don't want to generate,
as the probability of generating
that token goes down, so
does the loss term, which
means that you're not actually
updating the model as much
for this particular behavior.
What's important, though,
is that you still have
your teacher forcing objective.
So what's going to
happen is that the model
is going to learn to capture
both the distribution
of language from the training
corpus which it needs to do
to learn how to generate text.
But also it's going to learn
how to not say particular words
that you might not want it to.
And then what you can do is that
you can set this list of words
that you don't want the model
to generate to actually be words
that you've already
generated before.
And so in essence you're
teaching the model to not
say the same things again.
And that's just
naturally going to limit
the amount of repetition
that your model is going
to be able to spit
out and you're
going to be able to
generate more diverse texts
as the result as well.
But a second and
very important issue
that comes from training
with maximum likelihood
is what we often call
exposure bias, which
is that the context
that we train on
to generate the
next token are going
to look different from the ones
that we see at generation time.
And so why might that be?
Well, so what happens
during training
is that we always get a
token from a gold document
or human text as input.
It's the gold sequence
as we call it.
But then during
generation, we're
feeding our previously
generated tokens back
into the model as
the input rather than
these teacher forced tokens that
are from the gold documents.
And so that set of
tokens is actually
quite affected by things like
the distributions produced
by our model and the decoding
algorithm we use to get tokens.
And so can this end
up being a problem?
Well, yes because as
we've seen before,
the types of text that
our model generates
are often not a very close
approximation of human language
patterns in the training set.
And so there's going to be
an imbalance between the type
of text that our
model has learned
to predict, and to expect
to see, and the type of text
that it will see once we
actually start decoding.
And so once your model starts
receiving its own inputs which
are going to deviate from the
distribution of text to expect,
It's going to be very
challenging for it
to be able to generate coherent
text going forward because it's
not going to really know how to
synthesize its own information
that it's generated.
And so there's a
variety of ways to try
to counter this exposure
bias issue and many more
that that continue to come out.
And unfortunately there's
not really enough time
to talk about all of
them, so I've added
slides to discuss
two of them that
are based on semi-supervised
learning here.
But I really want to focus
more on two other approaches
that I personally
find very interesting.
The first is called
sequence rewriting.
And so in this
setting, your model
first learns to
retrieve a sequence
from an existing database
of human written prototypes.
So it's kind of like our nearest
neighbor decoders earlier will
be cached a bunch of phrases.
Here you cache a
bunch of sequences
that might be similar to the one
that you're supposed to produce
for this new situation.
And then what we do is that
once we take this sequence
and retrieve it,
we learn to edit it
by doing things like adding,
removing, or modifying tokens
to more accurately reflect the
context that we're actually
given rather than the one that
this original sequence was
designed for in the first place.
And so we can still
use an algorithm here
that tries to maximize
likelihood for training.
But because there's this sort
of latent variable of retrieving
the right prototype
that's involved,
it makes it less likely that
our generated text ends up
suffering from exposure
bias because you're already
starting from something that
looks more like a training
sequence that you
might have seen.
Another general class of
possibilities we can do
is to let our model learn
to generate text by learning
from its own samples.
And this naturally
maps itself nicely
to reinforcement learning,
which is actually
one of my favorite ways to
learn how to generate text.
In the setting you're going
to cast your text generation
model as a Markov decision
process where your state S is
the model's representation
of the preceding context
that you see, your
actions A are the words
that can be generated,
your policy is the decoder,
and your rewards are provided
by some type of external score.
And here you can learn
many different behaviors
for your text generation
model by rewarding it when
it exhibits those behaviors.
And so to kind of
quickly join this framing
with the perspective of
the text generation models
that we've seen so
far, you're going
to be taking actions
by sampling words hat
y from the distribution,
and then you're
going to feed them
back into the input
to get a new state,
which is what we've
been doing at every point.
What's different though, is
that as you generate text,
you're using some
external reward function
to compute rewards for each
token that you generate.
So you're rewarding every
action that you take.
And then you scale the sample
loss on this particular token
that you generate by
this reward, which
is going to encourage
the model to generate
the sequence in similar
contexts if the reward is high.
So to put it very
clearly, you're
minimizing the
negative log likelihood
of your sample token.
So here it's not a gold token.
Notice the hat that
is on the y expression
in the reward function.
And then you're going to
compute a reward for that token
and scale this negative log
likelihood by that reward.
And so if the reward
is high, the model
is going to be more
likely to generate
the same sequence in a
similar context in the future.
If the reward is low,
it will be less likely.
But this sort of brings
up a natural question,
what can we actually
use as a reward
to encourage the behaviors we
want in this text generation
system?
That's really up to you as
you design your generation
pipeline.
A common practice
in the early days
of using RL for
text generation was
to set the reward to
be the final evaluation
metric that you are
going to evaluate on.
And so here instead of having
a unique reward for each
generated token at
every time step,
you would just take the
final sequence score
that you get and reward every
token in the generated sequence
with that value.
And this was absolutely magical.
You would set your evaluation
metric as the reward,
and you'd end up learning to
get more reward because that's
what RL algorithms do, which
in turn means that you were
learning to generate
sequences that do better
on your evaluation metric.
So NLG benchmark scores were
shooting through the roof.
We were making real progress.
But it was actually all a lie.
Turns out as I'll talk
about later evaluation
metrics particularly
for text generation
are just approximations,
and it's not always clear
that optimizing to
those approximations
is going to lead to more
and better coherent text
generation.
Instead, oftentimes
what ends up happening
is that it just learns
to exploit the noise
in the evaluation metric.
And in fact, in their
large work where
they introduce Google's
neural machine translation
system in 2016, Google
researchers generally
found that training machine
translation models with RL
and BLEU scores as
rewards didn't actually
improve the translation quality
at all even if it did lead
to higher BLEU scores.
But so, designing
your reward function
is a very important
problem in RL
for actually learning the
behavior that you want.
And I've listed
some cool work here
on how you can actually learn
to tie fairly complex behaviors
to reward functions by actually
initializing the scores they
use as rewards as
neural networks that
get trained on an auxiliary
task ahead of time,
but can then be used to provide
scores as rewards to the system
that you produce.
So to go back to
our example earlier
of trying to create a dialogue
agent that is very positive
and only says
positive things, you
could use a sentiment
classifier to produce
a reward for the sequences
that you generate.
And so that's a lot of fun.
Unfortunately,
despite all the fun
that you can have using RL to
train text generation engines,
there's a bit of a
dark side too, which
is that reinforcement
learning algorithms can
be notoriously unstable.
And so to get these text
generation systems to learn
with RL, you often
have to be thorough
in tuning different dials in
your model setup accurately.
There's many of them.
Two of them that I think
are worth mentioning are one
that you always need to
pre-train with teacher forcing.
You generally can't train
with reinforcement learning
from scratch, and also
you need to provide
some type of baseline reward
that your model should
be achieving.
So for example, BLEU score
which I described earlier
is always a positive
value unless it's zero.
What that means that if you
use it alone as a reward,
every single sequence
that you sample
ends up being encouraged
in the future.
So what you want to have
is some type of baseline
that is an expectation
of how much reward
you should be getting which can
be subtracted from the reward
that you actually get so
that you can discourage
certain behaviors as well.
One last note about this
is that neural networks
are quite good at finding the
easiest way to learn something.
So if there's a way to
exploit your reward function,
it will find a way
to do it particularly
that's easier than learning
the behavior that you
want it to learn.
So something to remember
that's kind of important
if you try to use reinforcement
learning for text generation
systems, particularly because
they're such a large action
space of words that
it can generate to try
to accomplish their behaviors.
So to end the
section, I just want
to start off by saying
that in general we still
use teacher forcing as a
primary means of learning
to generate coherent text.
It has diversity
issues, but it still
lets us learn a model with
decent text generation
abilities.
One thing I haven't focused
too much on in this lecture
is the type of model that you
can use to actually generate
text because they tend to
be less universal and much
more designed to very
specific end tasks.
But in general a
common approach in NLG
is to try to design a
neural architecture that
allows your model
to be perhaps less
sensitive to the problems
of teacher forcing
or to address them with
additional loss terms that
are perhaps task specific.
Exposure bias though is a
problem everywhere, pretty
much regardless of your
neural architecture.
And to kind of mitigate
it you can either
train your model to
be more resistant
to its own distribution
changes through things
like semi supervised learning,
or you can change your pipeline
such that you're learning
to make modifications
to an existing sequence that
you retrieved from your training
set rather than trying to
learn how to generate sequences
from scratch.
The caveat there is that as
the type of text that you're
generating gets
longer and longer,
doing this kind of
retrieval and editing
becomes just as
challenging as generating
from scratch in many cases.
And finally, you can
use reinforcement
learning as another
means of learning
from your own examples.
And in effect, you
can also use it
to encourage different
behaviors than just likelihood
maximization.
But this type of learning can
end up being quite unstable
and unless your
reward is well shaped,
the model can often
learn to exploit it.
Are there online
language simulators
where you can train
with RL online
or are you only talking
about training offline?
No, in this setting
we're generally
talking about training offline.
So you train it all
ahead of time and then
you use your model as it's been
trained the first time around.
OK, Yeah.
So now we've finally
reached the section
that I hinted at earlier
on a very important topic,
evaluation, which to be honest
is something that we should be
thinking about
before we even start
designing a model or a training
algorithm or a decoding
algorithm.
It's how can we actually
check that our method is--
how can we act-- how
are we actually going
to evaluate that our
method is even working?
And today I want to talk a bit
about three types of evaluation
metrics.
So first we'll talk about
automatic eval metrics
because generally you
need to be able to rapidly
prototype and diagnose
failures in your model.
So it's essential to be able to
have this quick feedback even
if it's very coarse.
And in automatic
evaluation metrics,
we've traditionally used what
I'm calling content overlap
metrics which focus on how much
a sequence explicitly resembles
another sequence usually
in terms of word or phrase
matching.
Lately there's also been new
automatic evaluations that
are model based where we try to
use advances, and embeddings,
and neural models to define
more implicit similarity
measures between sequences.
And finally we'll talk a bit
about human evaluations, which
are kind of the gold standard
of evaluating text generation.
But they also do have downsides
that we'll get to as well.
And I just want to note
that some of these slides
here are actually
repurposed from slides
from Asli Celikyilmaz,
who's a leading
expert on NLG evaluation.
But so let's jump in.
So content overlap
metrics generally
compute an explicit similarity
score between two sequences,
the one that's been
generated by your model
and some gold standard reference
sequence that was attached
to the inputs that you had.
So in other words, a
sequence that you know
was an appropriate generation
for the inputs you had.
And these metrics are often
a popular starting point
because they're fast
and very efficient,
which is their main benefit.
As long as you have a reference
sequence to compare to,
you can compute z-scores
rapidly to get feedback.
And I'm going to categorize
them into two zones here
first, n-gram
overlap metrics that
compute different functions
of word and word-like overlap
and semantic overlap
metrics which
involve more complex
overlap functions based
off semantic structures.
Unfortunately besides
being fast and efficient,
most N-gram overlap
metrics don't actually
give you a great approximation
of sequence quality a lot
of times.
They're already not
ideal for something
like machine translation where
there can be multiple ways
to translate the same sequence
with things like synonyms,
and they get progressively
much worse for tasks that
are more open-ended than MT.
So for example in summarization,
the longer output texts
make it naturally harder
to measure something
using word match, and it's
something like dialogue,
it's incredibly open-ended
and in fact, you
can have multiple responses
to a particular utterance that
mean the same thing but
don't use any common words.
And so we can illustrate this
with a simple, fairly contrived
example where you have a
dialogue context utterance that
asks a question such as,
are you going to Antoine's
incredible CS224N lecture, a
completely unbiased reference
text derived from a human,
and then a dialogue agent that
spits out different answers,
such as yes which gets a pretty
high score on our n-gram
overlap metrics, or you know it
which already scores a lot
lower despite depicting
the exact same
idea, or yup which
actually gets a score of 0.
Meanwhile, a completely
incorrect answer, heck no,
gets the highest score
out of all of them,
which kind of
points to the issue
when you use n-gram
overlap measures
in a lot of applications,
you're going
to be missing the
salient elements of what
the generated sequence
should capture,
and instead be getting stylistic
similarities between text
even as you miss the
most important context.
And if you prefer
empirical validations
to contrived examples,
it's actually
been shown that many dialogue
evaluation metrics don't really
correlate well with
human judgments at all.
And this gets worse as your
sequence length increases
typically.
So with an open-ended task
like story generation,
you can get improved
scores by just matching
a whole lot of stop
words that have nothing
to do with the content
of the story itself.
We also have another
category of overlap metrics
that I'll call semantic
overlap metrics because they
don't necessarily tie directly
to the words you used,
but instead try to create
conceptual representations
of the generated and
reference outputs instead.
So the center one
here, spice for example
creates a scene graph
of your generated text
and then compares that
to your reference caption
to see how similar this more
semantic representation ends
up being.
But clearly, there's
some limitations
to how well explicit
content overlap
metrics can do, particularly
as we start thinking
about more open-ended tasks.
So in response over
the last few years,
there's been a focus on
using model-based metrics
whose representations come
from machine learning models,
and where they can be
used to actually evaluate
the fidelity of generated text.
And these are nice because
there's no more needing
explicit matches between
words in your reference
and generated text.
Instead, you can rely on
much more implicit notions
of similarity that you
get from word embeddings.
And so there's been a lot of
models developed in this area.
Some of the original
ones kind of
focused on defining
composition functions
over the embedding of words
in your generated in reference
sequences, and then
computing a distance
between the compositions
of the two sequences.
Some more involved
takes on this idea
are things like word
mover's distance
where here you actually
try to map word
vectors in both your generated
and reference sequences
into pairs with one another.
So each word vector is
paired to another word vector
in the opposite sequence and
the distance between them
is computed.
And then you allow
the evaluation
metric to actually compute
the optimal matching
between these pairs of words,
such as the total distances
minimized.
And BERTSCORE which
has become quite
popular over the last year or
so as an evaluation metric is
pretty much just
word mover's distance
but using contextualized
BERT embeddings
to compute these distances.
Sentence mover's
similarity is kind
of another extension of
word mover's similarity
that adds sentence embeddings
from recurrent neural networks
to this distance
optimization and that
allows it to be more effective
for evaluating let's say
long multi-sentence
text as opposed
to just single sentences.
And finally last year
there was a new model named
BLEURT, which is actually
a regression model that's
based on BERT.
And here it takes a
pair of sentences,
the reference on
the generated one
and returns a score that
indicates to what extent
the candidate is grammatical
and conveys the meaning
of the reference text.
So we can talk about a lot
more evaluation metrics that
are computed automatically,
and there's far more of them
than I actually
mentioned though they
do tend to fit in those two
categories that I described.
But it's important to remember
that at the end of the day,
the true mark of an NLG
system's performance
is whether it's valuable
to the human user that
has to interact with it
or read the text that's
produced from it.
And unfortunately,
automatic metrics
tend to fall short
of replicating
human opinions of the
quality of generated text.
And that's why for this
reason human evaluations
are viewed as the most
important form of evaluation
for text generation systems.
Almost all work in NLG
generally include some form
of human evaluation,
particularly
if the task is more open-ended.
And if it doesn't
well, let me be frank,
you should probably be
skeptical of any claim that's
being made by that work.
And, finally, another
use of human evaluations
is that in addition to
evaluating model performance,
you can also use them
to actually train
new machine learning models
that are meant to be evaluated,
that are meant to serve as
evaluation scoring functions
themselves.
So I guess the main thing to
mention about human evaluations
since we could talk
about them for a while is
that they're both very simple
but also very difficult to run.
They're simple because
you generally just need
to find judges and
ask them to rate
an intrinsic dimension of the
quality of your generated text.
So you have to define
a set of criteria
that you decide is
important for the task
that you're designing
a system for,
and that can be
things like fluency
where you just measure things
like grammar, spelling, word
choice.
Does this actually look
like human language?
Factuality, does
the text accurately
reflect facts that are
described in the context?
Common sense, does
it sort of follow
the logical rules of the
world that we might expect?
But once you've
defined these criteria,
you can have humans evaluate the
generated text for how well it
actually produces
text that caters
to these particular criteria.
One thing to note here is that
while these dimensions are
common and repeated across
different evaluations,
they can often be
referred to by other names
and explained to evaluators
in different terms,
and be measured
in different ways.
And in fact, one of the
problems with human evaluations
is that across works they tend
to be very unstandardized which
can make the replication of
human results quite difficult.
And that's why when you
read text generation papers,
you rarely see a comparison
of human evaluation
scores between two
different studies
even if they evaluated
the same dimensions.
But another set of issues
with human evaluations
beyond the fact that
they're slow, expensive,
and unstandardized is
that humans themselves
aren't actually perfect.
I guess there's a few negatives
that I can say about humans,
even though we're all humans
is that we tend to not
be very consistent folks, often
changing our minds about how we
view something
depending on something
as trivial as the time of day.
We don't always
reason in the way
that we're expected
to when presented
with a task such as
evaluating something.
We can lose concentration
and not really be
focused on what we were doing.
And we can often
misinterpret what
let's say a human
evaluation is asking
us to do such that we inject
our own biases into the task.
And on top of all
of these things,
when we run human
evaluations, we're
also dealing with the
fact that one of the big
motivators that our
human judges have
is to do the task as
quickly as possible, which
isn't a great mix, particularly
if we want them to really give
us high quality ratings.
But humans are kind
of the best thing
that we have to actually give
us the most accurate assessments
of whether text generation
systems are doing well
so we do the best that we can.
I'm actually going
to skip this slide,
but I mentioned earlier that one
of the things that we can also
do is use human ratings to
train models to actually predict
scores for text itself.
And so two systems that do
something along these lines I
provided citations
to here so that you
can take a look at them if
you're curious later on.
But so the takeaways
I kind of want
you to get from the section are
that evaluation is quite hard,
and particularly
in text generation.
So content overlap metrics do
provide a good starting point
for evaluating the
quality of generated text.
If you run these
n-gram overlap metrics
and they show scores that are
worse than they should be,
that's the first sign
that you have a problem.
But they're generally not
good enough on their own.
Model based metrics
tend to be more
correlated with human judgments
than content overlap ones
particularly as the
tasks become more
open-ended such as
dialogue and storytelling.
But the downside there
is that they're not
very interpretable
unlike with the content
overlap metric where you
can say exactly, oh, this
is why this score is this way
it's because these words match
up with these words, with a
model based metric you get
a much more implicit
definition of similarity which
while useful is also
less interpretable.
Human judgments are absolutely
critical because even
if they're inconsistent
and sometimes don't
do the task that
you want them to,
humans are actually able
to intrinsically evaluate
dimensions that we don't even
know how to formulate using
any type of automatic metric.
But lastly slightly
unrelated to what
I've spoken about this
section, I just I just
want to say that the number
one evaluator of any NLG
system that you create
should really be you.
Look at your model's
outputs as perhaps you
do a project that
involves NLG can really
be worth days,
weeks, and sometimes
months of staring at evaluation
metrics that are perhaps
a bit uninformative.
So if you design
NLG systems, make
sure to evaluate your own
generations very consistently.
So in this last section, I
think it's quite important
to talk about ethical topics
in natural language generation
as well because ultimately
while NLG really
allows us to tackle new and
interesting applications,
if we're not capable we
can end up deploying fairly
dangerous and harmful systems.
And as a warning,
I just want to say
that some of the content
on the next few slides
is going to potentially
be quite uncomfortable.
But I think it's important
to make very clear how
these systems can
go very, very wrong.
And without picking on
a particular example,
I do perhaps think that one
of the most famous examples
of this was the Tay
dialogue chatbot which was
released onto Twitter in 2016.
And within 24 hours
it had started
making some very
nasty comments that
exhibited racist, sexist,
anti-Semitic, white supremacist
meanings, which is
ultimately probably not what
the designers of
Tay had in mind.
So what actually ended up
going wrong with Tay, well,
here's the thing,
Tay behaved exactly
as we should have
expected it would.
It was designed to
learn to exhibit
the conversational
patterns of the users
that it interacted
with and it did that.
NLG models are very
good at capturing
the language distribution
of their training examples.
That's been the one
thing that we've
been remarkably consistent
on in the last few years.
And it turns out if their
training examples end up
having toxic content, they will
learn to repeat that content.
And this is perhaps
no clearer than if you
look at what
pre-trained language
models have to say about let's
say different demographics.
So if you remember, large
pre-trained language
models that underlie
many modern NLG systems,
they're trained on
massive corpora of text
which are often opaque and
crawled from online resources.
If it turns out that those
corpora have toxic content,
the language models are going
to learn it, and in fact
make it even worse.
And then it turns out that
if you prompt these language
models for certain
pieces of information,
it can spit out
that toxic content
showing very different
opinions across gender,
races, sexual orientations.
Now you can see that
it would actually
be rare to ask a
language model to weigh
in with their opinions
on this matter,
but you do have to ask yourself
if this type of information
is encoded in the model in some
way, in what other ways could
these learned patterns end up
being reflected by this model
once it's actually
deployed in practice?
And that kind of leads
us to the second problem
with these language models.
We actually don't really
know how information ends up
being learned and encoded by
them, which means that we don't
have a rigorous understanding
of what types of inputs
are going to trigger
what types of outputs.
And in fact, Wallace et al
showed in their EMNLP 2019 work
that this was a big problem
because if you prime
these models with particularly
adversarial inputs,
they would generally devolve
immediately into producing
very toxic content.
In other words, what it took
Tay 24 hours to learn how to do,
these systems can kind
of do out of the box
if primed with the
wrong examples.
And unfortunately,
the wrong examples
end up being a lot less nasty
than we might have expected,
a lot less nasty than the
ones on the previous slide
at the very least.
But in a work at EMNLP Findings
last year, a research group
showed that much more
innocuous looking inputs
could actually prime these
language models to go on pretty
toxic diatribes as before.
It wasn't as consistent
as in the previous work,
but it was still often enough.
And these examples
really go to show
that we need to be careful with
how these systems are deployed.
If you have an NLG system,
you need safeguards to stop it
from outputing harmful content.
And this goes
beyond the examples
of the toxic and toxicity
bias that I've shown today,
a model that can be
primed to generate
incorrect or
unfactual information
can be quite dangerous too.
And also NLG models
shouldn't be deployed
without an understanding
of who its users will be.
And there's always going to be
adversarial users for any model
that you create
even if you can't
think of them in the moment.
And that leads us
to the final point,
which is that the
advances in NLG
have really allowed us to
build text production systems
for many new applications.
As we do this though,
it's important to ask
does the content that
we're building a system
to automatically generate
for easy human ingestion,
does it really need to be
generated automatically?
And I think a good
example of this
is the work of Zeller's
et al at NeurIPS 2019,
which showed off the potential
dangers of fake news generators
from pre-trained
language models.
I actually thought
this was a great work
and it highlighted many
of the defenses that
could be developed against a
fake news generations system.
But the point is more so
that you should always
imagine that any
tool that you create
could be used in a negative way.
So a storytelling NLG
system can also potentially
be repurposed to do
fake news generation.
And you should really
always ask yourself
whether the positive
applications
of a particular
technology outweigh
the potential negative ones.
And that turns out to often
not be an easy question.
So I guess as concluding
thoughts for today, I just
want to mention that if you
start interacting with NLG
systems in practice,
you're quickly
going to see the fairly
large limitations that they
tend to have.
Even in tasks where
we've achieved a larger
amount of progress at
building systems that
can do the task
fairly well, there's
still a lot of
improvements that can be
made to make them even better.
In pretty much any NLG task at
the same time, evaluating it
effectively remains
a huge challenge.
We often have to rely
on humans to give us
the best estimates of how
well our system is doing.
And so, an area where a large
improvement would really
kind of bootstrap
larger improvements
in many other areas
of NLG would be
to find better automatic
evaluation for NLP systems.
On the other hand, on
a very optimistic note,
I do want to say that with the
advent of large-scale language
models, deep NLG research
hasn't been reset,
but it's never been easier
to jump in the space
and start playing
around with the systems,
and designing cool new tools
that can help humans ingest
content and information more
rapidly and more efficiently.
And as a result,
I think that it's
one of the most exciting
areas of NLP to work in.
And I think that if you
start working on it as well
you'll feel the same way.
And I would encourage
you to do so.
So thanks a lot for
having me today.
It was really exciting.