OK, so hi, everyone.
Welcome back to CS224N.
So today we get to have the
second of our invited speakers
for this quarter.
And so given all
of the excitement
that there's been about
transformer pre-trained
language models and
all the great things
have been done with them,
we're especially excited today
to be able to welcome
Colin Raffel who's
been one of the
key people who've
been pushing the exploration
of large pre-trained language
models.
In particular, he was very
interested in the development
of the T5 language model which
he'll be telling you plenty
about today.
But to tell you a
few more sentences.
So Colin worked for a number
of years at Google Brain,
including working with Geoff
Hinton on capsule networks.
He then got interested in
the effectiveness of transfer
using large pre-trained
language models.
And as part of the
work on that, he
started together
with other people
on building even bigger large
pre-trained language models
and doing a lot
of investigations
with those, which
led to the T5 papers
that you'll be
hearing about today.
So welcome, Colin.
Right, yeah, thanks so
much for the introduction
and for having me.
It's definitely an honor to
speak at the legendary CS224N
class.
So yeah, I'm going to be talking
today about large language
models kind of in general
but focusing specifically
on this model T5 that
we released about a year
and a half ago.
I'll be presenting five or
so papers that kind of should
represent the full spectrum
of good things, bad things,
and ugly things about
large language models.
And actually I'll talk a
bit about a paper that just
appeared on archive last night.
So hopefully everyone will
learn something new today,
even if you're already familiar
with some of these papers.
So just to give
you an idea of what
I'll be covering in
this talk, I kind of
will be answering each of
these questions in turn
over the course of
the presentation.
And I should mention that this,
since some of these papers
are new and some of
this material is new,
this is the first time I'll
be presenting these slides.
So if anything is
confusing, I understand.
There's a way for
you to ping questions
to me through the hosts and feel
free to ask about anything that
might turn out to be confusing.
So yeah, the first question
that I'll try to answer
is kind of the
answer we sort out
to focus on in the T5 paper,
which is which of the transfer
learning methods people have
proposed so far work best,
and what happens when
we scale them up?
And then after the
T5 paper, we decided
to investigate non-English
pre-trained language models.
T5 is an English only model.
There are lots of languages
spoken in the world.
So what happens when we
modify T5 so that it's
a massively multilingual model?
And then I'll talk
about another paper
where we try to investigate
what kinds of knowledge
and how much knowledge
a model picks up
over the course of pre-training.
And then relatedly
in a follow up
work we tried to figure
out if the model actually
memorized this training
data during pre-training.
If it actually, if we
can get it to spit out
verbatim entries
from the training
data set after
it's been trained.
And then finally, I'll talk
about a very recent work that's
similar in spirit to the
T5 paper, where the goal is
to answer not what transfer
learning methods work best,
but what modifications to
the transformer architecture
that people have
proposed to work best.
So just to motivate
this I actually
looked through some
of the lectures
that you all have
had so far just
to get a sense of what
you've learned already.
And I know that you
are, all are already
pretty familiar with this
transfer learning paradigm
that has kind of taken the field
of natural language processing
by storm.
But just as a quick refresher,
in this style of transfer
learning what we typically do is
take a bunch of unlabeled text
data and we apply some
unsupervised objective,
or you might say
self-supervised objective,
where you do something like
you mask words at random
and then you train the model
to predict the missing words.
So you can see these
blanks in the block
of text in green and
the missing words
that the language
model will be trained
to predict in the yellow
box at the bottom.
And then after we do this
pre-training for a while,
we fine tune the model on some
downstream supervised task.
This example, I'm showing
a sentiment analysis
task for movie reviews.
And the upshot of all
of this is that doing
this first unsupervised
pre-training step
is just ridiculously helpful,
not only does it usually
make the performance
better it often
gets you very good performance
with relatively little
fine tuning data compared
to training from scratch.
So this is really
a very common--
it's kind of the de
facto standard way
to attack many natural language
processing problems now.
And I think you've already
reviewed some of these methods
but because of how effective
the transfer learning recipe
was there really was a kind
of an explosion of work
on transfer learning starting
in maybe 2018, or so.
There some prior work
on other approaches
to doing transfer learning like
word vectors, like word2vec.
Some sort of preliminary
work that proposed the recipe
that I just described.
While some has supervised
sequence learning,
some work that suggested
that this kind of stuff
might be really possible, like
the unsupervised sentiment
neuron paper.
But I would say
around in 2018, there
was kind of a string of
papers that kicked off
the excitement in
the field, including
the universal language
model fine tuning paper,
the ELMO paper what
we now call GPT-1,
and of course the BERT
paper in late 2018.
And then starting in
2019, there really
was just an incredible
explosion of different methods
for doing transfer
learning, including
new transfer learning, sorry,
new pre-training objectives,
new data sets, new ways of
doing fine tuning, and so on.
And we started working on
the T5 project in late 2018.
And we noticed that as all
these methods were coming up,
it was getting harder
and harder to figure out
what actually works best.
And part of the reason for that
was just because there was so
many methods that were
being proposed kind of
simultaneously.
And when that happens, even when
everyone is working in earnest
with good faith, you might
have situations like this
where one paper
comes along, paper A
that proposes a new unsupervised
pre-training like technique
called FancyLearn, another
paper comes along maybe
around the same time with
a pre-training technique
called FancierLearn.
And paper A pre-trains on
Wikipedia for unlabeled data
while paper B uses Wikipedia and
the Toronto Books Corpus which
is a collection of novel text.
And then the question
obviously is, is FancierLearn
better than FancyLearn?
Well, it's hard to say because
they use different sources
of pre-training data.
You might imagine that maybe
they use different model sizes,
maybe they pre-train for a
different amount of time.
They use different optimizers.
There are tons of
design decisions
that come into play here.
And so given that these
design decisions can
make it hard to determine what
worked best our goal in the T5
paper was kind of to
step back, and just
say given the current
landscape of transfer learning,
all of the methods that
people have proposed,
what actually works best
when we compare them
in the same exact setting?
And once we know
what works best,
how far can we push these
tools that we already have?
And how much can we
explore the limits
and figure out how well
these things work at scale?
And so to attack this problem
we kind of the only thing
that we introduced,
since again we're
kind of exploring
existing techniques,
was this idea of
treating all text
problems in the same format.
And this kind of approach, this
dogma of treating every text
problem in the same format
gives rise to our model,
which we call the text-to-text
transfer transformer.
And so to explain
this format to you,
the basic idea is that we cast
every text based NLP problem
as a text-to-text task.
And by that I mean, the
model takes text as input
and it produces text as output.
So in things like English
to German translation,
this is pretty typical, we
feed in a English sentence
on the input and
we train the model
to predict a German
sentence on the output.
And you'll notice in
our case, we actually
also feed what we call
a task prefix, translate
English to German, that
just tells the model what
we want it to do with the input
because especially if we're
training a multi-task model if
you just feed the model "that
is good" the model doesn't
know what to do with it.
It doesn't know if you're
trying to do sentiment analysis,
or English to German
translation, or what.
So this shouldn't be
that surprising so far.
You probably learned about
encoder-decoder model, sequence
to sequence models,
and that's basically
all that we're doing here.
It maybe gets a
little more unusual
when we start to tackle things
like text classification tasks.
So this is an example
from the cola benchmark,
which is the Corpus of
Linguistic Acceptability.
And the goal here is
to take a sentence
and determine if the sentence
is quote-unquote "acceptable"
which kind of means whether
it's grammatically correct,
and also if it's
nonsense or not.
And in this case,
the sentence is
"The course is jumping well".
And of course, courses can't
jump so the sentence is not
acceptable.
But rather than training our
model through a classifier
layer that outputs a class
label, or a probability
distribution over
a class indices,
we actually train the model to
output the literal text "not
acceptable."
So it's outputting this
text string token by token.
And it can get even
a little weirder.
We can attack things
like regression problems
where effectively the model
is supposed to be outputting
a floating point value.
And we actually just do this
by taking the floating point
numbers, and converting
them to strings,
and training the model to
just predict the string.
And it turns out that at least
for this particular task, which
is the STSb benchmark,
it works perfectly fine.
And we ultimately
actually got state
of the art on this benchmark.
So doing this type
of sort of float
to string conversion with a
little bit of quantization
turns out to work fine
for regression problems.
And finally, the
main point of this
is that there are really
tons and tons of problems
that we can cast
into this format.
So here's an example of
abstract summarization,
we feed in a news
article on the left,
and we predict the
summary on the right.
And again, we can really
attack all of these problems
in exactly the same way.
So we're using exactly the
same objective during training.
And exactly the same
decoding procedure at test
time to attack a huge variety
of natural language processing
problems.
And the nicest part
about doing this
is that as long as a transfer
learning improvement is
applicable to our model and
to this text to text format,
we can try it on a huge
suite of downstream tasks
while using exactly
the same model, exactly
the same learning
rate, optimizer,
training procedure, exactly
the same inference procedure.
So we can get rid of a
ton of the confounders
that I mentioned earlier.
Hey, Colin.
Yeah.
Can you take a second as
we're, as you're discussing
the formatting here, to
talk about how the 3.8
sort of regression
example works,
and yeah, and just go that
one more time for students.
Yeah, absolutely.
So in this particular
task STSb, the goal
is to take in two sentences
and predict a floating point
number, which denotes
how similar those two
sentences are, and that
floating point number ranges
between 1.0 and 5.0.
So we basically took the
ground truth annotated values
that we're supposed to
regress, we quantized them
to the nearest 0.2 and
we cast it to a string.
And now we have a string
like the three period eight,
not three point eight.
But you could think of it
like three period eight
or four period zero.
And we just train the model
to predict that string,
which ultimately it's a string.
It's not a number anymore.
We just predict
it token by token.
So in a sense you can
kind of think of it
as converting the regression
problem to a classification
problem because you're
doing this quantization.
But you also more broadly
can just think of it
as converting the
regression problem
to a text-to-text problem,
which is what we're doing.
Thanks.
Yeah, it's a little funky
but I promise it works.
And great.
So the nice thing,
again, about using
this sort of
sequence-to-sequence
text-to-text format is
that we can actually
just use the original vanilla
transformer as it was proposed.
Because if you remember the
transformer was actually
proposed for English
to, well it was
proposed for machine
translation primarily,
which is a sequence-to-sequence
task taking
a language-- a sentence
in one language as input
and producing the corresponding
sentence in another language.
And so really, I won't say a lot
about the model that we used.
There are relatively
few changes that we
made to the standard
transformer architecture
as originally
proposed in Attention
Is All You Need when
constructing our T5 model.
I will towards the
end of the talk
discuss lots of
architectural modifications
that people have made
since, but for T5,
for the T5 paper we really
basically stuck to the basics.
So the next big question when
you're attacking a transfer
learning problem is, what should
my pre-training data set be?
And because of the
internet, there
are lots of possible sources
of unlabeled text data.
One common source is Wikipedia.
I'm displaying a ton
of Wikipedia articles
on the screen here.
And in undertaking
this project, one
of the factors that
we wanted to study
was the effect of the
pre-training data set itself.
And so we actually constructed
a new pre-training data
set that would allow us to vary
the size across many orders
of magnitude, also that
has a filtering pipeline
that would allow us to control
the quality and type of data
that was pre-trained on.
And I'll describe how we
built that data set now.
So the first thing
we did is we wanted
to source our data from a
publicly available source.
We didn't want to use some
Google internal web scrape
that we couldn't release.
So we made use of
these web scrapes
by a non-profit organization
called Common Crawl which
is really just an organization
that sends web crawlers out
through the internet and
downloads as much text
as they can.
And every month
they dump out what
they call web
extraced text which
is, you can think of them as
websites with all of the HTML
and JavaScript ideally removed.
And this produces text that
has a pretty decent amount
of natural language in it, also
a lot of boilerplate and menu
text, and also a little
bit of gibberish.
But as a whole it's kind
of a good starting point
for constructing these
pre-training data sets.
And then we took a few
steps to kind of try
to make it so this data
set was a little cleaner.
So the first thing
we did is we removed
any lines that didn't end in
a terminal punctuation mark.
We used a language classifier
to only retain English text.
We removed anything that
looked like placeholder text,
like lorem ipsum
text on the right.
We removed anything
that looked like code.
We de-duplicated things
on a sentence level.
So any time that any chunk of
text appeared on multiple pages
we only retained it on one
of the pages and so on.
And ultimately these heuristics
were relatively simple
but produced
reasonably clean text.
And I will discuss later
the effect of these choices
in cleaning.
That was one of the
experiments that we ran.
And so after doing
this we created
this data set called C4, which
is the colossal clean crawl
corpus.
And it's available in
TensorFlow Datasets.
You actually, you need to
do the processing yourself,
which is somewhat
computationally expensive
but nevertheless it
is entirely possible.
And it produces about 750
gigabytes of reasonably clean
natural text data.
OK, so now we have our
framework, our model,
our pre-training
dataset, we need
our pre-training objective.
What are we going to
do to train the model
on our unlabeled text.
And so just to explain the
objective that we chose kind
of for our baseline experimental
procedure, which again we
will experiment with different
pre-training objectives later.
Imagine that you have some
original text sentence
like "Thank you for inviting
me to your party last week."
And what we do is we basically
choose some words at random,
and technically we're
choosing tokens at random
but for now let's just
assume that tokens are words,
and we're going to
drop those tokens out.
And so we end up with
something that looks like this.
For every consecutive
span of tokens
that have been dropped
out, we replace it
with a sentinel token.
And each sentinel token
gets a unique index.
So one of them we call it, let's
just call it the sentinel X
and the other one will
be the sentinel Y.
And you can see that because
the words "for" and "inviting"
are subsequent words that
we decided to mask out
by randomly masking words.
We're going to replace
both of those words
with a single sentinel,
single unique sentinel token.
And then the model's goal will
just be to fill in the blanks.
And so if you're familiar
with the BERT pre-training
objective, this is
somewhat similar.
The fact that we're collapsing
subsequent tokens into a span
that we're going to be
replacing words from
is slightly different.
And the fact that we're
reconstructing just the missing
words, and not the
entire sequence
is maybe slightly different too.
OK, so now I'll
kind of talk through
our baseline
experimental procedure
that we're going to use.
We're going to kind of tweak
over time along various axes
to explore the landscape
of transfer learning,
at least circa when
this paper came out.
So to pre-train the
model we're going
to take a model that has a BERT
base size encoder and decoder.
So technically has twice
as many parameters as BERT
base, because there's a
BERT base size encoder
and a BERT base size decoder.
We're going to use the
denoising objective,
the sort of masked
language modeling objective
that I just described.
And we're going to apply
it on the C4 dataset
that I mentioned earlier.
We're going to pre-train
for about 34 billion tokens,
which is about a quarter as
long as BERT base was trained.
So it's not a ton
of pre-training time
but because we're
training on, we're
doing so many
experiments we need
to cut it back a little bit.
We're going to use an
inverse square root learning
rate schedule that turned
out to work reasonably well
in our setting but
is not a terribly
important design decision.
And then we'll fine tune on a
variety of downstream tasks,
the kind of tasks that people
cared a lot about at the time.
There's the GLUE
benchmark, which
is kind of a meta benchmark
of many individual downstream
tasks, like cola and STSb
that I already mentioned.
These are what some people
might call natural language
understanding tasks.
But for the most part
you can think of them
as sentence classification,
sentence pair classification,
or regression tasks.
We also consider the
CNN Daily Mail abstract
of summarization corpus.
This is a
sequence-to-sequence problem
where you are given
a news article
and you have to
output the summary.
The SQuAD question
answering benchmark,
which is a reading comprehension
benchmark where you're
given a paragraph and
you have to answer
a question about the paragraph.
You can either attack it in
an extractive setting where
you extract the answer
from the paragraph,
or an abstractive setting where
you just output the answer.
We use the abstractive
form because it's
a text-to-text problem.
We also included the
SuperGLUE benchmark,
which was a new benchmark
at the time that
was designed to essentially
be a more difficult version
of the GLUE benchmark.
It has a new set of tasks that
were hard for existing models.
And then finally we included
three translation datasets,
English to German, English to
French, and English to Romanian
translation.
English to French being
the largest, which
was an extremely large dataset.
And English to Romanian being
many orders of magnitude
smaller.
And we're going to fine
tune on each of these tasks
individually and separately.
So we take the pre-trained
model and separately fine
tune it on each of
these downstream tasks.
And we're going to fine tune
for up to 17 billion tokens.
But we're going to save
checkpoints along the way,
evaluate each checkpoint
on the validation set,
and report the performance
on the best checkpoint.
And note that this is not
an experimentally valid way
to report your
performance because you're
basically doing model
selection on the dataset
that you are, on the
data split that you are--
you're reporting performance
on the data split
that you're doing
model selection
on which is not a good way
to compare different methods.
But to compare
within methods, we're
reasonably comfortable
doing this.
So now I'm going to kind of
give you a very high level
overview of some of the
experimental results
in this paper.
This paper is pretty huge
in terms of just the number
of experiments we ran.
And so if I was to really
drill into this paper,
it probably would
take me the whole time
but there's other fun stuff that
I want to tell you about so.
But anyways the point is I will
be showing you lots of tables
like this one.
And so in these
tables on the columns
you have the performance on
the various downstream tasks
and on the rows you have
different experimental settings
that we considered.
So to give you an example,
here is kind of the scores
that we got from
our baseline which
is the exact experimental
procedure that I must describe,
that I just described.
And we also ran that
baseline 10 times
and reporting the standard
deviation on the second line.
And then in this
last line here we're
reporting the performance
of the same model
without any pre-training,
just basically only trained
separately with supervision on
all of these downstream tasks.
And just to point out a couple
of things on this table.
The first obvious thing
is that in most cases,
the no pre-training setting
is dramatically worse.
So indeed transfer learning
does tend to be helpful.
The place where that's
not true is actually
on this English to
French translation task.
And that's probably because
it's such a big task
that you actually
don't really need
pre-training to do well on it.
We wanted to include this
because if the performance
regresses on this
task then that's
something that we
should be worried about.
The next feature of
this table to notice
is this little star appeared.
That star will appear
any time there's
a row in the table that's
equivalent to our baseline.
And another little
thing to note maybe
if you're familiar with
the history, the score
that we got on
GLUE and SQuAD was
reasonably comparable to BERT.
So it's a decent sanity check.
We have a model that
has more parameters.
But it's only trained
for a quarter as long
and it nevertheless got
comparable performance
which using a similar
objective so we shouldn't
be too surprised about that.
And then the last
thing to mention
is that we're going to use
this standard deviation over
and over again, so that we
can bold entries in the table
when they're within one standard
deviation of the maximum value
for that dataset in the table.
So now I'll just make
a big disclaimer, which
is we're going to compare
lots of different things,
we're going to run
lots of experiments,
but we're not going to tweak any
hyperparameters because if we
did, like the change
the learning rate,
or whatever, it would be
just too computationally
expensive to do this for
each individual method.
Our hope is that
this is OK because we
are treating all problems in
exactly the same framework.
We're always doing text-to-text
maximum likelihood training.
So hopefully we can keep
hyperparameters fixed,
and arguably if you
propose a new method that
requires extensive
hyperparameter tuning
it's not a very useful
method for practitioners.
And we'll get into that
a little bit more later
when I talk about architectural
modifications too.
The other thing I'll
say is that, while we
did run lots of
experiments there's
no way we could be
comprehensive because there
were so many methods out there.
And the inclusion or exclusion
of one particular method
is not meant as a
judgment on its quality.
It's just, it's what
we were able to do
given the constraints that
we were working under.
So the first set of
experiments that we ran
were to compare different
model structures.
So as I mentioned earlier
the main baseline T5 model
is an encoder-decoder model.
And in this case, you have
a separate layer stack
that encodes a sequence, and
a separate layer stack that
decodes the target sequence.
Basically it generates
the target sequence
one token by token,
while attending back
to the encoder's
output to figure out
what it should condition on.
The next set up
that we considered
is an encoder-decoder
model except that all
of the relevant parameters in
the encoder-decoder are shared.
So there are basically
half as many parameters.
And then finally another
variant that we considered
as an encoder-decoder
model where the encoder
and decoder have half
as many layers as they
do in the baseline.
And that's because
we're also considering
single stack models,
the language model
and what we call a
prefix language model.
The language model is
a model that models
the sequence strictly
from the left
to right fashion,
in a causal fashion.
It basically just ingests
tokens one at a time
and predicts the next token.
And you can actually apply
these to text-to-text problems
by basically feeding
the input as a prefix
before you start
predicting anything.
Now if you just use a language
model in its strict format then
you still have to have what we
would call a causal mask, so
a causal attention
pattern on the prefix.
And that's actually how
the GPT series of models
treat all of their problems.
But because we are
explicitly denoting
part of the sequence as an input
and the rest of the sequence
as a target, we actually
can allow the model
to have full visibility, a
non-causal mask on the input
region of the sequence.
And when we make
that change we call
that the prefix language model.
And now the upshot
of all of this really
is that the encoder-decoder
model for our framework
turns out to work best.
You can see that when we
share the parameters it does
hurt performance a little
bit but maybe a little less
than you might expect.
The prefix language
model attains
slightly worse performance
but significantly better
performance than doing strictly
causal left-to-right language
modeling, which is what you
see in the fourth row here.
And finally having the
number of parameters
in the encoder and decoder
harms performance significantly.
One thing to note is that
in all of these cases,
we're processing the same
total sequence length.
It's the same input sequence
and the same target sequence.
So in most of these
cases, the total number
of flops required to
process the sequence
is the same, even though
the number of parameters
is twice as many in
the baseline model.
So the next thing we looked
into were different variants
on our pre-training objective.
So the first thing
we did was kind
of compare different
high level approaches,
maybe just training the model
to predict the next token one
token at a time, that's kind of
a language modeling objective.
Another would be a take
the input sequence,
shuffle it up, and
train the model
to predict the
unshuffled sequence,
or to consider a mass language
model style, a BERT style
objective like the one
that we mentioned earlier.
And now on the second step
that I'm showing here,
the results for, we considered
a BERT style objective,
where the model is
trained to predict
the entire original uncorrupted
input sequence, a MASS style
objective, which
is quite similar.
And then a replace
corrupted spans objective,
which is like the one that
I described at the beginning
that we're using in
our baseline model.
And finally a variant
where rather than replacing
each token with a
unique sentinel token
we just drop the mass
tokens completely
and train the model to
predict the dropped tokens.
And you can see that the latter
two options work roughly as
well as one another.
But another pertinent
difference between these sets
of objectives is that
the first two involve
predicting the
entire input sequence
and the last two basically
just involve predicting
the masked out tokens.
And when you only predict
the masked out tokens
you have a much shorter
target sequence.
And so the overall cost
is significantly lower
for pre-training.
So we decided that that
was the best approach
and then we considered
other hyperparameters
in our masking strategy, such
as how many tokens to mask out.
So the next thing we considered
were different variants
of a pre-training dataset.
In our baseline we
use the C4 dataset
that I proposed at the
beginning of the talk.
We also compared to pre-training
on only on unfiltered data
from C4.
So rather than doing all these
heuristic filtering steps,
we just take the raw web
extracted text from C4
and pre-trained on that.
And you can see that,
that does uniformly worse.
So it is, it does
seem to be true
that these cleaning steps
that we're doing are actually
useful.
The next four datasets
for our attempt
to pre-train on
similar datasets that
had been used in past work.
The real news dataset came
from the GROVER paper.
It's essentially pre-training
only on data from news sites.
Web text is this dataset that
was used in a GPT-2 paper
where you only train on
web text that was linked to
and received a reasonably
high score on Reddit.
And then the last two variants
are either Wikipedia alone,
or as was used in the
BERT paper, Wikipedia
with the Toronto Books Corpus.
And you might actually
notice that some
of these more
specialized datasets
we get better performance.
So for example, you can see that
on the Wikipedia and Toronto
Books Corpus on the
bottom row, we actually
do much better on SuperGLUE
with a score of a little over 73
compared to pre-training on C4.
And it turns out
this is because,
or we conjecture that this
is because SuperGLUE contains
a task called multi RC which
is a reading comprehension
task on news, sorry,
encyclopedia articles
and on novels.
So the basic takeaway
here is that when
you pre-train on data that's
similar to your downstream
task, that has a
similar domain you
often get a big boost
in that downstream task.
And that's indeed
what happened here.
Interestingly, you can also
see the opposite effect.
So if you look on Wikipedia
on the second to last row.
If you only pre-trained
on Wikipedia,
you end up doing
much worse on CoLA,
which is the Corpus of
Linguistic Acceptability tasks
that I mentioned early on.
And we conjecture that this
is because Wikipedia has
very little unacceptable text.
You're basically only
pre-training on clean text,
whereas C4 has some
ungrammatical texts,
some nonsense in it,
and so that actually
can boost your performance
a little bit on CoLA.
The last thing to
note is that while you
do see some gains sometimes on
using these smaller data sets,
these data sets are about
an order of magnitude
smaller than C4.
So then the natural question
is, does it actually
hurt you to pre-train
on a smaller dataset?
So to answer that
question, what we did
is basically took C4 and
artificially made it smaller,
so that it was repeated over
the course of pre-training.
And you can see here that
when you repeat the data
set 64 times, so it's 34
billion divided by 64 tokens,
because that's how much
pre-training we did.
You actually don't
sacrifice much performance.
The performance is
roughly the same.
But if you repeat the data set
256 times, 1,024 times or more
you actually start
to see degradation.
And the reason that we
think this is happening
is because you're
basically overfitting
during pre-training.
And you can get a sense
for whether that's true
or not by looking, just
looking at the training loss.
You can see that
the model attains
a much, much smaller training
loss as you repeat the data set
more and more times.
So the upshot of this
is that your data set
should be at least
as big that you
don't see significant
overfitting
during pre-training.
And later on when we
scale up these models
and pre-trained them
on much more data,
we would do enough repeats of
the smaller sort of more domain
specific data sets
that we imagine
we would see harmful effects.
The next thing we
experimented with
were multi-task
learning strategies.
So when you're doing
multi task learning you're
essentially training the model
on multiple tasks at once.
And most of the, in
all the experiments
I'm showing on this
slide here, we're
actually training
on every single task
at once, so the
pre-training task,
and all of the downstream
tasks together.
And the most pertinent
question when
you're doing multi-task
training like this
is, how often should I
sample data from each task?
So one approach is just to
sample data at an equal rate
across all of the tasks.
Another case is to
basically pretend
like you've just concatenated
all the datasets,
we call that
examples proportional
mixing because it's
equivalent to sampling
from the dataset in accordance
to how many examples there
are in the dataset.
The difficult thing
with that though,
is that our pre-training
dataset is so big
that its proportion
would be much, much, much
bigger than every
downstream task,
and we basically
would never train
on any of the downstream data.
So we introduced
this hyperparameter K
which is a constant
that basically
is how big should we pretend
that the pre-training data
set is.
The last thing
you can do is take
the number of examples
in each data set
and scale it by a temperature.
The larger the
temperature, the closer you
get to equal mixing, to uniform
sampling from each data set.
But at any rate, the main
takeaway from this table
is that you can get pretty
close to the performance
of separate
pre-training and fine
tuning like we do
on our baseline
if you get the mixing
strategy right.
But ultimately we
found that you do
tend to sacrifice
some performance when
doing multi-task training on
at least some of the tasks.
And Colin, there were lots of
questions back on the choice--
on the slide with the
different datasets,
one showing Realnews
and C4 and so on.
You want to take a couple?
Absolutely.
Yeah, so firstly if
you just look at this,
it still does kind
of look like you
can get great results with
more than an order of magnitude
less text than C4, and it seemed
like that's not the message
you wanted to be
putting forward.
Yeah, so there's a
little nuance here,
which is basically that in our
baseline, in these experiments
that I've been running
so far, we're actually
not pre-training for that long.
So as I mentioned earlier, we're
actually training for a quarter
as long as BERT and
actually for as a,
I believe 1/256th as long
as X on that for example.
And when later in
the paper, we're
going to pre-train for
much, much, much longer.
And in that case,
we would end up
repeating these datasets many,
many times over the course
of pre-training and we'd start
to see these negative effects
that I explained
on the next slide.
So that's why you're
then doing the repeat.
OK, someone then
asked about that
as to why you're training on the
same stuff over and over again.
That's the test.
Yeah, exactly.
And then on the datasets--
so to a first
approximation, does
C4 contain Wikipedia,
or partially--
It contains many, many
pages of Wikipedia
but not all of
Wikipedia, you know
the Common Crawl is
done by like-- it
is a sort of web
crawl by following
links at some priority
and ultimately it
didn't cover all of Wikipedia.
I don't actually know the exact
proportion of Wikipedia that's
included in C4 but definitely
when training on C4
you will see some
Wikipedia text.
It will be at a relatively
low proportion compared
to all of the other data that--
sources of data you'll see.
Sure.
And then someone wasn't quite
convinced with your argument
that the good
quality of Wikipedia
explained the worst performance
on CoLA because they thought,
well surely RealNews, that's
basically well-edited text as
well, and yet it
seems to work fine.
Yeah, it's a good point.
I'm not sure.
It could be that because
RealNews has quotes in it,
or maybe RealNews ended
up having some content
from the common
sections of sites.
I should say that when I--
the reason that they're
RealNews-like and WebText-like
is that these are our
own reproductions of them
so they might not be exactly
the same as the originally
proposed variants, because
WebText for example
was never released.
Yeah, but it's an
interesting point
and that's also why I would
say that it's a conjecture.
It's not something that I can
make a rigorous claim about.
Yeah.
OK.
Maybe we should let
you go on for now.
Great.
Thanks.
Yeah, thanks for
those questions.
So then the next
thing after looking
at these different multi-task
training strategies,
is to see if there's
any way for us
to close the gap between
multi-task training
and this pre-training followed
by separate fine tuning.
And we experimented with many
different strategies here,
basically, strict
multitask training,
doing multi-task training
followed by individual task
fine tuning, doing
multi-task training
but without any
unsupervised data.
And really the main takeaway
from all of these experiments
was that if you do the
multi-task training first,
including the unsupervised
task, and then you fine tune
the model on each
task separately, which
is the third row
here, you actually
don't really sacrifice
much performance at all.
You are-- you don't end
up with a multi-task model
because you're fine tuning
on each task individually.
But the nice thing
about this approach
is that you can monitor
that performance
on your downstream tasks while
you're doing pre-training.
And you don't sacrifice
much performance.
One setting that
we didn't consider
is the unsupervised
pre-training followed
by a supervised
multi-task training.
I wish that we had run that
but we just, we didn't.
So then sort of the last
set of experiments we ran
try to answer the
following question.
Let's say that someone comes
along and all of a sudden
gives you four times
as much compute,
what should you do with it?
And so there are a number
of things you could do.
You could increase the
number of training steps
by a factor of four.
You could increase your batch
size by a factor of four.
You can make your
model twice as big,
and train for twice as long.
You can make your model
four times as big.
You could train four models
separately and ensemble them.
Or you could do this last
thing, which doesn't actually
use four times as much compute,
where you pre-train one model
and you fine tune it
four times separately
and then ensemble those.
And the main takeaway here
is that scaling helps.
This is very unsurprising
especially in 2021,
but interestingly you
get significant gains
whether you just increase
the training time
or if you increase the size.
So you can see that
along both of these axes
we get significant
performance improvements
although the performance
improvements are more dramatic
when we increase the size.
And in particular,
you can see that we've
gone from a score of about
71 on SuperGLUE to 78 just
by making the model
four times bigger.
OK, so let me just kind of give
a quick recap of all of that.
And then use that
recap to explain
the design decisions that
went into the final sort of T5
models.
The first thing is
that we're going
to choose an encoder-decoder
architecture because that
seemed to work best in
our text- to-text format.
The next thing is
that we're going
to use the span prediction
objective, which is ultimately
quite similar to the
baseline objective
that I described earlier.
We will use the C4
dataset because it
did attain reasonable
performance,
but was large enough
that we didn't
have to worry about repeating
the data and seeing detrimental
overfitting during
pre-training when we scale up
the number of
pre-training steps.
We actually decided to do
multi-task pre-training
because we will be scaling up
the amount of pre-training.
Our longest training
runs took about a month
and we wanted to be able
to monitor performance
over the course of pre-training
without doing fine tuning.
So we're going to be doing
this multi-task pre-training
followed by fine tuning.
And then the last
thing, of course,
is we're going to train
bigger models for longer.
And specifically the model
sizes that we ended up
releasing we called small,
base, large, 3B, and 11B.
The small model has
60 million parameters.
It's about a quarter
as big as our baseline
which again was a BERT-base
size encoder, BERT-base size
decoder.
We also trained a model that
was a BERT-Large size encoder,
BERT-Large size decoder.
And then we created two
larger variants simply
by scaling up the feed-forward
dimension of the transformer
and the number of attention
heads in the transformer.
You can see our
largest model actually
had a hidden dimensionality
of 65,000 in the feed
forward layers.
The reason that we did this
kind of unusual way of scaling
up the parameter count is just
because the feed forward layers
are just gigantic
matrix multiplies
and that's the best way to make
use of hardware accelerators.
Can I just stick in
one more question?
Absolutely.
Someone was asking about how
you did the multi-task training,
like so was that sticking
a simple softmax classifier
on top for each task or?
So in our case, because we're
using this text-to-text format,
basically where-- you train on
exactly the same-- it's exactly
the same model, no
new classification
heads for every task.
The only difference is that each
task gets its own task prefix.
So if you remember all the
way back at the beginning
we say you know translate
English to German colon
English sentence, or summarize
colon English paragraph.
And that tells the
model what it should do.
And then you just
train the model
to predict the
corresponding target.
Cool, so the last
pertinent detail again
is that we did scale up
the amount of pre-training,
we ended up pre-training on
a trillion tokens of data
rather than 34 billion tokens.
So it's quite a lot
more pre-training,
although it's still
less pre-training that
was used in XLNet I
think by a factor of 2,
If I'm remembering correctly.
So here are the results.
And these were kind of the way
that things stood at the time
that we released the paper.
We ended up getting
state of the art results
on the GLUE meta
benchmark, CNN Daily Mail
abstractive summarization,
SQuAD question answering.
And we were actually
quite excited to see
how well we did on SuperGLUE.
We ultimately came pretty
close to the human score which
was a score of 89.8, and we
performed significantly better
than RoBERTa.
SuperGLUE, it turns
out is a benchmark that
benefits a lot from large
models and so you can really
see a dramatic increase
in the model's performance
as we scale the model up.
On the other hand, we did not
attain state of the art results
on any of the
translation datasets.
And the reason that we
think that this is true
is because all of
the state of the art
results at the time on
these translation datasets
used back translation.
And if you remember we did
English only pre-training
in our model.
And we expect that in terms of
making use of unlabeled data,
it's more effective to use
back translation for machine
translation problems than to use
this English only pre-training
that we did.
I should mention of
course these results
are now quite a bit stale.
And some of these
scores have been
beaten by subsequent models.
So now just quick, make a
plug that all of our code
is released, our pre-trained
models have been released.
You can make use of
them in our code base.
They're also, of course, in the
Hugging Face transformers code
base.
We made a colab at the time
that shows a pretty basic demo
of how to take one of
our pre-trained models
and basically train it on a
TSV file of inputs and targets.
So because all problems
are text-to-text problems,
you just need to give the
model some input text,
and some target text,
and that's all you
need to fine tune the model.
And you can make,
you can actually
fine tune up to the 3 billion
parameter model on a free colab
TPU using the link
at the bottom here.
Great so, so far
we've been talking
about an English only
pre-training model.
I mean we did apply it
to machine translation
and downstream tasks.
So a kind of a natural
question is, what
about all the other languages?
Why not train a
multilingual model?
And so that's something
that we did more recently.
And actually let me
just pause because I did
see a couple of
questions coming out.
I want to make sure that I
am not leaving anyone behind
as I move to the next section.
Sure.
So, one of the questions is
about the multi-task setting.
If you include an
unknown task prefix,
does anything
interesting happen?
And if you don't include
a prefix what does it do?
So if you include an
unknown task prefix,
or if you don't include a prefix
at all, what it will probably
do is apply the
unsupervised objective
because we actually
didn't use a task prefix
for the unsupervised objective.
Well I guess I
should say, what--
it's not quite,
that's not quite true
because there won't be any
sentinel tokens in the input.
So what we actually see
is it typically does
is it outputs kind
of some related
words and some other
sentinel tokens in gibberish.
It's not very useful
is I guess the upshot.
We have questions
about back translation,
I don't think they heard
about back translation
in the rest of the course.
So back translation is a
pretty straightforward method.
The basic idea is that if I
have unlabeled text data in one
language, I use my current
model to translate that data
to some particular language.
And I use that as training data
then subsequently for my model.
It's similar to self-training
if you're familiar with it.
Basically you're making
predictions on unlabeled data
and then using those
predictions to train the model.
Turns out to be helpful.
Yep, and then one detail
question, maximum input length
and maximum output length,
how did you choose them?
Did you do a study
on that as well?
Yeah, so most of the
tasks we considered
did not have input length
significantly longer
than 512 tokens
most of the time,
using the tokenization
strategy that we made use of.
And so we used a maximum
input length of 512
but we used that position
encoding scheme that
allows arbitrary input lengths.
And we actually have
in subsequent work
fine tuned T5 on
sequences of length 2,048.
Beyond that you start to get
into memory issues because
of attention's quadratic
memory complexity.
But in principle you can
apply it to long sequences.
And then maybe one last
thing if you have a second,
is talking again about
how translation again
seems to be not the, not
the killer app for this.
And so what's your intuition
as to why translation--
does it not benefit from
pre-training for what reason?
I'm not, I'm really not sure.
Yeah, I can only conjecture.
I think that pre-training
helps the model learn
the meaning of words.
It helps the model learn
some world knowledge which
I'll talk about a
little bit later,
and that's a very loose concept.
I think that for
translation learning
world knowledge is
not very useful,
because everything, all
of the knowledge you
need to translate a
sentence for the most part
is in the sentence.
And so basically all of the sort
of contextual knowledge style
information that you need to
produce the German sentence
in the input sentence.
So gaining world knowledge
during pre-training
is not very useful.
Of course it's useful
to know what words mean,
but to a certain extent that's
kind of the easiest signal
to pick up on during training.
And I imagine, that
would be my guess,
I don't have any rigorous
proof of any of this.
Thanks.
Great, so like I was saying, we
trained this English only model
and we wanted to address the
major shortcoming that really
only can speak one language.
So we introduced a model
called mT5, multilingual T5.
And really for
the most part, the
if you remember
one thing about mT5
it's basically that it's
exactly the same model
but trained on a
multilingual corpus.
And the text-to-text
format is the same.
We feed in task prefixes
but we can feed content
in different languages.
And we can do
classification tasks.
We can do question
answering tasks with mT5
in exactly the same way
that we can do with T5.
So like I said the
pertinent thing about mT5
was creating a
multilingual variant of C4.
Overall the process is
very similar to the process
we used for C4, except that
it includes 101 languages
that we detected using a open
source language detector.
We also extracted data from
more Common Crawl dumps,
because especially for
the low resource languages
it was hard to get enough data
from only one Common Crawl
dump.
And you can see a list of
languages that we include here.
Ultimately the data
set ended up being
about 27 terabytes in size.
So here's a distribution
of the number
of pages in the mC4 training
dataset for various languages.
You can see our most, our
highest resource language
is English where we have
about 3 billion pages
with 3 trillion tokens total.
The lowest resource
languages Yoruba
with only about 50,000 pages.
So you can see that
the amount of data
that we got for each language
varies by many, many orders
of magnitude.
Because of that
a common strategy
is to use this sort
of temperature scaling
that I mentioned earlier
where basically you
sample from data in
a particular language
by using a-- by scaling
the number of examples
in that language
by a temperature.
And as the, and I
apologize, the temperature
here is 1 over the temperature
that I described previously.
So in this case,
as the temperature
gets smaller and smaller,
you get closer and closer
to a uniform distribution.
The net effect of this is that
for very small temperatures
you tend to do better
on downstream tasks
on low resource
languages like Urdu,
but as you increase the
temperature so that you get,
so you basically are doing
examples proportional mixing
of the different
languages, you do better
on high resource
languages like Russian.
So we took, we took
mT4, we pre-trained mT5,
again basically everything
was kept the same,
we made the vocabulary a
bit bigger to accommodate
all the different languages.
But overall that
amount of pre-training
the model sizes, et cetera
are basically the same.
And ultimately got state of
the art on some of the tasks
in the XTREME benchmark.
You'll notice that we
don't report results
for some of these tasks,
that's partially because XTREME
is designed for sentence
encoders like BERT,
T5 is a-- and mT5 are
encoder-decoder models.
We did not experiment with
using the encoder on its own
but in order to attack
some of these problems,
like the sentence
retrieval problems,
you need a model that can output
a single vector representation
of your sequence.
And we don't have
that in T5 so we
didn't apply it to those tasks.
One interesting finding
from this paper,
that I'll just
quickly mention here,
is that there are
basically multiple settings
that people consider
multilingual benchmarks.
One is the case,
the zero-shot case.
And in that case, you
don't do any pre-training
on a language of, sorry, you
don't have any fine tuning data
on each particular language.
You only have pre-training
data on those languages.
So you fine tune, let's
say only in English,
and then you feed the model
some text in another language
and see if it produces
the right predictions.
The next setting is the
translate-train setting.
That's where you take a
machine translation model
and translate the data in the
English fine tuning corpus
into different languages.
And then the last setting is the
in-language multi-task setting.
That's the setting
where you assume
that you have gold
standard ground truth
data in every language that
you want the model to be
able to process data in.
And the takeaway
here actually is
that the difference
in performance
between small models and
our largest model as we
go along the x-axis
is much, much bigger
for the zero-shot and
translate-train settings
than it is for the
in-language multitask setting.
So what this suggests
to us is basically
that the model learns a much
wider distribution of languages
if it has a much larger
amount of parameters.
And it is able to do this
kind of like zero-shot task
learning, multilingual task
learning much better when
it has more parameters.
So kind of along those lines,
larger models can maybe
fit more knowledge
about more languages,
we had another paper
where we basically
tried to answer the
question, you know,
how much and what
kind of knowledge
does a model pick up
during pre-training?
And so to answer that
question, we took a,
we basically introduced
a new variant
of the question answering task.
So the question answering
task kind of comes
in a couple of
different flavors.
The simplest flavor, which
I've mentioned already
is reading comprehension.
And in that case, the
model is basically
given a paragraph or
an article, and then
it's asked a question about
the paragraph or article,
and it has to basically
extract the answer.
So you can see if it's being
asked, "what color is a lemon?"
It has to look in the
paragraph that it's seen,
and see that it's, the lemon
is a yellow fruit and output
the word "yellow".
So this is kind of the simplest
form of the question answering
task.
A more difficult form is
what people call open domain
question answering.
And in that case, you
assume that the model
is given a question
and has access
to a large external
database of knowledge,
maybe all of Wikipedia.
So the model has
to do two things.
It first has to
find the article,
or the snippet of
text, that contains
the answer in the database.
And then it has to extract
the answer from the article.
And so there's this
additional retrieval step
that makes the problem
quite a bit harder.
But we introduced a
sort of third variant
of question answering that
we call closed book question
answering.
The name takes inspiration
from closed book exams.
The goal here is that you just
feed the model the question.
It does not have access to
an external knowledge source.
It cannot look up
information anywhere.
It could only answer the
question based on the knowledge
that it picked up
during pre-training.
So if you feed the
model the question,
"what color is a lemon?"
It has to output the
model "yellow" correctly
because it so, so to speak knows
that the lemons are yellow.
So this is a good way, we
argue, of testing the knowledge,
the amount of knowledge
stored in the model
during pre-training.
So why would we
expect that to work?
Well, you can
imagine here, we're
doing our normal
pre-training of T5.
We're masking out words
and training the model
to predict the masked
out spans of words.
And you might imagine that
somewhere during pre-training
it sees a sentence that says,
"President Franklin blank
born blank January 1882."
The goal here would be to output
"D. Roosevelt was blank in".
And then during fine-tuning
we train the model
to predict when the year 1882,
when it was asked the question,
"when was Franklin
D. Roosevelt born?"
And you might hope that
it kind of recalls back
to its pre-training task
and recalls some knowledge
that it picked up during
pre-training in order
to answer this
question correctly.
So we took some standard
open domain question
answering datasets, natural
questions, web questions,
and trivia QA.
And basically removed
all of the context.
And trained our model to
predict the correct answer when
asked some particular
question, and then
evaluated its
performance on the test
set for each of these tasks.
And in this table we're
comparing the state of the art
results for an
open domain system,
these are systems that
explicitly retrieve knowledge
from an external
knowledge source,
compared to T5 when it's been
trained in this closed book
setting.
You'll notice that we're
actually using a slightly
different version of
T5 here, using T5.1.1.
The pertinent difference is just
that T5.1.1 was not multi-task
pre-trained.
It was only pre-trained using
an unsupervised objective.
The reason we did
that, again, is
because we want to measure
the amount of knowledge
that the model picked
up during pre-training.
And you can see we
actually got reasonably,
strong performance, maybe
respectable performance the--
I don't want to use the
performance, the word
performance again.
But the accuracy basically
on each of these datasets
increases as the
model size increases,
which maybe in a
loose way suggests
that the larger models
have picked up more
knowledge during pre-training.
But we ultimately
lagged behind the state
of the art results for
open domain systems
that explicitly
retrieve knowledge.
So to try to close this gap,
we made use of this objective
called salient span
masking from a paper called
"Retrieval Augmented
Language Model Pre-training."
And salient span masking
is a very simple idea.
The idea is that rather
than masking out words
at random in your
pre-training objective,
you actually mask out
entities explicitly.
So that's people's names,
places, dates et cetera.
And you basically just
use an off the shelf
named entity recognizer to
figure out what entities are
in your pre-training dataset.
And you train the model to
fill in salient spans instead
of random spans.
So what we did, is we took
T5.1.1 after it was pre-trained
and did continued pre-training
on salient span masking.
And then measured
the performance
on our downstream tasks
after fine tuning.
And you can see that the more
salient span mask pre-training
we did, the better, excuse
me, the better and better
the performance got when we fine
tuned on the downstream tasks.
And we ultimately were able
to close some of these gaps
significantly.
And actually outperformed the
best open domain system on web
questions by adding salient
span masking to T5.1.1.
So this just is a
message to tell you
that the objective matters, and
doing this kind of now people,
at the time people
didn't call it this,
but now people call this domain
adaptive, or task adaptive,
pre-training.
And this is a good way of
getting better performance
on your downstream tasks.
So I'm going to go
to the questions
here, if now is a good time.
Yes, that'd be great.
So for some context,
the students
in their most recent
assignment had
to make effectively a
mini T5 thing, where
the only questions that were
asked were from a simple domain
so that they could
pre-train on a single GPU.
And one of the
questions they have
is, how can we be sure that the
answer produced by the model
is not made up?
They were asked this on the
assignments as well, I think.
So if you don't have access
to a ground truth answer,
it's actually very hard to know.
There's a nice
paper that came out
after this paper called "How
Can We Know When Language Models
Know" and the goal of that paper
is to make it so that T5 is
what we call well-calibrated.
And when a model
is well calibrated
it means that when it
doesn't know the answer,
it doesn't output highly
confident predictions.
And this paper
explored various ways
of calibrating T5 for closed
book question answering.
And they ultimately found
that when the model doesn't
know the answer when
it's outputting something
made up that they
could effectively
make it be very unconfident
in its predictions.
So that's one way to do it.
Oh, I think you actually
are muted, John.
Great.
Thanks.
And then another
question is the knowledge
that's necessary for
doing this fine tuning
like the Q&A on these
fine tuning datasets,
is it knowledge that is all
present at pre-training time?
Yeah, so that's
also something that
was explored by a
subsequent paper, where
it was shown that actually there
is a decent amount of train
and test overlap in terms of
knowledge in these data sets.
So it's definitely
possible in these cases
that the model is
picking up knowledge
during fine tuning
and not pre-training.
However, just as kind of
a side experimental note,
we find that the
performance of T5
actually plateaus before
it makes a single pass
over the fine tuning dataset.
So basically T5 will
very, very quickly
figure out what the heck
you're trying to get it to do.
It doesn't even need to
see the full training set
before it gets basically its
maximum performance on the test
set.
So we don't actually
think that, that's
a major factor
for these results.
Great, and then last question.
How did the, if you studied it,
how did the multi-task model
do?
Yeah, those results
are in the paper.
The results are almost
exactly the same.
It's just, it's a little easier
to explain the whole knowledge
pre-training thing when you
are talking about T5.1.1.
In the interest of time, I
might skip these next three
slides, which are, the short
summary of these slides
is just that the evaluation
procedure that we use unfairly
penalizes closed book
question answering systems.
If you want to learn
a bit more about that
you can poke into
the paper a bit.
It doesn't really
support the main point
that I'm trying to make
in any meaningful way.
So, and I want to get to some
of the more recent papers
and I should be able to
have time to do that.
Cool, so we've kind of
answered this question,
how much knowledge does a model
pick up during pre-training?
The answer is arguably a lot.
So kind of a follow
up question is,
the model is kind of memorizing
this knowledge, right?
But does it also memorize,
do large language models also
memorize stuff that we
don't want them to memorize?
Specifically like private
data, like you can imagine,
let's say that somewhere in C4
is someone's social security
number.
We probably don't want our model
to memorize that, and spit it
out when we're decoding from it.
And we certainly don't
want it to happen
for unconditional models
like GPT-2 or GPT-3.
So in this next work we try
to answer this question here,
do large language
models memorize stuff
from their pre-training dataset?
And we can first
actually turn to experts
and see what experts think.
And here are two statements
made by the EFF and OpenAI
that were sent to the US
Patent and Trademark Office
when there were a call
for comments on basically
exactly this question.
And you can see
that in both cases,
these organizations
basically say,
there's basically no reason to
believe that a large language
model would output, would copy
data from its training dataset.
And OpenAI kind of calls this
a well constructed AI system.
And I think what
they actually mean
by that, If you read their
statement a little longer,
they kind of say if
you construct an AI
system appropriately, the
AI system will not overfit
to the training dataset.
And if it's not
overfit, we don't
expect them to actually output
any of their training set
in any non-trivial way.
So these are kind of
statements that were hunches.
And in this work we tried to
investigate more rigorously
whether they were true.
And the way that we
did that was basically
by taking the pre-trained GPT-2
model and feeding it prefixes.
So you can imagine, you take
a causal language model,
like GPT-2 that just predicts
tokens auto-regressively, you
feed it a prefix and then
ask it to basically predict
what comes next.
And we're showing here
this sort of odd prefix,
"East Stroudsburg
Stroudsburg" that we found
when we fed this particular
prefix into GPT-2,
it actually output
verbatim an address, name,
email address, phone number,
and fax number of a real person
that appears on the internet.
This example actually
only appears six times
on the entire public internet.
So it's unlikely that GPT-2 saw
this address very many times.
And the main point of
this work is that yes, it
does seem like GPT-2
at least has memorized
a significant amount of
non-trivial information
from its pre-training dataset.
So how did we
undertake this study?
We used this procedure that we
are, that's shown on the screen
here.
We basically consider
three different ways
of sampling data from GPT-2.
The first is just a sample
auto-regressively from it.
The next is to sample
auto-regressively
but with a decay in temperature.
This basically
means that you want
the model to become
more and more
confident in its predictions
over the course of sampling.
And the last option is to take
random text from the internet
and use that as conditioning
to GPT-2 before asking
it to generate what comes next.
So now for each
of these samples,
for each of these generations,
each of these 200,000
generations we did for each
of these sampling methods,
we want a way of kind of
trying to predict whether it
might be memorized or not.
And so we came up
with six metrics
to use to give us a notion of
whether a particular sample
from GPT-2 might be memorized.
All of these different
metrics basically
make use of GPT-2's
perplexity for the sample.
The perplexity, as I think
you probably learned,
is basically a measure of
how confident GPT-2 was
in generating this
particular sample.
You can also think of it as
a measure of compression.
So these metrics all make
use of the perplexity,
either we just measure GPT-2's
perplexity for the thing
that it generated, or we compute
the ratio of GPT-2's perplexity
to the perplexity for
another variant of GPT,
or to a text compression
library called zlib.
We also compared via
a ratio the perplexity
of the original sample
versus a lowercase version
of the sample.
And also a windowed
perplexity where we only
compute the perplexity over
a small window of the sample
instead of the whole thing.
We take the top, we do some
deduplication on the generation
and then choose the top
100 generations according
to each of these metrics.
So that will
ultimately give us 600
possible memorized generations.
And then we actually just
do a basic, excuse me,
a basic Google
search to see if we
can find that text
that GPT-2 generated
on the internet somewhere.
And if we do find
it on the internet
somewhere we ask the
GPT-2 authors was
this in the training
set or not, and they
checked for all of
the examples that we
found and let us know if GPT-2
actually spit out something
from its training dataset.
So just to give you an idea
of what these metrics are
and why they might be helpful.
This scatterplot is showing the
perplexity assigned by GPT-2
and the perplexity
assigned by zlib to 200,000
samples generated by GPT-2.
and you can see that most of
them kind of fall on this line,
there's a big clump of them
on the right there in gray.
But highlighted
here in red and blue
are samples that
kind of are outliers,
GPT-2 is assigning a much
lower perplexity to zlib,
sorry, to those
samples than zlib is.
And what that means is
that GPT-2 is very, very
good at predicting what comes
next in these samples and zlib
is not.
Zlib is kind of an
unbiased source, right.
It's not really pre-trained
on a bunch of data.
It's kind of data agnostic.
So it might be the
case that if GPT-2
is very good at predicting what
comes next in a given sequence,
but zlib is not, that GPT-2
has memorized those samples.
So all of these things
kind of in the top
left there are possible
memorized samples.
And actually we marked
the ones in blue
that it turned out, were
actually in the training data
set and that GPT-2
had memorized.
Overall, we found many examples
of verbatim text memorized
from the training dataset.
This included news, log files,
licenses, pages from Wikipedia,
URLs.
And we highlight
two types of data
here that we found that
GPT-2 had memorized
that in our opinion constitute
private information,
like named individuals
from non-news samples,
or contact information like
the example I showed early on.
And so you might ask, OK,
maybe it's not that surprising
that GPT-2 memorized
a news article
if that news article
appears hundreds of times
on the internet.
We actually got lucky
because it turned out
there were a bunch of
examples of memorized data
that only appeared
on one document
on the entire public internet.
It was basically a
paste, like a paste
of a bunch of URLs from Reddit,
from a controversial subreddit
called The Donald.
And all of these URLs had
exactly the same form.
It was
http://reddit.com/r/thedonald/
a bunch of random
numbers and letters,
slash the name of the thread.
Now this random numbers
and letters part
is nice because it's equally
hard to predict in all cases.
It's basically a random hash.
So we know that
part of the sequence
should be equally hard
for any model to memorize.
And what that means is
that we can memorize--
we can measure how many times
does a particular URL need
to appear in this list of URLs,
because there were repetitions
in the list, in order for
one of the particular GPT-2
sized models to memorize it.
And what we found was that the
largest variant GPT-2, GPT-2
XL, memorized a URL
that appeared 33 times
in this particular
document but not URLs that
appeared 17 times or fewer.
The medium sized model was only
really able to fully memorize
a URL that appeared 56 times.
And the small model really
didn't memorize any.
The half basically
means that we could
get it to spit out the URL
if we gave it some additional
prompting.
We basically hinted at
some of the numbers where.
And what the takeaway of
this is that we actually
by coincidence, because there
is this particular document
with the structure, we were able
to say reasonably confidently
that larger models tend
to memorize more data.
They need to see
examples, they need
to see particular examples
fewer times in order
to memorize them,
which we thought
was an interesting finding.
So, so far I have
kind of mostly been
talking about the benefits
of larger models, right.
Because larger models
did better on SuperGLUE,
larger models did better on
closed book question answering.
Of course, there is this
caveat that larger models also
seem to be better at memorizing
their training data set.
But larger models are
also inconvenient.
They are more computationally
expensive to run.
They consume more energy.
And they don't fit
on, for example
T5 11B doesn't fit
on a single GPU
unless you use kind
of clever methods.
So the last paper
that I'll discuss,
which is super recent
work is, can we
basically close
the performance gap
between large and small
models through improvements
to the transformer architecture?
So in this work we take
basically the same strategy
that we took in
the T5 paper, where
we took sort of the landscape
of existing modifications
to the transformer
architecture and evaluated them
in the same exact setting.
And there have been
lots of variants
proposed to the
transformer architecture.
In T5 we use basically the
standard encoder-decoder
architecture from the
"Attention Is All You
Need" Paper, that's
visualized here.
But there have been lots
and lots of modifications
that have been proposed since
the transformer was released
in 2017.
For example, maybe
people suggested
that you should factorize
your embedding matrix.
You should share the embedding
matrix and the softmax output
layer.
You should use different
forms of softmax,
like a mixture of softmax's,
or an adaptive softmax.
Different ways of
normalizing, or initializing,
the model, maybe different
attention mechanisms,
alternatives to
attention mechanisms
like lightweight and
dynamical convolutions.
Different nonlinearities
in the feed-forward layers,
different structures for
the feed-forward layers,
like a mixture of experts
to the switch transformer.
Completely different
architectures
that were inspired
by the transformer,
like the funnel
transformer, evolved
transformer, the universal
transformer, and so on.
Really, there have just been
tons and tons and tons of them.
And again, the
goal in this paper
was to take a bunch
of these modifications
and apply the same basic
methodology from the T5 paper
where we test them in the
same experimental setting.
Specifically, we basically
tested them in exactly the T5
setting that I described at
the beginning of the talk,
where we pre-trained a
T5 base sized model on C4
and then fine tune it on
a few downstream tasks.
I won't discuss
that too much more
because I gave a pretty
thorough introduction to it
at the beginning of the talk.
And so here is a sort of
a first set of results
that I'll show you.
Along the x-axis are different
transformer modifications,
I'm not labeling
which one is which
because I don't want to call
any particular modification out.
This is the validation
loss attained by the model
for the pre-training objective.
So when we do
pre-training on C4,
we hold out some
data from C4 and then
we basically measure
the validation loss
on the held out data.
So lower is better in this case.
And you can see this
dotted black line
is the performance
of the baseline model
without any transformer
modifications.
It's basically a
vanilla transformer.
And you can see that actually
some of the transformer
modifications did attain better
performance, which was good.
But a lot of them
didn't and a lot of them
actually got significantly
worse performance.
And but maybe even worse
some of these variants
of the transformer that
attained better performance
were pretty minor
changes, like for example
just taking the
ReLU in the dense--
ReLU dense layer and swapping
it with another non-linearity.
So it's a pretty minor change.
And some of the other really
highly performant ones
were actually ultimately
more expensive models.
We did use the same base model.
It was the same
T5 base size model
but some of these methods
like the switch transformer,
for example, increases the
parameter count dramatically.
So it has, it's more
expensive in terms of memory.
Some of the other methods
kind of by coincidence
maybe if you make
the model deeper,
it's not able to make use of
it, make use of the accelerator
as efficiently.
And so it makes the
training time and inference
time a little more expensive.
So once you factor out
the very simple changes
to the transformer and the
ones that ultimately made
the model more expensive
along some axis
there actually were very few, if
any modifications that improved
performance meaningfully.
And this is true on
the pre-training task.
It's also true on the
downstream tasks we considered.
So this is the
ROUGE-2 score, it's
just one of the metrics
people use on the XSum task.
XSum is, you can sort
of think of it like,
a harder version of CNN Daily
Mail via the summarization
task.
And you can see that
the model variants
that attained a better
validation score
tended to also attain a
better XSum ROUGE-2 score.
But again almost all of
the variants we tried
decreased the performance.
And just as an aside I kind of
alluded to this a little bit,
there is a reasonably
good correlation
between the validation loss
and the SuperGLUE score.
Although I'll just point
out a couple of interesting
points here.
One is this method called
transparent attention.
It attained a pretty
good validation loss
but ultimately a very
bad SuperGLUE score
which was surprising to us.
The switch transformer,
which I'll highlight here,
attained the best
validation loss
but it did not get the
best SuperGLUE score.
On the closed book
variant of web questions,
the switch transformer actually
achieveed nearly the best
validation and accuracy.
And we, this kind of supports a
loose conjecture in the field,
that scaling up the
number of parameters
improves the amount of knowledge
that the model can internalize.
But it doesn't help
the model reason.
So kind of very, very
loosely speaking again
this is kind of a
conjecture, SuperGLUE
requires deep
reasoning capabilities.
closed book web questions
requires knowledge
intensive capabilities.
And so a switch transformer,
which only scales up
the parameter count without
scaling up the processing,
maybe does better on
the web questions task.
So this kind of raises
a number, should
raise some red flags for you.
Because this is a pretty bold
claim that most of these things
don't actually help that much.
And there's kind of a
couple of possible reasons
that this could be the case.
One is that our
code base is just
very unusual and non-standard.
We don't think this is the case
because the code base that we
used was actually developed by
one of the people who invented
the transformer, Noam Shazeer.
And it's been used a lot.
It's been used in lots
of various papers.
It's basically the same as
the tensor2tensor code base.
And so we think that
arguably our code base
and the implementation detail
should be reasonably standard.
Maybe the tasks we
consider are non-standard.
We think this is
probably not true.
Pre-training followed by
fine tuning is pretty common.
Basically, all the
tasks we tested out on
have state of the art
results from transformers.
And actually we included
separately supervised
only training on
WMT English German,
which was the task that
transformer was actually
proposed on.
Maybe we need more
hyperparameter tuning,
because we didn't,
again, we didn't
do significant
hyperparameter tuning
for each of these methods.
To test how true
this was we actually
took one of the methods that
performed significantly worse
than we expected.
And we ran maybe a
couple hundred trials
of hyperparameter
optimization, one
of the researchers
on this paper spent
a long time trying to
get hyperparameters
right to make it work.
And it ultimately never worked
as well as the baseline method.
A next possibility that we've
implemented these modifications
incorrectly.
To sanity check
this, we actually
emailed the authors of all of
the different modifications
and asked them to check
our implementation.
All of the ones
that got back to us
said that it looked
correct to them.
And then finally
the last option is
that maybe these modifications
of the transformer
don't really kind of transfer.
They don't transfer across code
bases, and implementations,
and applications.
And to us at least, based on
the evidence that we have this
is a plausible possibility.
In my opinion, the best
way to control for this
is if you're proposing
a new modification
to the transformer, try to
apply it to as many code bases
and tasks as you can without
tweaking hyperparameters.
And if it works in all of those
settings then you're golden.
And your thing
probably will transfer.
And we think that
it's probably the case
that simpler modifications,
like changing the non-linearity,
are not so dependent
on hyperparameters
and implementation details.
And so they may be
the ones that are more
likely to transfer so to speak.
So that's all
discussed in this talk.
I recognize that was
kind of a whirlwind tour.
So I've linked all of the papers
that I discussed on this slide
here.
Of course, this was work done
by a huge and truly amazing
group of collaborators over
the course of these five papers
who I've listed on
the screen here.
And yeah, I'm happy to answer
any additional questions
that you all have.
OK, so thank you so much,
Colin for that great talk.
And yeah, it was a bit of
a fire hose of information.
I realized also there
was one thing I forgot
to say in my introduction.
So I guess I need
to have an afterword
as well, which is
that Colin has now
started as a professor at the
University of North Carolina.
So effectively the
University of North Carolina
is playing a big
part in this course
because it was also the
source of the Cherokee data
that we used for assignment
4 for the Cherokee English
translation.
So Go Tar Heels.
But yeah, so, yeah, so Colin's
happy to stay and answer
some questions.
So if you'd like to have more
questions, use the raise hand
and we'll then
sort of invite you
into the where people can
see each other Zoom Room.
And if you're up
to it would even
be nice to turn on
your video so people
can see who they're talking to.
And yeah, maybe in
the first instance
you should stop
sharing the screen.
And if there's something
you want to show again
you can turn it back on.
Yeah, maybe I'll
just say while there
are people are still around
on the point of me being
a professor at UNC, in the event
that there are any master's
or undergraduate students in
the audience who are applying
for PhD programs that the
application deadline for UNC
has actually, has
not occurred yet.
So if you maybe want to
apply to another school,
have another option, you're
excited about the work
that I presented, you
can still apply to UNC.
We have a remarkably late
application deadline.
So just a plug, in
case there's anyone
who is looking for a PhD.
And UNC is the oldest public
university in the nation.
And we did a full
UNC advertisement.
And I think we have the
second oldest CS department
too, which yeah, it's
been around for long.
It's pretty small.
It's only about
50 faculty or so.
So while we're waiting
for someone to join up--
We do have one question already
actually from [AUDIO OUT]
Yeah, hi.
Thanks for the lecture.
I have a question about earlier
when you discussed like the T5
overfitting, and how many
passes through the dataset it
took for it to over fit.
So I'm curious as
to if you think
some of the larger models like
the 3 billion, 11 billion,
ones with the scaled C4
layers are overfitting.
And kind of generally
how do you know
when a model is overfitting
especially on this scale?
Yeah, so I mean if you
measure overfitting
sort of the standard
way where you compare
the loss on training data versus
the loss on validation data,
we see that even in the
very, very large models
it's roughly the
same, which suggests
in the traditional sense
that there is no overfitting.
One reason for that is that
C4 is actually big enough
that we do just over
one pass over it
when we train for
a trillion tokens.
And you know you might hope
that you see limited overfitting
when you only see
each piece of data
basically once over
the course of training.
So it's sort of like
every time you're
seeing data it's new data.
So there's not a huge
difference between the data
on the training set
and the validation set.
Of course, there
is also this notion
of overfitting that's
kind of like worst case
overfitting, which ties into the
memorization work I mentioned.
It does seem that it's
possible for language models
to memorize data even when
they do relatively few passes
over the training
dataset and you
don't see kind of
average case overfitting
by comparing the training
loss and the validation loss.
I see.
That answers that.
Thank you.
Yep.
OK, then [AUDIO OUT]
there's a question or two.
Sure, sorry I was trying
to unmute my video
but I can't do that
for whatever reason.
First of all,
Colin, thank you so
much for this fantastic lecture.
I really enjoyed it.
One thing that I
particularly enjoyed
was the work that you guys
did on your training data
extraction attack, trying
to identify, really test
this hunch on OpenAI
and EFF's point
that these models don't
actually memorize trained data.
I'm wondering, I actually
have two questions.
One, have OpenAI and EFF
since changed their tone?
Since you actually
or has your team
actually published
the results of that?
And they since acknowledged
that well-constructed models
may actually do this?
And two, would this
approach actually work
for detecting other say
externally encoded biases
towards, or like
extreme biases which
are prevalent in
some language models?
Would you be able
to create packages
that could simulate these sorts
of attacks on these models
and then determine with
some degree of accuracy
how much these biases
actually are present?
Yeah, so with regards
to the first question,
I don't know of any
official statements that
have been made by
anyone but I will
say that actually on
the memorization paper
we had multiple
co-authors from OpenAI.
So it was very much a
cooperation with them.
I mean, we're all
scientists and you
know we all kind of make
hypotheses that sometimes turn
out correctly and incorrectly.
And so I think OpenAI
is definitely aware
and on the side of
the fact that yeah,
it is possible that these
models might memorize data even
when they don't exhibit
the traditional signs
of overfitting.
To the second point, the
way that people have kind of
measured this in
an ad hoc way is
by feeding a prefix
into the model
about a particular demographic
group, or type of person,
and see what the model
says about that person.
And I think in principle
you can kind of
think of our approach
as related to that,
except that we have this
additional step that kind of
measures whether the model is
generating that text because it
saw it in its training
data, basically
because the perplexity
is excessively
low for some continuation
compared to a model that wasn't
trained on the same data.
So it might be
interesting, for example,
if you feed the model
a prefix that you're
asking it to fill in some
offensive information
about some demographic
group, to check
whether the perplexity of the
model for its continuation
is dramatically lower
than zlib, for example.
And in that case,
you might think
that the bias actually, maybe
this like bias that the model
has picked up is because
it saw some, actually
a sentence that looks just
like that in its training data.
Or if it's a more
kind of loose concept,
that the model has internalized
over the course of training.
Fantastic.
Thank you, very, very
much for sharing.
Yeah, thanks for the questions.
OK, so next up I
guess is [AUDIO OUT]
Great, thank you for the talk.
That was super interesting.
So my question is sort
of what are your thoughts
on potentially doing
like multiple rounds
of pre-trainings, so to make
it more concrete, you know,
like let's say you have a
task somewhere like something
like response generation.
And you've got very bespoke
to the particular response
generation dataset that you
use, but potentially you
want to kind of spruce
that up by bringing
in some general dialogue
dataset that consists
of naturalistic human data.
So I'm wondering if you kind of
have any thoughts or intuitions
on how effective it
is to maybe start
with the general internet
and then fine tune
on this dialogue, unstructured
dialogue dataset, and then
fine tune on maybe a more kind
of tightly scoped response
generation dataset.
Yeah, so the technique
you're describing
sounds pretty similar to this
really excellent approach
that people now call domain
adaptive pre-training or task
adaptive pre-training.
I was introduced in
a paper called "Don't
Stop Pre-training," and then
there's a less catchy subtitle.
And the idea is very similar
to what you proposed.
Basically, you take
a pre-trained model
that was trained
on generic text,
you do what you might call like
intermediate task training,
or you do continued pre-training
on domain specific data.
And then finally,
you do fine tuning
on your specific
fine tuning dataset.
In their case, they're
considering things
like doing a scientific
text classification,
or biomedical text analysis.
And when they do an intermediate
pre-training step in domain
data, or even just doing
the pre-training objective
on the data from the task, it
definitely helps significantly.
And yeah, so that's a
very excellent intuition.
And I think that that's the most
similar method to what you're
describing.
It does kind of raise a clear
question that I don't think
has been addressed
to my knowledge
in the literature,
which is we usually
think of transfer learning as
pre-train and then fine tune.
And now we're doing kind
of like pre-training, then
maybe some more pre-training,
and then fine tuning.
And there are other methods
that kind of inject other steps
along the way.
And so there's this
natural question
of what should the
curriculum of tasks be?
How many intermediate
steps should there be?
What should the
intermediate steps be?
What's the benefit of one
domain versus the other?
How much domain shift is there?
And what are the corresponding
benefits and so on?
And I think there
would be, there's
a fascinating line of work
that would be better basically
better answering
those questions.
Great.
And what was the acronym called?
Yeah, so it's called a DAPT
or TAPT, Domain Adaptive
Pre-training or Task
Adaptive Pre-training.
The other paper's called
"Don't Stop Pre-training" which
is easy to remember if you like
the song "Don't Stop Believing"
which is how I,
don't know if it's
an intended reference to that
song, I assume it must be.
I think they should
have done a Don't
Stop Pre Trainin'
with an apostrophe
if they really wanted
to drive it home
but maybe that would
have been too cheesy.
But anyways yeah,
the paper's called
"Don't stop Pre-training."
All right, that's great.
Thank you so much.
Yeah.
Absolutely.
OK, next question is
[AUDIO OUT] I'm not sure quite
what that name corresponds to.
Yes, hi.
Thank you, Colin for the talk.
Found it really interesting.
I've got kind of an
open ended question.
I'm really looking
for some advice here.
So it feels like the recent
headline grabbing advancements
in the NLP industry
have been achieved
by building these
massive models,
like GPT-3 with billions of
parameters that oftentimes cost
millions of dollars to train.
And these advancements
are funded
by like larger organizations,
like Google, Facebook, OpenAI,
who more or less have infinite
resources to train, right?
So my question is as
a sole practitioner
with limited resources but an
infinite appetite for learning,
what are some ways
that I can participate
in these advancements
and kind of just partake
in what's happening
in the industry?
Yeah, absolutely.
I mean, I actually totally
sympathize with you
and agree with you in
the sense that most
of the development
of these models
is taking place by small
groups behind closed
doors at large corporations.
And that's not usually how I
like to see science developed.
I like to see it as a
community endeavor that
involves all kinds of
stakeholders with varying
amounts of resources.
And we're not really quite at
that stage with this work yet.
I do think that to the
extent that people are still
releasing pre-trained models,
which is true for example,
for T5 but not for GPT-3.
There is a lot of work to be
done on basically analysis.
Some of the stuff that we
were discussing earlier, you
know even the memorization
work is basically I
would say it's
like analysis where
some of the stuff
pertaining to bias involves
and analyzing these models.
And I think there's so
little that we actually know
about how these models work.
And what makes them
useful at scale
that there's plenty of room
for interesting analytical work
which requires
significantly less compute.
I guess I would say a
couple other things.
One is that I do really
hope that the field moves
more towards community
develop models and moves
towards frameworks that allow
people to collaboratively train
a model, for example like
in a distributed fashion.
I think that that's an
incredibly exciting research
direction.
It's something that I'm
working with my students
on in my lab at UNC now.
And the last thing I'll say,
and I actually don't usually
like saying this, but
I'll say it anyways.
I do think that our
field often undergoes
sort of a tick-tock pattern,
where we show something
is possible at
scale, and then we
show that the scale is
not necessary to achieve
the same thing.
And to some extent,
you could argue
that this has happened
already for GPT-3 in the sense
that we saw GPT-3
come along, get
outstanding results
on for example
SuperGLUE with only
32 examples per class.
And then there
was the paper that
proposed this method
called IPET, which I think
is interactive-- an iterative
pattern exploited training,
that is basically comparable
performance in a dramatically
smaller model with the
same amount of data.
And you can point
to other examples.
I personally like to attribute
the story of attention's
invention to the fact that
researchers at the Montreal
Institute for
Learning Algorithms
couldn't afford an
eight GPU machine,
so they couldn't run the
giant LSTM in the sequence
to sequence paper.
So they needed to
invent something
that worked better but didn't
require such a big model
so they invented attention.
Of course, it's not good
advice to give, to tell someone
that they should just go
invent something smaller
but I am at least hopeful that
some of these things that we've
shown are possible at scale
are also possible at a much
smaller scale.
So thank you.
Yeah.
And I think there's
no one else who
has a hand up at the moment.
Maybe now's the moment for
John to ask his question,
but if any other
people have questions,
now's a good point to jump in.
I was just going to ask
a question from the Q&A,
[AUDIO OUT] came in
and asked it live so.
Yeah, I will say one other thing
just quickly, which is that T5,
I was very, like I said I was
very excited that we achieved
near human performance
on SuperGLUE.
The model that came along and
actually closed that 0.5% gap
is a model that is about
10 times smaller in terms
of parameter count.
So that that's like another
reasonable example of,
I mean it's still
quite big but at least
as you make algorithmic and
architectural improvements
sometimes you can
close these gaps.
Well, thank you again, Colin.
And let you
whatever, have a beer
and go to bed or something.
Yeah, yeah, sounds great.
Yeah, thanks again
for having me.
It's such a pleasure
so, and I should
say if anyone has any
follow up questions
they think of later on I'm
always excited to get emails
about this kind of stuff.
It's the stuff I
like working on, so.
OK, thank you again for the
great and informative talk.