Hello, everyone.
Welcome back to CS224N.
And today, I'm delighted to
introduce our final guest
speaker, Yulia Tsvetkov.
So Yulia is
currently a professor
at Carnegie Mellon University.
But actually, starting
from next year
she's going to be a professor
at the University of Washington,
that you can already see
updated in her email address.
Yulia's research focuses on
extending the capabilities
of human language technology
beyond individual cultures
and across language
boundaries, so
lots of work that
considers the roles
of human beings in different
multilingual situations.
And today, she's going
to be giving a talk to us
on "Social & Ethical
Considerations in NLP Systems."
Just one more note on the
way things are going to run--
so Yulia has some
interactive exercises.
So what we're going to do is
for the interactive exercises,
you'll be asked to put something
into the Zoom comments--
sorry, the Zoom chats.
That means really
using the chat.
And you might want to set
who to the chat is to,
I think it's by default
panelists, which is OK,
or to Yulia.
So if it goes to the
panelists, it's good.
But probably not all
attendees, because that
would be a bit overwhelming.
And then if you have
questions, put them in the Q&A
as usual, because that'll
keep the two streams separate.
And as for our other
invited lecturers,
if you've got some
questions that you'd
like to ask Yulia at the
end, stay on the line
and raise your hand.
And we can promote people
to be panelists and have
a chat with Yulia.
OK, so without further ado, I'm
delighted to have you, Yulia.
Thank you very much, Chris.
I'm very excited to speak
to you all today despite--
unfortunately, I cannot see you.
But I'm excited.
So this lecture is
structured as follows.
We'll have three parts.
The first part will be
primarily a discussion
in which I will ask questions.
It's supposed to be interactive.
But I realize we are
very limited in ways
we can interact now.
So this is when please
put the responses, if you
want, in the chat window.
And I will answer
my own questions
following also your
responses, and maybe
read some of your responses.
So this will be the first part.
And the goal of this
part is to provide you
some practical tools.
When you have a new
problem to work on
in the AI in your
field, how would you
assess this problem in terms of
how ethical it is to solve it?
What kind of biases does
it incorporate, and so on?
So in the second
part, I will try
to generalize, to
give a review of what
are overall topics in the
intersection of ethics and NLP,
because it's actually
a very big field.
And what I will talk about today
is just a motivational lecture.
But there is a lot of
interesting technical content
and a lot of subfields
of this field.
And I will dive a little deeper
in one topic in this field,
specifically focusing
on algorithmic bias.
And if time is left,
which I am not sure about,
I will talk about
one or two projects
in my lab, so specific
research projects.
But if we don't have
time to cover it,
then you can always
read the paper.
So the first two parts are
more important for the purpose
of this lecture.
So let's start.
As far as I understand,
this is a course
on deep learning and
natural language processing.
So you've probably covered
various deep learning
architectures and their
applications to various NLP
tasks, like machine
translation, dialogue systems,
question answering.
And there is an
obvious question.
What does it all has
to do with ethics?
What does syntactic parsing
or part of speech tagging
has to do with ethics?
And the answer which
I want to suggest
is this quote, that--
it's a simple answer,
that the common misconception
is that language
has to do with words.
But it doesn't.
It has to do with people.
So every word, every
sentence that we produce,
language is produced by people.
It is directed
towards other people.
And everything that
is related to language
necessarily involves people.
And it has social meaning and
incorporates human biases.
And this is why,
also, models that we
build which will be
used by other people
may incorporate social biases.
So this is why decisions that
we make about our data, what
kinds of considerations that
we incorporate into our model,
may have direct impact on
people and maybe societies.
And to start this
lecture, we need
to start with understanding
what is ethics.
So what is ethics?
Here is a definition from
a textbook on ethics.
"Ethics is a study of
what are good and bad
ends to pursue in life and
what is right and wrong to do
in the conduct of life."
So it is a practical discipline.
And the primary goal is to
determine how one ought to live
and what actions one ought to
do in the conduct of one's life.
So to summarize, it
is very practical.
And it's simple.
It's just doing the good things
and doing the right things.
Then my question to
you is, how simple
it is to define what is
good and what is right?
So let's start discussion by
diving into various problems.
And we start with a
boring theoretical problem
which everybody knows about,
which is the trolley dilemma.
And we won't spend
too much time on it.
I am sure all of about it.
So it's a classical problem
in ethics in which--
so this is you,
standing near the lever.
And here is a trolley coming.
And there are several people.
So the trolley cannot
see the people.
And the people cannot
see the trolley.
And you are the only one
in control, in charge.
You can save people.
And maybe you need to make
decisions about people's life.
And you ask yourself, why me?
But the point here
is that imagine
that there are five
people on one side
and then no one
on the other side.
And then I would
ask you, would you
pull the lever to save five
people if the trolley is
supposed to go straight?
And if I would ask
you interactively,
everybody would say yes,
I will pull the lever.
And then I will follow up
with the next question.
OK, what about if five people
on one side and only one person
on the other side?
So would you pull the lever to
minimize the number of lives
that will be sacrificed?
And some people will not answer.
Some people will say yes.
Some people will say no.
And those who will say
yes, I will ask them,
what if this one person is your
brother and on the other side
just five random people?
What would be your answer?
And I can go on and
on and on to make
this problem harder and harder.
And as you can
imagine, there are--
the answers are
difficult. And also, we
don't know what the answer will
be in the actual situation.
And while this problem
is theoretical,
it is in part
becoming relevant now
when we talk about
self-driving cars.
So I am now moving
closer to the topics
that we will discuss today.
And I want to introduce
a new problem which
I call the chicken dilemma.
So in this dilemma,
let's train a classifier.
And this will be a
simple CNN classifier.
And the input to the
classifier is an egg.
And the classifier needs
to define the gender
of the chicken, of the chick.
And that decides if it's a hen,
it will go to egg laying farm.
And if it's a rooster, it
will go to a meat farm.
So first of all,
do you think you
can build such a classifier?
I'm sure every
student in this course
will easily build
this classifier.
And I'm sure it will have
a quite good accuracy.
And then the question to you
is, do you think it is ethical?
And I invite you to type
your responses in the chat.
Yes, no.
I mean, you can
justify a little bit.
Thank you.
Thank you for participating.
So could you repeat
the question?
So the question is,
there is an egg.
You need to determine
the gender of the chick.
And if it's a rooster, it
will go to a meat farm.
And if it's a hen, it will
go to an egg laying farm.
And the question
is, is this ethical?
So there are all
kinds of responses.
Let's see.
So yes and no--
but you can use the
exact same thing
to target ethnic groups
instead of chickens.
So, yes.
Thank you.
And I see there are many
interesting responses here.
Just the amount of responses,
I cannot even have time to read
them because--
so anyway, based
on this question,
I can tell you what
my thoughts are.
So as a vegetarian, I
maybe think it's unethical.
But as a mother, I actually
want my kids to eat meat.
And whether I think
it's ethical or not,
we are doing this anyway today.
And there are all kinds of
considerations, pro and cons.
For example, this is what
already is done today.
And then maybe such
classifier will minimize
the suffering of the animal.
But on the other hand, we hope
that in the future society,
the life of a chicken
will be as valuable
as the life of a person.
And I can continue on and on.
But from this example--
I also don't want to
stay on it too long--
you can see that the
questions of ethics
are difficult, that whether--
you don't know too
much about this field.
But you can feel what
is the right answer.
So ethics is inner-guiding.
It's moral principles.
And there are often
no easy answers.
So there are many gray areas.
And importantly, ethics
changes over time
with the values and
beliefs of people.
So whatever we discuss
today, we can think
it's ethical or not ethical.
But it may change
in a hundred years.
And maybe hundred
years ago, this
would not even be a question
why this would be unethical.
And another important
point is that this
is what we are doing today.
So what is ethical
is what is legal,
is not necessarily aligned.
We can do legal things that
will still be unethical.
And now having
this pimer, I want
to move to the actual
problems, the actual problems
that we can kind of be asked
to build and decide whether we
want to build them or not.
And the way I will
guide this discussion
is I will ask you
specific questions.
And I will ask you
for your answers.
And I realize it's
very difficult to read
the chat, the specific answers.
But the point is that
the types of questions
that I will ask you, these
would be the questions
that you could ask
yourself when you
need to build the technology.
And maybe the question whether
something is ethical or not
is a difficult question.
But let's try to
break down an analysis
of a specific application
of a specific model
to kind of derive
an answer which
will give us some tools to
derive an answer in an easier
way.
So here is the next classifier
that we want to build.
We want to build
an IQ classifier.
So we will be talking about
predictive technology.
So based on people's
personal data--
for example, facial images.
And maybe we can collect
the texts of these people
on social media.
Let's predict the
IQ of the person.
So if you don't
know what IQ is, IQ
is a general capacity
of an individual
to consciously adjust their
thinking to new requirements.
So it's basically how
intelligent a person is.
So this is already not
a hypothetical problem.
You can collect
individuals' data.
their texts online.
And you collect it.
And you can collect training
data to predict people's IQ.
But when I will ask you, is this
an ethical question or not, it
might be a difficult question
to answer immediately.
Thank you very much
for participating.
I really appreciate it.
I hope I can save this chat
later to read your answers.
OK, so let's start with
the first question.
We need to predict people's
IQ from their photos and text.
And then the first
question that if I
ask you, is it ethical
or not, I don't know.
And then you can
ask yourself, first,
who would benefit from
such a technology?
So can you think who would
benefit from a technology that
predicts an IQ of a person?
Hiring.
Right.
Employers, schools,
universities--
so it's your answers.
Right.
So overall, it can be a
useful technology, right?
Immigration Services can
benefit from it, right,
and invite only smart people to
immigrate to a country, right?
Even individuals with high IQ
can benefit from this, right,
because they would maybe
not need to do GRE and SAT.
They would not need
to write essays.
They would just need
to show their IQ.
OK, so this technology
can potentially be useful.
And then the next
question is, let's assume
we can build such a technology.
I will show you later
that we actually cannot.
But even if we can
build such a technology,
let's think about corner
cases and understand who can
be harmed by this technology.
So basically, what is the
potential for dual use?
How this technology
can be misused?
So assume that the classifier is
100% accurate now for a second.
And please think about it.
And type who do you think can
be harmed from such a classifier
and how this classifier
can be misused.
Right.
So I can see your answers.
And I wish we can
have this interactive.
But I can try to summarize
what I have read so far.
So first of all, one of
you wrote that IQ is--
let me just answer my
question because it's
difficult to summarize the chat.
The interactive
feature is difficult.
So I would think
about it in this way.
First of all, why would we want
to build such a classifier?
So to build a classifier to
predict an IQ, companies,
universities, they don't
really need to know your IQ.
What they're trying to predict
is your future success,
the way you will succeed
in a job or the way
you will study at school.
And then the question is,
is IQ is the right proxy
for future success?
And the answer is, no.
IQ correlates with
future success.
But it's not necessarily the
right proxy for future success.
And then, who are people
who could be harmed?
For example, people who have
lower IQ but very hard-working
people, people who have lower
IQ but have good soft skills--
so assuming that,
first of all, the IQ
is a proxy of future success
is a incorrect, biased proxy.
And this kind of problem of
using a proxy to the actual
label-- because we cannot
have the actual label,
the future success.
We cannot have this label.
It's actually very
common in other types
of predictive technology.
If you think about
parole decisions,
technology that decides
on parole decisions, what
they want to predict is
whether the individual
will recommit the crime.
But this is a label that
is very hard to obtain.
And this is why they might
resort to another label,
whether this individual will
be convicted of a crime again,
and build this technology to
predict future conviction.
But conviction of a
crime is a biased proxy
of the actual objective
that we want to have,
the likelihood to
make the crime.
And this is one example for
biased proxy, which does not
[INAUDIBLE] us to build the
right application for the goals
that we have.
So this is one problem.
The second problem
is IQ test itself.
It is a biased test.
So actually, we cannot
build an accurate classifier
for the right IQ.
And also, if we look at the
data that we use, this data--
picture, photos
on social media--
this data is biased itself.
So there are all
kinds of biases,
because of which we cannot
actually build the right model.
And this is why this classifier
will not be 100% accurate.
But there will be many
individuals who can be harmed.
And then there
will be questions.
For example, assume our
classifier that we built
is not actually accurate.
But it has high accuracy--
for example, 90% or 95%.
And then I would ask you, is
95% a good accuracy, or 99%
a good accuracy?
And then the questions to
think about is whether--
what would happen with
misclassification?
What would be an impact
on individual lives
if the classifier
makes mistakes?
And in this case,
the important point
is that the cost of
misclassification is very high.
It has effect on people's lives.
So accuracy may be not
the right evaluation
measure for this classifier.
And another question
that I could ask
is, for example, this
condition on this line,
that we find out that white
females have 99% accuracy,
but people with blond hair under
age 25 have only 60% accuracy.
So what does it tell you
about this classifier?
Right.
So the data set
itself is biased.
This means,
basically, that people
with blond hair
under the age of 25
are underrepresented
in your data set.
So there are all
kinds of questions
and all kinds of
probing questions
that you can ask about the
classifier to understand,
is this the right
problem to solve?
Who can be harmed?
Am I optimizing towards
the right objective?
Is my data biased?
And what is the cost
of misclassification?
How do I assess the
potential for dual use
and how much harm
this technology can
bring, in addition to
how useful it can be?
And then one last
question, which
is a hard one, I want to
ask you who is responsible?
So I'm your manager in Google.
And you're working in a country.
And I ask you, please
build an IQ classifier.
And you build an IQ classifier.
And you publish a paper
about the IQ classifier.
And this paper is
publicized on media.
So then the question
is, who is responsible?
Is it the researcher
or developer?
Is it the manager?
Is it the reviewer who
didn't catch the problems
with IQ classifier?
Is it university or company?
Or is it society?
Yeah.
So there is one nice
answer that I want to read,
is that all of us
should be responsible.
So in practice, there
is very little awareness
about understanding what
problems are ethical or not.
And there is no clear
policies here, right?
This is a complicated issue.
And it's not clear
who is responsible.
This is why assuming
that whoever
is aware of such dangers
should be responsible.
So I don't know what is the
right answer to this question.
So now, what is the difference
between the chicken quantifier
and the IQ classifier?
Right.
So one of your answers is that
one affects people and one does
not, right?
While chicken classifier
actually affects
chicken's lives and the IQ
classifier will not kill
anyone-- it can harm,
but will not kill--
we do feel that IQ
classifier currently can
have potentially worse impacts.
So AI systems are
pervasive in our world.
And the question about
ethics are specifically
raised commonly about
people-centered AI systems.
And these systems
are really pervasive.
So they interact with people
like conversational agents.
They reason about people,
such as profiling applications
or recommendation systems.
They affect people
in other lives,
like parole decision
applications that I mentioned,
face recognition,
voice recognition.
All of these, actually,
have this component
of predictive technology and
the human-centered technology.
And this is why ethics
is critical here.
So I want to move
to a next study.
The next study is a
study of detecting--
so we, again,
build a classifier.
And we want to
identify the ability
to accurately identify
one's sexual orientation
from mere observation.
So this study is
called "AI Gaydar."
And there are, as I mentioned,
many similar studies,
studies that predict potential
for terrorist attacks, studies
that predict
predictive policing.
And also, if you heard
about Cambridge Analytica,
all of them incorporate
very similar technology.
So let's talk about
this "AI Gaydar" study.
And the goal is to understand,
again, what kind of questions
we could ask about this study
and what kind of pitfalls
we could prevent if we
would ask these questions.
So to summarize the study,
the research question
is, we need to identify
the sexual orientation
from people's images.
And the data
collection process is
that we can download photos
from a popular American dating
website.
And there are 35,000 pictures,
all white, equal representation
for gay and straight,
for male and female.
Everybody is represented evenly.
The method that was used
is a deep learning model
to extract facial features
and grooming features,
and then a logistic
regression classifier
applied to classify the
final label, gay or straight.
And the accuracy of this
classifier is 81% for men
and 74% for women.
So this is a summary
of the study.
And I see rightfully, you
ask questions, why would
we ever need such an AI system?
This is a good question.
But I don't want to
publicize this study
or disparage a
specific researcher.
But this is a good
study to present
as an example of
what could go wrong
at all levels of the study.
So this is why I'm
discussing it now.
So what went wrong here?
So let's start with an ethics
of the research question.
So is it ethical at all to
predict sexual orientation
from facial--
from any kind of features?
And I see a lot of comments.
And thank you for the comments.
So first of all, this is
not a new research question.
From 19th century, there
were multiple studies
to correlate sexual identity
with some external features.
And then it was genetics.
People were looking for gay
genes, gay brains, gay ring
fingers, and so on.
So maybe moving from 19th
century to 21 century,
we can again ask, who can
benefit from such a classifier?
And who can be harmed
by such a classifier?
So what do you think?
Who could benefit from
such a classifier?
So autocratic
governments, right.
But also maybe dating
apps, advertisers,
conservative religious
groups, and so on.
So we could think, who would
want to use such a classifier?
Then, maybe who can be
harmed by such a classifier?
Now again, assuming-- we are
not thinking if it's possible
at all build such a classifier.
And as you can guess, we will
see that it's not possible.
But what would stop you from
building such a classifier?
What do you think could be
harmful in this classifier?
So yeah, thank you
for your answers.
I will summarize them.
So many people can be
harmed by such classifier.
And I summarized, basically,
many of your answers
here on this slide.
So this potentially can
be a dangerous technology.
So in many countries, being gay
person is prosecutable by law.
And it can lead even
to death penalty.
It might affect people's
employment, relationships,
health opportunities, right?
Importantly, this is not only
about sexual orientation.
So there are many attributes,
including sexual identity,
that are private for people,
that are protected attributes.
And they can be non-binary.
They can be intimate and
not visible publicly.
And most importantly is
that these attributes
are specifically those
attributes against which people
are discriminated against.
And this is why it is
especially dangerous
to build such a technology.
So in the paper, in the
published paper, the argument
for building this--
for presenting this
study was that this study
is an alert how easy it is
to build such a classifier,
and basically an
alert for to expose
the threat to the privacy
and safety of people.
And then I would be
interested to hear
if you have counter
arguments for this argument.
OK, so basically, there can
be many counterarguments.
One of them is that this is a
classifier, this technology.
So like a knife is a technology.
And with a knife,
you can kill people
and you can cook food, right?
And you don't necessarily
need to kill people
with a knife to expose
the dangers and harms
of this technology, right?
And another issue is
that this is actually not
possible to build such a
classifier with the data
that researchers had.
And this is what
we will see when
we will discuss additional
details about the data.
And another comment
is, as I said,
this is only one instance
of such a technology.
Here is another instance, which
is a successful startup called
Faception, which has
drawn a lot of funding.
And its goal is to
identify terrorists
based on facial features.
And unlike in the
previous study,
this startup doesn't show what
technology they developed.
But you can guess that it
can have similar dangers.
So in general, building
predictive technology
is very pervasive.
It's ubiquitous.
But it is always--
and sometimes, it's not as
kind of clear cut unethical.
For example, many people
in NLP published papers
on predicting gender
from comments.
And it is not clear, basically,
when the technology is clearly
harmful and unethical and
where it can be actually used
in good ways.
For example, we all want
our research to work, right?
And to work well and
to be personalized,
the algorithm actually needs
to know something about us.
So again, this is
not an easy question.
But in the case
of the classifier,
maybe it's already
on the extreme.
OK, let's move to
the data, again,
to discuss basically
what questions
could be asked about the data.
So here's how the
data was collected.
So photos were downloaded
from a popular American dating
website.
They were public.
And there were a few thousands
of images, all white,
and a balanced data set.
And my first question is, what
can you say about the data?
So is it OK to use this data
if there is no robots to steal,
the photos are public.
What can be counter arguments
to using people's photos
from a dating website?
There is a hint on the slide.
Lack of consent.
People did not intend
for their photos
to be used to build
a classifier--
private information.
Right.
So thank you for your answers.
So the points that I
wanted to emphasize here
is that it was legal
to collect this data.
But again, it's not
clear whether it
was ethical to collect this
data, because as you said,
people did not provide--
maybe did not provide--
35,000 people did not
provide consent for using,
specifically, this data.
And there are more
important global issue here
is that there is a difference
between data that is public
and data which is publicized.
So public, it's fine,
because these people
want to be found by
the social circle
that they are targeting when
they publish their photo
on the dating website.
But this does not
mean necessarily
that they want to be found
by a broader social circle,
by their families, by their
colleagues, and so on.
So there is a big difference
between the data that is public
and the data which
is publicized.
So overall, even if they did
not violate terms of service,
I don't know about it.
I didn't read in
depth, actually.
But they did violate
the social contract
because this was not the intent
of the user for their data
to be used in this way.
Next question about data--
so what do we think
about this data set?
It's 35,000 pictures,
all white, balanced
in terms of sexual
orientation and balanced
in terms of gender.
It's white.
OK, so does not
represent the population.
So, right.
So basically, you can
guess that this dataset.
has many, many
biases incorporated.
It contains only white people,
only people who self-disclose
their sexual identity.
It represents very certain
social groups-- people
who put their photos on the
dating website of specific age
of specific ethnicity.
And basically, these
are photos that
were carefully selected to
be attractive to their target
audience.
So this data set contains
many types of biases.
And also, as one
of you mentioned
and as is written on
this slide, the data set
is balanced, which does not
represent the true distribution
in the population.
So what does it mean?
This means that this model is
built on a very biased data
set.
And you as students at Stanford,
you understand that it cannot
be used, for example, on
a non-white population.
It cannot be used on the photos
of people not from that dating
website.
We don't actually know what
this classifier learned.
Maybe the most
important features
were the watermark of
this specific website.
I don't know.
Or some other confounds,
spurious confounds.
But the point is that once
the classifier is out,
those who want to
use it maliciously,
they don't know that this
technology is actually not
applicable for
any other data set
except for this
specific data set.
So this technology is biased.
And it also shows
that it's basically
not a credible result.
OK, so let's move on.
And final question is that--
this is a deep learning model.
It's a black box model.
And then there is the question
of how to analyze errors
in the learning model,
specifically when
we work on such a critical,
such sensitive topics
like predictive technology,
not necessarily predicting
sexual orientation,
but for example,
predicting gender, which is,
again used in many companies?
So it is very difficult
to understand whether it
is OK to use this technology.
But the point is
that we need to be
able to analyze it and
evaluate it properly.
And the last point is
about the accuracy again.
And I'm going back to the
points that I mentioned also
in the IQ classifier.
So the accuracy of this
classifier is 81% for men
and 74% for women.
Is it a good accuracy,
or is it a bad accuracy?
So the numbers are OK for some
tasks, but not for others.
But importantly, for
this type of problem,
it's important to
understand that the cost
of misclassification is
not equal to the cost
of correct prediction.
And here is kind
of visual examples.
So if my algorithm misclassifies
my dog as a cookie,
is the cost of this
misclassification
is high or low?
So I guess it's
just funny, right?
It's funny.
There is nothing offensive here.
And then the next question--
if my algorithm
misclassifies me with my dog,
is the cost of
misclassification high or low?
It can be funny, but
maybe not for everyone.
We already don't know.
And then the photo that I
don't put here but the one
that maybe many
of you have heard
is the gorilla incident that
happened in Google in 2016.
So in this case, there
was a misclassification
of an African-American
woman as a gorilla.
And to understand
how expensive is
the cost of this
misclassification,
we need to understand the
whole history of dehumanization
of Black people in
the US, and so on.
So we can see the difference.
For the same algorithm
and same types of errors,
there are different
types of errors that
are more expensive than others.
So this is why it is
important to assess
AI systems adversarially.
And now I just want to
reiterate the types of questions
that I ask because these are
the kinds of questions that you
might want to ask yourself next
time when you need to build
another predictive technology.
And the first is to understand
the ethics of the research
question.
And sometimes it's not
very easy to understand.
But just ask yourself these
more specific questions.
If I build this
technology, who could
benefit from such a technology,
and who can be harmed by it?
So try to see the corner cases.
And also, what about the data?
Could sharing this data have
major effect on people's lives,
like in the case of
AI data classifier?
The next question that we
can ask is about privacy.
What did we discuss?
Who owns the data?
And is this data not only
public or legal to use, but also
are we violating the social
circles to which the data is
publicized?
Are we violating a social
contract in the way
that the public data
is expected to be used?
And user consent is not
always possible to obtain.
But we need to understand
implicit assumptions of people
who put their data online.
Now the next question is, what
are possible biases in data?
What are artifacts in data?
What are distributions
for specific populations
and subpopulations?
How representative, or what
kind of misrepresentations
are in my data?
And next is, what is basically a
potential bias in these models?
When I build this
model, do I control
for confounding variables?
And do I optimize for
the right objective,
like in the case of
the IQ classifier?
And also, if I have biases,
does my system amplify biases?
And finally, it is not
enough to measure accuracy
because the semantics of false
positives and false negatives
can be different.
Sometimes the cost
of misclassification
is much higher than the
cost of correct prediction.
So I also need to
understand how to evaluate
the models properly.
And why is it
especially relevant
now is because, as
you all know, there
is an exponential growth
of user-generated data.
And it's really easy
to build the tools.
Each of us can build the
IQ classifier or gaydar.
But the question is, what kind
of technology we will produce?
So in this, I finish the
first part of the discussion.
And I put in this slide some
recommended papers and talks
specifically on the introductory
topics, on the impact of NLP.
And I think these are--
there are hundreds or
thousands of similar talks.
But these are my favorites.
So if you want to read
more, please take a look.
Should I stop for questions?
Or should we move
to the next part?
Right at the
moment, there aren't
any outstanding questions.
So maybe it's OK to
move on, unless anyone's
desperately typing.
OK.
And the chat window
is really nice.
There are so many responses.
Thank you all.
And I hope to get,
later, this chat.
I will read it.
I think we can save it, yeah.
Thank you.
OK, then we can move
on to the second part
about algorithmic bias.
So what are the topics in the
intersection of ethics and NLP?
So the first one is
algorithmic bias.
And this is about bias
in data and NLP models.
And this is something
that I will talk more
in the second part.
But the important to understand
that the field is much broader.
So the next topic is
incivility, so ability
to develop NLP tools to
identify-- to actually, data
analytics to understand the hate
speech, toxicity, incivility
online.
And this is a very
complicated field
because it's not only about
building the right classifiers.
There are many, many questions,
such as if I post hateful
comment, who does this
comment belong to?
Does it belong to a company?
Does it belong to me?
Should it be removed or not?
Because it is not clear
where is the boundary
between the free speech
and the moderated speech,
how to minimize the harms
but defend the democracy,
these questions are
very subjective.
And they're not regulated.
So this is a big,
difficult field.
The next field is about privacy.
So again, who does
this data belong
to, and how to protect privacy?
This field of privacy
is actually very, very
under-explored in NLP.
Among other fields,
I think there
is some research on incivility,
on algorithmic bias,
on other fields, but very
little research on privacy.
Misinformation-- so
information manipulation,
opinion manipulation, fake news.
So there is a
whole range of ways
that data can be
manipulated, from generated
texts and disinformation to just
advertisement and more subtle,
propaganda and subtle
opinion manipulation.
And there are many, many
interesting research projects
that can be done, really with
the focus on the language
of manipulation, which I think
is just an interesting topic
to explore.
And finally, the
technological divide--
so when we build our
tools, even if it's
a part of speech
tagger, what are
populations for which are
served by these tools.
So there is a certain
divide that technologies
are built unequally.
There is no one language,
no two languages.
There are 6,000
languages in the world.
And there are many populations.
And there are
certain areas of NLP
which are completely
under-explored.
For example,
language varieties--
we think we can solve
a problem for English,
for the problem of
dependency parsing.
But we don't account for
different varieties of English.
What about Nigerian English?
What about
African-American English?
What about Indian English?
So there is a
technological divide
that is currently present.
And as you see in the
bottom, this picture
shows that the field is
highly interdisciplinary.
So AI researchers cannot
actually solve the problem
of misinformation alone.
To be able to address the
problem of misinformation
or hate speech, we need to have
not only engineers, but also
ethicists and social scientists
and activists and politicians
who actually are responsible
for policies and the linguists,
because many of these phenomena
are interesting phenomena which
are not in words, but
more in pragmatics.
So this is a very interesting
field scientifically, but also
very challenging to work on.
And there are some
recommended resources.
And in particular, the one that
might be interesting to you
all is CS 384, is a
seminar by Dan Jurafsky,
that is an amazing, also, list.
So if you want to take a
look on specific subfields--
so this is a general overview.
And now I want to talk
about one of these subfields
and give some
explanation, why do
we have algorithmic
bias in our models?
So let's start, again,
with interaction.
I know you have the slides.
But don't look forward.
And I want to ask you questions.
And please type.
Which word is more likely to
be used by a female, giggle
or laugh?
Just type quickly.
Don't think too much.
So please look at the chat
and see the majority response.
It is absolutely giggle.
You're right.
Next question--
which word is more
likely to be used by a
female, brutal or fierce?
Oh, lovely.
It's like 99% fierce.
Thank you.
Next question--
which word is more
likely to be used by an older
person, impressive or amazing?
So actually, from what I
see, it's 100% impressive.
Very impressive.
Thank you for your answers.
Which word is more
likely to be used
by a person of a higher
occupational class, suggestions
or proposals?
Do you see how correctly
you answer my questions?
So next question--
why do we intuitively
recognize the default
social-- why do you all
know the right answer?
Right.
Our brains are biased.
So this is about implicit
biases in our brains.
And this is a very good example.
And you can also see
how language perpetuates
and propagates biases, right?
It's all in the language.
If you can could know
from one word who
is the person who said it, you
can imagine what kind of biases
we can extract
from a longer text.
So to understand what's
happening with biases,
we need to understand
how cognition works.
So we have-- this was introduced
by Kahneman and Tversky.
So conceptually,
our brain is divided
into System 1 and System 2.
So System 1 is our autopilot.
It is used to make
decisions without thinking.
It is very fast, parallel,
effortless, and so on.
System 2 is our logical part.
It knows how to analyze
and make decisions
that are unusual for us.
So it is not automatic.
And it's slow,
serial, controlled.
It requires a lot
of mental energy.
So our brain constantly
receives signals
through all the sensors,
through eyes, ears.
There is a lot of incoming data.
There is a lot of
pixels here around me.
But the actual part of
System 2 is only able
to produce a very small
portion of the signals
that we received.
So System 1 is automatic.
System 2 is effortful.
But in practice, over
95% of the signals
that we receive from the world
is relegated to System 1.
And the funny thing
is, as Kahneman wrote,
is that we identify
ourselves with System 2.
We believe that we are
conscious and reasonable beings.
But in practice, most of our
decisions are made by System 1.
So since we are using
autopilot most of our time,
our brain get--
all the information
that we perceive
gets categorized, clusters,
and labeled automatically.
And this is how cognitive
stereotypes are created.
And there are multiple,
multiple cognitive stereotypes
that are aimed to fill
the gaps if we don't
have enough meaning, or reduce
information-- generalize--
if we have too much information,
or to complete the facts if we
are missing facts, and so on.
And this leads to all
kinds of cognitive biases.
So examples of biases would
be in-group favoritism.
So we grew up seeing the
majority of specific people.
And we tend to like those
people more than the minorities.
Halo effect-- that
we know very little
about the person or a
specific social group,
but we tend to generalize.
Based on one trait,
we could generalize
about the whole group and
to other traits, and so on.
There are many biases.
And thanks to these
stereotypes, if I
asked you the
questions, the words,
or if I show you these
pictures, you immediately
know this is
calming, cute, tasty.
And if I show
these pictures, you
would know that maybe it's
dangerous, unpleasant.
And automatically,
when we see a snake,
we will automatically step
down, right, step back.
And we only need to invoke
System 2, for example,
if we decide to touch it.
But most of our
decisions are automatic.
And this is the
same exact mechanism
that creates social
stereotypes in our brains.
So we exactly, in
the same mechanism,
internalize these associations
and make generalizations
about specific groups.
And this is why, when I ask you
which word is more likely to be
used by an older person, 100%
of you typed the word impressive
would be used.
And importantly, these implicit
biases are very pervasive.
And they operate unconsciously.
And one important property
that they are transitive.
So specifically, we are
seeing that the Black
person is playing basketball.
And in the movie, we see that
a Black person uses drugs.
And we immediately
connect it and reinforce,
for example, the associations
with the specific groups.
And the social stereotypes are
not necessarily all negative.
I can name some on-the-surface
positive stereotypes.
For example, Asians
are good in math.
Importantly, they all
have negative effects,
even seemingly
positive stereotypes,
because they
pigeonhole individuals
and put expectations of them.
Or they can just be harmful.
And then, how do
these biases manifest?
They manifest in language.
And for example, they manifest
in subtle microaggressions.
And importantly,
microaggressions
should not correlate
necessarily with sentiment.
So sentiment analysis tools
would not detect them.
On the surface level,
microaggression
can be negative,
neutral, or positive,
like in these examples.
But they actually
bring prolonged harms,
even if they're meant
as a compliment.
And there was a lot of
research in social sciences
that showed that
they can even bring
more harms than
overt hate speech,
because they kind of bring
a significant emotional harm
and reinforce
problematic stereotypes.
So if I will collect these
conversations from Twitter,
do I look OK?
You are so pretty.
Is this a positive or negative?
It's probably a
positive interaction.
And then the next interaction--
check out my new physics paper.
Is it positive or
negative interaction?
Why physics?
You're so pretty.
So we don't know.
We don't have the right context.
And then for this
question, do I look OK?
And all kinds of
responses-- for example, you
are so pretty for your age.
In this case,
these are negative.
These are microaggressions.
They make us cringe, right?
And then the problem is that all
of this human-generated data,
which necessarily incorporates
a lot of microaggressions
and just stereotypes
that we all have--
we are not aware of them--
it is fed to our systems.
So there is a lot
of bias in language,
like the stereotypes
or historical biases
that are perpetuated.
For example, there
are more photos
of male doctors than
female doctors on the web.
Or human reporting biases--
and later, there are biases
also in our data sets.
So for example,
what kind of data
was sampled for annotation?
From which kind of populations?
From which language varieties?
From which locations?
And then, who are we
choosing as annotators?
So there is a bias
in who are annotators
that annotate our data.
And then there is
cognitive biases
of annotators
themselves, how they
treat what is a microaggression
and what is not,
or other questions.
And all these types
of biases later
propagate into our
computational systems.
And this is how we get
from cognitive bias,
social cognitive biases,
to algorithmic biases,
because if you remember
the System 1 and System 2,
currently the way we develop
systems, AI is only System 1.
And why is that?
Because currently, the
way we develop our tools,
the dominant paradigm is
a data-centric approach.
So we need a lot of data
to train good models.
And we do know well how
to leverage a lot of data.
But again, language
is about people.
It is produced by people.
But our existing
systems, they do not
leverage social
cultural context.
We don't know how
to incorporate--
we don't do it, usually.
We don't incorporate which
social biases are positive
and which inductive
biases are good
biases are bad to have.
So overall, our models
are really powerful.
And they're powerful at
making generalizations.
But we don't know how to control
for the right inductive biases,
which inductive biases
are good and which
inductive biases are not.
And then to go into
the next point,
is that these models
are opaque, right?
We don't also know how to
interpret well deep learning
networks, which means it's not
easy to analyze them and spot
the problems.
And as you can guess,
this is not only related
to the field of ethical NLP.
These are just interesting
research questions,
how to incorporate social
and cultural knowledge
into deep learning models, or
how to develop interpretation
approaches.
So what is missing?
Today, what is
missing, for example,
is that existing
classifiers for toxicity
detection-- if we want to build
data analytics to clean up
our data before it propagates
through the models,
we know only how to detect overt
toxic language, such as hate
speech, because we are
primarily sampling our data
and training our data
based on lexicons.
And there is almost no focus
on actual microaggressions
and more subtle
biases, which are often
not in words but in pragmatics
of the conversation,
and understanding who
are the people involved
in the conversation.
So today's tools,
they could be applied
to these kind of
microaggressions or hate speech
detection or sentiment analysis,
but they will necessarily fail.
The next point is that, again,
our models do not incorporate
social cultural knowledge.
And basically, the same comment
can be toxic or non-toxic
depending on who are the people
involved in the conversation.
But our models are data-centric
and not people-centric.
And the more general problem
is that the deep learning
models are really good at
picking spurious correlations.
And this is why, for
example, in this paper,
the three comments which the
only difference in these three
sentences is a
name, and probably
the association of this name
with race or ethnicity--
so our models do pick up
on spurious confounds.
So we think we
predict sentiment.
But we also predict
all kinds of labels
that correlate with sentiment,
but not necessarily are
true predictors of sentiment--
for example, gender or race.
And this is something
very pervasive.
And finally, the models
are not explainable.
So we kind of have
these deficiencies
just in core approaches
to deep learning.
And we have all this data.
And with this data, we
train conversational agents,
personal assistants,
all kinds of systems.
And why do we care now?
Because it can bring harms.
So what kind of unintended
harms it can bring?
Here is an example
of an image search.
If you search for three Black
teenagers-- and this is,
I searched for it when
I prepared this talk
for the first time.
So it was fixed, I guess.
But this is how it
was in June 2017.
And then when you
search for a doctor,
you'll get primarily
male doctors, right,
and primarily white.
And if you search
for a nurse, this
is a stereotypical
image of a nurse.
And if you search
for a homemaker,
this is just top search
results for these query words.
And if you search for
CEO, it's a very specific
stereotypical image of CEO.
And if you search
for a professor,
this one is my
personal favorite.
So you can see all male images.
And there is only one woman.
But if you look
at her background,
you can see these are
simple math facts.
So it's just an
error in the search.
She's not a professor.
And this is the result of,
for example, face recognition.
So these are two examples.
One camera does not
recognize Asian faces
and thinks they are blinked.
On the right, the camera--
this is a video of a
face-tracking camera that
is able to track white
faces, but immediately shuts
down when the Black face comes.
So it is not able to
track Black faces.
So these are all consequences
of the biased data that
propagates into models that do
not incorporate, intentionally,
basically safeguards against
very specific biases.
Now what's going on with
natural language processing?
So this is the slide from
the very beginning that
just lists all possible
applications that I
could think about.
As you can guess,
since 2016, there
are many, many
papers that just--
I don't think there is
any application or core
technologies of NLP left
which did not expose biases
in the NLP technologies.
So here is an example of bias
in the machine translation.
So this is visual.
This is why I'm showing it.
So there are other languages
that mark third person pronouns
with gender, and other languages
that do not mark third person
pronoun with gender.
So if you translate words from
a language such as Hungarian
or from Estonian, that
don't mark third person
pronoun with gender,
into English, which
does mark third person
pronoun as a gender,
you might see similar results.
You will not see them now.
This is what was exposed
maybe a year or two ago.
So basically, translation
from they are a nurse,
this would be, she's a nurse.
But they are the scientists.
The translations would
be, he's a scientist.
And same for engineer,
baker, teacher--
so all the stereotypes,
just historical
stereotypes that you
could think about.
So what are
possibilities to fix it?
One way to fix it
is actually simple.
You could treat
the target gender
just as a target language
is multilingual NMT.
So I don't know, but I suspect
you did look at this paper
on the multilingual neural
machine translation.
And basically, you can add in
another token, for example.
And you can
controllability generate
into female or male translation.
So the fix is not
difficult. But you
need to be aware of
potential dangers
to be able to fix the model.
And importantly,
this is not only
about fixing the model itself,
but also about fixing the user
interface, right?
So the way Google
fixed this interface
is they provided
different translations,
so basically all
possible translations
for different genders.
So the similar kind of
harms were shown especially
in dialogue systems.
So occasionally, such models
make big headings in news,
like Microsoft's
Tay chatbot that
became very racist
and sexist overnight,
and the GPT-3 based models that
was offering suicide advice.
And about two weeks ago,
there was a Korean chatbot
that became extremely
homophobic very quickly
and had to be removed.
So these titles come up again.
These headlines coming
again and again and again.
And I guess the point here is
that the way we do NLP today,
I call it a reactive approach.
So we expose a specific
problem, a problem in search,
a problem in chatbots,
racist chatbots,
or a problem in
machine translation.
And then it creates
bad publicity.
And then we start
revising the models.
But it's not necessarily
that we need to develop
the tools in this way, right?
So I hope that in
the future, we make
a paradigm shift towards
a more proactive approach.
And the specific-- what would
a proactive approach require
is, for example, building
new data analytics.
So basically, rather than
exposing biases, going further
up the pipeline and starting
actually with the data,
and building automatic
moderators and data
analytics that can
identify problematic text,
problematic images, beyond
the words of hate speech,
and then incorporating
the right inductive biases
into the models
and understanding
moving from the
data-centered approaches
to people-centered approaches,
incorporating social, cultural,
and pragmatic knowledge, and
in modeling the right research
questions on how to the
most spurious confounds,
but predict only the target
label, not necessarily picking
up on spurious
correlations, and finally,
on building more
interpretable models.
And importantly, that these
are not orthogonal research
directions--
so for example, to build
good data analytics,
you necessarily need to maybe
have an interpretable model,
and also be able to incorporate
the right social cultural
knowledge, because again,
the microaggressions,
the text is not
necessarily in words.
So what I was going
to do, if I had time,
is I was going to show two case
studies from-- research studies
from my group that specifically
focus on these data analytics,
identifying unsupervised bias
or an interpretable model
for making hate speech
classifiers more robust.
But I will skip it because
we are out of time.
You could show one.
You still have a few minutes.
You could show one
quickly for five minutes.
So basically, we have we
are trying to build these--
green boxes is what we
have today, hate speech
and sentiment analysis.
But we are trying to build
a new kind of class of model
specifically for
social bias analysis.
And in these models,
we would want
to detect who are
the people involved,
so who the comment, for
example, is directed to,
if it's a conversational
domain, and also
to understand what kinds of
microaggressions these are,
and also to maybe
generate explanations
or interpretations through
building more interpretable
models.
And these are the two papers
that I was going to talk about.
One is an unsupervised approach
to detection gender bias.
And one is on if we
have just few examples
of microaggressions in the
classifier of hate speech,
these examples of
microaggressions
are adversarial examples
to the classifier.
The classifier is not
able to deal with them.
But what we can do, we can
focus on interpretability
of the classifier
and, specifically,
making the classifier
understanding for each probing
example, which examples
in the training data
influenced the
classifier's decision--
so changing the approach
through interpretability from
interpreting specific
salient words in the input
of the classifier into
looking at the training data,
sorting the training
data and identifying
which examples where most
influential for classifier
predictions.
So using inference
functions, for example--
this is a paper that
Percy published in 2017.
And through this
classifier, we are
able to surface microaggressions
despite that the classifier
makes the wrong prediction.
So this is just the high-level,
very high-level summary
without talking about
the actual studies.
So I will skip--
let me just skip
the actual papers.
And the slides are there.
I'm happy to discuss later.
I just don't want
to go over time.
So to summarize, the field
of computational ethics
is super interesting.
And there are
interesting problems that
are technically interesting.
They're challenging.
So you don't need to
have a separate kind
of important problems and the
technical interesting problems.
We can work on important
problems which are also
technically interesting, and
focus on important things
like building better
deep learning models.
And these are
interesting subfields.
And if some of
you are interested
in specific projects, so
it's just in our course,
we just put together
a presentation
that just summarizes all
kinds of possible projects
you could do.
Thank you very much.
I wish I could see the audience.
This is so weird, but that's OK.
Thank you, Yulia,
for that great talk.
Yeah, so if people would like
to ask some questions to Yulia,
if you raise your hand, we can
promote you to be panelists.
And I think, then, we can even
have you turn on your cameras
if you want to show
Yulia a real human being.
But if we're waiting to
see if there are people
who would like to
do that, I mean,
there is one question that's
outstanding at the moment,
which is, "Do these
bots become racist,
sexist so quickly after exposure
to the public due to the public
intentionally trying
to bias them, or is it
that common talk
among the public
is racist, sexist enough to
bias any model upon exposure?"
So I think this is both.
But in the case, for example,
of Tay bot the way it was built
is it's a continual
learning system.
So it collects
inputs from people
and then uses them as a
kind of training examples
to generate forward answers.
And as usual, people pick up
on such things very quickly.
And then they intentionally
became racist and sexist
against the bot.
And the bot very quickly
learned to just mimic
the people's behavior.
So it was some malicious
attempt to kind of turn this bot
into racist and sexist.
But this is how the
model was designed,
to collect input
from people but not
monitor the kind of sentences
that are used or not used
in the training data.
So this is, again, going
back to the discussion
of that we actually don't
have good analytics.
Many of these analytics are
just blacklists or whitelists.
They're very, very primitive.
It's not very easy to
incorporate such constraints
into generation, automatic
filtering of data.
There is another question.
Can I ask my question?
Yes.
So I guess we are doing
Q&A with live people.
So you can ask the
question and then--
Yes.
I'm curious, can you go
into a little bit more
about how you measure
your model's performance?
Are there actually public
benchmark data sets you can--
or any sort of
well-defined metric--
that you can sort of
objectively measure
your model's improvements?
Are you talking about
specifically our papers
that I skipped?
Or just in general.
Are there-- I mean, I know
it's a very new field.
And maybe it's harder
to define really
objective measure of bias.
So how do you measure
progress in general?
Or you could also just mention--
This is a good question.
It's very difficult.
It's like there
is growing body of data sets.
For example, in U Dub,
Yejin Choi's group
created the Social
Bias Inference Corpus.
I don't remember what bias--
SBIC.
Overall, the problem of
evaluation is actually
very difficult. And there are
some problems in which there
are existing
evaluation data sets.
If you think about hate
speech, for example, there
are all kinds of data sets.
There are many data sets
for training and evaluating
performance of hate
speech classifiers.
But when we think about
biases, there are much less.
And the big problem here-- it's
not easy to collect such a data
set.
So if you think--
let me actually show why it
is difficult to collect a data
set of, say, microaggressions.
So a naive solution
would be to--
so if you think about
the standard way
of data collection, so
we would sample some data
from the internet.
And we give it to
Mechanical Turk annotators.
And then they would analyze,
is it biased or not?
And we build this
supervised classifier.
So this is what we cannot do in
the case of more subtle biases.
First, because we don't
have a strong lexical sieve
to sample the
right data because,
again, these biases
are not in words.
Like you would just sample
from the whole Reddit corpus?
It's not clear how to
annotate to make it feasible,
not too expensive.
But more importantly,
that every annotator
will incorporate
their own biases.
So you actually need very
well-trained annotators
and multiple
annotations per sample.
So the question of how
to create such a dataset
is very, very difficult.
In our study, we collected the--
so there is a website
called microaggressions.com
that has self-reported
microaggressions, when people
actually recall experiences of
microaggressions against them,
and they quote them.
And this is what we used
to evaluate our data.
But data collection
is as a big problem
currently as just modeling.
Do you want to ask a question?
Right now?
Yeah.
I don't have any other
questions to ask.
Oh, sorry.
OK, so I should go on.
OK, can you hear me?
Yes.
Thanks for the great lecture.
It's a very appropriate
topic for the guest lecture.
So I took the
course CS 182, which
introduced many
notions of fairness
through case studies
and assignments.
And I've been thinking a lot
about some of these functions.
And in the course,
there was mentioned
for research done
by Kleinberg who
showed three different
notions of fairness
can be simultaneously satisfied.
The calibration, which was
like the probability of outcome
given risk scores, the
false positive rate,
the false negative rate cannot
all be completely independent
across protective traits.
So if past a certain
point, these metrics just
become direct trade-offs,
is it the case that fairness
becomes subjective after that?
And I guess more generally,
in ethics research,
has there been frameworks of
creating sort of upper bounds
or constraints among
these different metrics
so we sort of measure how
close we get to the ideal?
This is a very
difficult question.
So right, the fairness research,
there are actually proofs that
you cannot satisfy both
the measures of performance
and inclusivity.
And this is why they
are measured separately,
the false positives,
false negatives.
And the question is whether--
because of this issue,
whether it becomes subjective?
It's even bigger, I guess.
The question here is even
bigger because the question
of inclusivity--
so it competes with the
question of monetization.
If you think who are
the main owners of data
and how they train
algorithms, the goal
is to basically have
better monetization.
Like, who will see
this advertisement?
But there is a competing
objective of inclusivity.
Will this
advertisement reach out
to all kinds of populations?
And it's not only--
it's not subjective.
There is kind of
a clear incentive,
for example, in companies
to maximize monetization
rather than inclusivity, right,
because it's also internal.
I don't have an
easy answer to this.
I agree.
It can be subjective.
Or it can be worse
than subjective
because these
objectives compete.
So would you say
it's sort of more--
the field of ethics
research overall
is more interdisciplinary
and a lot
of these answers
to these questions
are more context-dependent?
It's very
context-dependent, right.
It is very context-dependent.
As I mentioned, for example,
the same application,
in different
contexts, can be used
for good and for bad, right?
And different thresholds
on performance
can be applied for
different types of settings.
And also, I really think
I'm not qualified even
to answer this question, right?
We should ask maybe philosopher
or experts in policy, right,
because eventually, I'm--
I know how to build the tools.
And I'm trying to make
technologies more ethical.
But the question of
how they are deployed
and what are the
specific decisions,
it's very difficult
to control for
and to kind of give
definite answers about this.
OK, so here's another
difficult question for you
from [AUDIO OUT].
And you can't use
that cop-out answer.
So you said,
"Earlier, you showed
the example of "AI
Gaydar" with the question
of why would we
want to study this?
The author is
justified by claiming
that, given the widespread
use of facial recognition,
our findings have critical
implications for the protection
of civil liberties.
Given that some unscrupulous
governments may indeed
implement such technology
to oppress minorities
based on such things
as orientation,
do social scientists
have an obligation
to get ahead of this
threat by understanding
the properties of such models?
How do we weigh the
ethical trade-offs?"
Oh, gosh.
Now I need to respond
from the point of view
of all social scientists.
I can't.
I don't want to answer
philosophical questions.
But I kind of have
the answer about--
maybe a simple
answer to why I don't
agree with the
claim of researchers
that we need to expose
this technology,
to publish, actually,
this paper to expose
the dangers of this technology.
One of them, like the
knife analogy that I gave,
is one of the answers.
So if you think about
a similar field--
not a similar field,
but a similar type
of interaction in
security, right,
in cybersecurity,
so it's very common
to kind of break the algorithm
to show its vulnerabilities,
and then to iteratively fix it.
So this is the approach
that researchers took.
Let's show the
vulnerabilities, that we
are able to build
this technology,
to expose these threats.
But unlike with
the security field,
here the kind of exposure
of this technology,
publication of this technology,
can have real implications
of human life.
So again, the cost of
misclassification--
and if we think
about other problems,
like similar problems,
like the problems of--
I can give many other
similar problems
in which we can expose
this technology which
will harm people.
Like let's create a deep
fakes video, a porn video
with the professors.
We can do it, right, to expose
the danger of technology
of deep fakes.
But what kind of harm it will
bring to specific people who
were involved in
this kind of exposure
of the harm of this technology?
So I have the
answer of why it was
wrong to publish this
study in the first place
and why it's not
productive, is not helpful.
But it's very difficult to
answer the question, what
should social scientists do?
I don't know.
OK.
Well, could I ask
a question next?
Or it's just disappeared.
[INAUDIBLE]?
I think-- can you hear me now?
Yeah.
OK.
Thank you so much for the talk.
It's really interesting,
and as we've just seen,
really challenging stuff.
I guess my question is a
little bit more practical.
So maybe that's a
reprieve for you.
But unfortunately, it seems
like in a lot of NLP and AI
more broadly, some of
this ethics and bias stuff
is like kind of an afterthought.
A lot of projects don't
really necessarily take it
into account from the outset.
And it's more sort
of incidental.
So my question is, as we're
working on NLP projects,
maybe even for our final
course project, what
are some kind of concrete
steps that we could take
or a systematic
approach that we can
use to sort of incorporating
some of this ethics knowledge
in things that might not
explicitly seem like they have
a lot to do with ethics?
So it depends on
the project, right?
I cannot answer generally.
The first part of the lecture
was exactly about this.
If I build my project,
what kind of questions
I can ask to know if
there are some pitfalls?
If it's a different
project, I think overall,
these are important
questions which
are general for deep
learning models, which
could be later used to
create a better technology.
So how to incorporate
understanding
who are the people who
produced the language,
or who are the users?
Incorporating the
right inductive biases,
or a technology for
demoting confounds--
it doesn't have
to be specifically
on ethics-related problems
or interpretability
of deep learning.
It doesn't have to be
ethics kind of project.
But the kind of
technology, if you
can develop such a
technology, eventually it
can be useful for building such
better models that proactively
prevent unintended harms.
So I guess the strategy would
be sort of to just lay out
these general topics, pose these
questions to yourself-- maybe
write them down or
just think about them--
and then proceed as such?
Yeah, so this is how
I think about it.
I think about potential--
if this technology
would be deployed,
what could be corner cases?
What is potential for dual use?
If it works, kind of,
how can it be misused?
And also, when it doesn't
work, what kind of errors
can be harmful?
So this is-- if you go
back to in the slides
to the beginning of the
lecture, these questions,
they could be applied to
many kinds of technology.
And they give a more clear kind
of guidelines to what things--
how bad outcomes
could be prevented.
I'm sure maybe I'm missing
something totally, right?
All of this content--
much of this content
is just I came up
with it by reading
a lot of different papers.
But there is no
clear guidelines.
It's such a new field.
So maybe there are things
that I'm also missing.
Here's another question
from [AUDIO OUT]..
"Are models wrong
for being biased?
In the end, they just learn
what they're designed to learn.
And isn't our intervention to
correct this behavior actually
can cause a bias?"
This is a good question.
So it is kind of a
question that I also
have been thinking about.
Are models wrong for, for
example, reflecting accurately
the real world, right?
Do we need to devise
actively models
to make them fair when
the world is not fair,
when our data is not fair?
So first of all, the way
we train models today,
they don't only
perpetuate biases.
They amplify biases.
So this is a natural behavior
of a machine learning model
that basically, when you have
an input example for which
the confidence is lower, it will
default to a majority class.
This is why if your
data contains biases,
these biases will be amplified
in a machine learning
model trained on this data.
And this is clearly wrong.
Whether it is wrong to
build models that do not
reflect the actual true
distribution in the data,
it's much more
difficult questions.
But there are
clear kind of cases
in which I would say it is
wrong to build a model that,
in the search for CEO, shows
only male CEOs, while kind of--
because it amplifies
biases, but yeah.
This is already a
subjective kind of answer.
It's just my personal
opinion, because not
much to do with the research
that we are doing, right?
Well, would you like
to ask your question?
Yeah, one sec.
Let me, okay, I was
trying to set my video.
But it's saying I can't.
So I guess I'm
just going to ask.
By the way, I don't
see people, anyway.
Well, you could at the
start of the video.
But anyway, let's just go.
Yeah, I'll just ask.
So thank you so
much for your talk.
I have a question
on microaggressions?
So who is to decide what is
considered a microaggression?
Is it the people who
microaggressions are
potentially targeted against?
Is it philosophers
or social scientists
or just people in education?
And in case opinions differ, do
we just listen to the majority?
It all seems crucially important
to me, but very, very difficult
to standardize and kind of
reach a consensus, especially
because different cultures
perceive things differently.
Thank you very much
for these questions.
These are amazing questions.
These are difficult questions.
This is why we did not
create our own corpus
of microaggressions,
right, because it's
culturally dependent.
It's very, very personal.
It's subjective.
This is why we first focused
on a corpus of perceived
microaggressions, people
that actually felt
that the interactions
were negative,
because they knew that
these were microaggressions.
Who is to decide whether
something is microaggression?
Mm.
Yeah, I don't know.
This is very
difficult. What I can
think about practical
solutions about it--
I would say have very
well-trained annotators
who understand what
microaggression is.
So kind of, we explain
what is microaggression,
they see many examples, they
understand that for example,
a sentence that targets
a minority group,
and other things.
And then have many
annotators per one sentence.
So like in the, say, the study--
this is about other social
concepts that are abstract.
For example, in Dan
Jurafsky's study
on respect in
police interactions,
respect is also a
subjective thing, right?
So what they did, they
took every utterance,
and they had multiple
annotators, multiple trained
annotators, for each
utterance, and just increased
the number of voters of
whether an utterance is
respectful or not.
So practically, I
think this should
be the procedure for creating
corpus of microaggressions.
But a more philosophical
question is, who is to decide?
And it's a more difficult one.
Yeah, got it.
Thank you.
So there's still more questions.
But you're allowed
to say that you're
worn out at any point, Yulia.
And if you're not,
the next question--
I feel bad about not being
able to answer big questions
about society and--
but yeah, I'm happy to answer.
The next question is,
"Can you talk a bit more
about the unsupervised approach
to identifying implicit bias?"
I can.
I just need to think how to
talk about it in a few words.
So intuitively, we cannot create
a corpus which has an utterance
and then a label.
Is that sentence biased or not?
So we create a causal
framework in which our target
label is more objective.
Who is this sentence
directed to?
To a man or to a woman?
So our labels are gender labels.
And in a naive way, if given
a sentence towards a person,
without looking at the actual
person and their comment,
just by this comment
towards the person,
we can predict if it's
directed to a woman.
We can say that there is
some bias in the model--
that there is some
bias in the sentence.
But it's a naive
approach because there
are other kinds of ways in
which we can predict the target
gender, but which will not
be associated with bias.
For example, it's the context
of the current station,
the traits of the person that
we are writing to, and so on.
So the crux of our technology
is that we predict gender,
but demote all
kinds of confounds
in the task of detecting bias.
So we demote the signals
of the source sentence.
We demote the latent traits
of the target person.
And so we make this
task very difficult
to detect what is
the target gender.
And if, after all these
demotions of the confounds,
given an utterance that is
directed to a specific person,
we can still classify
this utterance that
is clearly directed to a woman.
It is likely that this
utterance contains bias.
So what I was going to talk
is all kinds of demotion
approaches that we develop.
But once we demote
these approaches
and we can still predict
the utterances, what
is the gender of the
target that would receive,
we actually can surface
some biased sentences.
So these are the main findings.
For example, if we look
at comments directed
to politicians, after
all these demotions,
and we see comments
that kind of clearly
predict the target
gender, we can
see that common for politicians
talk about their spouses,
about their family life, and
also about their competence
Maybe question their competence.
And if we look at common for
public figures, like actresses,
we can see a lot of words
that are just related
to objectification,
sexualization, regardless
of their source content.
So they can talk
about their movie.
But the comments will always
be about that she's sexy.
And this is what our
model is able to surface.
But again, it's
just initial study.
Needs a lot of work.
OK, so around here also
asks, "If microaggressions
are pulled from a site where
people can list what they have
experienced, isn't that
data very vulnerable
to social engineering?"
Yes.
This data is vulnerable.
So in our case, we
anonymize this data.
We extract only
quotes from the data.
We remove the actual
users who published it,
remove all the text
around these quotes.
And this is a good question.
Maybe we should also not make
this data public even yet.
Hey.
And there are more questions.
Good questions.
Thank you.
More questions.
So--
By the way, like if--
Chris, John.
I'm saying Chris, John because
these are the two faces,
the only faces that
I see on my screen.
So please let me know
when we need to finish.
I'm happy to continue answering.
We've often gone on
for a few more minutes.
So I can ask a couple
more questions.
OK.
So here's one that's
very prominent in AI
right at the moment.
"Do you think it is fair
for AI scientists in tech
and academia, who
are definitely not
representative of the
general population,
to decide what is
biased and what is not,
i.e., the act of de-biasing
itself might be biased?"
Yeah, this is one
problem also that--
this is like more general
problem, that researchers--
even those who work
on the bias, can
incorporate their own biases.
We currently don't have any
other alternative, right?
We don't have a
training how to do it.
We don't have--
I think it's a good thing
to work on these topics,
to try to promote these
topics as much as possible,
with an awareness that we as
researchers can incorporate
our own biases.
So this is what we also, right,
in the ethical implications
sections in the paper, that
we try to identify bias.
We try to de-bias.
But there are
limitations to this study
because we could incorporate our
own biases into our analysis,
right?
This is how we
interpreted these results.
Maybe this is what
we were looking for
and this is a confirmation bias.
Yeah.
OK, maybe should
just have one more--
oh, no.
A new question just turned up.
Maybe it'll have to
be two questions more.
[INAUDIBLE]
They're still coming in.
Now it's-- I mean, maybe I
should do that one immediately,
because it directly relates
to that answer, which was,
"How are the perspectives of
community stakeholders-- i.e.,
people from minoritized groups--
included when these systems are
being built?
This is a wonderful
question too, yeah.
Currently, not very good.
Actually, we currently
have a paper also
in submission about analysis
of how race have been treated
in NLP systems, starting
from data sets to models
to potential users.
And one of the
things that we found
is that even people who
work on identifying racism,
they don't involve
actually in-group members.
Yeah, you identified yet another
problem in the community.
The perspectives of community
are not often incorporated.
In our acquisition paper, we try
to advocate for its importance.
But all these questions
are very good.
But maybe somebody like Chris,
who has a lot of influence,
could make changes
in the community.
It's very difficult
to make such changes.
I guess I'm hopeful
that there's actually
starting to be a bit
of change right now.
I mean, one can be
pessimistic given the history,
and one can be pessimistic
given the current statistics.
But you know, I
actually believe that
through recent events of Black
Lives Matter and other things,
that there's actually
just more genuine attempts
to create change around--
well, certainly the Stanford
computer science department,
but I think more generally
around the field of AI,
than there's been at any
time in the past 30 years
when I've been watching it.
Right.
Even when I did my postdoc
at Stanford in 2016,
we started working on the
problem of gender bias.
And it was a total outlier.
I didn't know if what I'm doing
will be relevant to anyone.
And then now look.
We discuss this as a kind
of relevant question.
This is already an amazing
change in the community.
And if there will
be more focus also
on the right hiring
which clearly now
has more awareness than ever.
Right.
I'm also more optimistic now
than, say, three years ago.
OK, well maybe I'll do this--
But these are wonderful
questions for which there
are no good answers yet, yeah.
Maybe you can do this
as the last question,
unless you say something that
really elicits a lot more.
"What do you think
the social and ethics
space might look like, say,
5 to 10 years down the line?
Do you think the
industry might come down
to a unified standard of
ethics for AI systems,
given that a lot of the
challenges come from the fact
that social and
ethics discussions are
often subjective?"
Yeah, I'm also optimistic
about the field
of ethics in five years.
These are difficult problems.
The field of ethics,
by the way, itself
is 2000 years old, right?
Aristotle already
asked these questions.
And now we're asking
these questions about AI.
But given the current awareness
and the bad publicity,
is that currently, companies
are the main players, right?
It's more even than governments.
And there is a big
incentive at companies
to fix things because
of the bad publicity.
And for example, today
I read an article
about that Google will
stop advertisement
that track the profile
users, like these plug-ins.
So overall, I do see a
very positive trajectory.
It's very difficult to
predict what exactly
will be like in five years.
I don't think all the
problems will be resolved.
But overall, I'm optimistic also
about that new policies will
be already not entirely
in the hands of decisions
of companies.
And definitely about research,
because I see how many students
now are interested in
these topics, which
is totally amazing.
OK.
Oh, and another comment that
I want to make is actually,
NLP is important in all this,
which was much less said.
The field of fairness
very much focused
on the image recognition.
But I think more and more,
we'll see more and more research
on NLP and language,
which is also exciting.
OK, well maybe we should
call it quits at that point.
Thank you so much, Yulia.
Thank you very much.