Good afternoon, folks.
Welcome to lecture 18.
Today, we'll be
talking about some
of the latest and greatest
developments in neural NLP,
where we've come, and
where we're headed.
Chris, just to be sure,
are my presentation notes
visible from this
board at this time?
You're visible.
OK, but not my
presenter notes, right?
Correct.
OK, good, thank you.
So just as a reminder, note that
your guest lecture reactions
are due tomorrow at 11:59 PM.
A great job with the
project milestone reports.
You should have
received feedback now.
If not, contact
the course staff.
I think we had some
last-minute issues,
but if that's not resolved,
please contact us.
Finally, the project
reports are due very soon,
on March 16th,
which is next week.
There's one question on
Ed about the leaderboard,
and the last day to
submit on the leaderboard
is March 19th as well.
OK, so for today,
we'll start by talking
about extremely large
language models and GPT-3
that have recently gained
a lot of popularity.
We'll then take a closer
look at compositionality
and generalization of
these neural models, why
transformer models
like BERT and GPT-3
have really high performance
on all benchmarks?
They just fail in
really surprising ways
when they provide.
How can we strengthen
our understanding
of evaluating these models so
they more closely reflect task
performance in the real world?
And then, we end by
talking about how
we can move beyond this really
limited paradigm of teaching
models language
only through text
and look at language grounding.
Finally, I'll give
some practical tips
on how to move forward in
your neural NLP research,
and this will include
some practical tips
for the final project as well.
OK, so this meme
really kind of captures
what's been going on
in the field, really,
and it's just that ability
to harness unlabeled data
has vastly increased
over the last few years.
And this has been made possible
due to advances in not just
hardware, but also systems,
and our understanding
of self-supervised
training, so we
can use lots and lots
of unlabeled data.
So based on this, here's
a general representation
learning recipe that just
works for, basically,
most modalities.
So the recipe is
basically as follows.
So convert your data.
If it's images, convert it.
Or it's not-- it's
really modality-agnostic.
So you take your data out, if
it's images, text, or videos,
and you convert it into
a sequence of integers.
And in step two,
you define a loss
function to maximize
data likelihood,
or create a denoising
auto-encoder loss.
Finally, in step three, train
on lots and lots of data.
Certain properties
emerge whenever
we scale up model size.
And this is really the
surprising fact about scale.
So to give some examples of this
recipe in action, here's GPT-3.
Which can learn to do a really
nontrivial classification
problem with just
two demonstrations.
And we'll talk more
about this soon.
Another example, as
we saw in lecture 14,
is T5, which does
really effective closed
book QA by storing
knowledge in its parameters.
Finally, just so I
cover another modality,
here's a recent
text-to-image generation
model with really impressive
zero shot generalization.
OK, so now let's
talk about GPT-3
So how big, really,
are these models?
This table kind of
presents some numbers
to put things in perspective.
So we have a
collection of models,
starting with
medium-size LSTMs, which
was sort of a staple in
pre-2016 NLP, all the way
to humans, who have
100 trillion synapses.
And somewhere in
the middle, we have
GPT-2 with over a billion
parameters and GPT-3 with over
150 billion parameters.
And this exceeds the number
of synaptic connections
in a honeybee brain.
So obviously, anyone
with a little knowledge
of neuroscience
knows that this is
an apples-to-oranges
comparison, but the point here
is that the scale
of these models
is really starting to
reach astronomical numbers.
So here are some
facts about GPT-3.
For one, it's a large
transformer with 96 layers.
It has more or less the
same architecture as GPT-2,
with the exception that to
scale up attention computation,
it uses these locally banded
sparse attention patterns.
And I really encourage
you to look at the paper
to understand the details.
The reason we
mention this here is
because it kind of
highlights that scaling up
is simply not just
changing hyperparameters,
as many might believe,
and it was really
non-trivial engineering
and algorithms
to make computations efficient.
Finally, all of this is
trained on 500 billion tokens
taken from The Common
Crawl, Toronto Book
Scholars, Wikipedia.
So what's new
about GPT-3, right?
So let's look at some of the
results on the paper first.
So obviously, it does better
on language modeling and text
completion problems.
As you can see
from this table, it
does better than GPT-2 at
language modeling in the Penn
Treebank, as well as
better on story completion
on the story completion
data set called LAMBADA.
To get a flavor
of what's to come,
let's take a closer look at this
LAMBADA story completion data
set.
So the task here is that
we're given a short story,
and we are supposed to
fill in the last word.
Satisfying the
constraints of the problem
can be hard for a language
model, which could generate
a multi-word completion.
But with GPT-3, the
really new thing
is that we can just give
a few examples as prompts
and sort of communicate a task
specification to the model.
And now, GPT-3 knows
how the completion
must be a single word.
This is a very, very
powerful paradigm,
and we get some more examples
of this in-context learning
in a couple more slides.
So apart from language
modeling, it's
really good at these
knowledge-intensive tasks,
like closed-book QA, as well
as reading comprehension.
And here, we
observe that scaling
up parameters results
in a massive improvement
in performance.
So now let's talk about
in-context learning.
GPT-3 demonstrates some
level of task adaptation
to completely new tasks.
This happens via what's
called in-context learning.
As shown in the figure,
the model training
can be characterized as
having an outer loop that
learns the set of
parameters that
makes the learning of the inner
loop as efficient as possible.
And with this sort
of framework in mind,
we can really see how a good
language model can also serve
as a good few-shot learner.
So in this segment, we will
have some fun with GPT-3
and look at some demonstrations
of this in-context learning.
So to start off,
here is an example
where someone's trying to
create an application that
converts language, a
language description,
to bash one-liners.
The first three
examples are prompts,
followed by generated
examples from GPT-3.
So it gets a list of
running processes, right?
This one is easy.
It probably just involves
looking through a hash table.
Some of the more
challenging ones
that involve copying
over some spans
from the texts-- like the scp
example is kind of interesting,
as well as a harder
one to parse, grep.
The scp example comes up
a lot during office hours,
so GPT-3 knows how to do that.
Here's a somewhat
more challenging one,
where the model is
given a description
of a database in
natural language,
and it starts to
emulate that behavior.
So the text in bold is sort of
the prompt given to the model.
The prompt includes
somewhat of a function,
function specification
of what a database is.
So it says that the database
begins knowing nothing,
and the database knows
everything that's added to it,
and the database does
not know anything else.
And when you ask the
question to the database,
if the answer is
there in the database,
the database must
return the answer.
Otherwise, it should say it
does not know the answer.
So this is very new
and very powerful.
And the prompt also
includes some example usages
of when you ask 2 plus 2,
the database does not know.
When you ask the
capital of France,
the database does not know.
And then you add in
a fact that Tom is
20 years old to the database.
And now you can start
asking questions
like, where does Tom live?
And as expected, it says that
the database does not know.
But now, if you ask
it, what's Tom's age,
the database says that
Tom is 20 years old.
And if you ask what's
my age, the database
says, basically, that
it does not know,
because that's not been added.
So this is really powerful.
Here's another one.
Now, in this example,
the model is asked
to blend concepts together.
And so there's a
definition of what
does it mean to blend concepts.
So if you take
airplane and car, you
can blend that and
get flying car.
That's essentially--
there's a Wikipedia
definition of what
concept blending is, along
with some examples.
Now, let's look at some
problems for what GPT-3 answers.
So the first one
is straightforward.
Two-dimensional space
blended with 3D space gives
2.5-dimension space.
The one that is somewhat
interesting is old and new
gets recycled.
Then, triangle and
square gives trapezoid.
That's also interesting.
The one that's really nontrivial
is a geology plus neurology
is sediment neurology, and
I had no idea what this was.
It's apparently correct.
So clearly, it's able to do
these very flexible things just
from a prompt.
So here's another
class of examples
that GPT-3 gets somewhat
right, and these
are these copycat
analogy problems
which have been
really well-studied
in cognitive science.
And the way it works
is that I'm going
to give you some
examples, and then
ask you to induce a
function from these examples
and apply it to a new query.
So if a b c changes to a b
d, what does p q i change to?
Well, p q i must
change to p q s,
because the function you've done
is that the last letter must
be incremented by 1.
And this function,
humans can now
apply to examples
of varying types.
So p repeated twice, q repeated
twice, r repeated twice
must change to p repeated
twice, q repeated twice,
and s repeated twice.
And it seems like GPT-3
is able to get them right,
more or less, but the
problem is that if you
ask it to generalize to
examples that have an increasing
number of repetitions,
then, that we're
seeing in the prompt,
it's not able to do that.
So in this situation, you
ask it to make an analogy
where the letters are
repeated four times.
And it's never seen that before.
It doesn't know what to do.
And so it gets all
of these wrong.
So there's a point
to be made here
about just maybe
these prompts are not
enough to convey the function
the model should be learning,
and maybe with more
examples, it can be done.
But the point is
that it probably
does not have the same
kind of generalization
that humans have.
And that brings us to sort of
limitations of these models
and some open questions.
So just looking at the paper
and parsing through the results,
it seems like the model is bad
at logical and mathematical
reasoning, and anything
that involves doing
multiple steps of reasoning.
And that explains why
it's bad at arithmetic,
why it's bad at word
problems, why it's not
great at analogy-making.
And even like traditional
textual intermediate datasets
that seem to require
logical reasoning, like RTE.
So the second, more
subtle point is
that it's unclear
how we can make
permanent updates to the model.
Maybe if I wanted you
to model a new concept,
that's possible
to do it while I'm
interacting with the system.
But once the interaction's
over, it kind of
restarts and does not have
a notion of knowledge.
And it's not that this is
something that the model cannot
do in principle, but just
something that's not really
been explored.
It doesn't seem to exhibit
human-like generalizations,
often called systematicity, and
I talk a lot more about that.
And finally,
language is situated,
and GPT-3 is just
learning from text,
and there's no exposure
to other modalities.
There's no interaction.
So maybe the aspects of
meaning that it acquires
are somewhat
limited, and maybe we
should explore how we can
bring in other modalities.
So we'll talk a lot more about
these last few limitations
in the rest of the
lecture, but maybe I
can pause for some questions
now, if there are any.
I don't think there's a
big, outstanding question,
but I mean, I think some people
aren't really clear on few-shot
setting and prompting
versus learning,
and I think it might
actually be good to explain
that a bit more.
OK, yeah.
So maybe let me take
a simple example.
Let me take this example here.
So prompting just
means that-- so GPT-3,
if you go back to
first principles,
right, GPT-3 is basically
just a language model.
And what that means
is, given a context,
it will tell you what's the
probability of the next word,
right?
So if I can give it a
context w1 through wk,
GPT-3 will tell me what's
the probability of WK+1
for [INAUDIBLE] the vocabulary.
So that's what a
language model is.
A prompt is
essentially a context
that gets prepended before
GPT-3 can start generating.
And what's happening
with in-context learning
is that the context
that you append,
that you prepend to GPT-3
are basically x, y examples.
So that's the prompt, and
the reason why it's also--
it's equivalent to
few-shot learning
is because you prepend a
small number of x, y examples.
So in this case, if I just
prepend this one example that's
highlighted in
purple, then that's
essentially one-shot learning
because I just give it
a single example as context.
And now, given this query, which
is also appended to the model,
it has to make a prediction.
So the input/output
format is the same
as how a few-shot
learner would receive,
but since it's a language
model, the training dataset
is essentially presented
as the context.
So someone is still
asking, can you
be more specific about the
in-context learning setups?
What is the task?
Right, so let's see.
Maybe I can go to--
yeah, so maybe I can
go to this slide.
So the task is just that
it's a language model.
So it gets a context, which
is just a sequence of tokens,
and the task is just to--
so you have a
sequence of tokens,
and then the model
has to generate,
given a sequence of tokens.
And the way you can convert that
into an actual machine learning
classification problem is that--
so for this example, maybe you
give it 5 plus 8 equals 13,
7 plus 2 equals 9, and
then 1 plus 0 equals,
and now, GPT-3 can
fill in a number there.
And so that's how you convert it
into a classification problem.
The context here would be these
two examples of arithmetic,
like 5 plus 8 equals 13
and 7 plus 2 equals 9.
And then, the query
is 1 plus 0 equals.
And then, the model, since
it's just a language model,
it has to fill in 1 plus
0 equals question mark.
So it fills in something there.
It doesn't have to
fill in numbers;
it could fill in anything.
But if it fills in a 1,
it does the right job.
So that's how you can
take a language model
into few-shot learning with it.
I'll keep on these questions.
How is in-context learning
different from transfer
learning?
So I guess the--
in-context learning,
I mean, you can
think of in-context learning
as being a kind of transfer
learning, but transfer
learning does not
specify the mechanism
through which the transfer is
going to happen.
With in-context
learning, the mechanism
is that the training
examples are sort of
appended to the model, which
is a language model, just
in order.
So let's say you have
x, y, x1, y1, x2, y2,
and these are just appended
directly to the model.
And now it makes prediction on
some queries, some queries that
are drawn from this data set.
So yes, it is a subcategory
of transfer learning,
but transfer learning
does not specify
exactly how this transfer
learning is achieved.
But in-context learning
is very specific
and says that for
language models,
you can essentially concatenate
the training data set
and then present that
to the language model.
If people still aren't
sufficiently clear on what is
and what isn't happening
with learning and prompting,
so another question is so
in-context learning still
needs fine tuning question mark?
We need to train GPT-3 to do
in-context learning, question
mark?
Right, so there are two parts
to this question, right?
So the answer is, yes and no.
So of course, the model
is a language model.
So it needs to be trained.
So you start with some
random parameters,
and you need to train them.
But the model is trained
as a language model, right?
And once the model
is trained, you
can now use it to do
transfer learning.
And the model parameters in
in-context learning are fixed.
You do not update
the model parameters.
All you do is that you give
it these small training
sets to the model,
which is just appended
to the model as context,
and now the model
can start generating
from that point on.
So in this example, if 5 plus 8
equals 13 and 7 plus 2 equals 9
are two x, y examples, in
vanilla transfer learning, what
you would do is that you would
take some gradient steps,
update your model parameters,
and then make a prediction on 1
plus 0 equals what, right?
But with in-context
learning, all you're doing
is you just concatenate 5
plus 8 equals 13 and 7 plus 2
equals 9 through the
model's context window
and then make it predict what
1 plus 0 should be equal to.
Maybe we should end
for now with one
other bigger-picture
question, which
is, do you know of
any research combining
these models with reinforcement
learning for the more
complicated reasoning tasks?
So that is an
excellent question.
There is some
recent work on kind
of trying to align language
models with human preferences,
where yes, there is some
amount of fine-tuning
with reinforcement
learning based
on these preferences
from humans.
So maybe you want to do a
summarization problem in GPT-3,
and the model produces
multiple summaries.
And for each summary,
maybe you have a reward
that is essentially
a human preference--
like maybe I want to
include some fact,
and I don't want to include
some other non-important fact.
And so I can construct
a reward out of that,
and I can fine-tune the
parameters of my language model
basically using
reinforcement learning
based on this reward, which is
essentially human preferences.
So there's some very recent
work that tries to do this.
But I'm not sure--
yeah, I'm not aware
of any work that
tries to use reinforcement
learning to teach reasoning
to these models,
but I think it's
an interesting future
direction to explore.
OK, maybe you should
go on at this point.
OK.
OK, so we'll talk a bit more
about these last two points--
so systematicity and
language grounding.
So just to start off, how
do you define systematicity?
So really, the
definition is that there
is a definite and predictable
pattern among the sentences
that native speakers of
a language understand.
And so there's a systematic
pattern among the sentences
that we understand.
What that means is, let's say
there's a sentence like, "John
loves Mary" right?
And if a native speaker
understands the sentence,
then they should also be able
to understand the sentence,
"Mary loves John."
And closely related to
this idea of systematicity
is the principle of
compositionality.
And for now, I'm going to ignore
the definition by Montague
and just look at the
rough definition,
and then we can come
back to this other, more
concrete definition.
But the rough definition
is essentially
that the meaning
of an expression
is a function of the
meaning of its parts.
So that brings us
to the question,
are human languages
really compositional?
And here are some examples that
make us think that maybe yes.
So if you look at,
what is the meaning
of the noun phrase
"brown cow," so it
is composed of the
meaning of the adjective
brown and the noun cow.
So all the things that are brown
and all things that are cow,
take the intersection
and get "brown cow."
Similarly, red rabbits, it's
all things that are red,
all the things that are rabbits,
combine them, get red rabbits.
And then, kicked the
ball, this verb phrase
can be understood as you
have some agent that's
performing a kicking
operation on the ball.
But this is not always
the case, that you
can get at the meaning
of the whole thing
by combining meanings of parts.
So here you have
some counter-examples
that people often use.
So a red herring does not mean
all the things that are red
and all things that
are herring, and "kick
the bucket" definitely
does not mean
that there's an agent
that's kicking the bucket.
So while these examples are
supposed to be provocative--
we think that language is
mostly compositional-- there's
lots of exceptions.
But for the vast majority of
sentences that we've never
heard before, we're
able to understand
what they mean by piecing
together the words
that the sentence
is composed of.
And so what that means is
that maybe compositionality
of representations is a
helpful prior that could lead
to systematicity in behavior.
And that brings us
to the questions
that we ask in the segment.
Are neural representations
compositional?
And the second question
is, if so, do they
generalize systematically?
So how do you even
measure if representations
that a neural network learns
exhibit compositionality?
So let's go back
to this definition
from Montague, which says
that compositionality
is about the existence of
a homomorphism from syntax
to semantics.
And to look at that, we
have this example, which
is, Lisa does not skateboard.
And we have a syntax tree
corresponding to this example.
And the meaning of
the sentence can
be composed according
to the structure that's
decided by the syntax.
So meaning of "Lisa
does not skateboard"
is a function of the
meaning of "Lisa"
and "does not skateboard."
The meaning of "does
not skateboard"
is a function of "does"
and "not skateboard."
The meaning of "not skateboard"
is a function of "not"
and "skateboard."
So that's good, and
so this gives us
one way of formalizing how we
can measure compositionality
in neural representations.
And so compositionality of
representations could be
thought of as how well the
representation approximates
an explicitly homomorphic
function in a learnt
representation space.
So what we are going to
do is essentially measure,
if we were to construct a neural
network whose computations are
based exactly according
to these parse trees,
how far are the representations
of a learnt model from this
explicitly compositional
representation?
And that will give
us some understanding
of how compositional
the neural networks'
representations really are.
So to unpack that a little
bit, instead of having--
yeah, so instead of
having denotations,
we have representations
in the node.
And to kind of be more
concrete about that,
we first start by
choosing a distance
function that tells us how far
away two representations are.
And then, you also need
a way to compose together
two constituents to give us sort
of the meaning of the whole.
But once we have that,
we can start by--
we can create an explicitly
compositional function, right?
So what we do is we have
these representations
at the leaves that are
initialized randomly,
and the composition function
that's also initialized
randomly, and then a forward
pass according to this syntax,
is used to compute the
representation of "Lisa
does not skateboard."
And once you have
this representation,
you can create a loss function.
And this loss function
measures, how far
are the representations
of my neural network
from this second sort
of proxy neural network
that I've created?
And then I can basically
optimize both the composition
function and the
embeddings of the leaves.
And then, once the
optimization is finished,
I can measure, how far
was the representation
of my neural net from this
explicitly compositional
network on a handout set?
And that then tells me
whether the representations
that my neural net learned were
actually compositional or not.
So to see how well this
works, let's look at a plot.
And this is relatively
complex, but just
to unpack this a little bit,
it plots the mutual information
between the input that the
neural network receives versus
the representation against
this tree reconstruction error
that we were talking about.
And to give some more
background about what's to come,
there is a theory which
is called the information
bottleneck theory, which
says that as a neural network
trains, it first
tries to maximize
the mutual information
between the representation
and the input in an attempt to
memorize the entire data set.
And that is called--
that is a memorization phase.
And then, once
memorization is done,
there is a learning or a
compression phase where
this mutual information
starts to decrease
and the model is essentially
trying to compress the data
or consolidate the knowledge in
the data into its parameters.
And what we're seeing here
is that as the model learns--
which is characterized by
decreasing mutual information--
we see that the
representations themselves
are becoming more and
more compositional.
And overall, we
observe that learning
is correlated with increased
compositionality as measured
by this tree
reconstruction error.
So that's really encouraging.
So now that we have a method
of measuring compositionality,
of representations
in these neural nets,
how do we start to
create benchmarks?
Let's see if they are
generalizing systematically
or not.
So to do that, here is a
method for taking any data set
and splitting it into
a train/test split that
explicitly tests for this
kind of generalization.
So to do that, we use this
principle called maximizing
the compound divergence.
And to illustrate how
this principle works,
we look at the store example.
So in the store example,
we have a training data
set that consists
of just two examples
and a test data set
of just two examples.
The atoms are defined as sort
of the primitive elements--
so entity words,
predicates, question types.
So in the store example,
Goldfinger, Christopher Nolan,
these are all sort of
the primitive elements,
and the compounds
are the compositions
of these primitive elements.
So, "Who directed entity?"
would be the composition
of the question type
"did x predicate y" and
then the predicate direct.
So here's a basic machinery
for producing compositionally
challenging splits.
So let's start by introducing
two distributions.
So first distribution is
the normalized frequency
distribution of the atoms.
So given any data set, if we
know what the notion of atoms
are, we can basically
compute the frequency of all
of the atoms and then normalize
that by the total count,
and that's going to give
us one distribution.
And we can repeat the same
thing for the compounds,
and that will give us a
second frequency distribution.
So note that these are just
two probability distributions,
and once we have these
two distributions,
we can essentially define the
atom and compound divergence
simply as this quantity here.
And where there is the Chernoff
coefficient between two
categorical distributions,
the Chernoff coefficient
basically measures how far two
categorical distributions are.
So just to get a bit more
intuition about this,
if we set p to q, then
the Chernoff coefficient
is 1, which means these
representations are maximally
similar.
And then, if p is non-zero,
everywhere q is 0--
or if p is 0 in all the
places where q is 0--
then the Chernoff
coefficient is exactly 0,
which means that these two
distributions are maximally
far away.
And the overall goal by
describing this objective
is that--
this loss objective
is just that we
are going to maximize
the compound divergence
and minimize the
atom divergence.
And so what is the intuition
behind doing such a thing?
So what we want is to ensure
that the unigram distribution,
in some sense, is constant
between the train and test
split so that the model does
not encounter any new words.
But we want the compound
divergence to be very high,
which means that these same
words that the model has seen
many times must appear in
new combinations, which
means that we are testing
for systematicity.
And so if you follow
this procedure
for a semantic parsing data
set, let's say, what we see
is that as you
increase the scale,
we see that this
model just does better
and better at a
compositional generalization.
But just pulling out a
quote from this paper,
pre-training helps for
compositional generalization
but doesn't fully solve it.
And what that means
is that maybe,
as you keep scaling
up these models,
you'll see better and
better performance,
or maybe it starts to
saturate at some point.
In any case, we
should probably be
thinking more
about this problem,
instead of just trying
to brute-force it.
So now, this segment
kind of tells us
that the way we
split a data set,
we can measure for
different kinds of--
we can measure different
behaviors of the model.
And that tells us
that maybe we should
be thinking more critically
about how we're evaluating
models in NLP in general.
So there has been a
revolution, basically,
over the last few
years in the field
where we're seeing all of
these large transform models
beat all of our benchmarks.
At the same time, there is
still not complete confidence
that once you deploy these
systems in the real world,
they're going to be--
going to maintain
their performance.
And so it's unclear
if these gains
are coming from spurious
correlations or some real task
understanding.
And so how do we
design benchmarks
that accurately tell us
how well this model is
going to do in the real world?
And so I'm going
to give one example
of works that try to
do this, and that's
the idea of dynamic benchmarks.
And the idea of
dynamic benchmarks
is basically saying that
instead of testing our models
on static test sets, we
should be evaluating them
on an ever-changing
dynamic benchmark.
And there's many recent
examples of this,
and the idea dates back to
a 2017 workshop at EMNLP.
And so the overall schematic
looks something like this--
that we start with a training
data set and a test data set,
which is the static corpora.
We train a model
on that, and then,
once the model is trained,
we deploy that and then
have humans create new
examples that the model fails
to classify.
And crucially, we're looking
for examples the model does not
get right, but humans
have no issue figuring out
the answer to.
So by playing this game
of whack-a-mole where
we humans figure
out what are sort
of the holes in the
model's understanding,
and then add that back
into the training data,
retrain the model, deploy
it again, have humans create
new examples, we can
essentially construct
this never-ending data
set, this never-ending test
set which can hopefully be
a better proxy of estimating
real-world performance.
So this is some very
cutting-edge research,
and one of the main challenges
of this class of works
is that it's unclear how
much this can scale up.
Because maybe after
multiple iterations
of this whack-a-mole, humans
are just fundamentally
limited by creativity.
So figuring out how to deal with
that is really an open problem.
And current approaches just
use examples from other data
sets to prompt humans to
think more creatively.
But maybe we can come up with
better, more automated methods
of doing this.
So this brings us to sort
of the final segment.
Or actually, let me stop
for questions at this point
and see if people
have questions.
Here's a question.
With dynamic
benchmark, doesn't this
mean that the model
created will also
need to continually
test/evaluate
the models on the new
benchmarks, new data test,
new data sets?
Wait a second.
Sorry, yeah.
So with dynamic
benchmarks, yes, it's
absolutely true that you will
have to continuously keep
training your model.
And that's just to ensure that
the reason your model is not
doing well on the test
set doesn't have to do
with this domain mismatch.
And what we are really trying
to do is v measure how--
just come up with
a better estimate
of the model's performance
on the overall task,
and just trying to get
more and more data.
So yes, to answer
your question, yes, we
need to keep lecturing
the model again and again.
But this can be automated.
OK, so I'll move on
to language grounding.
So in this final
segment, I'll talk
about how we can move beyond
just training models on text
alone.
So many have
articulated the need
to use modalities
other than text
if we some day want to get at
real language understanding.
And this has-- ever since we've
had these big language models,
there has been sort of a
re-kindling of this debate.
And recently, there was
multiple papers on this.
And so at ACL last year,
there was this paper
that argues through
multiple thought experiments
that it's actually
impossible to acquire
meaning from form alone,
where meaning refers
to the communicative
intent of a speaker
and form refers to
text or speech signals.
A more moderate version
of this was put forward
by the second paper,
where they say
that training on
only web-scale data
limits the world scope
of models and limits
the aspects of meanings that
the model can actually acquire.
And so here's a
look at a diagram
that I've borrowed
from the paper.
And what they say
is the error where
we were training models on
the supervised data sets,
models were limited
in world scope 1.
And now that we've moved on
to exploiting unlabeled data,
we're now in world scope
2, where models just
have strictly more signal to get
more aspects of meaning here.
If you mix in additional
modalities to this--
so maybe you mix in videos,
and maybe you mix in images--
then that expands out the whole
scope of the model further,
and now, maybe it can apply
more aspects of meaning, such
that it knows that the lexical
item "red" refers to red image
visibility.
And then, if you
go beyond that, you
can have a model
that is embodied,
and it's actually
living in an environment
where it can interact with its
data, conduct interventions
and experiments.
And then, if you go out,
go even beyond that,
you can have models that
live in a social world
where they can interact
with other models.
Because after all, the purpose
of language is to communicate.
And so you can have a social
world where models can
communicate with other models.
That kind of expands out
aspects of the world.
And so GPT-3 is
in world scope 2.
So there are a lot of open
questions in this space.
So given that there are all of
these good arguments about how
we need to move
beyond text, what
is the best way to
do this at scale?
We know that babies cannot
learn language from watching TV
alone, for example.
So there has to be
some intervention,
and there has to be
interactions, then,
that need to happen.
But at the same
time, the question
is, how far can models go by
just training on static data,
as long as we have additional
modalities, especially when we
combine this with scale?
And if interactions
with the environment
are really necessary, how do we
collect data and design systems
that interact minimally or
in a cost-effective way?
And then, finally, could
pre-training on text
still be useful if any of
these other research directions
become more sample-efficient?
So if you're interested in
learning more about this topic,
I highly encourage
you to take CS224U,
which is offered in the spring.
They have multiple lectures
on just language grounding.
OK, so in this
final segment, I'm
going to talk a little
bit more about how
you can get involved with NLP
and deep learning research
and how you can
make more progress.
So here are some
general principles
for how to make progress
in your own NLP research.
So I think the most
important thing
is to just read
broadly, which means--
and not just read the latest
and greatest papers on arXiv,
but also read pre-2010
statistical NLP.
Learn about the mathematical
foundations of machine
learning to understand
how generalization works.
So take CS229M.
Learn more about language,
which means taking classes
in the Linguistics Department.
In particular I would
recommend Linguist 130a,
and also take CS224u.
And finally, if you
want to take inspiration
from how babies
learn, then definitely
read about child language
acquisition literature.
It's fascinating.
Finally, learn your
software tools,
which involves scripting
tools, version control, data
wrangling, learning how
to visualize quickly
with Jupyter Notebooks.
And deep learning often involves
running multiple experiments
with different types of
parameters and different ideas,
all in parallel.
And sometimes, it can
get really hard to keep
track of everything.
So learn how to use
experiment management
tools like weights and biases.
And finally, I'll talk
about some, really quick,
final project tips.
So first, let's
just start by saying
that if your approach
doesn't seem to be working,
please do not panic.
Put assert statements
everywhere,
and check if the computations
that you're doing are correct.
Use breakpoints
extensively-- and I'll
talk a bit more about this.
Check if the loss function that
you've implemented is correct.
And one way of debugging that is
to see that the initial values
are correct.
So if you're doing a theory
classification problem,
then the initial loss should
be the natural log of k.
Always, always, always start
by create a small training data
set which has 5 to 10
examples and see if your model
can completely overfit to that.
If not, there's a problem
with your training loop.
Check for saturating
activations and dead ReLUs.
And often, this
can be fixed by--
maybe there's some
problems to gradients,
or maybe there's some problems
with the initialization.
Which brings me to
the next point--
check the gradient values.
See if they're too
small, which means
that maybe you should be using
residual connections or LSTMs.
Or if they're too
large, then you
should use gradient clipping.
In fact, always use
gradient clipping.
Overall, be methodical.
If your approach doesn't
work, come up with hypotheses
for why this might be the case.
Design Oracle
experiments to debug it.
Look at your data, and look at
the errors that it's making,
and just try to be
systematic about everything.
So I'll just say a little
bit more about breakpoints.
So there's this great
library called pdb.
It's like gdb, but
it's for Python.
So that's pdb.
To create a breakpoint, just
add the line import pdb,
pdb.set_trace before the
line you want to inspect.
So earlier today, I was
trying to play around
with the Transformers
library, and I was trying
to do question answering.
So I have a really
small training corpus,
and the context
is, one morning, I
shot an elephant in my pajamas.
How he got into my
pajamas, I don't know.
And the question is,
what did I shoot?
And to solve this
problem, I basically
imported a organizer
and a BERT model,
and I initialized my tokenizer,
initialized my model,
I tokenized my input.
I set my model
into the eval mode,
and I tried to
look at the output.
But I get this error,
and at face value
it's not clear what's
causing this error.
And so the best way to look
at what's causing this error
is to actually put a breakpoint.
So right after model.eval,
I put a breakpoint,
because I know that that's
where the problem is.
So the problem is in line 21, so
I put a breakpoint at line 21.
And now, once I put
this breakpoint,
I can just run my
script again, and it
stops before executing line 21.
And at this point, I can
examine all of my variables.
So I can look at
the tokenized input,
because maybe that's
where the problem is.
And lo and behold, I see
that it's actually a list.
So it's a dictionary of lists,
whereas models typically
expect a dodged answer.
So now I know what
the problem is,
and that means I can
quickly go ahead and fix it,
and everything just looks.
So this just shows
that you should just
breakpoints everywhere if
your code is not working,
and it can just help you
debug really quickly.
OK, so finally, I
would say that if you
want to get involved with
an independent research,
and if you really like
to find a project,
we have the CLIPS
program at Stanford.
And this is a way for
undergrads, masters students,
and PhDs who are interested
in doing NLP research
and want to get involved
with the NLP group.
So we highly encourage
you to apply to CLIPS.
And so yeah, so I'll
conclude today's class
by saying that we've made a lot
of progress in the last decade,
and that's mostly due
to clever understanding
of neural networks, data,
hardware, all of that
combined with scale.
We have some really
amazing technologies
that can do pretty
exciting things,
and we saw some
examples of that today.
In the short term,
I expect that we'll
see more scaling,
because it just
seems to help-- so perhaps
even larger models.
But this is not trivial.
So I said that before,
and I'll say it again,
scaling requires really
non-trivial engineering
efforts, and sometimes
even clever algorithms.
And so there's a lot
of interesting systems
work to be done here.
But in the long
term, we really need
to be thinking more
about these bigger
problems of systematicity,
generalization.
How can we make our models
learn a new concept really
quickly so that it's
fast and efficient?
And then, we also need
to create benchmarks
that we can actually just--
if my model that has some
[INAUDIBLE] and some sentiment
analysis data set and I
deploy it in the real world,
that should be
reflected in the number
that I get from the benchmark.
So we need to make
progress in the way
that we evaluate models.
And then, also,
figuring out a way
to move beyond text in
a more tractable way,
this is also really essential.
So yeah, that's it.
Good luck with
your final project.
I can take more
questions at this point.
So I answered a question
earlier that, actually, I
think you could also opine on.
It was the question of
whether you have a large model
that's pre-trained on language,
if it will actually help you
in other domains--
like you apply it to
vision stuff, yeah.
Yeah, so I guess the
answer is actually yes.
There was a paper that came
out relatively recently,
like just a few days
ago, that it just takes--
I think it was GPT-2?
I'm not sure.
It's one large transformer model
that's pre-trained on text,
and other modalities,
and I think it definitely
applied to images,
and I think it
applied to math problems
and some more modalities
and showed that it's actually
pretty effective at transfer.
So if you pre-train
on text, and then you
move to a different
modality, that helps.
I think part of
the reason for that
is just that across
modalities, there
is a lot of autoregressive
structure that is shared.
And I think one reason for
that is that language is really
referring to the
world around it,
and so you might expect
that there is some--
there is some
correspondence that's
just beyond
autoregresssive structure.
So there's also works that
show that if you have just
text-only representations and
image-only representations,
you can actually learn a simple
linear classifier-- like you
can learn to align with
these representations.
And all of these works are just
showing that there's actually
a lot more in common
between modalities
than we thought
in the beginning.
So yeah, I think yeah, it's
possible to pre-train on text
and then fine-tune on
your modality of interest.
And it should probably
be effective--
of course, based on
what the modality is.
But for images and videos,
it's certainly effective.
No more questions?
Well, a couple of
questions have turned up.
One is, what's the
difference between CS224u
and this class in terms of
the topics covered and focus?
Do you want to answer
that one, Shikar,
or should I have a
go at answering it?
Maybe you should
answer this one.
OK, so next quarter, CS224u,
Natural Language Understanding,
is co-taught by Chris
Potts and Bill McCartney.
So in essence it's
meant to be different
that natural language
understanding focuses
on what its name is--
sort of how to build
computer systems that
understand the sentences
of natural language.
Now, in truth, the boundary
is kind of complex,
because we do some natural
language understanding
in this class as well.
And certainly,
for the people who
are doing the default
final project,
question-answering, well, that's
absolutely a natural language
understanding task.
But the distinction is
meant to be that at least
a lot of what we
do in this class--
things like the assignment
3 dependency parser
or building the
machine translation
system in assignment 4--
that they are in some sense
natural language processing
tasks where processing
can mean anything,
but it commonly means you're
doing useful, intelligent stuff
with human language input, but
you're not necessarily deeply
understanding it.
So there is some
overlap in the classes.
If you do CS224u, you'll
certainly see word vectors
and transformers again.
But the emphasis is on doing a
lot more with natural language
understanding tasks.
And so that includes things
like building semantic parsers--
so they're the kind
of devices that
will respond to
questions and commands
such as an Alexa or
Google Assistant will do--
building relation
extraction systems
which get out particular facts
out of a piece of text, of, oh,
this person took on this
position at this company,
looking at grounded language
learning and grounded language
understanding, where
you're not only
using the language
but the world context
to get information,
and other tasks that--
I mean, I guess you
can look at the website
to get more details of it.
Relevant to this class,
I mean, a lot of people
also find it an opportunity
to just get further
in doing projects in the area
of natural language processing.
That's by the nature of
the structure of the class,
since it more
assumes that people
know how to build deep
learning, natural language
systems at the beginning,
rather than a large percentage
of the class going
into, OK, you have
to do all of these assignments.
Although there are little
assignments earlier on
that there's more time to work
on a project for the quarter.
OK, here's one more question
that maybe Shikar could do.
Do you know of
attempts to crowdsource
dynamic benchmarks--
e.g.
users uploading
adversarial examples
for evaluation in
online learning?
Yeah, so actually,
the main idea there
is to use crowdsourcing, right?
So in fact, there
is this bench--
so there is this platform that
was created by [INAUDIBLE]..
It's called DynaBench, and
the objective is just that.
To construct this
dynamically-evolving benchmark,
we are just going to offload
it to users of this platform.
And you can-- it
essentially gives you
utilities for
deploying your model
and then having humans
try to fool the model.
Yeah, so this is--
it's basically how
the dynamic evaluator,
the dynamic benchmark
collection actually works.
So you deploy a model
on some platform,
and then you get humans
to fool the system, yeah.
Here's a question.
Can you address the problems
of NLP models not able
to remember really long
contexts and techniques to infer
on really large input length?
Yeah, so I guess there have
been a few works recently
that kind of try to scale
up transformers to really
large context lengths.
One of them is
like the reformer,
and there's also
the Transformer XL.
That was-- I think it
was one of the first ones
to try and do that.
I think what is unclear is
whether you can combine that
with the scale of
these GPT-like models,
and if you see qualitatively
different things
once you do that.
And part of it is
just that all of this
is just so recent, right?
But yeah, I think
the open question
there is that, can you take
these really long context
transformers that can
operate over long contexts,
combine that with
scale of GPT-3,
and then get models
that can actually
reason with these
really large contexts?
Because I guess a
hypothesis of scale
is that once you train
language models at scale,
it can start to do these things.
And so to do that
for long context,
we actually need to have long
context transformers that
are trained at scale.
And I don't think people
have done that yet.
So I'm seeing this
other question
about language acquisition.
Chris, do you have
some thoughts on this?
Or maybe I can just
present to everyone.
So the question is,
what do you think
we can learn from baby
language acquisition?
Can we build a language model
in a more interactive way,
like reinforcement learning?
Do you know any
of these attempts?
That's a big, huge
question, and I
think the short and non-helpful
answer is that there are kind
of no answers at the moment.
People have certainly tried to
do things at various scales,
but we just have
no technology that
is the least bit
convincing for being
able to replicate
the language learning
ability of a human child.
But after that prologue,
what I could say is, I mean,
yeah, there are definitely
ideas to have in your head.
So there are clear
results, which
is that little kids don't
learn by watching videos.
So it seems like interaction
is completely key.
Little kids don't learn
from language alone.
They're in a very rich
environment where people
are sort of both learning
stuff from the environment
in general, and in
particular, they're
learning a lot from what
language acquisition
researchers refer
to as "attention,"
which is different to
what we mean by attention.
But it means that
the caregiver will
be looking at the object
that's the focus of interest,
and commonly other
things as well,
like picking it up, and bringing
it near the kid, and all
those kinds of things.
And babies and young kids get
to experiment a lot, right?
So regardless of
whether it's learning
what happens when
you have some blocks
that you stack up
and play with them,
or you're learning language,
you sort of experiment
by trying some things and see
what kind of response you get.
And again, that's essentially
building on the interactivity
of it, that you're getting
some kind of response
to any utterance you make.
And this is something
that's been hotly debated
in the language
acquisition literature.
So a traditional
Chomskyan position
is that if human beings don't
get effective feedback--
supervised labels--
when they talk--
and in some very narrow sense,
well, that's true right.
It's just not the case
that after a baby tries
to say something,
that they get feedback
of, syntax error in English
on word 4, or they get given,
here's the semantic form I
took away from your utterance.
But in a more indirect way, they
clearly get enormous feedback.
They can see what
kind of response
they get from their
caregiver at every corner.
And so in your question,
you were suggesting that,
well, somehow, we
should be making
use of reinforcement learning,
because we have something
like a reward signal there.
And in a big picture way,
I'd say, huh, yeah, I agree.
In terms of a much more specific
way as to, well, how could
we possibly get that to
work, to learn something
with the richness
of human language,
I think we don't have much idea.
But there has started
to be some work.
So people have been
sort of building
virtual environments, which
you have your avatar in,
and that you can manipulate
in the virtual environment,
and there's linguistic input,
and it can succeed in getting
rewards for sort
of doing a command,
where the command can
be something like,
pick up the orange block,
or something like that.
And to a small extent,
people have been
able to build things that work.
I mean, as you might be picking
up, I mean, I guess so far,
at least, I've just been
kind of underwhelmed,
because it seems like the
complexity of what people have
achieved is sort of just
so primitive compared
to the full complexity
of language, right?
The kind of
languages that people
have been able to
get systems to learn
are ones that can
do pick up commands,
where they can learn "blue
cube" versus "orange sphere,"
and that's sort of about
how far people have gotten.
And that's sort of such a teeny,
small corner of what's involved
in learning a human language.
One thing I'll just
add to that is I
think there are some
principles of how
kids learn that you
could have tried
to apply to deep learning.
And one example
that comes to mind
is curriculum
learning, where there's
a lot of literature that
shows that babies tend
to pay attention to things
that is just slightly
challenging for them, and
they don't pay attention
to things that are
extremely challenging
and also don't pay attention
to things that they
know how to solve.
And many researchers
have really tried
to get curriculum
learning to work,
and the verdict on that is
that it seems to kind of work
when you're in reinforcement
learning settings,
but it's unclear if
it's going to work on
like supervised
learning settings.
But I still think that
it's under-explored,
and maybe there should
be more attempts
to kind of see if you can look
at the curriculum learning
and if that improves anything.
Yeah, I agree.
Curriculum learning
is an important idea
which we haven't
really talked about,
but it seems like it certainly
is central to human learning.
And there's been some
minor successes with it
in the machine learning
world, but it sort of
seems like it's
an idea you should
be able to do a lot
more with in the future
as you move from
models that are just
doing one narrow task to trying
to do a more general language
acquisition process.
Shall I attempt the
next question as well?
OK, the next question
is, is the reason
humans learn languages
better just because we
are pre-trained over millions
of years of physics simulation?
Maybe we should pre-train
a model the same way.
So I mean, I presume what you're
saying is "physics simulation,"
you're evoking evolution when
you're talking about millions
of years.
So this is a controversial,
debated, big question.
So again, if I invoke
Chomsky again-- so
Noam Chomsky is sort of the most
famous linguist in the world.
And essentially, Noam Chomsky's
career, starting in the 1950s,
is built around the idea
that little children get
such dubious linguistic input--
because they hear a
random bunch of stuff,
they don't get much feedback
on what they say, et cetera--
that language could not
be learned empirically
just from the data observed,
and the only possible assumption
to work from is significant
parts of human language
are innate in the human genome.
Babies are born with it, and
that explains the miracle
by which very little
humans learn amazingly
fast how human languages work.
Now, to speak in
credit for that idea,
for those of you who have not
been around little children,
I mean, I think one does
just have to acknowledge,
human language acquisition
by live little kids,
I mean, it does just seem
to be miraculous, right,
that you go through
this sort of slow phase
for a couple of years where the
kid sort of goos and gaas some
syllables.
And then, there's a fairly long
period where they've picked up
a few words, and they
can say, juice, juice
when they want to drink some
juice, and nothing else.
And then, it just seems like
there's this phase change where
the kids suddenly
realize, wait, this
is a productive,
generative sentence system!
I can say whole sentences!
And then, in an
incredibly short period,
they seem to
transition from saying
one- and two-word utterances
to suddenly they can say,
Daddy come home in garage,
putting bike in garage.
And you go, wow, how did they
suddenly discover language?
So it is kind of amazing.
But personally,
for me, at least,
I've just never believed
the strong versions
of the hypothesis
that human beings have
much in the way of
language-specific knowledge
or structure in
their brains that
comes from genetic inheritance.
Clearly, humans do have
these very clever brains,
and if we're at the level of,
saying, being able to think,
or being able to interpret
the visual world, that's
things that have developed
over tens of millions of years.
And evolution can be a large
part of the explanation,
and humans are
clearly born with lots
of vision-specific
hardware in their brains,
as are a lot of other creatures.
But when you come
to language, no one
knows when language was--
in a sort of modern-like form--
first became available,
because there
aren't any fossils of
people saying the word
"spear" or something like that.
But to the extent that
there are estimates
based on what you can see of
the spread of proto-humans
and their apparent
social structures,
from what you can
find in fossils,
most people guess that language
is at most a million years old.
And that's just too short a
time for any significant--
for evolution have built
any significant structure
inside human brains that's
specific to language.
So I kind of think that
the working assumption
has to be that there's
just about nothing
specific to language
in human brains,
and the most
plausible hypothesis--
not that I know very much about
neuroscience when it comes down
to it-- is that humans were
being able to repurpose
hardware that was originally
built for other purposes,
like visual scene
interpretation and memory,
and that that gave a basis of
having all this clever hardware
that you could then
use for language.
So it's kind of like GPUs were
invented for playing computer
games, and we were able
to repurpose that hardware
to do deep learning.
OK, we've got a lot have
come out at the end.
OK, so this one
was answered live.
Let's see.
Yeah, if you could name--
I guess this is
for either of you--
one main bottleneck as to
if we could provide feedback
efficiently to our systems
like babies are given feedback,
what's the bottleneck
that remains
in trying to have more
human-like language
acquisition?
I mean, I can opine on this.
Or were you saying
something, Shikar?
Yeah, I was just
going to say that I
think it's a bit of everything.
I think in terms of models, one
thing I would say is that we
know that there's more feedback
connections and feed-forward
connections in the brain, and
we haven't really figured out
a way of--
so of course, we had RNNs,
which sort of implements
you can move to a algorithm that
sort of implements a feedback
loop.
But we still haven't
really figured out
how to use that knowledge, that
the brain has a lot of feedback
connections, and then apply
that to practical systems.
So I think on the modeling,
and maybe that's one problem.
There is-- I think [INAUDIBLE]
learning is maybe one of them,
but I think the
one that's probably
going to have the most bang
for the buck is really just
figuring out how we
can move beyond text.
And I think there's just
so much more information
that's available that
we're just not using.
And so I think that's where
most of the progress might come,
is from figuring out what's
most practical way of going
beyond text.
This is what I think.
OK, let's see.
What are some
important NLP topics
that we have not
covered in this class?
I'll do that.
Well, sort of one
answer is, a lot
of the topics that are
covered in CS224u, because we
do make a bit of an effort
to keep them disjoint.
They're not fully-- right.
So there's sort
of lots of topics
in language understanding that
we haven't covered, right?
So if you want to make a
voice assistant like Alexa,
Siri, or Google
Assistant, well, you
need to sort of be
able to interface
with systems APIs that can do
things like delete your mail
or buy you concert tickets.
And so you need to be able
to convert from language
into an explicit semantic
form that can interact
with the systems of the world.
And we haven't talked
about that at all.
So there's lots of language
understanding stuff.
There's also lots of
language generation things.
So effectively, for language
generation, all we have done
is--
neural language
models, they are great.
Run them, and they
will generate language.
And in one sense, that's true.
It's just awesome the
kind of generation
you can do with things
like GPT-2 or -3.
But where that's missing is
that's really only giving you
the ability to produce fluent
text, where it rabbits off
and produces fluent text,
that, if you actually
wanted to have a good natural
language generation system,
you also have to have
higher-level planning of what
you're going to talk
about and how you
are going to express it, right?
So that in most situations in
natural language, you think,
OK, well, I want to
explain to people something
about why it's important to
do math classes at college.
Let me think how
to organize this.
Maybe I should talk about some
of the different applications
where math turns up and how
it's a really good grounding.
Whatever-- you plan out, here's
how I can present some ideas.
And that kind of natural
language generation
we're not doing and we
haven't done any of.
Yeah, so that's
what I was saying--
more understanding,
more generation, which
is most of NLP, you could say.
I mean, obviously, there are,
then, sort of particular tasks
that we can talk about that
we either have or have not
explicitly addressed.
OK, has there been any work
in putting language models
into an environment in
which they can communicate
to achieve a task?
And do you think this would
help with unsupervised learning?
So I guess there's been a lot of
work on emergent communication,
and also self-play, where you
have these different models
which are initialized
as language models that
attempt to communicate with
each other to solve some task.
And then, you have
a reward at the end
whether they were able to
finish the task or not.
And then, based on
that reward, you
attempt to learn the
communication strategy.
And this started out as emergent
communication with self-play,
and then there was recent work--
I think it was like either
last year or the year
before that-- where they
showed that if you initialized
these models with language
model pre-training,
you basically prevent
this problem of language
drift, where the language
or the communication
protocol that your
models end up learning
has nothing to do
with actual language.
And so yeah, I mean
from that sense,
there has been some work.
But it's very little of it.
I think it's some groups
that tried to study
this, but nothing beyond that.
OK, I mean, the last two
questions are about genes.
Well, there's one question
about whether genes
may have some correlations
from social cues
or a reward-based system.
I don't know if either of
you have opinions about this,
but if you do--
Yeah, I mean, I don't
have anything very deep
to say about this question.
So it's on the
importance of social cues
as opposed to pure
reward-based systems.
Well, I mean, in some
sense, a social cue
you can also regard as
a reward, that people
like to have other people
put a smile on their face
when you say something.
But I do think generally,
when people are saying,
what have we not covered,
another thing that we've barely
covered is the social
side of language.
So a huge, interesting
thing about language
is it has this very
dynamic, big dynamic range.
So on the one hand, you can
talk about very precise things
in language.
So you can sort of talk
about math formulas,
and steps in a proof,
and things like that,
so that there's a lot of
precision in language.
But on the other
hand, you can just
phatically mumble, mumble
whatever words at all,
and you're not really sort
of communicating anything
in the way of a
propositional content.
What you're really
trying to communicate
is, oh, I'm thinking
about you right now.
Oh, I'm concerned with
how you're feeling,
or whatever it is in the
circumstances, right?
So that a huge part
of language use
is in forms of
social communication
between human beings.
And that's another big
part of actually building
successful natural
language systems, right?
So if you think
negatively about something
like the virtual assistants
I've been falling back on a lot,
is that they have virtually
no ability as social language
users, right?
So we're now training a
generation of little kids
that what you should
do is sort of bark
out commands as if
you were serving
in the German Army in
World War II or something
and that there's none of the
kind of social part of how
to use language to
communicate satisfactorily
with human beings and to
maintain a social system,
and that that's a huge
part of human language use
that kids have to learn and
learn to use successfully,
right?
A lot of being
successful in the world
is, when you want someone
to do something for you,
you know that there are good
ways to ask them for it.
Yes, some of it is choice of
how to present the arguments,
but some of it is by
building social rapport,
and asking nicely
and reasonably,
and making it seem like you're
a sweet person that other people
should do something for.
And human beings are
very good at that,
and being good at that is
a really important skill
for being able to
navigate the world well.