OK.
Hi, everyone.
Welcome back to CS224N.
So today is a pretty
key lecture where
we get through a number
of important topics
for neural networks,
especially as it is applied
to natural language processing.
So right at the
end of last time,
I started into recurrent
neural networks.
So we'll talk in detail more
about recurrent neural networks
in the first part of the class.
And we emphasized
language models.
But then also getting a
bit beyond that and then
looked at more advanced kinds
of recurrent neural networks
towards the end
part of the class.
I just wanted to sort of say
a word before getting underway
about the final project.
So hopefully, by
now, you've started
looking at assignment
3, which is
the middle of the five
assignments for the first half
of the course.
And then in the second half of
the course, most of your effort
goes into a final project.
So next week, the
Thursday lecture
is going to be
about final projects
and choosing the final
project, and tips
for final projects, et cetera.
So it's fine to delay
thinking about final projects
until next week if you want.
But you shouldn't
delay it too long
because we do want
you to get underway
with what topic you're going
to do for your final project.
If you are thinking
about final projects,
you can find some
info on the website,
but note that the info
that's there at the moment
is still last
year's information,
and it will be being updated
over the coming week.
We'll also talk about
project mentors.
If you've got ideas of
people who on your own
you can line up as
a mentor, that now
would be a good time
to ask them about it.
And we'll sort of talk about
what the alternatives are.
OK.
So last lecture, I
introduced the idea
of language models, so
probabilistic models that
predict the probability of next
words after a word sequence,
and then we looked at
n-gram language models
and started into recurrent
neural network models.
So today, we're
going to talk more
about the simple RNNs we saw
before, talking about training
RNNs and uses of RNNs.
But then we'll also
look into the problems
that occur with RNNs and
how we might fix them.
These will motivate a more
sophisticated RNN architecture
called LSTMS, and we'll talk
about other more complex RNN
options, bidirectional
RNNs, and multilayer RNNs.
Then next Tuesday,
we're essentially
going to further
exploit and build
on the RNN based architectures
that we've been looking at
to discuss how to build a
neural machine translation
system with the
sequence-to-sequence
and model with attention.
And effectively
it's that model is
what you'll use in
assignment 4, but it also
means that we'll be
using all of the stuff
that we're talking about today.
OK.
So if you remember
from last time,
this was the idea of a simple
recurrent neural network
language model.
So we had a sequence of words
as our context for which we've
looked up word embeddings.
And then the recurrent
neural network model
ran this recurrent layer,
where at each point,
we have a previous hidden
state, which can just
be 0 at the beginning
of a sequence,
and you have feeding it in
to the next hidden state,
the previous hidden state,
and transform the encoding
of a word using this
recurrent neural network
equation that I have on the
left that's very central.
And based on that, you compute
a new hidden representation
for the next time step.
And you can repeat that along
for successive time steps.
Now, we also usually want
our recurrent neural networks
to produce outputs.
So I only show it
at the end here.
But at each time
step we're then also
going to generate an output.
And so to do that, we're
feeding the hidden layer
into a softmax layer.
So we're doing another matrix
multiply, add on a bias,
put it through the
softmax equation.
And that then gives
the probability
distribution over words.
And we can use that to
predict how likely it
is that different
words are going
to occur after the
students opened their.
OK.
So I introduced that
model, but I hadn't really
gone through the specifics of
how we train this model, how
we use it and evaluate it.
So let me go through this now.
So here's how we train
an RNN language model.
We get a big corpus of
text, just a lot of text.
And so we can regard that
as just a long sequence
of words, x1 to xT.
And what we're going to do
is feed it into the RNN-LM.
So for each
position, we're going
to take prefixes
of that sequence.
And based on each
prefix, we're going
to want to predict the
probability distribution
for the word that comes next.
And then we're going
to train our model
by assessing how good
a job we do about that.
And so the loss function we use
is the loss function, normally
referred to as cross-entropy
loss in the literature,
which is this negative
log likelihood loss.
So we are going to predict
some word to come next.
Well, we have a probability
distribution over predictions
of what word comes next.
And actually, there was an
actual next word in the text.
And so we say, well,
what probability
did you give to that word?
And maybe we gave it a
probability estimate of 0.01.
Well, it would have been great
if we'd given a probability
estimate of almost
1, because that
meant we're almost
certain that what
did come next in our model.
And so we'll take a
loss to the extent
that we are giving
the actual next word
a predicted probability
of less than 1.
So then getting an
idea of how well
we're doing over
the entire corpus,
we work out that
loss at each position
and then we work out the average
loss of the entire training
set.
So let's just go
through that again
more graphically in the
next couple of slides.
So down at the bottom,
here is our corpus of text.
We're running it through
our simple recurrent neural
network.
And at each position, we've
predicting a probability
distribution over words.
We then say, well,
actually, in each position,
we know what word
is actually next.
So when we're at time step
1, the actual next word
is students, because we can see
it just to the right of us here
and we say, what
probability estimate
did you give to students and to
the extent that it's not high?
I.e., it's not 1.
We take a loss.
And then we go on
to the time step 2,
and we say, well,
at time step 2,
you predict the probability
distribution over words.
The actual next word is opened.
So to the extent
that you haven't
given the high
probability to open,
you take a loss and
then that repeats.
And time step 4, we're hoping
the model will predict their.
At time step 4, we are hoping
the model will predict exams.
And then to work out our overall
loss within averaging out
per time step loss.
So in a way this is a
pretty obvious thing to do.
But note that there is
a little subtlety here.
And in particular,
this algorithm
is referred to in the
literature as teacher forcing.
And so what does that mean?
Well, you can
imagine what you can
do with a recurrent
neural network is,
say, okay, just
start generating.
Maybe I'll give you a
hint as to where to start.
I'll say the sentence
starts, the students,
and then let it run and see
what it generates coming next.
It might start
saying, the students
have been locked
out of the classroom
or whatever it is, right?
And that, we could say
is, well, that's not
very close to what
the actual text says.
And somehow we want
to learn from that.
And if you go in that
direction, there's
a space of things
you can do that leads
into more complex algorithms
such as reinforcement learning.
But from the perspective of
training these neural models,
that's unduly complex
and unnecessary.
So we have this very
simple way of doing
things, which is
what we do is just
predict one time step forward.
So we say, we know that
the prefix is the students.
Predict the probability
distribution
over the next word.
It's good to the extent
that you give probability
mass to opened.
OK, now the prefix is
the students opened.
Predict a probability
distribution
over the next word.
It's good to the extent that you
give probability mass to their.
And so effectively,
at each step,
we are resetting to what
was actually in the corpus.
So you know it's possible
after the students opened,
the model thinks that by
far the most probable thing
to come next is a, or the, say.
I mean, we don't actually
use what the model suggested.
We penalize the model for
not having suggested their.
But then we just go with
what's actually in the corpus
and ask it to predict again.
This is just a
little side thing.
But it's an important
part to know
if you're actually training
your own neural language model.
I sort of present it as one huge
corpus that we chug through.
But in practice, we don't chug
through a whole corpus one
step at a time.
What we do is we
cut the whole corpus
into shorter pieces,
which might commonly
be sentences or
documents or sometimes
they're literally just pieces
that are chopped, right?
So you'll recall that stochastic
gradient descent allows
us to compute a loss and
gradients for a small chunk
of data and update.
So what we do is we
take these small pieces,
compute gradients from those,
and update weights and repeat.
And in particular, we get a
lot more speed and efficiency
in training if we
aren't actually
doing an update for just
one sentence at a time
but actually a
batch of sentences.
So typically what
we'll actually do
is we'll feed to the
model 32 sentences,
say, of a similar
length at the same time,
compute gradients for them,
update weights, and then get
another batch of
sentences to train on.
How do we train?
I haven't sort of gone
through the details of this.
I mean, in one sense, the answer
is just like we talked about
in lecture 3.
We used backpropagation to
get gradients and update
parameters.
But let's take at least a minute
to go through the differences
and subtleties of the
recurrent neural network case.
And the central
thing that's a bit--
as before, we're
going to take our loss
and we're going to
back propagate it
to all of the parameters of the
network, everything from word
embeddings to biases, et cetera.
But the central bit that's
a little bit different
and is more complicated is that
we have this WH matrix that
runs along the sequence
that we keep on applying
to update our hidden state.
So what's the derivative
of Jt of theta
with respect to the
repeated weight matrix Wh?
And well, the answer to
that is that what we do
is we look at it
in each position
and work out what the partials
are of Jt with respect to Wh
in position 1 or position 2,
position 3, position 4, et
cetera, right
along the sequence.
And we just sum up
all of those partials.
And that gives us partial for
Jt with respect to Wh overall.
So the answer for
recurrent neural networks
is the gradient with
respect to repeated
weight in our current
network is the sum
of the gradient with respect
to each time it appears.
And let me just then go through
a little why that is the case.
But before I do that, let
me just note one gocha.
I mean, it's just not
the case that this
means it equals t
times the partial of Jt
with respect to Wh.
Because we're using Wh
here, here, here, here, here
through the sequence.
And for each of the
places we use it,
there's a different
upstream gradient
that's being fed into it.
So each of the
values in this sum
will be completely
different from each other.
Well, why we get this
answer is essentially
a consequence of what we talked
about in the third lecture.
So to take the simplest
case of it, right,
that if you have a
multivariable function f(x,
y) and you have two
single variable functions,
x(t) and y(t) which are
fed one input t, well,
then the simple version of
working out the derivative
of this function is you take
the derivative down one path
and you take the derivative
down the other path.
And so, in the
slides in lecture 3,
that was what was summarized
on a couple of slides
by the slogan gradient
sum at outward branches.
So t has outward branches.
And so you take gradient
here on the left, gradient
on the right, and you
sum them together.
And so really what's happening
with a recurrent neural network
is just many pieces
generalization of this.
So we have one Wh
matrix and we're
using it to keep on updating the
hidden state at time 1, time 2,
time 3, right through time t.
And so what we're going
to get is that this
has a lot of outward branches.
And we're going to
sum the gradient path
at each one of them.
But what is this
gradient path here?
It kind of goes down here
and then goes down there.
But actually the bottom
part is that we're just
using Wh at each position.
So we have the partial
Wh used at position i
with respect to
the partial of Wh
which is just our weight
matrix for our recurrent neural
network.
So that's just one.
Because we're just using
the same matrix everywhere.
And so we are just then summing
the partials in each position
that we use that.
OK, practically, what
does that mean in terms
of how you compute this?
Well, if you're doing
it by hand, what happens
is you start at the end just
like the general lecture 3
story.
You work out derivatives with
respect to the hidden layer
and then with respect to
Wh at the last time step.
And so that gives you
one update for Wh.
But then you continue
passing the gradient back
to the t minus 1 time step.
And after a couple more
steps of the chain rule,
you get another update for Wh.
And you simply sum that onto
your previous update for Wh.
And then you go to ht minus 2.
You get another update for Wh.
And you sum that onto
your update for Wh.
And you go back all
the way and you sum up
the gradients as you go.
And that gives you a
total update for Wh.
And so there's sort
of two tricks here.
And I'll just mention
the two tricks.
You have to kind of separately
sum the updates for Wh.
And then once you've finished,
apply them all at once.
You don't want to actually
be changing the Wh
matrix as you go.
Because that's then
invalid because
the forward calculations were
done with the constant Wh
that you had from the previous
state all through the network.
The second trick
is, well, if you're
doing this for sentences,
you can normally just go back
to the beginning
of the sentence.
But if you've got
very long sequences,
this can really slow
you down if you're
having to sort of run
this algorithm back
for a huge amount of time.
So something people
commonly do is
what's called truncated back
propagation through time where
you choose some
constant, say 20,
and you say, well,
I'm just going
to run this back propagation
for 20 time steps, sum those 20
gradients, and
then I'm just done.
That's what I'll update
the Wh matrix with.
And that works just fine.
So now given a corpus, we
can train a simple RNN.
So that's good progress.
But this is a model that can
also generate text in general.
So how do we generate text?
Well, just like in our
n-gram language model,
we're going to generate
text by repeated sampling.
So we're going to start
off with an initial state
and this slide is imperfect.
So the initial state
for the hidden state
is normally just taken
as a zero vector.
And while then we need to have
something for a first input.
And on this slide,
the first input
is shown as the first word, my.
And if you want to
feed a starting point,
you could feed my.
But a lot of the
time, you'd like
to generate a
sentence from nothing.
And if you want to do
that, what's conventional
is to additionally have a
beginning of sequence token
which is a special token.
So you'll feed in the
beginning of sequence token
in at the beginning
as the first token.
It has an embedding.
And then you use the RNN update.
And then you generate using
the softmax a next word.
And well, you generate a
probability distribution
over next words.
And then at that point,
you sample from that.
And it chooses some
word like favorite.
And so then, the trick
is for doing generation
that you take this word that
you sampled and you copy it
back down to the input and then
you feed it in as an input.
Next step of your RNN,
sample from the softmax,
get another word, and just keep
repeating this over and over
again.
And you start
generating the text.
And how you end is as well as
having a beginning of sequence
special symbol, you
usually have an end
of sequence special symbol.
And at some point, the
recurrent neural network
will generate the end
of sequence symbol.
And then you say, OK, I'm done.
I'm finished generating text.
So before going on for more
of the difficult content
of the lecture, we can just have
a little bit of fun with this
and try training up
and generating text
with our recurrent
neural network model.
So you can generate--
you can train
an RNN on any kind of text.
And so that means one of the
fun things that you can do
is generate text
in different styles
based on what you
could train it from.
So here, Harry Potter,
there is a fair amount
of corpus of text.
So you can train an RNN-LM
L on the Harry Potter books.
And then say, go off
and generate some text.
And it'll generate
text like this.
"Sorry," Harry
shouted, panicking--
"I'll leave those brooms
in London, are they?"
"No idea," said Nearly Headless
Nick, casting low close
by Cedric, carrying the
last bit of treacle Charms
from Harry's shoulder,
and to answer him
the common room perched
upon it, four arms
held a shining knob from
when the spider hadn't
felt it seemed.
He reached the teams too.
Well, so on the one
hand, that's still
kind of a bit
incoherent as a story.
On the other hand, it sort
of sounds like Harry Potter.
It's certainly the kind of
vocabulary and constructions
it uses.
And I think you'd agree that,
even though it gets sort
of incoherent, it's sort
of more coherent than what
we got from an
n-gram language model
when I showed a generation
in the last lecture.
You can choose a very
different style of text.
So you could, instead, train the
model on a bunch of cook books.
And if you do that,
you can then say,
generate based on what you've
learned about cook books.
And it'll just
generate a recipe.
So here's a recipe,
chocolate ranch barbecue.
Categories, yield six servings.
2 tablespoons of
Parmesan cheese, chopped.
1 cup of coconut milk.
Three eggs beaten.
Place each pasta
over layers of lumps.
Shape mixture into the moderate
oven and simmer untill firm.
Serve hot in bodied fresh,
mustard, orange, and cheese.
Combine the cheese
and salt together,
the dough in a large
skillet, add the ingredients
and stir in the
chocolate and pepper.
So, you know, this
recipe makes no sense.
And it's sufficiently
incoherent.
There's actually even
no danger that you'll
try cooking this at home.
But something that's interesting
is although this really just
isn't a recipe and
the things that
are done in the
instructions have
no relation to the ingredients,
the thing that's interesting
that it has learned is this
recurrent neural network model
is that it's really mastered the
overall structure of a recipe.
It knows the recipe has a title.
It often tells you about
how many people it serves.
It lists the ingredients.
And then it has
instructions to make it.
So that's sort of fairly
impressive in some sense
for high level text structuring.
So the one other thing
I wanted to mention
was when I say you can
train an RNN language
model on any kind of text, the
other difference from where
we were in n-gram
language models
was on n-gram
language models, that
just meant counting
n-grams and meant
it took 2 minutes,
even on a large corpus,
with any modern computer.
Training your RNN
LM actually can then
be a time intensive activity.
And you can spend
hours doing that,
as you might find next
week when you're training
machine translation models.
OK, how do we decide if
our models are good or not?
So the standard evaluation
metric for language models
is what's called perplexity.
And what perplexity is is kind
of like when you were training
your model, you use
teacher forcing over
a piece of text that's a
different piece of text which
isn't text that was
in the training data.
And you say, well,
given a sequence
of t words, what
probability do you give
to the actual t plus 1-th word?
And you repeat that
at each position.
And then you take the
inverse of that probability
and raise it to the 1 on t for
the length of your text sample.
And that number
is the perplexity.
So it's a geometric mean of
the inverse probabilities.
Now after that explanation,
perhaps an easier way
to think of it is that
the perplexity is simply
the cross entropy
loss that I introduced
before exponentiated.
But it's now the
other way around.
So low perplexity is better.
So there's actually
an interesting story
about these perplexities.
So a famous figure in the
development of probabilistic
and machine learning approaches
to natural language processing
is Fred Jelinek who
died a few years ago.
And he was trying to interest
people in the idea of using
probability models and machine
learning for natural language
processing at a time-- i.e.,
this is the 1970s and early
1980s--
when nearly everyone
in the field of AI
was still in the thrall
of logic-based models
and blackboard
architectures and things
like that for artificial
intelligence systems.
And so Fred Jelinek was
actually an information theorist
by background, then got
interested in working
with speech and
then language data.
So at that time,
the stuff that's--
this sort of exponential or
using cross-entropy losses
was completely bread and
butter to Fred Jelinek
that he'd found
that no one in AI
could understand the
bottom half of the slide.
And so he wanted to come
up with something simple
that AI people at that
time could understand.
And perplexity has a kind
of a simple interpretation
you can tell people.
So if you get a
perplexity of 53,
that means how uncertain
you are of the next word
is equivalent to the
uncertainty of that
you're tossing a 53-sided dice
and it coming up as a 1, right?
So that was kind of an
easy, simple metric.
And so he introduced that idea.
But you know, I
guess things stick.
And to this day, everyone
evaluates their language models
by providing perplexity numbers.
And so here are some
perplexity numbers.
So traditional n-gram
language models commonly
had perplexities over 100.
But if you made them really
big and really carefully,
you could get them down
into a number like 67.
As people started to
build more advanced
recurrent neural networks,
especially as they
moved beyond the kind
of simple RNNs, which
is all I've shown you
so far, which one of is
in the second line of the slide,
into LSTMs, which I talk about
later in this
course, that people
started producing much
better perplexities.
And here, we're getting
perplexities down to 30.
And this is results actually
from a few years ago.
So nowadays people
get perplexities
of even lower than 30.
You have to be realistic in
what you can expect, right?
Because if you are
just generating a text,
some words are
almost determined.
So if it's something like
Sue gave the man a napkin.
He said thank.
Basically 100%, you should
be able to say the word that
comes next is you.
And so that you can
predict really well.
But if it's a lot
of other sentences
like, he looked out the
window and saw something,
right, no probability
model in the world
can give a very good
estimate of what's
actually going to be
coming next at that point.
And so that gives us the
sort of residual uncertainty
that leads to perplexities
that are, on average,
might be around 20 or something.
So we've talked a lot
about language models now.
Why should we care
about language modeling?
Well, there's sort of an
intellectual scientific answer
that says, this is a
benchmark task, right?
If want we want to do is
build machine learning models
of language and our
ability to predict
what word will come next in the
context, that shows how well we
understand both the
structure of language
and the structure
of the human world
that language talks about.
But there's a much
more practical answer
than that, which is
language models are really
the secret tool of natural
language processing.
So if you're talking
to any NLP person
and you've got
almost any task, it's
quite likely they'll say, oh,
I bet we could use a language
model for that.
And so language
models are sort of
used as not the whole solution,
but a part of almost any task.
Any task that involves
generating or estimating
the probability of text.
So you can use it for predictive
typing, speech recognition,
grammar correction, identifying
authors, machine translation,
summarization, dialogue,
just about anything
you do with natural language
involves language models.
And we'll see examples of
that in following classes,
including next Tuesday where
we're using language models
for machine translation.
OK, so a language
model is just a system
that predicts the next word.
A recurrent neural network is
a family of neural networks
which can take sequential
input of any length,
they reuse the same
weights to generate
a hidden state and optionally,
but commonly, an output
on each step.
Note that these two
things are different.
So we've talked about
two ways that you
could build language models.
But one of them is
RNNs being a great way.
But RNNs can also be used
for a lot of other things.
So let me just quickly
preview a few other things
you can do with RNNs.
So there are lots
of tasks that people
want to do in NLP which
are referred to as sequence
tagging tasks where we'd
like to take words of text
and do some kind
of classification
along the sequence.
So one simple common one is
to give words parts of speech.
The is a determiner.
startled is an adjective.
Cat is a noun.
Knocked is a verb.
And well, you can do
this straightforwardly
by using a recurrent
neural network
as a sequential
classifier where it's now
going to generate
parts of speech
rather than the next word.
You can use a recurrent
neural network, the sentiment
classification.
Well, this time
we don't actually
want to generate an output
at each word, necessarily.
But we want to know what the
overall sentiment looks like.
So somehow we want to get
out a sentence encoding
that we can perhaps put through
another neural network layer
to judge whether the sentence
is positive or negative.
Well, the simplest
way to do that
is to think, well,
after I've run
my LSTM through the
whole sentence, actually
this final hidden state, it's
encoded the whole sentence.
Because remember I
updated that hidden state
based on each previous word.
And so you could say that
this is the whole meaning
of the sentence.
So let's just say that
is the sentence encoding
and then put an extra classifier
layer on that with something
like a softmax classifier.
That method has been used.
And it actually works
reasonably well.
And if you sort of train
this model end to end,
well, it's actually then
motivated to preserve sentiment
information in the hidden state
of the recurrent neural network
because that will allow
it to better predict
the sentiment of the
whole sentence, which
is the final task and
hence loss function
that we're giving the network.
But it turns out that you can
commonly do better than that
by actually doing things
like feeding all hidden
states into the
sentence encoding,
perhaps by making
the sentence encoding
an element-wise max or an
element-wise mean of all
the hidden states.
Because this then
more symmetrically
encodes the hidden state
over each time step.
Another big use of
recurrent neural networks
is what I'll call language
encoder module uses.
So any time you have some
text, for example here
we have a question, what
nationality was Beethoven,
we'd like to construct some
kind of neural representation
of this.
So one way to do it is to run
a recurrent neural network
over it.
And then just like last
time, to either take
the final hidden state or
take some kind of function
of all the hidden states
and say that's the sentence
representation.
And we could do the same
thing for the context.
So for question
answering, we're going
to build some more neural
net structure on top of that.
And we'll learn more about
that in a couple of weeks
when we have the question
answering lecture.
But the key thing is
what we've built so far,
we used to get sentence
representation.
So it's a language
encoder module.
So that was the
language encoding part.
We can also use RNNs to
decode into language.
And that's commonly used in
speech recognition, machine
translation, summarization.
So if we have a
speech recognizer,
the input is an audio signal.
And what we want to do is
decode that into language.
Well, what we could do
is use some function
of the input, which
is probably itself
going to be a neural net,
as the initial hidden
state of our RNN-LM.
And then we say, start
generating text based on that.
And so it should
then, we generate word
at a time by the method
that we just looked at.
We turn the speech into text.
So this is an example of a
conditional language model
because we're now generating
text conditioned on the speech
signal.
And a lot of the time, you can
do interesting more advanced
things with recurrent
neural networks
by building conditional
language models.
Another place you can use
conditional language models
is for text
classification tasks,
including sentiment
classification.
So if you can condition
your language model
based on a kind
of sentiment, you
can build a kind of
classifier for that.
And another use that we'll
see a lot of next class
is for machine translation.
OK, so that's the
end of the intro
to doing things with recurrent
neural networks and language
models.
Now, I want to move on and
tell you about the fact
that everything
is not perfect and
these recurrent
neural networks tend
to have a couple of problems.
And we'll talk about those.
And then, in part,
that will then
motivate coming up with a
more advanced recurrent neural
network architecture.
So the first problem
to be mentioned
is the idea of what's
called vanishing gradients.
And what does that mean?
Well, at the end
of our sequence,
we have some overall loss
that we're calculating.
And well, what we want to do
is back propagate that loss.
And we want to back propagate
it right along the sequence.
And so we're working out the
partials of J4 with respect
to the hidden state at time 1.
And when we have
a longer sequence,
we'll be working out the
partials of J20 with respect
to the hidden state at time 1.
And how do we do that?
Well, how we do it is by
composition and the chain rule.
We've got a big long chain
rule along the whole sequence.
Well, if we're doing that, we're
multiplying a ton of things
together.
And so the danger of
what tends to happen
is that as we do these
multiplications, a lot of time
these partials between
successive hidden states
become small.
And so what happens
is as we go along,
the gradient gets smaller
and smaller and smaller,
and starts to peter out.
And to the extent
that it peters out,
well, then we've kind of
gotten no upstream gradient
and therefore we won't be
changing the parameters at all.
And that turns out to
be pretty problematic.
So the next couple of slides
sort of say a little bit
about the why and
how this happens.
What's presented here is a
kind of only semi-formal wave
your hands at the kind of
problems that you might expect.
If you really want
to sort of get
into all the
details of this, you
should look at the
couple of papers
that are mentioned
in small print
at the bottom of the slide.
But at any rate, if
you remember that this
is our basic recurrent
neural network equation,
let's consider an easy case.
Suppose we sort of get
rid of our non-linearity
and just assume that it's
an identity function.
OK, so then when
we're working out
the partials of the
hidden state with respect
to the previous hidden
state, we can work those out
in the usual way according
to the chain rule.
And then, if sigma is simply
the identity function,
well then, everything
gets really easy for us.
So only-- the sigma
just goes away.
And only the first term
involves h at time t minus 1.
So the later terms go away.
And so our gradient
ends up as Wh.
Well, that's doing it
for just one time step.
What happens when
you want to work out
these partials a number
of time steps away?
So we want to work it out,
the partial of time step i
with respect to j.
Well, what we end
up with is a product
of the partials of
successive time steps.
And well, each of those
is coming out as Wh
and so we end up getting Wh
raised to the l-th power.
And while our
potential problem is
that if Wh is small
in some sense,
then this term gets
exponentially problematic.
It becomes vanishingly
small as our sequence length
becomes long.
Well, what can we mean by small?
Well, a matrix is small
if its eigenvalues
are all less than 1.
So we can rewrite
what's happening
with this success
of multiplication,
using eigenvalues
and eigenvectors.
And I should say that all
eigenvalues less than 1
is sufficient, but not
necessary conditioned for what
I'm about to say, right?
So we can rewrite things using
the eigenvectors as a basis.
And if we do that, we end
up getting the eigenvalues
being raised to the lth power.
And so if all of our
eigenvalues are less than 1,
if we're taking a
number less than 1,
then raising it
to the lth power,
that's going to approach 0
as the sequence length grows.
And so the gradient vanishes.
OK, now the reality is
more complex than that.
Because actually, we always use
a nonlinear activation sigma.
But in principle, it's sort
of the same thing apart from,
we have to consider in the
effect of the nonlinear
activation.
OK, so why is this a problem
that the gradients disappear?
Well, suppose we're wanting to
look at the influence of time
steps well in the future, on
the representations we want
to have early in the sentence.
Well, what's happening
late in the sentence
just isn't going to be giving
much information about, what
we should be storing in
the h at time 1 vector.
Whereas on the other hand,
the loss at timestep 2
is going to be giving
a lot of information
at what should be stored in the
hidden vector at timestep 1.
So the end result of
that is that what happens
is that, these
simple RNN's are very
good at modeling nearby effects.
But they're not good at all
at modeling long-term effects.
Because the gradient signal from
far away is just lost too much.
And therefore, the model
never effectively gets
to learn what information
from far away,
it would be useful to
preserve into the future.
So let's consider
that concretely,
for the example of language
models that we've worked on.
So here's a piece of text.
When she tried to
print her tickets,
she found that the
printer was out of toner.
She went to the stationery
store to buy more toner.
It was very overpriced.
After installing the
toner into the printer,
she finally printed her--
and well, you're all
smart human beings.
I trust you can all guess what
the word that comes next is.
It should be tickets.
But well, the problem
is that for the RNN
to start to learn
cases like this,
it would have to carry through
in its hidden state, a memory
of the word tickets for
sort of, whatever it is,
about 30 hidden state updates.
And well, we'll train
on this example.
And so we'll be wanting
it to predict tickets
as the next word.
And so a gradient update
will be sent right back
through the hidden states
of the LSTM corresponding
to this sentence.
And that should
tell the model, it's
good to preserve information
about the word tickets,
because that might be
useful in the future.
Here it was useful
in the future.
But the problem is that, the
gradient signal will just
become far too weak out
after a bunch of words.
And it just never
learns that dependency.
And so what we find
in practice is,
the model is just
unable to predict
similar long-distance
dependencies at test time.
And I've spent quite a long
time on vanishing gradients.
And then really,
vanishing gradients
are the big problem
in practice with using
recurrent neural networks
or the long sequences.
But I have to do
justice to the fact
that you could actually, also
have the opposite problem.
You can also have
exploding gradients.
So if a gradient becomes too
big, that's also a problem.
And it's a problem because
the stochastic gradient update
step becomes too big, right?
So remember, our
parameter update
is based on the product of the
learning rate and the gradient.
So if your gradient is huge,
right, you've calculated,
oh, it's got a
lot of slope here,
this has a slope of 10,000,
then your parameter update
can be arbitrarily large.
And that's potentially
problematic.
That can cause a bad update,
where you take a huge step
and you end up at a weird and
bad parameter configuration.
So you think you're
coming up with a--
to a steep hill to climb.
And while you want to
be climbing the hill
to high likelihood,
that actually
the gradient is so steep that
you make an enormous update.
And then suddenly, your
parameters are over in Iowa.
And you've lost your
hill altogether.
There's also the
practical difficulty
that we only have
so much resolution
in our floating point numbers.
So if your gradient
gets too steep,
you start getting not a numbers
in your calculations, which
ruin all your hard
training work.
We use kind of an
easy fix to this,
which is called gradient
clipping, which is, we
choose some reasonable number.
And we say, we're just not going
to deal with gradients that
are bigger than this number.
A commonly used number is 20.
Some thing that's got a range
of spread, but not that high.
You can use 10, 100, something.
We're sort of in that range.
And if the norm of the gradient
is greater than that threshold,
we simply just scale it down,
which means that we then
make a smaller gradient update.
So we're still moving in
exactly the same direction,
but we're taking a smaller step.
So doing this gradient
clipping is important.
But it's an easy
problem to solve.
OK, so the thing that we've
still got left to solve
is, how to really solve this
problem of vanishing gradients.
So the problem is,
yeah, these RNNs just
can't preserve information
over many timesteps.
And one way to think
about that intuitively
is, at each timestep,
we have a hidden state.
And the hidden state is
being completely changed
at each timestep.
And it's being changed in
a multiplicative manner
by multiplying by Wh,
and then putting it
through a nonlinearity.
Maybe we could make
some more progress,
if we could more
flexibly maintain
a memory in our recurrent
neural network, which
we can manipulate in a
more flexible manner, that
allows us to more easily
preserve information.
And so this was an idea that
people started thinking about.
And actually, they started
thinking about it a long time
ago in the late 1990s.
And Hochreiter and
Schmidhuber came up
with this idea that got called
long short-term memory RNNs.
So a solution to the problem
of vanishing gradients.
I mean, so this 1997
paper is the paper
you always see cited for LSTMs.
But actually, in terms of what
we now understand as an LSTM,
it was missing part of it.
In fact, it's missing what,
in retrospect, has turned out
to be the most important
part of the modern LSTM.
So really, in some
sense, the real paper
that the modern LSTM is due to
is this slightly later paper
by Gers, still Schmidhuber,
and Cummins from 2000,
which additionally
introduces the forget gate
that I'll explain in a minute.
Yeah, so this was
some very clever stuff
that was introduced.
And it turned out later to
have an enormous impact.
If I just diverge from
the technical part
for one more moment.
That for those of
you who, these days,
think that mastering neural
networks is the path to fame
and fortune, the funny
thing is, at the time
that this work was done, that
just was not true, right?
Very few people were
interested in neural networks.
And although long short-term
memories have turned out
to be one of the most important,
successful, and influential
ideas in neural networks
for the following 25 years,
really, the original authors
didn't get recognition
for that.
So both of them
are now professors
at German universities.
But Hochreiter moved over
into doing bioinformatics work
to find something to do.
And Gers, actually, is doing
kind of multimedia studies.
So that's the fates of history.
OK, so what is an LSTM?
So a crucial
innovation of an LSTM
is to say, well,
rather than just having
one hidden vector in
the recurrent model,
we're going to build a model
with two hidden vectors
at each timestep,
one of which is still
called the hidden state
h, and the other of which
is called the cell state.
Now arguably, in retrospect,
these were named wrongly.
Because as you'll see,
when we look at it
in more detail, in
some sense, the cell
is more equivalent to the
hidden state of the simple RNN
than vice versa.
But we're just going with the
names that everybody uses.
So both of these are
vectors of length n.
And it's going to
be the cell that
stores long-term information.
And so we want to
have something that's
more like memory, meaning
like RAM in the computer.
So the cell is designed
so you can read from it,
you can erase parts of
it, and you can write
new information to the cell.
And the interesting
part of an LSTM is then,
it's got control structures
to decide how you do that.
So the selection of
which information
to erase, write, and
read is controlled
by probabilistic gates.
So the gates are also
vectors of length n.
And on each
timestep, we work out
a state for the gate vectors.
So each element of the gate
vectors is a probability.
So they can be open probability,
1, closed probability, 0,
or somewhere in between.
And their value will be
saying, how much do you erase?
How much do you write?
How much do you read?
And so these are dynamic
gates, with a value
that's computed based
on the current context.
OK, so in this next slide,
we go through the equations
of an LSTM.
But following this, there
are some more graphic slides,
which will probably be
easier to absorb, right?
So we, again-- just
like before, it's
a recurrent neural network.
We have a sequence
of inputs, xt.
And we're going to,
at each timestep,
compute a cell state
and a hidden state.
So how do we do that?
So firstly, we're
going to compute
values of the three gates.
And so we're computing
the gate values,
using an equation that's
identical to the equation
for the simple recurrent
neural network.
But in particular--
whoops, sorry, I'll
just say what the
gates are first.
So there's a forget
gate, which we
will control what is kept in
the cell at the next timestep,
versus what is forgotten.
There's an input
gate, which is going
to determine which parts of
a calculated new cell content
get written to the cell memory.
And there's an
output gate, which
is going to control what
parts of the cell memory
are moved over into
the hidden state.
And so each of these is
using the logistic function.
Because we want them
to be, in each element
of this vector, a
probability which
will say whether
to fully forget,
partially forget,
or fully remember.
Yeah, and the equation
for each of these
is exactly like the
simple RNN equation.
But note, of course, that
we've got different parameters
for each one.
So we've got forgetting
weight matrix
W with a forgetting bias,
and a forgetting multiplier
of the input.
So then we have the other
equations that are really
the mechanics of the LSTM.
So we have something that will
calculate a new cell content.
So this is our candidate update.
And so for calculating
the candidate update,
we're, again, essentially using
exactly the same simple RNN
equation.
Apart from now, it's
usual to use tahh.
So you get something that,
as discussed last time,
is balanced around 0.
Okay, so then to actually
update things, we use our gates.
So for our new cell
content, what the idea is,
is that we want to
remember some, but probably
not all of what we had in the
cell from previous timesteps.
And we want to store some, but
probably not all of the value
that we've calculated
as the new cell update.
And so the way we do that is, we
take the previous cell content.
And then, we take its Hadamard
product with the forget vector.
And then, we add to it
the Hadamard product
of the input gate times
the candidate cell update.
And then for working out
the new hidden state,
we then work out which
parts of the cell
to expose in the hidden state.
And so after taking a tanh
transform of the cell,
we then take the Hadamard
product with the output gate.
And that gives us our
hidden representation.
And it's this hidden
representation
that we then put
through a softmax layer,
to generate our next output
of our LSTM recurrent neural
network.
Yeah, so the gates and the
things that they're put with
are vectors of size n.
And what we're doing is, we're
taking each element of them
and multiplying them
element-wise to work out
a new vector.
And then, we get two vectors
that we're adding together.
So this way of doing
things element-wise,
you sort of don't really see in
standard linear algebra course.
It's referred to as
the Hadamard product.
It's represented by
some kind of circle.
Actually, in more
modern work, it's
been more usual to represent
it with this slightly bigger
circle, with the dot at the
middle as the Hadamard product
symbol.
And someday, I'll change
these slides to be like that.
But I was lazy in
redoing the equations.
But the other notation
you do see quite often
is, just using the
same little circle
that you use for
function composition,
to represent Hadamard product.
Okay, so all of these things
are being done as vectors
of the same length n.
And the other thing
that you might notice
is that the candidate update,
and the forget input and output
gates, all have a
very similar form.
The only difference is three
logistics and one tanh.
And none of them
depend on each other.
So all four of those can
be calculated in parallel.
And if you want to have an
efficient LSTM implementation,
that's what you do.
OK, so here's the more
graphical presentation of this.
So these pictures
come from Chris Olah.
And I guess he did such a
nice job at producing pictures
for LSTMs, that almost
everyone uses them these days.
And so this sort of pulls
apart the computation graph
of an LSTM unit.
So blowing this up, you've got
from the previous timestep,
both your cell and
hidden recurrent vectors.
And so you feed
the hidden vector
from the previous timestep
and the new input xt
into the computation of the
gates, which is happening down
at the bottom.
So you compute the forget gate.
And then, you use the forget
gate in a Hadamard product,
here drawn as actually
a time symbol.
So forget some cell content.
You work out the input gate.
And then, using the input gate
and a regular recurrent neural
network-like computation, you
can compute candidate new cell
content.
And so then, you add
those two together
to get the new cell content,
which then heads out
as the new cell
content, at time t.
But then you also have
worked out an output gate.
And so then you take
the cell content,
put it through
another nonlinearity,
and Hadamard product it
with the output gate.
And that then gives you
the new hidden state.
So this is all kind of complex.
But as to understanding why
something that's different
is happening here,
the thing to notice
is that the cell
state from t minus 1
is passing right through this
to be the cell state at time t,
without very much
happening to it.
So some of it is being
deleted by the forget gate.
And then some new stuff
is being written to it,
as a result of using this
candidate new cell content.
But the real secret
of the LSTM is
that new stuff is
just being added
to the cell with
an addition, right?
So in the simple RNN,
at each successive step,
you are doing a multiplication.
And that makes it
incredibly difficult
to learn to preserve
information in the hidden state,
over a long period of time.
It's not completely impossible.
But it's a very
difficult thing to learn.
Whereas with this new
LSTM architecture,
it's trivial to preserve
information in the cell
from one timestep to the next.
You just don't forget it.
And it'll carry
right through with,
perhaps some new stuff
added in to also remember.
And so that's the sense in
which the cell behaves much more
like RAM, in a conventional
computer that is storing stuff.
And extra stuff can
be stored into it.
And other stuff can be deleted
from it, as you go along.
OK, so the LSTM
architecture makes
it much easier to preserve
information for many timesteps,
right?
So in particular, standard
practice with LSTMs
is to initialize the forget
gate to a 1 vector, which
is just so that a starting point
is to say, preserve everything
from previous timesteps.
And then, it is then
learning when it's
appropriate to forget stuff.
All right.
In contrast, it's very hard to
get a simple RNN to preserve
stuff for a very long time.
I mean, what does
that actually mean?
Well, I've put down
some numbers here.
I mean, what you get in practice
depends on a million things.
It depends on the
nature of your data,
and how much data
you have, and what
dimensionality your hidden
states are, blurdy, blurdy,
blur.
But just to give you some
idea of what's going on
is, typically, if you
train a simple recurrent
neural network, that its
effective memory, its ability
to be able to use things in the
past to condition the future,
goes for about seven timesteps.
You just really can't get it
to remember stuff further back
in the past than that.
Whereas for the LSTM,
it's not complete magic.
It doesn't work forever.
But it's effectively able
to remember and use things
from much, much further back.
So typically, you find
that with an LSTM,
you can effectively remember and
use things about 100 time steps
back.
And that's just
enormously more useful
for a lot of the natural
language understanding tasks
that we want to do.
And so that was precisely what
the LSTM was designed to do.
And I mean, so in particular,
just going back to its name,
quite a few people
misparsed its name.
The idea of its
name was, there's
a concept of short-term memory,
which comes from psychology.
And it had been
suggested for simple RNNs
that the hidden state of the
RNN could be a model of humans'
short-term memory.
And then, there would be
something somewhere else
that would deal with
human long-term memory.
But while people had found that
this only gave you a very short
short-term memory, so what
Hochreiter and Schmidhuber were
interested in was
how we could give--
construct models with a
long short-term memory.
And so that, then, gave
us this name of LSTM.
LSTMs don't guarantee that there
are no vanishing or exploding
gradients.
But in practice, they provide--
they don't tend to explode
nearly the same way again.
That plus sign is crucial,
rather than a multiplication.
And so they're a much
more effective way
of learning long-distance
dependencies.
OK, so despite the fact
that LSTMs were developed
around 1997, 2000, it was
really only in the early 2010s,
that the world woke up to them
and how successful they were.
So it was really
around 2013 to 2015
that LSTMs sort
of hit the world,
achieving state
of the art results
on all kinds of problems.
One of the first
big demonstrations
was for handwriting recognition,
then speech recognition.
But then going on to a lot
of natural language tasks,
including machine translation,
parsing, vision and language
tasks like image captioning,
as well, of course,
using them for language models.
And around these years, LSTMs
became the dominant approach
for most NLP tasks.
The easiest way to build
a good strong model
was to approach the
problem with an LSTM.
So now in 2021,
actually, LSTMs are
starting to be supplanted,
or have been supplanted
by other approaches,
particularly transformer
models, which we'll get to in
the class in a couple of weeks
time.
So this is the sort of
picture you can see.
So for many years, there's
been a machine translation
conference.
And so a bake off competition
called WMT, Workshop
on Machine Translation.
So if you look at the
history of that, in WMT 2014,
there was zero neural
machine translation systems
in the competition.
2014 was actually
the first year,
that the success of LSTMs
for machine translation
was proven in a
conference paper.
But nothing occurred
in this competition.
By 2016, everyone had jumped
on LSTMs as working great.
And lots of people, including
the winner of the competition,
was using an LSTM model.
If you then jump ahead
to 2019, then there's
relatively little use of LSTMs.
And the vast majority of people
are now using transformers.
So things change quickly
in neural network land.
And I keep on having to
rewrite these lectures.
So a quick further note
on vanishing and exploding
gradients.
Is it only a problem with
recurrent neural networks?
It's not.
It's actually a problem
that also occurs anywhere
where you have a lot
of depth, including
feedforward and convolutional
neural networks.
Any time when you've got long
sequences of chain rules, which
give you multiplications,
the gradient
can become vanishingly
small as it backpropagates.
And so generally, lower
layers are learned very slowly
and are hard to train.
So there's been a lot of
effort in other places as well,
to come up with different
architectures that
let you learn more
efficiently in deep networks.
And the commonest
way to do that is
to add more direct
connections, that
allow the gradient to flow.
So the big thing and vision
in the last few years
has been ResNets,
where the Res stands
for residual connections.
And so the way they're
made-- this picture
is upside down, so the
input is at the top,
is that you have these
sort of two paths that
are summed together.
One path is just
an identity path.
And the other one goes through
some neural network layers.
And so therefore,
its default behavior
is just to preserve
the input, which
might sound a little bit like
what we just saw for LSTMs.
There are other methods.
There have been DenseNets,
where you add skip connections
forward to every latent layer.
HighwayNets were also actually
developed by Schmidhuber,
and sort of reminiscent of
what was done with LSTMs.
So rather than just having
an identity connection,
as a ResNet has, it
introduces an extra gate.
So it looks more like
an LSTM, which says,
how much to send the input
through the highway versus how
much to put it through
a neural net layer?
And those two are then
combined into the output.
So essentially, this
problem occurs anywhere
when you have a lot of depth in
your layers of neural network.
But it first arose--
and it turns out
to be especially
problematic with
recurrent neural networks.
They are particularly
unstable, because of the fact
that you've got this one weight
matrix that you're repeatedly
using through the time sequence.
OK, so--
Chris, we've got a couple
of questions, more or less,
about whether you would
ever want to use an--
like a simple RNN
instead of an LSTM?
How does the LSTM learn
what to do with its gates?
Can you opine on those things?
Sure.
So I think, basically
the answer is,
you should never use a
simple RNN these days.
You should always use an LSTM.
I mean, obviously, that
depends on what you're doing.
If you're wanting to do some
analytical paper or something,
you might prefer a simple RNN.
And it is the case
that you can actually
get decent results
with simple RNNs,
providing you are very careful
to make sure that things aren't
exploding nor vanishing.
But in practice,
getting simple RNNs
to work and preserve
long context
is incredibly difficult,
where you can train LSTMs
and they will just work.
So really, you should
always just use an LSTM.
Now wait, the
second question was?
I think there's a
bit of confusion
about whether the gates
are learning differently.
Oh, yeah.
So the gates are
also just learned.
So if we go back
to these equations,
this is the complete model.
And when we're training
the model, every one
of these parameters, so
all of these W, U, and b's,
everything is simultaneously
being trained by backprop.
So that what you hope,
and indeed it works,
is the model is
learning, what stuff
should I remember for a
long time, versus what
stuff should I forget?
What things in the
input are important,
versus what things in the
input don't really matter?
So it can learn things
like function words,
like a and the
don't really matter,
even though everyone
uses them in English.
So you can just not
worry about those.
So all of this is learned.
And the models do, actually,
successfully learn gate values
about what information is
useful to preserve long-term,
versus what information
is really only
useful short-term, for
predicting the next one or two
words.
Finally, the gradient
improvements, due to the-- so
you said that the
addition is really
important between the new cell
candidate and the cell state.
And I don't think-- at
least, a couple of students
have sort of questioned that.
So if you want to go over that
again, that might be useful.
Sure.
So what we would like is
an easy way for memory
to be preserved long-term.
And one way, which
is what ResNets use,
is just to completely have a
direct path from Ct minus 1
to Ct, and will preserve
entirely the history.
So kind of there's
a default action
of preserving information
about the past long-term.
LSTMs don't quite do that.
But they allow that
function to be easy.
So you start off with
the previous cell state.
And you can forget some
of it by the forget gate.
So you can delete stuff
out of your memory.
That's a useful operation.
And then, well,
you're going to be
able to update the
content of the cell
with the write operation that
occurs in the plus, where,
depending on the input
gate, some parts of what's
in the cell will be added too.
But you can think of
that adding as overlaying
extra information.
Everything that was in the
cell that wasn't forgotten
is still continuing on
to the next timestep.
And in particular, when you're
doing the backpropagation
through time, that there isn't--
I want to say, there
isn't a multiplication
between Ct and Ct minus 1.
And there's this unfortunate
time symbol here.
But remember that's the
Hadamard product, which
is zeroing out part of
it with the forget gate.
It's not a multiplication by a
matrix, like in the simple RNN.
I hope that's good.
OK, so there are a
couple of other things
that I wanted to get
through before the end.
I guess I'm not going to
have time to do both of them,
I think.
So I'll do the last one,
probably, next time.
Though these are
actually simple and easy
things, that they
complete our picture.
So I sort of briefly
alluded to this example
of sentiment classification,
where what we could do
is run an RNN, maybe an
LSTM, over a sentence,
call this our representation
of the sentence,
and you feed it into
a softmax classifier
to classify for sentiment.
So what we're actually
saying there is that,
we can regard the hidden
state as a representation
of a word in context.
That the low, that we have just
a word vector for terribly.
But we then looked
at our context
and say, OK, we've now created
a hidden state representation
for the word terribly, in
the context of the movie was.
And that proves to be
a really useful idea,
because words have different
meanings in different contexts.
But it seems like there's a
defect of what we've done here,
because our context only
contains information
from the left.
What about right context?
Surely, it would also be useful
to have the meaning of terribly
depend on exciting.
Because often, words
mean different things
based on what follows them.
So if you have
something like red wine,
it means something quite
different from a red light.
So how could we deal with that?
Well, an easy way to deal
with that would be to say,
well, if we're just
wanting to come up
with a neural encoding
of a sentence,
we could have a second RNN with
completely separate parameters
learned.
And we could run it backwards
through the sentence
to get a backward
representation of each word.
And then, we could get
an overall representation
of each word and context by
just concatenating those two
representations.
And now we've got a
representation of terribly
that has both left
and right context.
So we're simply
running a forward RNN.
And when I say RNN
in here, that just
means any kind of
recurrent neural network.
So commonly, it'll be an LSTM.
And a backward one.
And then at each
timestep, we're just
concatenating their
representations,
with each of these
having separate weights.
And so then we regard
this concatenated thing
as the hidden state, the
contextual representation
of a token at a particular
time, that we pass forward.
This is so common, that people
use a shortcut to denote that.
And they'll just draw this
picture with two-sided arrows.
And when you see that picture
with two-sided arrows,
it means that you're running
two RNNs, one in each direction.
And then, concatenating their
results at each timestep.
And that's what you're going
to use later in the model.
Okay, so if you're doing
an encoding problem,
like for sentiment
classification or question
answering, using bidirectional
RNNs is a great thing to do.
But they are only applicable
if you have access
to the entire input sequence.
They're not applicable
to language modeling.
Because in a language
model, necessarily, you
have to generate
the next word based
on only the preceding context.
But if you do have the
entire input sequence,
that bidirectionality
gives you greater power.
And indeed, that's been an
idea that people have built on
in subsequent work.
So when we get to transformers
in a couple of weeks,
we'll spend plenty of time
on the BERT model, where
that acronym stands for
Bidirectional Encoder
Representations
from Transformers.
So part of what's important in
that model is the transformer.
But really, a central
point of the paper
was to say that you could build
more powerful models using
transformers by, again,
exploiting bidirectionality.
OK, there's one teeny
bit left on RNNs.
But I'll sneak it
into next class.
And I'll call it
the end for today.
And if there are
other things you'd
like to ask questions about,
you can find me on Nooks
again in just a minute.
Okay, so I'll see you
again next Tuesday.